<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="a-thal" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">a-thal</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Alpha-Thalassemia</title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Origa</surname>
            <given-names>Raffaella</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche e Sanit&#x000e0; Pubblica<break/>Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi di Cagliari<break/>Ospedale Regionale per le Microcitemie<break/>Cagliari, Italy</aff>
          <email>raffaella.origa@unica.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Moi</surname>
            <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche e Sanit&#x000e0; Pubblica<break/>Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi di Cagliari<break/>Ospedale Regionale per le Microcitemie<break/>Cagliari, Italy</aff>
          <email>pmoi@unica.it</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="xlmr" document-type="chapter">Alpha-Thalassemia X-Linked Intellectual Disability Syndrome</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="alpha1-a" document-type="chapter">Alpha-1 Antitrypsin Deficiency</related-object>
      <abstract id="a-thal.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Alpha-thalassemia (&#x003b1;-thalassemia) has two clinically significant forms: hemoglobin Bart hydrops fetalis (Hb Bart) syndrome, caused by deletion of all four &#x003b1;-globin genes; and hemoglobin H (HbH) disease, most frequently caused by deletion of three &#x003b1;-globin genes.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Hb Bart syndrome, the more severe form, is characterized by fetal onset of generalized edema, pleural and pericardial effusions, and severe hypochromic anemia, in the absence of ABO or Rh blood group incompatibility. Additional clinical features include marked hepatosplenomegaly, extramedullary erythropoiesis, hydrocephalus, and cardiac and urogenital defects. Death usually occurs in the neonatal period.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>HbH disease is characterized by microcytic hypochromic hemolytic anemia, splenomegaly, mild jaundice, and sometimes thalassemia-like bone changes. Individuals with HbH disease may develop gallstones and experience acute episodes of hemolysis in response to oxidant drugs and infections.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of Hb Bart syndrome is established in a fetus with the characteristic radiographic and laboratory features. Identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> that result in deletion or inactivation of all four &#x003b1;-globin alleles confirms the diagnosis. The diagnosis of HbH disease is established in a proband with the characteristic laboratory and clinical features. Identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> that result in deletion or inactivation of three &#x003b1;-globin alleles confirms the diagnosis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Intrauterine blood transfusions, improved transfusion strategies, and rarely curative hematopoietic stem cell transplant may allow survival of children with Hb Bart syndrome. For HbH disease, occasional red blood cell transfusions may be needed during hemolytic or aplastic crises. Red blood cell transfusions are very rarely needed for severe anemia affecting cardiac function and erythroid expansion that results in severe bone changes and extramedullary erythropoiesis.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of primary manifestations:</italic> Because of the severity of Hb Bart syndrome and the risk for maternal complications, prenatal diagnosis and early termination of pregnancies at risk has usually been considered. However, recent advances in intrauterine and postnatal therapy have increased treatment options &#x02013; thus complicating the ethical issues for health care providers and families facing an affected pregnancy.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> Monitor individuals with HbH disease for hemolytic/aplastic crisis during febrile episodes; in those who require chronic red blood cell transfusions, iron chelation therapy should be instituted; for those who are not red blood cell transfusion dependent, iron chelation with deferasirox can be considered to reduce liver iron concentration.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> For HbH disease, hematologic evaluation every six to 12 months; assessment of growth and development in children every six to 12 months; monitoring of iron load with serum ferritin concentration and periodic quantitative measurement of liver iron concentration.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> In HbH disease, inappropriate iron therapy, oxidant drugs such as sulphonamides, and some antimalarials.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> Test the sibs of a proband as soon as possible after birth for HbH disease so that monitoring can be instituted.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Pregnancy management</italic>: Complications reported in pregnant women with HbH disease include worsening anemia, preeclampsia, congestive heart failure, and threatened miscarriage; monitoring for these issues during pregnancy is recommended.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>Alpha-thalassemia is usually inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. At conception, each sib of an individual with Hb Bart syndrome has a 25% chance of having Hb Bart syndrome, a 50% chance of having &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion or inactivation <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;), and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
          <p>At conception, if one parent has &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) and the other parent is an &#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier (1-gene deletion; -&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;), each sib of an individual with HbH disease has a 25% chance of having HbH disease, a 25% chance of having &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait, a 25% chance of being an &#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Each child of an individual with HbH disease inherits either the two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> and has &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait or is an &#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier and is thus an obligate heterozygote; risk to the child of having the disease depends on the allele inherited from the other parent.</p>
          <p>Family members, members of ethnic groups at risk, and gamete donors should be considered for carrier testing. Couples who are members of populations at risk for &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) can be identified prior to pregnancy as being at risk of conceiving a fetus with Hb Bart syndrome. Prenatal testing may be carried out for couples who are at high risk of having a fetus with Hb Bart syndrome or for a pregnancy in which one parent is a known &#x003b1;-thalassemia carrier with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) when the other parent is either unknown or unavailable for testing.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="a-thal.GeneReview_Scope">
        <title><italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> Scope</title>
        <table-wrap id="a-thal.Tc" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Alpha-Thalassemia (&#x003b1;-Thalassemia)</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1" id="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenotype&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1" id="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1 hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin Bart hydrops fetalis (Hb Bart) syndrome</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1 hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loss of all 4 &#x003b1;-globin genes</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1 hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin H (HbH) disease</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1 hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loss of 3 &#x003b1;-globin genes</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1 hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-thalassemia trait</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1 hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loss of 2 &#x003b1;-globin genes either <italic toggle="yes">in cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;, &#x003b1;<sup>0</sup> carrier) or <italic toggle="yes">in trans</italic> (-&#x003b1;/-&#x003b1;)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1 hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_1_1 hd_h_a-thal.Tc_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loss of 1 &#x003b1;-globin gene (-&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;, &#x003b1;<sup>+</sup> carrier)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>For synonyms and outdated names see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Nomenclature">Nomenclature</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="a-thal.TF.c.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>In descending order of severity</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="a-thal.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Alpha-thalassemia (&#x003b1;-thalassemia) has two clinically significant forms: hemoglobin Bart hydrops fetalis syndrome (deletion of all 4 &#x003b1;-globin genes; --/--), and hemoglobin H disease (most frequently caused by deletion of 3 &#x003b1;-globin genes; --/-&#x003b1;).</p>
          <sec id="a-thal.Hemoglobin_Bart_Hydrops_Fetalis_S">
            <title>Hemoglobin Bart Hydrops Fetalis Syndrome</title>
            <p>Hemoglobin Bart hydrops fetalis (Hb Bart) syndrome <bold>should be suspected</bold> in fetuses with the following ultrasonographic features and/or laboratory features.</p>
            <p>
              <bold>Radiographic features</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>An at-risk fetus with increased nuchal thickness, thickened placenta, increased cerebral media artery velocity, and increased cardiothoracic ratio on ultrasonography examination at 13 to 14 weeks' gestation</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>A fetus with generalized edema, ascites, and pleural and pericardial effusions detected by ultrasonography examination at 22 to 28 weeks' gestation</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Laboratory features</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Red blood cell indices: severe macrocytic hypochromic anemia, in the absence of ABO or Rh blood group incompatibility (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv">Table 1</xref>)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Reticulocytosis: variable; may be more than 60%</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Peripheral blood smear with large, hypochromic red cells and severe anisopoikilocytosis</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="a-thal.Hemoglobin_H_Disease">
            <title>Hemoglobin H Disease</title>
            <p>Hemoglobin H (HbH) disease <bold>should be suspected</bold> in an infant or child with the following newborn screening results, clinical features, and/or laboratory features.</p>
            <p><bold>Newborn screening.</bold> Hb Bart &#x0003e;15% at birth</p>
            <p>Note: (1) Newborn screening for sickle cell disease offered by several states/countries may detect Hb Bart in the newborn with &#x003b1;-thalassemia (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genes-r-us.uthscsa.edu/sites/genes-r-us/files/nbsdisorders.pdf">National Newborn Screening Status Report</ext-link>). (2) Reference ranges may very among laboratories performing newborn screening (3) Low concentrations of Hb Bart (1%-8%) are indicative of the carrier states and usually do not need further evaluation.</p>
            <p>
              <bold>Clinical features</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Hepatosplenomegaly</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Mild thalassemia-like bone changes (e.g., hypertrophy of the maxilla, bossing of the skull, and prominence of the malar eminences)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Mild jaundice</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Laboratory features</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Red blood cell indices: mild-to-moderate (rarely severe) microcytic hypochromic hemolytic anemia (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv">Table 1</xref>)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Moderate reticulocytosis: 3%-6%</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Peripheral blood smear with anisopoikilocytosis, and very rare nucleated red blood cells (i.e., erythroblasts)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Red blood cell supravital stain showing HbH inclusions (&#x003b2;<sub>4</sub> tetramers) in 5% to 80% of erythrocytes following incubation of fresh blood smears with 1% brilliant cresyl blue for one to three hours</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <table-wrap id="a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 1. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Red Blood Cell Indices in Individuals with Hemoglobin Bart Hydrops Fetalis and Hemoglobin H Disease</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_1">Red Blood Cell Indices</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Normal</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Affected</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Male</th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin Bart hydrops fetalis&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin H disease&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Mean corpuscular volume (MCV, fl)</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.1&#x000b1;5.01</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.6&#x000b1;5.5</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136&#x000b1;5.1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Children: 56&#x000b1;5<break/>Adults: 61&#x000b1;4</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH, pg)</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9&#x000b1;1.9</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2&#x000b1;2.1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9&#x000b1;9</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4&#x000b1;1.2</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Hemoglobin (Hb, g/dL)</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9&#x000b1;1.0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0&#x000b1;0.9</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-8</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: 10.9&#x000b1;1.0<break/>Female: 9.5&#x000b1;0.8</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
              <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.1.1">
                  <label>1. </label>
                  <p>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.vaeusorn.1985">Vaeusorn et al [1985]</xref>
                  </p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.1.2">
                  <label>2. </label>
                  <p>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.galanello.1992.1">Galanello et al [1992]</xref>
                  </p>
                </fn>
              </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="a-thal.Hemoglobin_Analysis">
            <title>Hemoglobin Analysis</title>
            <p>Qualitative and quantitative hemoglobin (Hb) analysis (by cellulose acetate electrophoresis, weak-cation high-performance liquid chromatography [HPLC], and supplemental techniques such as isoelectric focusing and citrate agar electrophoresis) identifies the amount and type of Hb present. The Hb pattern in &#x003b1;-thalassemia varies by &#x003b1;-thalassemia type (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha">Table 2</xref>). The Hb types most relevant to &#x003b1;-thalassemia are:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Hemoglobin A (HbA). Two &#x003b1;-globin chains and two &#x003b2;-globin chains (&#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>&#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Hemoglobin F (HbF). Two &#x003b1;-globin chains and two &#x003b3;-globin chains (&#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>2</sub>)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Hemoglobin Bart (Hb Bart). Four &#x003b3;-globin chains (&#x003b3;<sub>4</sub>)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Hemoglobin H (HbH). Four &#x003b2;-globin chains (&#x003b2;<sub>4</sub>)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Hemoglobin A2 (HbA2). Two &#x003b1;-globin chains and two &#x003b4;-globin chains (&#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>&#x003b4;<sub>2</sub>)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Hemoglobin Portland. Two &#x003b6;-globin chains and two &#x003b3;-globin chains (&#x003b6;<sub>2</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>2</sub>)</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <table-wrap id="a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 2. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Hemoglobin Patterns in Alpha-Thalassemia (Age &#x0003e;12 Months)</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1">Hemoglobin Type</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_2">Normal</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Affected</th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Hb Bart hydrops fetalis syndrome&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbH disease&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>HbA</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96%-98%</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60%-90%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>HbF</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1%</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Hb Bart</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85%-90%</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2%-5%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>HbH</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8%-40%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>HbA2</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2%-3%</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;2.0%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Hb Portland</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10%-15%</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
              <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.2.1">
                  <label>1. </label>
                  <p>Deletion or inactivation of all four &#x003b1;-globin chains makes it impossible to assemble HbF and HbA. Fetal blood contains mainly Hb Bart (&#x003b3;<sub>4</sub>) and 10%-15% of the embryonic hemoglobin Portland (&#x003b6;<sub>2</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>2</sub>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.2.2">
                  <label>2. </label>
                  <p>Deletion or inactivation of three &#x003b1;-globin chains</p>
                </fn>
              </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Genetic_Counseling">Genetic Counseling</xref> for information about hematologic testing to identify alpha-thalassemia trait and alpha-thalassemia silent carrier status.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of <bold>hemoglobin Bart hydrops fetalis syndrome is established</bold> in a fetus with the above <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Hemoglobin_Bart_Hydrops_Fetalis_S">ultrasonographic and laboratory features</xref>. Identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in both <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> that results in deletion or inactivation of all four &#x003b1;-globin alleles (e.g., 2 &#x003b1;-globin deletions in the homozygous state; --/--) on molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv">Table 1</xref>) confirms the diagnosis and allows for family studies.</p>
          <p>The diagnosis of <bold>hemoglobin H disease is established</bold> in a proband with the above <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Hemoglobin_H_Disease">clinical and laboratory features</xref>. Identification of pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> on molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv">Table 1</xref>) that results in deletion or inactivation of three &#x003b1;-globin genes (e.g., a 2 &#x003b1;-globin-deletion allele <italic toggle="yes">in trans</italic> with a single &#x003b1;-globin-deletion allele; --/-&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>) confirms the diagnosis and allows for family studies.</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="a-thal.F1">Figure 1</xref> for a diagnostic algorithm for hemoglobinopathies.</p>
          <p>Molecular testing approaches can include <bold>targeted deletion analysis for common deletions</bold>, <bold>sequence analysis</bold>, and <bold>deletion analysis</bold> of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and the HS-40 regulatory region.</p>
          <p><bold>Targeted deletion analysis</bold> for common deletions of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> can be performed first.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Common two &#x003b1;-globin-gene deletions (&#x003b1;&#x000ba;-genotype)</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>The Southeast Asian deletion (&#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>SEA</sup>)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>The Filipino deletion (&#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>FIL</sup>)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>The Mediterranean deletion (&#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>MED</sup>)</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
              <p>Note: (1) These common deletions are typically founder variants (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Prevalence">Prevalence</xref>). (2) More than 20 different deletions ranging from ~6 kb to &#x0003e;300 kb and removing both &#x003b1;-globin genes (and sometimes embryonic <italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic>) have been reported.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Common single &#x003b1;-globin-gene deletions (&#x003b1;<sup>+</sup>-genotype)</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>The 3.7-kb deletion (-&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>) deletion</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>The 4.2-kb deletion (-&#x003b1;<sup>4.2</sup>) deletion</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
              <p>Note: In addition to these two common deletions, rare deletions involving a single &#x003b1;-globin gene have been reported.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Sequence analysis</bold> of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> can be performed next if a common deletion was not identified.</p>
          <p>Note: Non-deletion or &#x0201c;trait&#x0201d; <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> variants are designated as (&#x003b1;<sup>ND</sup>&#x003b1;/) or (&#x003b1;<sup>T</sup>&#x003b1;/); variants in <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> are designated as (&#x003b1;&#x003b1;<sup>ND</sup> /) or (&#x003b1;&#x003b1;<sup>T</sup> /) (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>).</p>
          <p><bold>Deletion analysis</bold> of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>, and the HS-40 regulatory region located 40 kb upstream from the &#x003b1;-globin cluster can be performed next to detect uncommon deletions associated with &#x003b1;-thalassemia if pathogenic variants have not been identified by targeted deletion testing or sequence analysis.</p>
          <p><bold>Further testing</bold> for genes associated with genetic disorders similar to &#x003b1;-thalassemia, such as <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBB</italic> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered if clinically indicated.</p>
          <table-wrap id="a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Alpha-Thalassemia</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genes&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Pathogenic Variants&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Targeted common deletion analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~85%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5,&#x000a0;6</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~15%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Deletion analysis&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;5%</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.3.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="a-thal" object-id="a-thal.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.3.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.3.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.harteveld.2014.1">Harteveld [2014]</xref>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.3.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>Targeted deletion assays can detect specific deletions within the &#x003b1;-globin gene cluster. The method commonly used to identify targeted deletion is GAP-PCR.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.3.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.3.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>Targeted analysis for known pathogenic variants (genotyping) may also be used. Methods used may include: allele-specific PCR, allele-specific oligonucleotide testing, and restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) testing.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.3.7">
                <label>7. </label>
                <p>Methods that may be used to detect rare or unknown deletions include: Southern blotting, quantitative PCR, long-range PCR and MPLA. The same methods may be used to detect duplications of the &#x003b1;-cluster. Deletion analysis should include the HS-40 regulatory region located 40 kb upstream from the &#x003b1;-globin cluster.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="a-thal.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>The clinically significant phenotypes of alpha-thalassemia (&#x003b1;-thalassemia) are hemoglobin Bart hydrops fetalis (Hb Bart) syndrome and hemoglobin H (HbH) disease. The severity of the &#x003b1;-thalassemia syndromes depends on the extent of &#x003b1;-globin chain defect (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</xref>).</p>
          <p><bold>Hb Bart syndrome</bold> is the most severe clinical condition related to &#x003b1;-thalassemia. Affected fetuses are either delivered stillborn at 30 to 40 weeks&#x02019; gestation or die soon after birth.</p>
          <p>The main clinical features are generalized edema and pleural and pericardial effusions as a result of congestive heart failure induced by severe anemia. Notably, red cells with Hb Bart have an extremely high oxygen affinity and are incapable of effective oxygen delivery. The blood smear shows large hypochromic macrocytes and numerous nucleated red cells. Extramedullary erythropoiesis, marked hepatosplenomegaly, and a massive placenta are common.</p>
          <p>Retardation in brain growth, hydrocephalus, cardiovascular deformities, and urogenital defects have been reported.</p>
          <p>A very small number of individuals survive following intrauterine transfusions and repeated frequent transfusions after birth.</p>
          <p>Maternal complications during pregnancy commonly include: preeclampsia, polyhydramnios or oligohydramnios, antepartum hemorrhage, and premature delivery.</p>
          <p><bold>HbH disease.</bold> The phenotype of HbH disease varies. Although clinical features usually develop in the first years of life, HbH disease may not present until adulthood or may be diagnosed only during routine hematologic analysis in an asymptomatic individual.</p>
          <p>The majority of individuals show microcytic hypochromic hemolytic anemia (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_indiv">Table 1</xref>), enlargement of the spleen and less commonly of the liver, mild jaundice, and sometimes mild-to-moderate thalassemia-like skeletal changes (e.g., hypertrophy of the maxilla, bossing of the skull, and prominence of the malar eminences) that affects the facial features. Leg ulcers are rare.</p>
          <p>Individuals with HbH disease may develop gallstones and experience acute episodes of hemolysis in response to oxidant drugs and infections. Rarely, aplastic crisis due to infection of parvovirus B19 may occur in individuals with HbH disease.</p>
          <p>While the majority of individuals with HbH disease have minor disability, some are severely affected, requiring regular blood transfusions; in very rare cases hydrops fetalis is present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.lorey.2001.72">Lorey et al 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.chui.2003.791">Chui et al 2003</xref>].</p>
          <p>Significant iron overload is uncommon but has been reported in older individuals, usually as a result of repeated blood transfusions or increased iron absorption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.taher.2012.970">Taher et al 2012</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>The phenotype of the &#x003b1;-thalassemia syndromes depends on the degree of &#x003b1;-globin chain deficiency relative to &#x003b2;-globin production. The correlation between &#x003b1;-thalassemia pathogenic variants, &#x003b1;-globin mRNA levels, &#x003b1;-globin synthesis, and clinical manifestations of &#x003b1;-thalassemia is well documented.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Hb Bart syndrome</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Most often caused by large deletions on both alleles (&#x003b1;-globin --/--)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Rarely, an individual with Hb Bart syndrome will have a non-deletion variant.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>HbH disease</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Most often caused by a large deletion on one allele <italic toggle="yes">in trans</italic> with a single &#x003b1;-globin-gene deletion (--/-&#x003b1;) or other non-deletion inactivating variant (--/&#x003b1;<sup>ND</sup>&#x003b1; or --/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;<sup>ND</sup>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Individuals homozygous for the Constant Spring variant (&#x003b1;<sup>CS</sup>&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;<sup>CS</sup>&#x003b1;) or <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> poly (A) pathogenic variant may have HbH disease.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Individuals who are homozygous or compound heterozygous for highly unstable &#x003b1;-globin gene variants may have HbH disease.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Rarely, HbH disease is caused by a compound heterozygous or homozygous HS40 deletion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.coelho.2010.147">Coelho et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.sollaino.2010.2193">Sollaino et al 2010</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Alpha-thalassemia trait</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>May result from deletion or inactivation of two &#x003b1;-globin genes <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>May result from deletion of a single gene on both alleles (e.g., -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>/-&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>May result from non-deletion variants inactivating <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>(&#x003b1;<sup>ND</sup>&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;)</p>
              <p>Individuals with alpha-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) have slightly lower RBC indices than individuals with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">trans</italic>. The most severe alleles in descending order are: two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>, non-deletion <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> variant, -&#x003b1;<sup>4.2</sup>, -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup> (because of compensatory increase of &#x003b1;-globin production from the remaining <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>), and non-deletion <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> variant. For the -&#x003b1;<sup>4.2</sup> deletion, evidence is inconclusive for a compensatory increase in the expression of the remaining &#x003b1;-globin gene.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The phenotype may be modified by triplication or quadruplication of the &#x003b1;-globin genes on one chromosome.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Alpha-thalassemia silent carrier</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Results from deletion of one &#x003b1;-globin gene (-&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) or inactivation of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> (&#x003b1;&#x003b1;<sup>ND</sup>/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The genotypes causing silent alpha-thalassemia may have a completely silent hematologic phenotype or may present with a moderate thalassemia-like hematologic picture (i.e., reduced MCV and MCH, but normal HbA2 and HbF), similar to individuals with &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>The &#x003b1;-thalassemias have been classified on the basis of the total globin production from each of the two &#x003b1;-globin genes, <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>, present on chromosome 16:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>When both &#x003b1;-globin genes on a chromosome are deleted or inactivated, the allele is referred to as &#x003b1;<sup>0</sup> (no output of &#x003b1;-globin from the chromosome). An individual with the genotype --/&#x003b1;&#x003b1; is referred to as an &#x003b1;<sup>0</sup> carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When one &#x003b1;-globin gene on a chromosome is deleted or inactivated by a non-deletion variant the allele is called &#x003b1;<sup>+</sup> (some &#x003b1;-globin is produced). An individual with the genotype -&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1; is referred to as an &#x003b1;<sup>+</sup> carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Alpha-thalassemias have also been classified based on the number of globin genes that are missing or abnormal: alpha-thalassemia 1 (-&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;, &#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier); alpha-thalassemia 2 (-&#x003b1;/-&#x003b1; or --/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;, &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.lehmann.1984.552">Lehmann &#x00026; Carrell 1984</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>Since the early 1960s, prevalence of &#x003b1;-thalassemia has been determined in several populations using the percent of Hb Bart in cord blood. However, because not all newborns with &#x003b1;-thalassemia (mainly &#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carriers) have increased Hb Bart, the prevalence of &#x003b1;-thalassemia derived from this measure may be underestimated.</p>
          <p>More precise data have been obtained using molecular testing. For detailed references for the frequency of &#x003b1;-thalassemia in each population, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.piel.2014.1908">Piel &#x00026; Weatherall [2014]</xref>.</p>
          <sec id="a-thal.Africa">
            <title>Africa</title>
            <p>The highest allele frequency (0.30-0.40) of the -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>allele has been observed in the equatorial belt including Nigeria, Ivory Coast, and Kenya.</p>
            <p>The two &#x003b1;-globin-gene deletion in <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) has been reported very rarely in North Africa and in the African American population.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="a-thal.The_Mediterranean">
            <title>The Mediterranean</title>
            <p>Alpha-thalassemia trait caused by -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>/-&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup> is common, with the highest allele frequency reported in Sardinia (0.18) and the lowest in Spain.</p>
            <p>The two &#x003b1;-globin-gene deletion in <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) is very rare (0.002); thus, Hb Bart hydrops fetalis is only rarely reported.</p>
            <p>A remarkable aspect of &#x003b1;-thalassemia variants identified in the Mediterranean population is the heterogeneity of variants, particularly the non-deletion variants.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="a-thal.The_Arabian_Peninsula">
            <title>The Arabian Peninsula</title>
            <p>Frequency of the -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>allele (causing &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait) varies from 0.01 to 0.67, with the highest values being observed in Oman.</p>
            <p>The two &#x003b1;-globin-gene deletion in <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) is extremely rare.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="a-thal.India">
            <title>India</title>
            <p>Alpha-thalassemia trait reaches very high allele frequency (0.35-0.92) in the Indian tribal population of Andra Pradesh; in other tribes, the frequency is much lower (0.03-0.12). Both the -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>allele and the -&#x003b1;<sup>4.2</sup>allele variably contribute to incidence of &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait.</p>
            <p>The two &#x003b1;-globin-gene deletion in <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) is very rare.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="a-thal.Southeast_Asia">
            <title>Southeast Asia</title>
            <p>Alpha<sup>0</sup>-thalassemia alleles (&#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>SEA</sup>, &#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>THAI</sup>, &#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>FIL</sup>) and &#x003b1;<sup>+</sup>-thalassemia alleles (-&#x003b1;) are very common, causing a major public health burden.</p>
            <p>Alpha-thalassemia caused by Hb<sup>Constant Spring</sup> (Hb<sup>CS</sup>) alleles is also common.</p>
            <p>The incidence of Hb Bart hydrops fetalis is expected to be between 0.5 and 5 per 1000 births and HbH disease between 4 and 20 per 1000 births.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="a-thal.Oceania">
            <title>Oceania</title>
            <p>The distribution of &#x003b1;-thalassemia, extensively studied by DNA-based methods, follows a pattern consistent with the degree of malaria endemicity. The prevalence of &#x003b1;<sup>-</sup>-thalassemia is low in the highlands and high in the coastal areas and the lowlands where malaria is hyperendemic.</p>
            <p>Some alpha-thalassemias have unusual mutation mechanisms; for example, some affected individuals on the island of Vanuatu who have normal &#x003b1;-globin genes without deletions or variants have a variant in a regulatory element that creates a GATA-1 site and activates a cryptic promoter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.de_gobbi.2006.1215">De Gobbi et al 2006</xref>].</p>
            <p>The two &#x003b1;-globin-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) is very rare.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disor">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p><bold>Alpha-thalassemia/intellectual disability syndrome, chromosome 16-related</bold> (ATR-16 syndrome; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/141750">OMIM</ext-link>), a contiguous gene deletion syndrome, results from a large terminal deletion of the distal short arm of chromosome 16 from 16p13.3, which includes <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and additional flanking genes. Among the few reported individuals with deletion of 16p (without deletion or duplication of other genomic material), microcephaly and short stature were variable; IQ ranged from 53 to 76 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.lindor.1997.451">Lindor et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.gibson.2008.225">Gibson et al 2008</xref>]. Facial features are distinctive; talipes equinovarus (club foot) is common, as are hypospadias and cryptorchidism in males [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.lindor.1997.451">Lindor et al 1997</xref>]. Typically, hematologic features are those of the &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait reflecting deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> configuration (i.e., --/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;). While routine cytogenetic studies may be sufficient to identify the deletion, in some instances cryptic subtelomeric deletions are detected only with subtelomeric FISH studies, MLPA, or chromosomal microarray [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.harteveld.2007.283">Harteveld et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.gibson.2008.225">Gibson et al 2008</xref>]. The deletion may be <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> or inherited from a parent who carries a balanced chromosome rearrangement.</p>
        <p><bold>Acquired &#x003b1;-thalassemia (&#x003b1;-thalassemia-myelodysplastic syndrome [ATMDS]).</bold> In the context of a clonal myeloid disorder such as myelodysplastic syndrome, somatic variants causing an acquired form of &#x003b1;-thalassemia HbH disease in individuals who were previously hematologically normal may arise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.steensma.2005.443">Steensma et al 2005</xref>]. Red cell indices are usually hypochromic and microcytic, in contrast to the normocytic or macrocytic indices typical of myelodysplastic syndrome. Although most cases of ATMDS have been linked to pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> on the X chromosome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.gibbons.2003.446">Gibbons et al 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.steensma.2004a.2019">Steensma et al 2004a</xref>], acquired deletions of chromosome 16p may be causative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.steensma.2004b.1518">Steensma et al 2004b</xref>]. For unknown reasons, some individuals with myeloid disorders have small amounts (&#x0003c;1%) of HbH.</p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="xlmr" document-type="chapter"><bold>Alpha-thalassemia X-linked intellectual disability syndrome</bold></related-object> is NOT an allelic disorder (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="a-thal.Hydrops_Fetalis">
          <title>Hydrops Fetalis</title>
          <p>Hydrops fetalis is associated with many conditions in addition to Hb Bart, including immune-related disorders (e.g., alloimmune hemolytic disease, Rh isoimmunization), fetal cardiac anomalies, chromosomal abnormalities, fetal infections, genetic disorders, and maternal and placental disorders. The combination of a hydropic fetus with a very high proportion of Hb Bart, however, is found in no other condition.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Hemoglobin_H_HbH_Disease">
          <title>Hemoglobin H (HbH) Disease</title>
          <p><bold>Hemolytic anemias.</bold> HbH disease can be distinguished from other hemolytic anemias by: (1) microcytosis, which is uncommon in other forms of hemolytic anemia; (2) the fast-moving band (HbH) on hemoglobin electrophoresis; (3) the presence of inclusion bodies (precipitated HbH) in red blood cells after supravital stain; and (4) absence of morphologic or enzymatic changes characteristic of other forms of inherited hemolytic anemia (e.g., hereditary spherocytosis/elliptocytosis, G6PD deficiency). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="epb42-spherocytosis" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">EPB42</italic>-Related Hereditary Spherocytosis</related-object>.</p>
          <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="xlmr" document-type="chapter"><bold>Alpha-thalassemia X-linked intellectual disability (ATRX) syndrome</bold></related-object> is characterized by distinctive craniofacial features, genital anomalies, severe developmental delays, hypotonia, intellectual disability, and mild-to-moderate anemia secondary to alpha-thalassemia. Craniofacial abnormalities include small head circumference, telecanthus or widely spaced eyes, short nose, tented vermilion of the upper lip, and thick or everted vermilion of the lower lip with coarsening of the facial features over time. Although all individuals with ATRX syndrome have a normal 46,XY karyotype, genital anomalies range from hypospadias and undescended testicles to severe hypospadias and ambiguous genitalia, to normal-appearing female genitalia. Global developmental delays are evident in infancy and some affected individuals never walk independently or develop significant speech. Affected individuals do not reproduce. ATRX syndrome is caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> and inherited in an X-linked manner.</p>
          <p>An unknown percent of 46,XY individuals with ATRX syndrome have a mild form of HbH disease, evident as hemoglobin H inclusions (&#x003b2;<sub>4</sub> tetramers) in erythrocytes following incubation of fresh blood smears with 1% brilliant cresyl blue (BCB). In ATRX syndrome, the &#x003b1;-globin gene cluster and the HS-40 regulatory region of chromosome 16 are structurally intact.</p>
          <p>Acquired variants in <italic toggle="yes">ATRX</italic> can arise in myelodysplastic syndrome and cause an acquired form of HbH disease (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disor">Genetically Related Disorders</xref>, <bold>Acquired &#x003b1;-thalassemia</bold>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Carrier_States___Thalassemia_and">
          <title>Carrier States (&#x003b1;&#x000ba;-Thalassemia and &#x003b1;+-Thalassemia)</title>
          <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="b-thal" document-type="chapter"><bold>Beta-thalassemia</bold></related-object><bold>.</bold> Microcytosis and hypochromia are present in &#x003b1;&#x000ba;-thalassemia carriers, hematologically manifesting &#x003b1;<sup>+</sup>-thalassemia carriers, and &#x003b2;-thalassemia carriers; &#x003b2;-thalassemia carriers, however, are distinguished by a high percent of HbA2.</p>
          <p><bold>Iron deficiency anemia.</bold> Alpha-thalassemia trait can be confused with iron-deficiency anemia because MCV and MCH are lower than normal in both conditions. However, in iron deficiency anemia, the red blood cell count is decreased, while it is usually increased in &#x003b1;<sup>0</sup>-thalassemia carriers. Though some overlap with &#x003b1;-thalassemia carrier states exists, individuals with iron deficiency anemia show a marked increase in red blood cell distribution width (RDW), a quantitative measure of RBC anisocytosis. The RDW is usually normal or close to normal in thalassemia. The determination of the RBC zinc protoporphyrin concentration and iron studies (serum iron concentration, transferrin saturation) can be used to diagnose iron deficiency anemia with certainty. Iron deficiency and thalassemia can coexist, complicating diagnosis.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <p>In 2013, the Thalassemia International Federation published <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK190453/">Guidelines for the Management of Non Transfusion-Dependent Thalassemia (NTDT)</ext-link>, including beta-thalassemia intermedia, HbH disease and HbE/beta-thalassemia. Guidelines for the management of HbH disease with hemolytic crisis have been developed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.fucharoen.2009">Fucharoen &#x00026; Viprakasit 2009</xref>] (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://asheducationbook.hematologylibrary.org/content/2009/1/26.long">full text</ext-link>).</p>
        <sec id="a-thal.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Dia">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with alpha-thalassemia (&#x003b1;-thalassemia), the following phenotype-based evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <p><bold>Hemoglobin Bart hydrops fetalis (Hb Bart) syndrome.</bold> See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantat">Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</xref>.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Hemoglobin H (HbH) disease</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Differentiation of deletion (mild) from non-deletion (moderate-to-severe) forms of HbH disease by appropriate molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> is important at presentation because of varying severity.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consider referral to a hematologist.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consider consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p><bold>Hb Bart syndrome</bold> was previously considered a universally fatal condition, however, its prognosis is shifting because of prenatal diagnosis, intrauterine blood transfusions, improved transfusion strategies, and (rarely) curative hematopoietic stem cell transplant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.pecker.2017.151">Pecker et al 2017</xref>]. Although the Thalassemia International Guidelines recommend a transfusion strategy similar to &#x003b2;-thalassemia for these individuals; however, no reports on optimal transfusion management exist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.amid.2016.1208">Amid et al 2016</xref>]. Because few children with Hb Bart syndrome survive, clinical trials to assess these treatment approaches are lacking.</p>
          <p>The advances in intrauterine and postnatal therapy have resulted in ethical dilemmas for the family and health care provider.</p>
          <p><bold>HbH disease.</bold> Most individuals with HbH disease are clinically well and survive without any treatment.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Occasional red blood cell transfusions may be needed if the hemoglobin level suddenly drops because of hemolytic or aplastic crises.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Chronic red blood cell transfusions should be considered in selected individuals only. Clear indications for red blood cell transfusions are severe anemia affecting cardiac function and massive erythroid expansion, resulting in severe bone changes and extramedullary erythropoiesis. Note: These events are quite rare in HbH disease.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Iron chelation therapy may be needed in individuals with iron loading caused by regular blood transfusion, inappropriate iron therapy, or abnormal iron absorption.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Splenectomy should be performed only in individuals with massive splenomegaly or hypersplenism; the associated risks for severe, life-threatening sepsis and venous thrombosis should be considered.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Other complications, such as gallstones and leg ulcers, require appropriate medical or surgical treatment.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Prevention_of_Primary_Manifestati">
          <title>Prevention of Primary Manifestations</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Hb Bart syndrome</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Because of the severity of Hb Bart syndrome and the risk for maternal complications during the pregnancy with a fetus with this disorder, prenatal diagnosis and early termination of affected pregnancies is usually considered. Future studies on the functional outcomes of children with Hb Bart syndrome who have received chronic transfusion, intrauterine transfusions, and hematopoietic stem cell transplant, will allow physicians to improve the informed decision-making process for families weighing the risk-benefit profile of present treatment options.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complicat">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>
            <bold>HbH disease</bold>
          </p>
          <p>During febrile episodes, a clinical evaluation is recommended because of the increased risk of hemolytic/aplastic crisis (similar to G6PD deficiency, hemolysis in HbH disease can be triggered by infection or oxidative stresses).</p>
          <p>When chronic red blood cell transfusions are instituted for individuals with HbH disease, the management should be the same as for all individuals who have been polytransfused, including use of iron chelation therapy (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="b-thal" document-type="chapter">Beta-Thalassemia</related-object>).</p>
          <p>In individuals with HbH disease who are not red blood cell transfusion dependent, the only iron chelator specifically approved is deferasirox, which has been shown to be superior to placebo in reducing liver iron concentration in those older than age ten years who have beta-thalassemia intermedia, HbE/beta-thalassemia, and HbH disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.taher.2012.970">Taher et al 2012</xref>].</p>
          <p>Regular folic acid supplementation should be recommended, as for other hemolytic anemias.</p>
          <p>If splenectomy is required, antimicrobial prophylaxis is usually provided, at least until age five years, to decrease the risk of overwhelming sepsis caused by encapsulated organisms. Use of antimicrobial prophylaxis notwithstanding, a careful clinical evaluation of splenectomized individuals with fever is recommended.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>
            <bold>HbH disease</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Hematologic evaluation every six to 12 months to determine the steady state levels of hemoglobin</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In children, assessment of growth and development every six to 12 months</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Monitoring of iron load with annual determination of serum ferritin concentration in individuals who have been transfused, in older individuals, and in those given inappropriate iron supplementation. Since serum ferritin may underestimate the degree of iron overload, a periodic quantitative measurement of liver iron concentration is also recommended [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.musallam.2012.s16">Musallam et al 2012</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>
            <bold>HbH disease</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Inappropriate iron therapy</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Oxidant drugs including sulphonamides; some antimalarials because of the risk of hemolytic crisis</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>The sibs of a proband should be evaluated as soon as possible after birth to determine if they have HbH disease so that appropriate monitoring can be instituted. Evaluations can include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation of red blood cell indices, red blood cell supravital stain for HbH inclusions and hemoglobin analysis by HPLC</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Targeted molecular analysis if the pathogenic variants in the family are known</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic analysis (according to the frequency of &#x003b1;-globin gene pathogenic variants in each geographic area) if the pathogenic variants in the family are not known.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>During pregnancy several complications have been reported in women with HbH disease, including worsening of anemia (with occasional need of red cell transfusions), preeclampsia, congestive heart failure, and threatened miscarriage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.origa.2007.326">Origa et al 2007</xref>]. Monitoring for these possible complications is recommended.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="a-thal.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Alpha-thalassemia (&#x003b1;-thalassemia) is usually inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Risk_to_Family_Members__Hemoglobi">
          <title>Risk to Family Members &#x02013; Hemoglobin Bart Hydrops Fetalis (Hb Bart) Syndrome</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of a fetus with Hb Bart syndrome have &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Individuals with &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait typically have mild hypochromic (low MCH), microcytic (low MCV) anemia, and normal HbA2 and HbF.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> At conception, each sib of a proband with Hb Bart syndrome has a 25% chance of having Hb Bart syndrome, a 50% chance of having &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion in <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;), and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Hb Bart syndrome is often not compatible with postnatal life.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Other family members of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of having &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Individuals with &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait typically have mild hypochromic (low MCH), microcytic (low MCV) anemia, and normal HbA2 and HbF.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Risk_to_Family_Members__Hemoglobi_1">
          <title>Risk to Family Members &#x02013; Hemoglobin H (HbH) Disease</title>
          <p><bold>Parents of a proband.</bold> The parents of a child with HbH disease usually have different genotypes:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Most commonly, one parent has &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) and the other parent is an &#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier (1-gene deletion; -&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;). Rarely, one parent has &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) and the other parent is an &#x003b1;-thalassemia carrier with a non-deletion variant.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Alternatively, though less likely, one parent has &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) and the other parent has &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">trans</italic> (-&#x003b1;/-&#x003b1;). These parents have a 50% chance of having offspring with HbH disease and a 50% chance of having offspring with one-gene deletion (&#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier; -&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Uncommonly, both parents carry a specific <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> non-deletion &#x003b1;-thalassemia variant (e.g., &#x003b1;<sup>T</sup> Saudi, HBA2:c.*93_*94delAA)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Individuals with &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait typically have mild microcytosis and normal HbA2 and HbF.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Alpha-thalassemia silent carriers (loss of 1 &#x003b1;-globin gene) are either hematologically normal or have a mild reduction of MCV and MCH.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> At conception, each sib of an individual with HbH disease whose parents have the most common variants (1 parent has --/&#x003b1;&#x003b1; and the other parent has -&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) has a 25% chance of having HbH disease, a 25% chance of having &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;), a 25% chance of being an &#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier with loss of one &#x003b1;-globin gene, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Offspring of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Each child of an individual with HbH disease inherits a loss of two &#x003b1;-globin genes <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (&#x003b1;-thalassemia trait) or a loss of one &#x003b1;-globin gene (&#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier) and is thus an obligate heterozygote.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Given the high carrier rate of &#x003b1;-thalassemia in certain populations, it is appropriate to offer carrier testing to the reproductive partner of an individual with &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a loss of two &#x003b1;-globin genes <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Other family members of a proband with either Hb Bart syndrome or HbH disease.</bold> Each sib of the proband's parents is at risk of having loss of one &#x003b1;-globin gene (&#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier) and/or &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a loss of two &#x003b1;-globin genes <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Carrier_Detection">
          <title>Carrier Detection</title>
          <p>Individuals who should be considered for carrier testing:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Family members</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Members of ethnic groups at risk (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Prevalence">Prevalence</xref>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Gamete donors for assisted reproductive technologies (ART)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Alpha-thalassemia trait</bold> is associated with a moderate, thalassemia-like hematologic picture (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha">Table 4</xref>). Identification relies on molecular genetic testing of the &#x003b1;-globin genes, <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used">Table 3</xref>).</p>
          <p><bold>Alpha-thalassemia silent carriers</bold> may have normal hematologic findings or may have a moderate, thalassemia-like hematologic picture similar to individuals with &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha">Table 4</xref>). Identification relies on molecular genetic testing of the &#x003b1;-globin genes, <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used">Table 3</xref>).</p>
          <table-wrap id="a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 4. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Red Blood Cell Indices in Alpha-Thalassemia Trait and Silent Carrier</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_1">Red Blood Cell Indices</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Normal</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Carrier&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Male</th>
                  <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th>
                  <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha-Thalassemia Trait&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup><break/>(--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1; or -&#x003b1;/-&#x003b1;)</th>
                  <th headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha-Thalassemia Silent Carrier<break/>(-&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;)</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Mean corpuscular volume (MCV, fl)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.1&#x000b1;5.01</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.6&#x000b1;5.5</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.6&#x000b1;4.1</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.2&#x000b1;6.9</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH, pg)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9&#x000b1;1.9</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2&#x000b1;2.1</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9&#x000b1;1.3</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2&#x000b1;2.3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Hemoglobin (Hb, g/dL)</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9&#x000b1;1.0</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_2 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0&#x000b1;0.9</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: 13.9&#x000b1;1.7<break/>Female: 12.0&#x000b1;1.0</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_1_3 hd_h_a-thal.T.red_blood_cell_indices_in_alpha_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: 14.3&#x000b1;1.4<break/>Female: 12.6&#x000b1;1.2</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.4.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.higgs.2001_1">Higgs &#x00026; Bowden [2001]</xref>
                </p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p>2. Alpha-thalassemia carriers with the two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) have slightly lower RBC indices.</p>
          <p><bold>Qualitative and quantitative hemoglobin (Hb) analysis</bold> (by cellulose acetate electrophoresis, weak-cation high-performance liquid chromatography [HPLC], and supplemental techniques such as isoelectric focusing and citrate agar electrophoresis) identifies the amount and type of Hb present (<xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1">Table 5</xref>).</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Hemoglobin A (HbA). Two &#x003b1;-globin chains and two &#x003b2;-globin chains (&#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>&#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hemoglobin F (HbF). Two &#x003b1;-globin chains and two &#x003b3;-globin chains (&#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>2</sub>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hemoglobin H (HbH). Four &#x003b2;-globin chains (&#x003b2;<sub>4</sub>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hemoglobin A2 (HbA2). Two &#x003b1;-globin chains and two &#x003b4;-globin chains (&#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>&#x003b4;<sub>2</sub>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hemoglobin Bart (Hb Bart). Four &#x003b3;-globin chains (&#x003b3;<sub>4</sub>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hemoglobin Portland. Two &#x003b6;-globin chains and two &#x003b3;-globin chains (&#x003b6;<sub>2</sub>&#x003b3;<sub>2</sub>)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 5. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Hemoglobin Patterns in Alpha-Thalassemia Trait and Silent Carrier</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin Type</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha-thalassemia trait&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup><break/>(--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1; or -&#x003b1;/-&#x003b1;)</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha-thalassemia silent carrier&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup><break/>(-&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;)</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>HbA</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96%-98%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96%-98%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96%-98%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>HbF</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1.0%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>HbH</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>HbA2</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2%-3%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5%-3.0%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2%-3%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Hb Bart</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Hb Portland</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.hemoglobin_patterns_in_alphatha_1_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.5.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>Deletion or inactivation of two &#x003b1;-globin genes either in <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> configuration (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) or in <italic toggle="yes">trans</italic> configuration (-&#x003b1;/-&#x003b1;)</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="a-thal.TF.5.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>Deletion or inactivation of one &#x003b1;-globin gene (-&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;)</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Population_Screening">
          <title>Population Screening</title>
          <p><bold>Alpha-thalassemia trait with a loss of two</bold>
<bold>&#x003b1;-globin genes <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;).</bold> Because of the high carrier rate for the two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) in certain populations and the availability of genetic counseling and prenatal diagnosis, it is ideal to screen (prior to or early in pregnancy) couples who are members of at-risk populations to identify those at risk of conceiving a fetus with Hb Bart syndrome:</p>
          <p>If both members of a couple are carriers of an &#x003b1;&#x000ba;-thalassemia deletion variant (e.g., genotype --<sup>SEA</sup>/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;), all of their offspring have a 1/4 risk of having Hb Bart syndrome.</p>
          <p>If both members of the couple are carriers of the &#x003b1;&#x000ba;-thalassemia deletion variant in which both <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> as well as <italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic> are deleted (i.e., genotype &#x02013;<sup>FIL</sup>/&#x003b1;&#x003b1; or genotype &#x02013;<sup>THAI</sup>/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;), they are not at risk of having offspring with Hb Bart syndrome because homozygotes for such pathogenic variants are lost shortly after conception.</p>
          <p>If both members of the couple are carriers of a deletion involving both <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>, but only one of them has a deletion that extends into <italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic> (e.g., a couple with genotypes &#x02013;<sup>SEA</sup>/&#x003b1;&#x003b1; and &#x02013;<sup>FIL</sup>/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;), the couple is at risk of having offspring with Hb Bart syndrome because the single <italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic> in the fetus produces sufficient &#x003b6;-globin for fetal development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.chui.1998.2213">Chui &#x00026; Waye 1998</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Alpha-thalassemia silent carrier.</bold> Prospective identification of &#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carriers is not strongly indicated, as the offspring of these carriers are not at risk for Hb Bart syndrome.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="a-thal.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who have HbH disease, are carriers, or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantat">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p><bold>High-risk pregnancies.</bold> Prenatal testing is possible for couples confirmed by DNA analysis to be at risk of having a fetus with Hb Bart syndrome because both parents are carriers of a two-gene deletion <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (--/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;). Molecular genetic testing can be performed either on fetal DNA extracted from cells obtained by chorionic villus sampling or by amniocentesis.</p>
          <p><bold>Ultrasound examination.</bold> Ultrasonography can also be useful in the management of pregnancies at risk for Hb Bart syndrome. In the first trimester, increased nuchal thickness, particularly in an at-risk pregnancy, should prompt appropriate evaluation.</p>
          <p><bold>Indeterminate-risk pregnancies.</bold> An indeterminate-risk pregnancy is a pregnancy for which ONE of the following is true:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>One parent has &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a loss of two &#x003b1;-globin genes <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (e.g., --/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) and the other has an &#x003b1;-thalassemia-like hematologic picture but no &#x003b1;-thalassemia variant identified by molecular genetic testing.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The mother has known &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait with a loss of two &#x003b1;-globin genes <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> (e.g., --/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;) and the father is unknown or unavailable for testing. This is of concern if the father belongs to a population with a high carrier rate for &#x003b1;-thalassemia <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen">pathogenic variants</xref>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>In both cases, the options for prenatal testing should be discussed in the context of formal genetic counseling. In such cases, the strategy is fetal DNA analysis for the known &#x003b1;-thalassemia variant; if the known &#x003b1;-thalassemia variant is present, globin chain synthesis analysis is performed using a fetal blood sample obtained by percutaneous umbilical blood sampling (PUBS).</p>
          <p><bold>Preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)</bold> may be an option for some families in which the pathogenic variants have been identified.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="a-thal.HBA1_HBA2_and_HBZ">
          <title><italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic></title>
          <p>Alpha-globin genes are duplicated (<italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>) and lie in the telomeric region of chromosome 16 (16p13.3) within a cluster that also contains an embryonic &#x003b1;-like gene (<italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic>), and two pseudogenes (<italic toggle="yes">HBZP</italic> [&#x003c8;-&#x003b6;] and <italic toggle="yes">HBAP1</italic> [&#x003c8;-&#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>]). <italic toggle="yes">HBD</italic> (&#x003c8;-&#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>), previously considered a pseudogene, was recently demonstrated to produce mRNA, although a very little amount [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.goh.2005.1466">Goh et al 2005</xref>]. A &#x003b8; gene (<italic toggle="yes">HBQ1</italic>) with an unknown function is located at the 5' end of the cluster (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="a-thal.F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> are embedded within two markedly homologous regions that extend for approximately 4 kb. Their sequence homology is maintained by gene conversion and unequal crossover events. In this DNA region, three highly homologous segments, named X, Y, and Z, separated by non-homologous segments, have been defined (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="a-thal.F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
          <p>As a result of unequal genetic exchange, individuals who are phenotypically normal may have four, five, or six &#x003b1;-globin genes and two to six <italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic>-like genes. <italic toggle="yes">HBA</italic>-like globin genes are arranged in the cluster in the order in which they are expressed during development. The genes encoding the &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-globin chain <italic toggle="yes">(HBA1</italic>) and the &#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>-globin chain <italic toggle="yes">(HBA2</italic>) display a marked homology resulting from repeated rounds of gene conversion.</p>
          <p>The level of transcription of the two genes differs, as <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> produces two to three times more &#x003b1;-globin than <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>. Regarding the translation profile of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> mRNA and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> mRNA, contrasting results in which percentages of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> mRNA are higher or only slightly higher than percentages of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> mRNA have been reported. The different expression of the two &#x003b1;-globin genes has important clinical implications for the amount of structural &#x003b1;-variant resulting from inactivation of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>, and for the pathophysiology of the deletion and non-deletion pathogenic variants of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>.</p>
          <p>The expression of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> is regulated by a region (HS-40) located 40 kb upstream from the &#x003b1;-globin cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="a-thal.F2">Figure 2</xref>). This region contains multiple binding sites for transcriptional factors (NF-E2, GATA-1). The deletion of HS-40 results in an &#x003b1;-thalassemia phenotype, in spite of the structural integrity of both &#x003b1;-globin genes.</p>
          <sec id="a-thal.Gene_Structure">
            <title>Gene Structure</title>
            <p>Both <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> have three coding exons. The mRNAs produced by <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> have identical coding regions and can be distinguished only by their 3' UTR. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="a-thal" object-id="a-thal.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="a-thal.Pathogenic_Variants">
            <title>Pathogenic Variants</title>
            <p>See <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used">Table 3</xref>. Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and/or <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> is the most common cause of &#x003b1;-thalassemia.</p>
            <p><bold>Deletion of two &#x003b1;-goblin genes <italic toggle="yes">in</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>.</bold> Different deletions varying from approximately 6 kb to more than 300 kb and removing both &#x003b1;-globin genes <italic toggle="yes">(HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>) (and sometimes the embryonic <italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic> gene) result in the complete absence of &#x003b1;-chain production from that allele. Most of these deletions are founder variants that arose by one of several molecular mechanisms, including illegitimate recombination, reciprocal translocation, and truncation of chromosome 16. More than 20 different &#x003b1;&#x000ba;-thalassemia deletions have been reported to date:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>The most common alleles are the Southeast Asian (--<sup>SEA</sup>) and the Filipino (--<sup>FIL</sup>) types.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Two deletion alleles, -(&#x003b1;)<sup>5.2</sup> and -(&#x003b1;)<sup>20.5</sup>, remove <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and part of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.higgs.2001">Higgs 2001</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>A deletion removing <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and the theta gene (<italic toggle="yes">HBQ1</italic>) extends downstream centromeric from the &#x003b1;-globin gene cluster. The silencing of intact <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> in this chromosome is related to an antisense RNA transcribed from the widely expressed <italic toggle="yes">LUC7L</italic>, becoming juxtaposed to the normal <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> by the deletion, and running through the <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.tufarelli.2003.157">Tufarelli et al 2003</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Several deletions of the HS-40 region also result in the silencing of the intact &#x003b1;-globin genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.higgs.2001">Higgs 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.coelho.2010.147">Coelho et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.sollaino.2010.2193">Sollaino et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.wu.2016">Wu et al 2016</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Deletion of one &#x003b1;-goblin gene.</bold> Reciprocal recombination between the Z boxes, which are 3.7 kb apart, or between the X boxes, 4.2 kb apart, gives rise to chromosomes with a single &#x003b1;-globin gene. The two resulting &#x003b1;-thalassemia variants are referred to respectively as the 3.7-kb rightward deletion (-&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>) and the 4.2-kb leftward deletion (-&#x003b1;<sup>4.2</sup>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="a-thal.F2">Figure 2</xref>):</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>In relation to the location of the crossover within the Z box, the -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup> deletion is subdivided into three varieties named I, II, and III.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>In addition to the -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup> and the -&#x003b1;<sup>4.2</sup> common alleles, other rare deletions involving a single &#x003b1;-globin gene have been reported.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>These recombination events also result in the production of chromosomes containing three &#x003b1;-globin genes. A triplicated &#x003b1;-globin gene inherited with heterozygous &#x003b2;-thalassemia results in a mild thalassemia intermedia phenotype.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Non-deletion &#x003b1;-thalassemia.</bold> Less frequently, &#x003b1;-thalassemia results from single-nucleotide variants or oligonucleotide insertion/deletion in regions critical for &#x003b1;-globin gene expression. In non-deletion &#x003b1;-thalassemia, the affected gene is denoted T (e.g., &#x003b1;<sup>T</sup> Saudi). Considered as a group, the non-deletion &#x003b1;-thalassemia variants appear to have a more severe effect on &#x003b1;-globin gene expression and hematologic phenotype than single &#x003b1;-globin-gene deletions. This phenomenon may be explained by the majority of the variants affecting <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>, whose expression may predominate over <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.higgs.2001">Higgs 2001</xref>]. No compensatory increase in expression in the remaining functional &#x003b1; gene occurs when the other is inactivated by a single-nucleotide variant, in contrast to the compensatory increase in expression in the remaining functional &#x003b1; gene when a single &#x003b1;-globin gene is deleted (e.g., the - &#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup> deletion).</p>
            <p>At present, more than 70 well-defined causes of non-deletion &#x003b1;-thalassemia are listed in the public HGMD (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hgmd.org">www.hgmd.org</ext-link>).</p>
            <p>The molecular mechanisms leading to the silencing of either <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> include: variants involving RNA splicing, the polyadenylation signal, the initiation of mRNA translation, as well as missense variants of the termination, in-frame deletions, frame-shift variants, and nonsense variants. Variants of &#x003b1;-globin genes that result in the production of hyper-unstable globin variants such as Hb<sup>Quong Sze</sup> and that are unable to assemble into stable &#x003b2;<sub>4</sub> tetramers and are thus rapidly degraded, may also result in &#x003b1;-thalassemia (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen">Table 6</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.higgs.2001">Higgs 2001</xref>].</p>
            <p>The most common non-deletion variant, which is frequently seen in Southeast Asia, is Hb<sup>Constant Spring</sup> (Hb<sup>CS</sup>), resulting from a nucleotide change in the stop codon of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>. This variant leads to the production of an &#x003b1;-globin chain elongated by 31 amino acids. Hb<sup>CS</sup> is produced in very small amounts because its mRNA is unstable. Heterozygotes for Hb<sup>CS</sup> and other rare elongated variants, along with the presence of the Hb variant, result in &#x003b1;-thalassemia trait.</p>
            <p>Some of the variants causing &#x003b1;-chain structural variants may occur in a chromosome with only one &#x003b1;-globin gene (e.g., HbQ<sup>Thailand</sup>, HbG<sup>Philadelphia</sup>). For more information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="a-thal" object-id="a-thal.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>.</p>
            <table-wrap id="a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 6. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Selected <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> Pathogenic Variants</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change&#x000a0;<sup>1,&#x000a0;2</sup>
<break/>(Conventional Nomenclature&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup>)</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Common Name<sup>2</sup></th>
                    <th id="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: c.2T&#x0003e;C</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: p.Met1Thr</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;<sup>NcoI</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_4" rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=nuccore&#x00026;val=NM_000517.4">NM_000517.4</ext-link>
                      <break/>
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=protein&#x00026;id=4504345">NP_000508.1</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: c.377T&#x0003e;C</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: p.Leu126Pro<break/>(Alpha2 Leu125Pro)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb<sup>Quong Sze</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: c.427T&#x0003e;C</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: p.Ter143Glnext32<break/>(Alpha2 142, Stop&#x0003e;Gln)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb<sup>Constant Spring</sup> (Hb<sup>CS</sup>)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: c.94_95delAG</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: p.Arg32AspfsTer24<break/>(The deletion of 2 nucleotides causes a frameshift &#x00026; premature termination at codon [TAA])</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: c.[339C&#x0003e;G; 340_351delCTCCCCGCCGAG]</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: p.[His113Gln; Leu114_Glu117del]<break/>(Alpha2 His112Gln <italic toggle="yes">and</italic> deletion of codons 113-116 -Leu-Pro-Ala-Glu)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb<sup>Lleida</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_4" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=nuccore&#x00026;val=NM_000517.4">NM_000517.4</ext-link>
                      <break/>
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=protein&#x00026;id=4504345">NP_000508.1</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: c.95+2_95+6delTGAGG</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;<sup>HphI</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>: c.223G&#x0003e;C</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>: p.Asp75Gly<break/>(Asp74Gly)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb<sup>Q-Thailand</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=nuccore&#x00026;id=14456711">NM_000558.3</ext-link>
                      <break/>
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=protein&#x00026;val=4504347">NP_000549.1</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: c.207C&#x0003e;G<break/>or <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>: 207C&#x0003e;A</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>: p.Asn69Lys<break/>(Asn68Lys)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb<sup>G Philadelphia</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_4" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=nuccore&#x00026;val=NM_000517.4">NM_000517.4</ext-link>
                      <break/>
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=protein&#x00026;id=4504345">NP_000508.1</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>: c.*94A&#x0003e;G</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;<sup>T</sup>Saudi</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">HBA2:</italic> c.[-2_-3delAC; -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup>]&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and of nucleotides that additionally impair translation of the remaining <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_4" rowspan="8" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=nuccore&#x00026;id=1817575">Z84721.1</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x003b1;<sup>4.2</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-(&#x003b1;)<sup>5.2</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and 5&#x02019; end of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-(&#x003b1;)<sup>20.5</sup><break/>(g.15164_37864del22701)&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and 5&#x02019; end of <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>FIL</sup><break/>(g.11684_43534del31851)&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>MED</sup><break/>(g.24664_41064del16401)&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>SEA</sup><break/> (g.26264_45564del19301)&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;&#x02212;<sup>THAI</sup><break/>(g.10664_44164del33501)&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion of <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_a-thal.T.selected_hba1_and_hba2_pathogen_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
              <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn>
                  <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.6.1">
                  <label>1. </label>
                  <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.6.2">
                  <label>2. </label>
                  <p>Only functional globin genes involved in the deletion are given; deleted pseudogenes are not listed.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.6.3">
                  <label>3. </label>
                  <p>Globin variants are given by their conventional nomenclature (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://globin.cse.psu.edu/">globin.cse.psu.edu</ext-link>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.6.4">
                  <label>4. </label>
                  <p>Denotes two variations in one allele: deletion of AC at -2 and -3 before ATG initiation codon in <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic> configuration on an -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup> deletion allele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.viprakasit.2003.133">Viprakasit et al 2003</xref>]</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.6.5">
                  <label>5. </label>
                  <p>
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="a-thal.REF.pressley.1980.4889">Pressley et al [1980]</xref>
                  </p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="a-thal.TF.6.6">
                  <label>6. </label>
                  <p>Coordinates from entries in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://globin.cse.psu.edu">Globin Gene Server</ext-link>; it is not known if all deletions in these categories will have precisely the same nucleotide coordinates.</p>
                </fn>
              </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The &#x003b1;-globin chains produced by HBA1 and HBA2 mRNAs have identical amino acid sequences. The heterodimer protein hemoglobin A is made up of two &#x003b1; chains and two &#x003b2; chains.</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> The consequence of a deletion of one &#x003b1;-globin gene is reduced production of &#x003b1;-globin chains by the affected chromosome (&#x003b1;-thalassemia silent carrier; -&#x003b1;/&#x003b1;&#x003b1;). For example, measurement of &#x003b1;-globin mRNA indicates that the -&#x003b1;<sup>4.2</sup> variant is not associated with a compensatory increase in expression in the remaining <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>, whereas with the -&#x003b1;<sup>3.7</sup> variant, the remaining <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> expression is roughly halfway between that of normal <italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="a-thal.F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="a-thal.Published_GuidelinesConsensus_Sta">
          <title>Published Guidelines/Consensus Statements</title>
          <ref-list id="a-thal.Published_GuidelinesConsensus_Sta.reflist0">
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.acog_committee_on_obstetrics.2007.229">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <collab>ACOG Committee on Obstetrics</collab>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>ACOG Practice Bulletin No. 78: Hemoglobinopathies in pregnancy.</article-title>
                <source>Obstet Gynecol.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>109</volume>
                <fpage>229</fpage>
                <lpage>37</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17197616</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.fucharoen.2009">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="web">Fucharoen S, Viprakasit V. Hb H disease: clinical course and disease modifiers. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://asheducationbook.hematologylibrary.org/content/2009/1/26.long">online</ext-link>. 2009. Accessed 12-20-16</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.taher.2013">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="web">Taher A, Vichinsky E, Musallam K, Cappellini MD, Viprakasit V. <italic toggle="yes">Guidelines for the Management of Non Transfusion Dependent Thalassaemia</italic>. Weatherall D, ed. Thalassaemia International Federation. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK190453/">online</ext-link>. 2013. Accessed 12-21-16.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="a-thal.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.amid.2016.1208">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Amid</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brien</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kirby-Allen</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Odame</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2016</year>
                <article-title>Optimizing chronic transfusion therapy for survivors of hemoglobin Barts hydrops fetalis.</article-title>
                <source>Blood</source>
                <volume>127</volume>
                <fpage>1208</fpage>
                <lpage>11</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26732098</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.chui.2003.791">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chui</surname>
                    <given-names>DH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fucharoen</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chan</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Hemoglobin H disease: not necessarily a benign disorder.</article-title>
                <source>Blood</source>
                <volume>101</volume>
                <fpage>791</fpage>
                <lpage>800</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12393486</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.chui.1998.2213">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chui</surname>
                    <given-names>DH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Waye</surname>
                    <given-names>JS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998</year>
                <article-title>Hydrops fetalis caused by alpha-thalassemia: an emerging health care problem.</article-title>
                <source>Blood</source>
                <volume>91</volume>
                <fpage>2213</fpage>
                <lpage>22</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9516118</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.coelho.2010.147">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coelho</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pican&#x000e7;o</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seuanes</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seixas</surname>
                    <given-names>MT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Faustino</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010</year>
                <article-title>Novel large deletions in the human alpha-globin gene cluster: Clarifying the HS-40 long-range regulatory role in the native chromosome environment.</article-title>
                <source>Blood Cells Mol Dis</source>
                <volume>45</volume>
                <fpage>147</fpage>
                <lpage>53</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20580289</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.de_gobbi.2006.1215">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Gobbi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viprakasit</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hughes</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fisher</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Buckle</surname>
                    <given-names>VJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ayyub</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gibbons</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vernimmen</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoshinaga</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Jong</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cheng</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rubin</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wood</surname>
                    <given-names>WG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bowden</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Higgs</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>A regulatory SNP causes a human genetic disease by creating a new transcriptional promoter.</article-title>
                <source>Science.</source>
                <volume>312</volume>
                <fpage>1215</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16728641</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.fucharoen.2009.26">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fucharoen</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viprakasit</surname>
                    <given-names>V.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Hb H disease: clinical course and disease modifiers.</article-title>
                <source>Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <fpage>26</fpage>
                <lpage>34</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20008179</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.galanello.1992.1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Galanello</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aru</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dess&#x000ec;</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Addis</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Paglietti</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Melis</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cocco</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Massa</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Giagu</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barella</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Turco</surname>
                    <given-names>MP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maccioni</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cao</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1992</year>
                <article-title>HbH disease in Sardinia: molecular, hematological and clinical aspects.</article-title>
                <source>Acta Haematol.</source>
                <volume>88</volume>
                <fpage>1</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1414154</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.gibbons.2003.446">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gibbons</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pellagatti</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garrick</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wood</surname>
                    <given-names>WG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malik</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ayyub</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Langford</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boultwood</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wainscoat</surname>
                    <given-names>JS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Higgs</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Identification of acquired somatic mutations in the gene encoding chromatin-remodeling factor ATRX in the alpha-thalassemia myelodysplasia syndrome (ATMDS).</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>34</volume>
                <fpage>446</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12858175</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.gibson.2008.225">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gibson</surname>
                    <given-names>WT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harvard</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Qiao</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Somerville</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lewis</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rajcan-Separovic</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Phenotype-genotype characterization of alpha-thalassemia mental retardation syndrome due to isolated monosomy of 16p13.3.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A</source>
                <volume>146A</volume>
                <fpage>225</fpage>
                <lpage>32</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18076105</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.goh.2005.1466">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goh</surname>
                    <given-names>SH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>YT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhanu</surname>
                    <given-names>NV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cam</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Desper</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martin</surname>
                    <given-names>BM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moharram</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gherman</surname>
                    <given-names>RB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miller</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>A newly discovered human alpha-globin gene.</article-title>
                <source>Blood</source>
                <volume>106</volume>
                <fpage>1466</fpage>
                <lpage>72</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855277</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.harteveld.2007.283">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harteveld</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kriek</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bijlsma</surname>
                    <given-names>EK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Erjavec</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Balak</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Phylipsen</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Voskamp</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Capua</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>White</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Giordano</surname>
                    <given-names>PC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Refinement of the genetic cause of ATR-16.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>122</volume>
                <fpage>283</fpage>
                <lpage>92</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17598130</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.harteveld.2014.1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harteveld</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>State of the art and new developments in molecular diagnostics for hemoglobinopathies in multiethnic societies.</article-title>
                <source>Int J Lab Hematol</source>
                <volume>36</volume>
                <fpage>1</fpage>
                <lpage>12</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23721114</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.higgs.2001">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Higgs DR. Molecular mechanisms of alpha thalassemia. In: Steinberg MH, Forget PG, Higgs DR, Nagel RL, eds. <italic toggle="yes">Disorders of Hemoglobin: Genetics, Pathophysiology, and Clinical Management.</italic> Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press; 2001:405-30</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.higgs.2001_1">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Higgs DR, Bowden DK. Clinical and laboratory features of the alpha-thalassemia syndromes. In: Steinberg MH, Forget PG, Higgs DR, Nagel RL, eds. <italic toggle="yes">Disorders of Hemoglobin: Genetics, Pathophysiology, and Clinical Management.</italic> Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press; 2001:431-69.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.lehmann.1984.552">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lehmann</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrell</surname>
                    <given-names>RW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Nomenclature of the alpha-thalassaemias.</article-title>
                <source>Lancet.</source>
                <year>1984</year>
                <volume>1</volume>
                <fpage>552</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6199634</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.lindor.1997.451">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindor</surname>
                    <given-names>NM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valdes</surname>
                    <given-names>MG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wick</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thibodeau</surname>
                    <given-names>SN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jalal</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>De novo 16p deletion: ATR-16 syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>72</volume>
                <fpage>451</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9375730</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.lorey.2001.72">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lorey</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Charoenkwan</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Witkowska</surname>
                    <given-names>HE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lafferty</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patterson</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eng</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Waye</surname>
                    <given-names>JS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Finklestein</surname>
                    <given-names>JZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chui</surname>
                    <given-names>DH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>Hb H hydrops foetalis syndrome: a case report and review of literature.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Haematol</source>
                <volume>115</volume>
                <fpage>72</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11722414</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.musallam.2012.s16">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Musallam</surname>
                    <given-names>KM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cappellini</surname>
                    <given-names>MD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wood</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taher</surname>
                    <given-names>AT</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>Iron overload in non-transfusion-dependent thalassemia: a clinical perspective.</article-title>
                <source>Blood Rev</source>
                <volume>26</volume>
                <supplement>Suppl 1</supplement>
                <fpage>S16</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22631036</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.origa.2007.326">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Origa</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sollaino</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Giagu</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barella</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Campus</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mandas</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bina</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Perseu</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Galanello</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Clinical and molecular analysis of haemoglobin H disease in Sardinia: haematological, obstetric and cardiac aspects in patients with different genotypes.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Haematol.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>136</volume>
                <fpage>326</fpage>
                <lpage>32</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17129226</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.pecker.2017.151">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pecker</surname>
                    <given-names>LH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Guerrera</surname>
                    <given-names>MF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Loechelt</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Massaro</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abraham</surname>
                    <given-names>AA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fasano</surname>
                    <given-names>RM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meier</surname>
                    <given-names>ER</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Homozygous &#x003b1;-thalassemia: Challenges surrounding early identification, treatment, and cure.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer.</source>
                <year>2017</year>
                <volume>64</volume>
                <fpage>151</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27573913</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.piel.2014.1908">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Piel</surname>
                    <given-names>FB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Weatherall</surname>
                    <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>The &#x003b1;-thalassemias.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>371</volume>
                <fpage>1908</fpage>
                <lpage>16</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25390741</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.pressley.1980.4889">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pressley</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Higgs</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aldridge</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Metaxatou-Mavromati</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clegg</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Weatherall</surname>
                    <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1980</year>
                <article-title>Characterisation of a new alpha thalassemia 1 defect due to a partial deletion of the alpha globin gene complex.</article-title>
                <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>4889</fpage>
                <lpage>98</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6255436</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.sollaino.2010.2193">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sollaino</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Paglietti</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Loi</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Congiu</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Podda</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Galanello</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010</year>
                <article-title>Homozygous deletion of the major alpha-globin regulatory element (MCS-R2) responsible for a severe case of hemoglobin H disease.</article-title>
                <source>Blood</source>
                <volume>116</volume>
                <fpage>2193</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20864588</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.steensma.2005.443">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steensma</surname>
                    <given-names>DP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gibbons</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Higgs</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Acquired alpha-thalassemia in association with myelodysplastic syndrome and other hematologic malignancies.</article-title>
                <source>Blood</source>
                <volume>105</volume>
                <fpage>443</fpage>
                <lpage>52</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15358626</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.steensma.2004a.2019">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steensma</surname>
                    <given-names>DP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Higgs</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fisher</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gibbons</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004a</year>
                <article-title>Acquired somatic ATRX mutations in myelodysplastic syndrome associated with alpha thalassemia (ATMDS) convey a more severe hematologic phenotype than germline ATRX mutations.</article-title>
                <source>Blood</source>
                <volume>103</volume>
                <fpage>2019</fpage>
                <lpage>26</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592816</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.steensma.2004b.1518">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steensma</surname>
                    <given-names>DP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viprakasit</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hendrick</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goff</surname>
                    <given-names>DK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leach</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gibbons</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Higgs</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004b</year>
                <article-title>Deletion of the alpha-globin gene cluster as a cause of acquired alpha-thalassemia in myelodysplastic syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Blood</source>
                <volume>103</volume>
                <fpage>1518</fpage>
                <lpage>20</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576055</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.taher.2012.970">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taher</surname>
                    <given-names>AT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Porter</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viprakasit</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kattamis</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chuncharunee</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sutcharitchan</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Siritanaratkul</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Galanello</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Karakas</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lawniczek</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ros</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Habr</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cappellini</surname>
                    <given-names>MD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>Deferasirox reduces iron overload significantly in nontransfusion-dependent thalassemia: 1-year results from a prospective, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study.</article-title>
                <source>Blood.</source>
                <volume>120</volume>
                <fpage>970</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22589472</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.tufarelli.2003.157">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tufarelli</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stanley</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garrick</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sharpe</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ayyub</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wood</surname>
                    <given-names>WG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Higgs</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Transcription of antisense RNA leading to gene silencing and methylation as a novel cause of human genetic disease.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>34</volume>
                <fpage>157</fpage>
                <lpage>65</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730694</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.vaeusorn.1985">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">Vaeusorn O, Fucharoen S, Ruangpiroj T, et al. Fetal pathology and maternal morbidity in hemoglobin Bart's hydrops fetalis: an analysis of 65 cases. Bangkok, Thailand: First International Conference on Thalassemia. 1985.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.viprakasit.2003.133">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viprakasit</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ayyub</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>May</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Dinucleotide deletion in -alpha3.7 allele causes a severe form of alpha+ thalassemia.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Haematol</source>
                <volume>71</volume>
                <fpage>133</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12890155</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="a-thal.REF.wu.2016">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wu</surname>
                    <given-names>MY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>He</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yan</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>DZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A novel selective deletion of the major &#x003b1;-globin regulatory element (MCS-R2) causing &#x003b1;-thalassemia.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Haematol.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <month>Feb</month>
                <day>25</day>
                <comment>Epub ahead of print</comment>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26915575</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="a-thal.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="a-thal.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Antonio Cao, MD (1929-2012)</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Antonio Cao, MD, Professor of Pediatrics at Cagliari University (Italy), was a world-renowned expert in the field of pediatrics and genetics. He was best known for his leadership role in understanding, diagnosing, preventing, and treating thalassemia. Among other honors, he received the Allan Award from the American Society of Human Genetics (1993) and the M&#x000e4;rta Philipson's Award for Progress in Paediatrics, given by the Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm (2000). Professor Cao was passionate about science and new discoveries, intuitive, demanding, and extremely innovative in his research; all of us in this field &#x02013; and our patients &#x02013; are deeply indebted to him for his work and his inspiration will continue to guide us in the years ahead.&#x02014; Renzo Galanello, MD</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Renzo Galanello, MD (1948-2013)</bold>
          </p>
          <p>Renzo Galanello, MD, Professor of Pediatrics at the University of Cagliari (Italy) was internationally recognized as an expert in the field of thalassemia, to which he contributed hundreds of papers. He was the right arm of his mentor Professor Antonio Cao in the program of thalassemia control in Sardinia. He defined the theoretical criteria, flow charts and practical actuation of the carrier screening for thalassemia as a prerequisite to prenatal diagnosis. The efficacy of the screening, tightly linked to the development of improved methods of prenatal diagnosis, led to the near-eradication of beta-thalassemia in Sardinia, establishing a model of disease control that was adopted in numerous other countries worldwide. Lately, he was among the leading scientists in the clinical validation of novel oral chelators and diagnostic assessment of cardiac iron overload. Dr Galanello was a member of national and international scientific societies and editorial committees of hematology journals, and scientific advisor of the Thalassemia International Federation, which expressed well the sad feelings of his friends and colleagues with the following commemorative words: "Professor Galanello, you will be greatly missed, but indeed all you have left behind as a doctor and a person will never be forgotten, will remain in the books, in the literature, in our minds but very importantly in our hearts."</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Author_History">
          <title>Author History</title>
          <p>Antonio Cao, MD; Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche (2005-2012)Renzo Galanello, MD; Ospedale Regionale Microcitemie (2005-2013)Paolo Moi, MD (2013-present)Raffaella Origa, MD (2013-present)</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="a-thal.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>29 December 2016 (sw) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>21 November 2013 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>7 June 2011 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>14 July 2008 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>1 November 2005 (me) Review posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>3 January 2005 (rg) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="a-thal.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Diagnostic algorithm for hemoglobinopathies</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="a-thal-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="a-thal.F2" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Diagram of the &#x003b1;-globin gene cluster. In order from centromere to telomere, the genes include: &#x003b1;1 (<italic toggle="yes">HBA1</italic>, encoding &#x003b1;1-globin); &#x003b1;2 (<italic toggle="yes">HBA2</italic>, encoding &#x003b1;2-globin); &#x003c8;&#x003b1;1, <italic toggle="yes">HBD</italic> (previously called &#x003c8;&#x003b1;2), &#x003c8;&#x003b6;1, and &#x003b6;2 (<italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic>, encoding &#x003b6;2-globin). &#x003c8;&#x003b1;1, <italic toggle="yes">HBD</italic> (previously called &#x003c8;&#x003b1;2), and &#x003c8;&#x003b6;1 were all considered pseudogenes. Recently, very low levels of HBD mRNA has been detected in cord blood, adult blood, and bone marrow. HS-40 is a <italic toggle="yes">cis</italic>-acting regulatory element located 40 kb upstream of <italic toggle="yes">HBZ</italic>. X, Y, and Z are homologous regions separated by non-homologous DNA regions; they constitute evolutionary duplication units. During meiosis, misalignment of chromosome homologs followed by reciprocal recombination at X, Y, or Z results in deletion-duplication events, i.e., the loss of a single &#x003b1;-globin gene on one chromosome and the triplication of &#x003b1;-globin genes on the other chromosome.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="a-thal-Image002" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
