<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="dguok-mtddepl" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">dguok-mtddepl</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Deoxyguanosine Kinase Deficiency</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: DGUOK Deficiency; <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Hepatocerebral Form</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>El-Hattab</surname>
            <given-names>Ayman W</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, FAAP, FACMG</degrees>
          <aff>Division of Clinical Genetics and Metabolic Disorders<break/>Pediatric Department<break/>Tawam Hospital<break/>Al-Ain, United Arab Emirates</aff>
          <email>elhattabaw@yahoo.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Scaglia</surname>
            <given-names>Fernando</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, FAAP, FACMG</degrees>
          <aff>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics<break/>Baylor College of Medicine<break/>Houston, Texas</aff>
          <email>fscaglia@bcm.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wong</surname>
            <given-names>Lee-Jun</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics<break/>Baylor College of Medicine<break/>Houston, Texas</aff>
          <email>ljwong@bcm.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="dent" document-type="chapter">Dent Disease</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="dmtn" document-type="chapter">Diabetes Mellitus, 6q24-Related Transient Neonatal</related-object>
      <abstract id="dguok-mtddepl.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>The two forms of deoxyguanosine kinase (DGUOK) deficiency are a neonatal multisystem disorder and an isolated hepatic disorder that presents later in infancy or childhood. The majority of affected individuals have the multisystem illness with hepatic disease (jaundice, cholestasis, hepatomegaly, and elevated transaminases) and neurologic manifestations (hypotonia, nystagmus, and psychomotor retardation) evident within weeks of birth. Those with isolated liver disease may also have renal involvement and some later develop mild hypotonia. Progressive hepatic disease is the most common cause of death in both forms.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>Reduced mitochondrial (mt) DNA copy number in liver or muscle can be used to confirm mtDNA depletion. Detection of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> establishes the diagnosis of DGUOK deficiency.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Care is best provided by a multidisciplinary team. Children with cholestatic liver disease may require formulas with enriched medium-chain-triglyceride content and fractional meals with enteral nutrition at night for adequate nutrition. Ongoing monitoring of gross motor development and skills with the intervention of appropriate therapies is appropriate in these children. Liver transplantation is controversial because of the frequent severe neurologic involvement due to the underlying mitochondrial disease.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> Avoidance of nutritional deficiencies; adherence to normal immunization schedule.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Routine monitoring of hepatic function, nutritional status, gross motor development and skills, and urine for proteinuria and aminoaciduria.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>DGUOK deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Carrier testing for at-risk relatives, prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk, and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible if the <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> pathogenic variants in the family are known.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of deoxyguanosine kinase (DGUOK) deficiency (<italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>-related hepatocerebral mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome) should be suspected in individuals with a combination of the following clinical, supportive laboratory, and liver biopsy findings.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Clinical features</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Multisystem disease.</bold> Neonatal-onset progressive liver disease (jaundice, cholestasis, hepatomegaly, and elevated transaminases) and neurologic manifestations (hypotonia, nystagmus, and psychomotor retardation)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Isolated hepatic disease.</bold> Later-infantile or childhood-onset hepatic disease that is progressive and/or induced by viral illness</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Supportive laboratory findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Lactic acidosis and hypoglycemia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Elevated transaminases alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In some cases, elevated serum gammaglutamyltransferase (GGT), alpha fetoprotein (AFP), and ferritin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008b.330">Dimmock et al 2008b</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In most cases, plasma amino acid profile showing elevated tyrosine, phenylalanine, and methionine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.leanza.2008.16437">Leanza et al 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.mudd.2012.228">Mudd et al 2012</xref>].</p>
              <p>Note: (1) Elevated serum concentration of tyrosine or phenylalanine can be detected on newborn screening in the majority of neonates with multisystem DGUOK deficiency. (2) Infants with DGUOK deficiency do not excrete succinylacetone in the urine, whereas urinary excretion of succinylacetone is diagnostic for <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="tyrosinemia" document-type="chapter">tyrosinemia type 1</related-object>. (3) When transient, elevation of serum concentration of tyrosine may be falsely attributed to transient tyrosinemia of the newborn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.lee.2009.55">Lee et al 2009</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Liver biopsy findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Liver histology typically reveals cholestasis, but may show microsteatosis, fibrosis, giant cell hepatitis, or cirrhosis. Electron microscopy may reveal an increase in the number of mitochondria and abnormal cristae, findings common to all hepatocerebral mtDNA depletion syndromes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008b.330">Dimmock et al 2008b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.alhussaini.2014">Al-Hussaini et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Mitochondrial DNA content in liver tissue of affected individuals is typically less than 20% of matched control mtDNA content. Liver typically shows a combined deficiency of electron transport chain (ETC) complexes I, III, and IV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008b.330">Dimmock et al 2008b</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of DGUOK deficiency is established in a proband by the identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> on molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing approaches can include a combination of <bold>gene-targeted testing</bold> (multi-gene panel or single-gene testing) and <bold>genomic testing</bold> (comprehensive genomic sequencing) depending on the phenotype.</p>
          <p>Gene-targeted testing requires the clinician to determine which gene(s) are likely involved, whereas genomic testing does not. Because the phenotype of mtDNA depletion syndromes is broad, children with the distinctive clinical and laboratory findings of neonatal multisystem disease are likely to be diagnosed using gene-targeted testing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dguok-mtddepl.Option_1">Option 1</xref>), whereas the phenotype of those with isolated hepatic disease may be indistinguishable from many inherited disorders with liver disease and thus is more likely to be diagnosed using genomic testing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dguok-mtddepl.Option_2">Option 2</xref>).</p>
          <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Option_1">
            <title>Option 1</title>
            <p>When the phenotypic and laboratory findings suggest the diagnosis of neonatal multisystem disease due to DGUOK deficiency, molecular genetic testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold> or use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> is performed first. If only one pathogenic variant is found, gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis is performed next.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dguok-mtddepl.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of the condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting secondary findings. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing based tests.</p>
                <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Option_2">
            <title>Option 2</title>
            <p>When the phenotype is indistinguishable from many other inherited disorders with liver disease, molecular genetic testing approaches can include a combination of <bold>genomic testing</bold> (comprehensive genomic sequencing) or <bold>gene-targeted testing</bold> (multi-gene panel):</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Comprehensive genome sequencing</bold> (when clinically available) includes exome sequencing and genome sequencing. For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dguok-mtddepl.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may be considered.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <table-wrap id="dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 1. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Hepatocerebral Form</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                    <th id="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with Pathogenic<break/>Variants&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~95%&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~5%&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
              <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn id="dguok-mtddepl.TF.1.1">
                  <label>1. </label>
                  <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dguok-mtddepl" object-id="dguok-mtddepl.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="dguok-mtddepl.TF.1.2">
                  <label>2. </label>
                  <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dguok-mtddepl.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="dguok-mtddepl.TF.1.3">
                  <label>3. </label>
                  <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="dguok-mtddepl.TF.1.4">
                  <label>4. </label>
                  <p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hgmd.cf.ac.uk/">The Human Gene Mutation Database</ext-link> (HGMD)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="dguok-mtddepl.TF.1.5">
                  <label>5. </label>
                  <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
                </fn>
              </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Deoxyguanosine kinase (DGUOK) deficiency presents in the majority of affected individuals as neonatal multisystem disease and in the minority of affected individuals later in infancy or childhood as isolated hepatic disease.</p>
          <p>Affected sibs sharing the same pathogenic variants have exhibited multisystem disease and isolated hepatic disease with divergent long-term outcomes. Similarly, diverse long-term outcomes have been observed in affected individuals from unrelated families harboring the same pathogenic variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.tadiboyina.2005.289">Tadiboyina et al 2005</xref>].</p>
          <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Neonatal_Multisystem_Disea">
            <title>Neonatal Multisystem Disease</title>
            <p>Most affected infants have lactic acidosis and hypoglycemia in the first week of life. Within weeks of birth, all infants with this form of disease have hepatic disease and neurologic dysfunction.</p>
            <p>Neurologic manifestations include hypotonia, psychomotor retardation, and typical rotary nystagmus developing into opsoclonus. Neurologic features, particularly profound hypotonia, significant psychomotor retardation, and nystagmus, are associated with poor long-term outcome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008a.1480">Dimmock et al 2008a</xref>].</p>
            <p>Brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is usually normal. However, subtentorial abnormal myelination and globus pallidus hyperintensity have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.brahimi.2009.221">Brahimi et al 2009</xref>].</p>
            <p>Liver involvement includes jaundice, cholestasis, hepatomegaly, and elevated transaminases. Hepatic dysfunction progresses in the majority of children, causing neonatal- or infantile-onset liver failure with ascites, edema, and coagulopathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008b.330">Dimmock et al 2008b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.alhussaini.2014">Al-Hussaini et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.sezer.2015.124">Sezer et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.mckiernan.2016.592">McKiernan et al 2016</xref>].</p>
            <p>The prognosis for neonatal multisystem disease is poor: most affected children die of liver failure before age four years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.sezer.2015.124">Sezer et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Isolated_Hepatic_Disease">
            <title>Isolated Hepatic Disease</title>
            <p>A minority of affected children initially presents in infancy or childhood with isolated hepatic disease manifesting as jaundice, cholestasis, hepatomegaly, and elevated transaminases. Compared to neonatal multisystem disease, this form is associated with a less severe and later-onset liver disease. The liver disease, occasionally induced by a viral illness, is typically progressive and can lead to liver failure. However, hepatic disease has undergone reversal in one individual with isolated liver disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.mousson_de_camaret.2007.377">Mousson de Camaret et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008b.330">Dimmock et al 2008b</xref>].</p>
            <p>One individual with isolated liver disease subsequently developed hepatocellular carcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.freisinger.2006.1129">Freisinger et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.grabhorn.2014.464">Grabhorn et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p>Although neurologic manifestations are typically absent, long-term follow up suggests that individuals with isolated hepatic disease may subsequently develop mild hypotonia and some may also have renal involvement manifest as proteinuria and aminoaciduria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008a.1480">Dimmock et al 2008a</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Other less frequent manifestations.</bold> The following variable phenotypes have occasionally been reported:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Non-cirrhotic portal hypertension with onset during infancy or childhood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.vilarinho.2016.1977">Vilarinho et al 2016</xref>]</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Neonatal hemochromatosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.hanchard.2011.262">Hanchard et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.pronicka.2011.61">Pronicka et al 2011</xref>]</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Adult-onset myopathy presenting with limb weakness, ophthalmoplegia, and ptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.ronchi.2012.3404">Ronchi et al 2012</xref>]</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Juvenile-onset myopathy presenting with weakness and fatigability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.buchaklian.2012.92">Buchaklian et al 2012</xref>]</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.GenotypePhenotype_Correlat">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>No clear genotype/phenotype correlation is evident among individuals with <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> pathogenic missense variants. Affected sibs with the same <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> missense variants have exhibited divergent long-term outcomes. Similarly, diverse long-term outcomes have been observed in affected individuals from unrelated families harboring the same missense variants. These findings suggest that in individuals with pathogenic missense variants, the genotype and/or family history may not be helpful in predicting long-term outcome.</p>
          <p>In contrast, two null variants have been typically associated with multisystem disease and a more severe clinical phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008b.330">Dimmock et al 2008b</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>No large population-based studies have evaluated the prevalence of mtDNA depletion in general or DGUOK deficiency specifically. DGUOK deficiency is one of the most common causes of hepatocerebral mtDNA depletion syndromes and is estimated to account for 15%-20% of all mtDNA depletion cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.sezer.2015.124">Sezer et al 2015</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Genetically_Related_Alleli">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Multisystem_Disease">
          <title>Multisystem Disease</title>
          <p>The neonatal multisystem form of DGUOK deficiency needs to be differentiated from other mtDNA depletion syndromes, a genetically and clinically heterogeneous group of autosomal recessive disorders that are characterized by a severe reduction in mtDNA content leading to impaired energy production in affected tissues and organs. <xref ref-type="table" rid="dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet">Table 3</xref> includes the currently known mtDNA depletion syndromes.</p>
          <p>Mitochondrial DNA depletion syndromes occur as a result of defects in mtDNA maintenance caused by pathogenic variants in nuclear genes that function in either mitochondrial nucleotide synthesis (<italic toggle="yes">TK2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">TYMP</italic>) or mtDNA replication (<italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TWNK</italic> [formerly <italic toggle="yes">C10orf2</italic>]).</p>
          <p>Mitochondrial DNA depletion syndromes are phenotypically classified into hepatocerebral, encephalomyopathic, neurogastrointestinal, and myopathic forms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.elhattab.2013.186">El-Hattab &#x00026; Scaglia 2013</xref>].</p>
          <table-wrap id="dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndromes</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenotype</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome #, Type</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_1" rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Hepato-<break/>cerebral&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, hepatocerebral type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4A, Alpers type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="alpers" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic>-Related Disorders</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">MPV17</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6<italic toggle="yes">,</italic> hepatocerebral type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mpv17-mtdep" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">MPV17</italic>-Related Hepatocerebral Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">TWNK</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C10orf2)</italic></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7, hepatocerebral type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/271245">271245</ext-link></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_1" rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Encephalo-<break/>myopathic&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, encephalomyopathic type w/methylmalonic aciduria</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="sucla2-def" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Encephalomyopathic Form with Methylmalonic Aciduria</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">FBXL4</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13, encephalomyopathic type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fbxl4-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">FBXL4</italic>-Related Encephalomyopathic Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9, encephalomyopathic type w/methylmalonic aciduria</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="suclg1-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Encephalomyopathic Form with Methylmalonic Aciduria</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8A, encephalomyopathic type w/renal tubulopathy</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rrm2b-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>-Related Mitochondrial Disease</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">OPA1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14, encephalocardiomyopathic type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/616896">616896</ext-link></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Neurogastro-<break/>intestinal&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">TYMP</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, MNGIE type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mngie" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial Neurogastrointestinal Encephalopathy Disease</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4B, MNGIE type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="alpers" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic>-Related Disorders</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8B, MNGIE type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rrm2b-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>-Related Mitochondrial Disease</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_1" rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Myopathic&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">TK2</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, myopathic type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="tk2-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">TK2</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Myopathic Form</related-object>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">AGK</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10, cardiomyopathic type (Sengers syndrome)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/212350">212350</ext-link></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">MGME1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11, myopathic type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/615084">615084</ext-link></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">SLC25A4</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12B, cardiomyopathic type</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dguok-mtddepl.T.mitochondrial_dna_deplet_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/615418">615418</ext-link></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="dguok-mtddepl.TF.3.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See hyperlinked <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> or OMIM phenotype entry for more information.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dguok-mtddepl.TF.3.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>Within each phenotypic category, mtDNA depletion syndromes are ordered by relative prevalence.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Isolated_Hepatic_Disease_1">
          <title>Isolated Hepatic Disease</title>
          <p>The differential diagnosis of the isolated hepatic form of DGUOK deficiency involves other genetic and non-genetic age-specific causes of cholestatic liver diseases, including the following.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Genetic causes</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="alagille" document-type="chapter">Alagille syndrome</related-object>
              </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="cf" document-type="chapter">Cystic fibrosis</related-object>
              </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="galactosemia" document-type="chapter">Galactosemia</related-object>
              </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="tyrosinemia" document-type="chapter">Tyrosinemia type 1</related-object>
              </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="citrin" document-type="chapter">Citrin deficiency</related-object>
              </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Inborn errors of bile acid synthesis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="alpha1-a" document-type="chapter">Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency</related-object>
              </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="npc" document-type="chapter">Niemann-Pick disease type C</related-object>
              </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="lal-def" document-type="chapter">Acid lipase deficiency (Wolman disease)</related-object>
              </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Peroxisomal biogenesis disorders (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rcdp" document-type="chapter">Rhizomelic Chondrodysplasia Punctata Type 1</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pbd" document-type="chapter">Zellweger Syndrome Spectrum</related-object>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pfic" document-type="chapter">Progressive familial intrahepatic cholestasis</related-object>
              </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Non-genetic causes</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Extrahepatic biliary atresia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Choledochal cyst</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hypothyroidism</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Total parenteral nutrition (TPN) cholestasis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Neonatal hemochromatosis</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Evaluations_Following_Init">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with DGUOK deficiency, the following evaluations are recommended.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>For both neonatal multisystem diseases and isolated hepatic disease</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation of hepatic status by a physician familiar with the care of children with liver failure. Initial testing should include measurement of serum concentrations of ALT, AST, GGT, bilirubin, albumin, and coagulation profile.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hepatic sonography and AFP to screen for hepatocellular carcinoma. AFP is a sensitive, but not specific, marker used to differentiate hepatocellular carcinoma from nonmalignant liver disease. Although the value of a highly elevated serum concentration of AFP in the detection of hepatocellular carcinoma in DGUOK deficiency is not known, the possibility of hepatocellular carcinoma should be considered in individuals with a solid tumor detected by abdominal ultrasound examination <italic toggle="yes">and</italic> a highly increased serum AFP concentration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.freisinger.2006.1129">Freisinger et al 2006</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Nutritional assessment by a dietician with experience in managing children with hepatic failure</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Additional evaluation for neonatal multisystem diseases</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Measurement of plasma lactate and fasting blood sugar</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Comprehensive neurologic examination and developmental/cognitive assessment. Neuroimaging may be considered.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Additional evaluation for isolated hepatic disease.</bold> Urine analysis and evaluation for urine amino acids to evaluate for renal involvement</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Treatment_of_Manifestation">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Management requires a multidisciplinary team including specialists in hepatology, neurology, child development, nutrition, and clinical genetics.</p>
          <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Management_of_Neurologic_M">
            <title>Management of Neurologic Manifestations in Neonatal Multisystem Disease</title>
            <p>Hypotonia may be significant. Therefore, ongoing monitoring of gross motor development and skills with the intervention of appropriate therapies is appropriate in these children.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Management_of_Liver_Involv">
            <title>Management of Liver Involvement in both Neonatal Multisystem Disease and Isolated Hepatic Disease</title>
            <p>Management of liver disease should be guided by the results of initial evaluation in consultation with a hepatologist.</p>
            <p>Children with cholestatic liver disease or renal disease are at significant risk of nutritional insufficiency; therefore, a dietician with experience in managing children with hepatic and renal dysfunctions should be involved in their care:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Formulas with an enriched medium-chain-triglyceride content may provide better nutritional support for infants with cholestasis than formulas with predominantly long-chain triglycerides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.feranchak.2007">Feranchak &#x00026; Sokol 2007</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Cornstarch may reduce symptomatic hypoglycemia in individuals with isolated hepatic disease.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Fractional meals and enteral nutrition during the night can result in good nutritional control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008b.330">Dimmock et al 2008b</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Affected individuals often develop life-threatening liver failure, but the benefits of liver transplantation are disputable because of the frequent severe neurologic involvement due to the underlying mitochondrial disease. A total of 14 individuals with DGUOK deficiency were reported to have undergone liver transplantation.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>The one-year survival rate was 64%.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Five of the 14 survived longer than five years.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Eight of the 14 died within two years of transplantation from severe pulmonary hypertension (3/8), neurologic degeneration (2/8), procedure-related complications (2/8), and early postoperative multi-organ failure (1/8).</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Although survival after liver transplantation for DGUOK deficiency is lower than survival after liver transplantation for other indications, a significant proportion of affected individuals survived more than five years despite initial neurologic abnormalities. Nevertheless, a decision to perform liver transplantation for individuals with DGUOK deficiency remains difficult because neurologic manifestations may occur and/or worsen after liver transplantation despite their absence before transplantation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.grabhorn.2014.464">Grabhorn et al 2014</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Prevention_of_Secondary_Co">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Nutritional deficiencies such as essential fatty acid deficiency and fat-soluble vitamin deficiency need to be prevented. Specific management requires a dietician experienced in the management of individuals with liver disease. Affected individuals need to be supplemented with fat-soluble vitamins and essential fatty acids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.feranchak.2007">Feranchak &#x00026; Sokol 2007</xref>].</p>
          <p>Because they have not been associated with clinical decompensation in persons with DGUOK deficiency, routine immunizations (including influenza vaccine) are recommended at this time for all individuals with DGUOK deficiency and their household contacts.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>No clinical guidelines for surveillance are available. The following evaluations are suggested, with frequency varying according to the severity of the condition.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Neonatal multisystem disease:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Hepatic function</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Nutritional status</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Developmental and neurologic assessment</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>AFP and hepatic sonography to monitor for hepatocellular carcinoma.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Isolated hepatic disease</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Hepatic function</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Nutritional status</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Evidence of renal disease (proteinuria and aminoaciduria)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>AFP and hepatic sonography to monitor for hepatocellular carcinoma</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dguok-mtddepl.Related_Genetic_Counseling">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Therapies_Under_Investigat">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Deoxyguanosine kinase (DGUOK) deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected child are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> pathogenic variant).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> The offspring of an individual with DGUOK deficiency would be obligate heterozygotes (carriers) for a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>. To date, however, fertility is unknown, as no affected individuals have reproduced.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier of a <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Carrier_Heterozygote_Detec">
          <title>Carrier (Heterozygote) Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> pathogenic variants in the family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Related_Genetic_Counseling">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>Although penetrance of DGUOK deficiency is probably complete, age of onset and severity of the clinical symptoms vary, even in the same family.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are carriers or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preim">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for DGUOK deficiency are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> The gene is approximately 33 kb in size and consists of seven coding exons. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dguok-mtddepl" object-id="dguok-mtddepl.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
        <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> There are no common pathogenic variants or mutation hot spots [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008b.330">Dimmock et al 2008b</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> Deoxyguanosine kinase (DGUOK) is a mitochondrial protein that has a molecular weight of 28 kd with 277 amino acids.</p>
        <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Missense, nonsense, and splice-site variants result in a reduction or absence of DGUOK enzyme activity, which causes an imbalance of the mitochondrial deoxynucleotide pools. Because the mitochondria depend heavily on the salvage pathway for the supply of deoxynucleotides, DGUOK deficiency results in mitochondrial DNA depletion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dguok-mtddepl.REF.ashley.2007.1400">Ashley et al 2007</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="dguok-mtddepl.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.alhussaini.2014">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Al-Hussaini A, Faqeih E, El-Hattab AW, Alfadhel M, Asery A, Alsaleem B, Bakhsh E, Ali A, Alasmari A, Lone K, Nahari A, Eyaid W, Al Balwi M, Craig K, Butterworth A, He L, Taylor RW. Clinical and molecular characteristics of mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome associated with neonatal cholestasis and liver failure. J Pediatr. 2014;164:553-9.e1-2.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.ashley.2007.1400">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ashley</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adams</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Slama</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeviani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Suomalainen</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Andreu</surname>
                    <given-names>AL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Naviaux</surname>
                    <given-names>RK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Poulton</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Defects in maintenance of mitochondrial DNA are associated with intramitochondrial nucleotide imbalances.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>16</volume>
                <fpage>1400</fpage>
                <lpage>11</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483096</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.brahimi.2009.221">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brahimi</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jambou</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sarzi</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Serre</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boddaert</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Romano</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Lonlay</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Slama</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munnich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>R&#x000f6;tig</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonnefont</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lebre</surname>
                    <given-names>AS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The first founder DGUOK mutation associated with hepatocerebral mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>97</volume>
                <fpage>221</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19394258</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.buchaklian.2012.92">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Buchaklian</surname>
                    <given-names>AH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Helbling</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ware</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dimmock</surname>
                    <given-names>DP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Recessive deoxyguanosine kinase deficiency causes juvenile onset mitochondrial myopathy.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>107</volume>
                <fpage>92</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22622127</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008a.1480">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dimmock</surname>
                    <given-names>DP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dunn</surname>
                    <given-names>JK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feigenbaum</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rupar</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horvath</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Freisinger</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mousson de Camaret</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wong</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Abnormal neurological features predict poor survival and should preclude liver transplantation in patients with deoxyguanosine kinase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Liver Transpl.</source>
                <year>2008a</year>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>1480</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18825706</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.dimmock.2008b.330">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dimmock</surname>
                    <given-names>DP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dionisi-Vici</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrozzo</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shieh</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tang</surname>
                    <given-names>LY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Truong</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schmitt</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sifry-Platt</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lucioli</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santorelli</surname>
                    <given-names>FM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ficicioglu</surname>
                    <given-names>CH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wierenga</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Enns</surname>
                    <given-names>GM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Longo</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lipson</surname>
                    <given-names>MH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vallance</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Craigen</surname>
                    <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wong</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Clinical and molecular features of mitochondrial DNA depletion due to mutations in deoxyguanosine kinase.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>2008b</year>
                <volume>29</volume>
                <fpage>330</fpage>
                <lpage>1</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18205204</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.elhattab.2013.186">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>El-Hattab</surname>
                    <given-names>AW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA depletion syndromes: review and updates of genetic basis, manifestations, and therapeutic options.</article-title>
                <source>Neurotherapeutics.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>186</fpage>
                <lpage>98</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23385875</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.feranchak.2007">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Feranchak A, Sokol R. Medical and nutritional management of cholestasis in infants and children. In: Suchy FJ, Sokol RJ, Balistreri WF, eds. <italic toggle="yes">Liver Disease in Children</italic>. 3 ed. New York, NY: Cambridge University Press; 2007:190-231.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.freisinger.2006.1129">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Freisinger</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>F&#x000fc;tterer</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lankes</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gempel</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berger</surname>
                    <given-names>TM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spalinger</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoerbe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schwantes</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindner</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santer</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burdelski</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Setzer</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Walker</surname>
                    <given-names>UA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horv&#x000e1;th</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Hepatocerebral mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome caused by deoxyguanosine kinase (DGUOK) mutations.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Neurol.</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>63</volume>
                <fpage>1129</fpage>
                <lpage>34</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16908739</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.grabhorn.2014.464">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grabhorn</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsiakas</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Herden</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fischer</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Freisinger</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marquardt</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ganschow</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Briem-Richter</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santer</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Long-term outcomes after liver transplantation for deoxyguanosine kinase deficiency: a single-center experience and a review of the literature.</article-title>
                <source>Liver Transpl.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>464</fpage>
                <lpage>72</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24478274</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.hanchard.2011.262">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hanchard</surname>
                    <given-names>NA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shchelochkov</surname>
                    <given-names>OA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roy</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wiszniewska</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Popek</surname>
                    <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Karpen</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wong</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Deoxyguanosine kinase deficiency presenting as neonatal hemochromatosis.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>103</volume>
                <fpage>262</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21478040</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.leanza.2008.16437">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leanza</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ferraro</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reichard</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bianchi</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Metabolic interrelations within guanine deoxynucleotide pools for mitochondrial and nuclear DNA maintenance.</article-title>
                <source>J Biol Chem.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>283</volume>
                <fpage>16437</fpage>
                <lpage>45</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417473</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.lee.2009.55">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>NC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dimmock</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hwu</surname>
                    <given-names>WL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tang</surname>
                    <given-names>LY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>WC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chinault</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wong</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Simultaneous detection of mitochondrial DNA depletion and single-exon deletion in the deoxyguanosine gene using array-based comparative genomic hybridisation.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Dis Child.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>94</volume>
                <fpage>55</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19103789</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.mckiernan.2016.592">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McKiernan</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ball</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santra</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Foster</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fratter</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Poulton</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Craig</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McFarland</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rahman</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hargreaves</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gupte</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sharif</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>RW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Incidence of primary mitochondrial disease in children younger than 2 years presenting with acute liver failure.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>63</volume>
                <fpage>592</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27482763</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.mousson_de_camaret.2007.377">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mousson de Camaret</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taanman</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Padet</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chassagne</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayen&#x000e7;on</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clerc-Renaud</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mandon</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zabot</surname>
                    <given-names>MT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lachaux</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bozon</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Kinetic properties of mutant deoxyguanosine kinase in a case of reversible hepatic mtDNA depletion.</article-title>
                <source>Biochem J.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>402</volume>
                <fpage>377</fpage>
                <lpage>85</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17073823</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.mudd.2012.228">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mudd</surname>
                    <given-names>SH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wagner</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Luka</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stabler</surname>
                    <given-names>SP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Allen</surname>
                    <given-names>RH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schroer</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wood</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wong</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Two patients with hepatic mtDNA depletion syndromes and marked elevations of S-adenosylmethionine and methionine.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>105</volume>
                <fpage>228</fpage>
                <lpage>36</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22137549</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.pronicka.2011.61">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pronicka</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>W&#x00119;glewska-Jurkiewicz</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taybert</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pronicki</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Szyma&#x00144;ska-D&#x00119;bi&#x00144;ska</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Karkuci&#x00144;ska-Wi&#x00119;ckowska</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jak&#x000f3;bkiewicz-Banecka</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kowalski</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Piekutowska-Abramczuk</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pajdowska</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Socha</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sykut-Cegielska</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>W&#x00119;grzyn</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Post mortem identification of deoxyguanosine kinase (DGUOK) gene mutations combined with impaired glucose homeostasis and iron overload features in four infants with severe progressive liver failure.</article-title>
                <source>J Appl Genet.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>52</volume>
                <fpage>61</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21107780</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.ronchi.2012.3404">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ronchi</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garone</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bordoni</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gutierrez Rios</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calvo</surname>
                    <given-names>SE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ripolone</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ranieri</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rizzuti</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Villa</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Magri</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Corti</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bresolin</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mootha</surname>
                    <given-names>VK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moggio</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Comi</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sciacco</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Next-generation sequencing reveals DGUOK mutations in adult patients with mitochondrial DNA multiple deletions.</article-title>
                <source>Brain.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>135</volume>
                <fpage>3404</fpage>
                <lpage>15</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23043144</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.sezer.2015.124">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sezer</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oz&#x000e7;ay</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Balci</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alehan</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Novel deoxyguanosine kinase gene mutations in the hepatocerebral form of mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Child Neurol.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>30</volume>
                <fpage>124</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24423689</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.tadiboyina.2005.289">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tadiboyina</surname>
                    <given-names>VT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rupar</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Atkison</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feigenbaum</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kronick</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hegele</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Novel mutation in DGUOK in hepatocerebral mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome associated with cystathioninuria.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>135</volume>
                <fpage>289</fpage>
                <lpage>91</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15887277</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dguok-mtddepl.REF.vilarinho.2016.1977">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vilarinho</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sari</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yilmaz</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stiegler</surname>
                    <given-names>AL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boggon</surname>
                    <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jain</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Akyol</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dalgic</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>G&#x000fc;nel</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lifton</surname>
                    <given-names>RP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Recurrent recessive mutation in deoxyguanosine kinase causes idiopathic noncirrhotic portal hypertension.</article-title>
                <source>Hepatology.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>63</volume>
                <fpage>1977</fpage>
                <lpage>86</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26874653</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Author_History">
          <title>Author History</title>
          <p>David Dimmock, MD; Medical College of Wisconsin (2009-2016)Ayman W El-Hattab, MD, FAAP, FACMG (2016-present)Fernando Scaglia, MD, FAAP, FACMG (2009-present)Lee-Jun Wong, PhD (2009-present)</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dguok-mtddepl.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>22 December 2016 (bp) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>18 June 2009 (et) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>10 February 2009 (fs) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
