<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="gsd9" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">gsd9</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Phosphorylase Kinase Deficiency</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: Glycogen Storage Disease Type IX, GSDIX, PhK Deficiency, Phosphorylase b Kinase Deficiency</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Goldstein</surname>
            <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Biochemical Genetics Laboratory<break/>Duke University Medical Center<break/>Durham, North Carolina</aff>
          <email>golds018@mc.duke.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Austin</surname>
            <given-names>Stephanie</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <aff>Clinical Genetics<break/>Department of Pediatrics<break/>Duke University Medical Center<break/>Durham, North Carolina</aff>
          <email>stephanie.austin@duke.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kishnani</surname>
            <given-names>Priya</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Clinical Genetics<break/>Department of Pediatrics<break/>Duke University Medical Center<break/>Durham, North Carolina</aff>
          <email>kishn001@mc.duke.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bali</surname>
            <given-names>Deeksha</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Biochemical Genetics Laboratory<break/>Duke University Medical Center<break/>Durham, North Carolina</aff>
          <email>bali0001@mc.duke.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2011-05-31" date-type="created">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="prs" document-type="chapter">Phosphoribosylpyrophosphate Synthetase Superactivity</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="pitt-hopkins" document-type="chapter">Pitt-Hopkins Syndrome</related-object>
      <abstract id="gsd9.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Phosphorylase kinase (PhK) deficiency causing glycogen storage disease type IX (GSD IX) results from deficiency of the enzyme phosphorylase b kinase, which has a major regulatory role in the breakdown of glycogen. The two types of PhK deficiency are <italic toggle="yes">liver PhK deficiency</italic> (characterized by early childhood onset of hepatomegaly and growth retardation, and often, but not always, fasting ketosis and hypoglycemia) and <italic toggle="yes">muscle PhK deficiency</italic>, which is considerably rarer (characterized by any of the following: exercise intolerance, myalgia, muscle cramps, myoglobinuria, and progressive muscle weakness). Symptoms and biochemical abnormalities of liver PhK deficiency are thought to improve with age.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The enzyme PhK comprises four copies each of four subunits (&#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, &#x003b3;, and &#x003b4;). Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1,</italic> encoding subunit &#x003b1;, cause the rare X-linked disorder muscle PhK deficiency; pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2,</italic> also encoding subunit &#x003b1;, cause the most common form, liver PhK deficiency (X-linked liver glycogenosis); pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB,</italic> encoding subunit &#x003b2;, cause autosomal recessive PhK deficiency in both liver and muscle; and pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2,</italic> encoding subunit &#x003b3;, cause autosomal recessive liver PhK deficiency. Diagnosis is based on clinical findings, assay of PhK activity in erythrocytes, or liver or muscle tissues (depending upon presentation) and confirmatory findings on molecular genetic testing.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Liver PhK deficiency: hypoglycemia can be prevented with frequent daytime feedings that are high in complex carbohydrates and protein. When hypoglycemia or ketosis is present, Polycose<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> or fruit juice is given orally as tolerated or glucose by IV. Liver manifestations (e.g., cirrhosis, liver failure, portal hypertension) are managed symptomatically. Muscle PhK deficiency: Physical therapy based on physical status and function; optimization of blood glucose concentrations by a metabolic nutritionist based on activity.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of primary manifestations:</italic> Liver PhK deficiency: Diet high in complex carbohydrates and protein to prevent hypoglycemia and ketosis if present. Muscle PhK deficiency: Little published information is available.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> Liver PhK deficiency: IV glucose infusion preoperatively for elective procedures followed by intraoperative and post-operative IV glucose infusion to prevent hypoglycemia; malignant hyperthermia precautions when general anesthesia is required.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Liver PhK deficiency: Regular evaluation by a metabolic physician and a metabolic nutritionist. Monitoring of blood glucose concentration and blood ketones routinely as well as during times of stress (e.g., illness, intense activity, rapid growth, puberty) and reduced food intake. In children younger than age 18 years, liver ultrasound examination should be performed every 12 to 24 months. With increasing age, CT or MRI using intravenous contrast should be considered to evaluate for complications of liver disease. Muscle PhK deficiency: Regular evaluation by a metabolic physician, a metabolic nutritionist, and physical therapist.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Liver PhK deficiency: Large amounts of simple sugars as they will increase liver storage of glycogen; prolonged fasting; high-impact contact sports if significant hepatomegaly is present; drugs known to cause hypoglycemia such as insulin and insulin secretogogues (the sulfonylureas); alcohol (which may predispose to hypoglycemia). Muscle PhK deficiency: Vigorous exercise; medications like succinylcholine and statins that can cause rhabdomyolysis.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> Molecular genetic testing (if the family-specific pathogenic variants are known) and/or evaluation by a metabolic physician (if the family-specific pathogenic variants are not known) allow early diagnosis and treatment for sibs at increased risk for liver PhK deficiency.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Pregnancy management:</italic> Dietary management to maintain euglycemia throughout pregnancy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>-related liver PhK deficiency and <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic>-related muscle PhK deficiency are inherited in an X-linked manner. <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>-related liver and muscle PhK deficiency and <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>-related liver PhK deficiency are inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">X-linked inheritance</italic>: If the mother is a carrier, the chance of transmitting it in each pregnancy is 50%. Males who inherit the pathogenic variant will be affected; females who inherit the pathogenic variant will be carriers. Affected males pass the pathogenic variant to all of their daughters and none of their sons. Carrier testing for at-risk female relatives and prenatal testing for pregnancies at risk are possible if the pathogenic variant in the family has been identified.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">Autosomal recessive inheritance</italic>: At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Carrier testing for at-risk relatives and prenatal testing for pregnancies at risk are possible if the pathogenic variants in the family have been identified.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="gsd9.GeneReview_Scope">
        <title><italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> Scope</title>
        <table-wrap id="gsd9.Tc" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_gsd9.Tc_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphorylase Kinase Deficiency: Included Phenotypes</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.Tc_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Liver phosphorylase kinase deficiency</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Muscle phosphorylase kinase deficiency</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>For synonyms and outdated names see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.Nomenclature">Nomenclature</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Phosphorylase kinase deficiency causing glycogen storage disease type IX (GSD IX) results from deficiency of the enzyme phosphorylase b kinase (PhK), an enzyme with a key regulatory role in the breakdown of glycogen. Deficiency of this enzyme, which comprises four copies each of four subunits (&#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, &#x003b3;, and &#x003b4;), results in considerable clinical variability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.chen.2001">Chen 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.kishnani.2010">Kishnani &#x00026; Chen 2010</xref>].</p>
        <p>For the purposes of this review, phosphorylase kinase (PhK) deficiency has been divided into: liver PhK deficiency and muscle PhK deficiency (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gsd9.F1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s">Table 1</xref>). Liver PhK deficiency is further divided into three subtypes based on the gene in which pathogenic variants occur (<italic toggle="yes">PHKB, PHKA2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>) and inheritance pattern. It should be noted that pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> result in PhK deficiency both in liver and muscle. However, the symptoms from muscle involvement can be mild or absent; thus, this subtype may be clinically indistinguishable from the liver PhK deficiencies caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>.</p>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>-related PhK deficiency is also known as X-linked liver glycogenosis (XLG) and is divided into two biochemical subtypes, XLG1 and XLG2, depending on enzyme activity in various tissues.</p>
        <table-wrap id="gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Table 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Phosphorylase Kinase (PhK) Enzyme Subunits and Genes that Encode Them</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th>
                <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of all GSD IX</th>
                <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tissue Affected</th>
                <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme Subunit</th>
                <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOI</th>
                <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Exons</th>
                <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" colspan="7" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Associated with PhK deficiency</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~17%&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup> muscle PhK deficiency</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XL</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~75% liver PhK deficiency</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XL</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muscle and liver&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalytic</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6 hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" colspan="7" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Not known to be associated with PhK deficiency</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">PHKG1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalytic</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">CALM1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory; calcium binding</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">CALM2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory; calcium binding</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">CALM3</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory; calcium binding</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>MOI = mode of inheritance</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="gsd9.TF.1.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>The genetic basis of muscle PhK deficiency appears to be heterogeneous. A pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> was found in one of six persons screened [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003a.516">Burwinkel et al 2003a</xref>]. None of the remaining affected individuals had pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PHKG1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">CALM1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">CALM2</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">CALM3</italic> (encoding calmodulin), <italic toggle="yes">PYGM</italic> (encoding muscle glycogen phosphorylase), or <italic toggle="yes">PRKAG2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PRKAG3</italic> (encoding the liver and muscle regulatory gamma 3 subunit of AMP-dependent kinase which may, directly or indirectly, affect PhK activity).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="gsd9.TF.1.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>Despite PhK deficiency in muscle in individuals with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>, symptoms of muscle disease may not be present in childhood and this condition may be clinically indistinguishable from other liver PhK deficiencies caused primarily by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <sec id="gsd9.Liver_PhK_Deficiency">
          <title>Liver PhK Deficiency</title>
          <p>The three subtypes of liver PhK deficiency, caused by pathogenic variants in three different genes (<italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>), cannot be distinguished by their clinical features, which can range from mild to severe.</p>
          <p>Liver PhK deficiency should be suspected in a child with:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Hepatomegaly</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Growth retardation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Fasting ketosis and hypoglycemia</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Blood / serum</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Liver transaminases are elevated</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Triglycerides and cholesterol may be mildly elevated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.tuchman.1986.627">Tuchman et al 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.willems.1990.268">Willems et al 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.morava.2005.703">Morava et al 2005</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Fasting hyperketosis and hypoglycemia, if present, can range from mild to severe</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Uric acid and lactic acid concentrations are usually normal, but can be elevated in some affected individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.morava.2005.703">Morava et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Glucagon response is normal in most, but not all, affected individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.baussan.1981.107">Baussan et al 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.dunger.1982.384">Dunger &#x00026; Leonard 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.gray.1983.107">Gray et al 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.van_den_berg.1990.442">Van den Berg &#x00026; Berger 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.willems.1990.268">Willems et al 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003b.834">Burwinkel et al 2003b</xref>]. In controls, glucagon stimulates glycogenolysis and thus causes a rise in blood glucose concentrations.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Liver histology</bold> usually shows distended hepatocytes as a result of excess glycogen accumulation. Septal fibrosis and low-grade inflammatory changes may also be seen. Rarely, liver cirrhosis and adenomas have been reported; so far these findings have been found in persons with <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> pathogenic variants only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.chen.2001">Chen 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.kishnani.2010">Kishnani &#x00026; Chen 2010</xref>]. However, liver cirrhosis may also be associated with pathogenic variants in other genes that encode PhK subunits, such as <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> [Author, personal observation].</p>
          <p><bold>Liver glycogen content.</bold> Biochemical testing of snap-frozen liver biopsy tissue shows remarkably elevated glycogen content with normal glycogen structure.</p>
          <p><bold>Phosphorylase b kinase (PhK)</bold>
<bold>activity</bold> is reduced in liver, erythrocytes, and leukocytes of most (not all) individuals with liver PhK deficiency.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Normal PhK activity in erythrocytes is 1.0 &#x003bc;mol/min/g hemoglobin and in liver it is 0.1 &#x003bc;mol/min/mg protein.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Abnormal range is lower than 10% of normal level in the tissue being tested.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Muscle PhK activity is normal in individuals with pathogenic variants in either <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> and can be deficient in those with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>.</p>
          <p>Notes: (1) PhK is a labile enzyme that is highly sensitive to handling conditions and temperature exposure; thus, it is recommended that patient blood samples be accompanied by a control blood sample drawn at the same time from an unrelated individual. Samples need to be kept cold (4<sup>0</sup> C) at all times including during transport. (2) In a subset of affected individuals, in vitro PhK activity is normal or even elevated in erythrocytes and leukocytes and variable in liver. Most of these persons have a <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> pathogenic variant (XLG2 biochemical subtype; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.Testing_Strategy">Testing Strategy</xref>); however, elevated PhK activity in blood cells has also been associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> and could potentially result from variants in other genes as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997b.170">Burwinkel et al 1997b</xref>]. (3) Assay of PhK activity on snap-frozen liver biopsy tissue can help with diagnosis of liver PhK deficiency irrespective of which gene is mutated; however, normal PhK activity in liver does not rule out the diagnosis of liver PhK deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.keating.1985.609">Keating et al 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1994.620">Hendrickx et al 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1996.649">Hendrickx et al 1996</xref>; Author, personal observation]. (4) Because the enzyme PhK activates the enzyme glycogen phosphorylase b to the active form, phosphorylase a, activity of total phosphorylase could be reduced in individuals with PhK deficiency. Because primary deficiency of muscle or liver glycogen total phosphorylase causes GSD V and VI, respectively, low total phosphorylase activity in individuals with PhK deficiency could lead to a misdiagnosis of GSD V (if muscle symptoms are present) or GSD VI (if liver symptoms are present). Therefore, simultaneous assessment of PhK activity and total phosphorylase activity in liver or muscle biopsy, along with glycogen content, is recommended to permit accurate interpretation of test results. (5) PhK deficiency may be secondary to a different, primary metabolic defect. For example, deficient PhK activity in some individuals with Fanconi-Bickel syndrome or pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PRKAG2</italic> may be a secondary phenomenon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1999.240">Burwinkel et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2005.1034">Burwinkel et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.akman.2007.499">Akman et al 2007</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Muscle_PhK_Deficiency">
          <title>Muscle PhK Deficiency</title>
          <p>Muscle PhK deficiency with a confirmed pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> has been found in only six individuals. It should be suspected in any individual ranging in age from childhood to adulthood with any of the following findings:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Exercise intolerance</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Myalgia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Muscle cramps</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Myoglobinuria</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Progressive muscle weakness</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Serum concentration</bold> of creatine kinase may be above the upper limits of normal. Note: Normal ranges tend to be laboratory specific.</p>
          <p><bold>Forearm ischemic exercise test</bold> is usually normal (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="gsd5" document-type="chapter">Glycogen Storage Disease V</related-object> for details about this test), indicating that glycogenolysis is normal under maximal exercise (anaerobic) conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.haller.2008.1872">Haller 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF._rngreen.2008.1876">&#x000d8;rngreen et al 2008</xref>]. In contrast, conditions of submaximal exercise (cycle test) resulted in blunted glycogen breakdown in one individual who was studied. This suggests that PhK plays a larger role in the activation of muscle glycogen phosphorylase b (myophosphorylase) during submaximal exercise than during maximal exercise. During maximal exercise, metabolites such as AMP, inosine monophosphate, and inorganic phosphate may be sufficient for activation of myophosphorylase b [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF._rngreen.2008.1876">&#x000d8;rngreen et al 2008</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Electromyography</bold> is usually normal.</p>
          <p><bold>Muscle histology</bold> shows excessive amounts of subsarcolemmal glycogen accumulation.</p>
          <p><bold>Muscle glycogen content</bold> measured biochemically is always elevated with normal glycogen structure.</p>
          <p><bold>Phosphorylase b kinase (PhK)</bold>
<bold>enzyme activity</bold> is markedly reduced in muscle but normal in liver, blood cells, and fibroblasts. Because the enzyme PhK activates the enzyme glycogen phosphorylase in muscle, the activity of glycogen phosphorylase (phosphorylase-a) may be reduced in muscle in individuals with muscle PhK deficiency.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Molecular_Genetic_Testing">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Testing</title>
          <p><bold>Genes.</bold> The enzyme phosphorylase kinase (PhK) is made up of four subunits (&#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, &#x003b3;, and &#x003b4;) encoded by eight independent genes located either on the X chromosome or various autosomes. Of these eight genes, four are known to harbor pathogenic variants that cause PhK enzyme deficiency (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>The two X-linked genes are:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKA1,</italic> which causes the rare disorder X-linked muscle PhK deficiency;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2,</italic> which causes the most common form of liver PhK deficiency, also known as X-linked liver glycogenosis (XLG).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>The two autosomal genes are:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKB,</italic> which causes PhK deficiency in both liver and muscle but manifests primarly with liver symptoms with or without muscle involvement;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKG2,</italic> which causes PhK deficiency in liver.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Evidence for locus heterogeneity</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Other genes encoding subunits of the enzyme PhK, such as <italic toggle="yes">PHKG1</italic> and the muscle exon of <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> (exon 26), are considered to be candidates for muscle PhK deficiency; to date, however, no pathogenic variants have been identified in these genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003b.834">Burwinkel et al 2003b</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The three genes encoding calmodulin (<italic toggle="yes">CALM1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">CALM 2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">CALM3</italic>) are ubiquitously expressed and are candidates for PhK deficiency in liver or muscle; to date, no pathogenic variants have been reported in the literature (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="gsd9.T.phosphorylase_kinase_phk_enzyme_s">Table 1</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Clinical testing</bold>
          </p>
          <p>
            <bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> (X-linked)</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Sequence analysis of the coding region and associated intronic regions of genomic DNA.</bold> Data are not yet available on variant detection frequency for sequence analysis of these two genes [Author, communication].</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic>.</bold> In one study a pathogenic variant was found in only one of six individuals with PhK deficiency in muscle, suggesting that other factors (e.g., a pathogenic variant in another gene or genes or falsely low PhK activity due to sample handling conditions) may be involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003b.834">Burwinkel et al 2003b</xref>].</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>.</bold> The detection frequency for pathogenic variants is unknown but expected to be close to 100% in males.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Note: Lack of amplification by PCR prior to sequence analysis can suggest a putative exonic or whole-gene deletion on the X chromosome in an affected male; confirmation may require additional testing by deletion/duplication analysis. Sequence analysis cannot detect deletion of an exon(s) or a whole gene (large deletion) on an X chromosome in a carrier female.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Deletion/duplication analysis</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic>.</bold> No deletions or duplications have been reported; thus, the variant detection frequency is unknown.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>.</bold> Deletion of exon(s) has been reported in individuals with liver PhK deficiency. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.fukao.2007.179">Fukao et al [2007]</xref> reported a deletion extending from intron 19 to intron 26.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> (autosomal recessive)</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Sequence analysis of the coding region and associated intronic regions</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>.</bold> The variant detection frequency may be somewhat lower than 100% because deletions of exon(s) that are not detectable by sequence analysis have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997b.170">Burwinkel et al 1997b</xref>].</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>.</bold> The variant detection frequency is not known but is expected to be close to 100%.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Deletion/duplication analysis</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>.</bold> An exon deletion has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997b.170">Burwinkel et al 1997b</xref>], but the detection frequency for this test method is unknown.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>.</bold> No deletions or duplications have been reported; thus, the variant detection frequency of <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> deletion/duplication analysis is unknown.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: As yet, no pathogenic variants have been reported in <italic toggle="yes">PHKG1</italic>, the gene encoding the muscle-expressed gamma subunit of PhK..</p>
          <table-wrap id="gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 2. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Phosphorylase Kinase Deficiency</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup>
<break/>(MOI)</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variants Detected&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variant Detection Frequency by Test Method&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> (XL)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence variants</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~100%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None to date&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> (XL)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence variants</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon or whole-gene deletions</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> (AR)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence variants</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon or whole-gene deletions</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> (AR)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence variants</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~100%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None to date&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_gsd9.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_test_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>MOI = mode of inheritanceXL=X-linkedAR= autosomal recessive1. See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="gsd9" object-id="gsd9.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein. 2. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants.3. The ability of the test method used to detect a variant that is present in the indicated gene.4. In this X-linked gene, sequence analysis can detect small intragenic deletions/insertions, missense, nonsense, and splice-site variants in males and females. Lack of amplification by PCR prior to sequence analysis can suggest a putative exon or whole-gene deletion on the X chromosome in affected males; confirmation may require additional testing by deletion/duplication analysis. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>. 5. Testing that identifies deletions/duplications not readily detectable by sequence analysis of the coding and flanking intronic regions of genomic DNA; included in the variety of methods that may be used are: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and chromosomal microarray (CMA) that includes this gene/chromosome segment.6. No deletions or duplications involving either <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> as causative of phosphorylase kinase deficiency have been reported. 7. Examples of pathogenic variants detected by sequence analysis may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Testing_Strategy">
          <title>Testing Strategy</title>
          <p>
            <bold>To confirm/establish the diagnosis in a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <p><bold>Liver PhK deficiency</bold> should be considered for any child with hepatomegaly and growth retardation, with or without evidence of fasting ketosis and hypoglycemia. (see also <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>)</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Assay of PhK activity in erythrocytes should be performed in individuals with a suspected diagnosis of liver PhK deficiency. While it is recommended that liver biopsy be reserved for those individuals for whom no clear diagnosis can be made from blood-based testing, some specialists may recommend liver biopsy to further evaluate the etiology of hepatomegaly. In this case, electron microscopy, measurement of glycogen content, assay of PhK activity, and assay for enzyme deficiencies causing other liver glycogenoses (such as GSD VI and GSD III) should be performed. Results of the assay of PhK activity should be interpreted with caution because false positive and false negative results have been reported.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Deficiency of erythrocyte and/or liver PhK activity finding should be confirmed by molecular genetic testing. The order in which genes are tested can be guided by the following:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>Gender</bold>: Males are most likely to have X-linked liver PhK deficiency <italic toggle="yes">(PHKA2</italic>). Females are more likely to have an autosomal recessive subtype <italic toggle="yes">(PHKB</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>) but could be manifesting heterozygotes of the X-linked subtype (<italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>) as a result of skewed X-chromosome inactivation.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>Family history</bold>: If the family history is consistent with X-linked inheritance (<italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>) or autosomal recessive inheritance (<italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>).</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>Presence of consanguinity</bold> suggests an autosomal recessive subtype (<italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>).</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>Severity of manifestations</bold> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">Genotype/Phenotype Correlations</xref>). Based on current knowledge:</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Mutation of <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> appears to result in an increased risk for liver fibrosis and cirrhosis, although not in all individuals.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Mutation of <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> appeard to be associated with a particularly mild clinical and biochemical phenotype.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>The clinical phenotype associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> varies from mild to severe.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If erythrocyte or liver PhK enzyme activity is normal, consider molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> because a significant proportion of individuals with pathogenic variants in this gene do not have PhK deficiency in vitro (XLG2 subtype) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1999.1541">Hendrickx et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.carri_re.2008.664">Carri&#x000e8;re et al 2008</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Normal PhK enzyme activity in blood cells (leukocytes) in vitro has also been found in individuals with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997b.170">Burwinkel et al 1997b</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: When the diagnosis of liver PhK deficiency is confirmed through detection of pathogenic variants, liver biopsy is not needed. Liver biopsy should be reserved for instances in which no diagnosis can be made from erythrocyte enzyme analysis and molecular genetic testing.</p>
          <p><bold>Muscle PhK deficiency</bold> should be suspected in an individual with muscle cramps and myoglobinuria on exercise, or progressive muscle weakness and atrophy. These symptoms are suggestive of several different disorders (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>).</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> identifies a causative variant in a minority of this group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003a.516">Burwinkel et al 2003a</xref>]; however, if the family history is consistent with X-linked inheritance, molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> is recommended. In some instances of PhK deficiency in muscle and normal <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> sequence analysis, the cause remains unexplained.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>For simplex cases (i.e., those with no family history of muscle PhK deficiency), muscle biopsy can be performed for histology and assay of enzyme activity to investigate PhK deficiency or other differential diagnoses. If PhK deficiency is found, molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> should be performed.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Carrier testing for relatives at risk for the two forms of X-linked PhK deficiency</bold>, caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>, requires prior identification of the pathogenic variant in the family<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></p>
          <p>Note: (1) Female carriers are heterozygotes for these X-linked disorders. Carriers of pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> may develop mild hepatomegaly, short stature in childhood, and biochemical abnormalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.willems.1990.268">Willems et al 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.morava.2005.703">Morava et al 2005</xref>], and theoretically more severe symptoms (including hypoglycemia) resulting from skewed X-chromosome inactivation. No symptoms have been reported in female carriers of pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.bak.2001.286">Bak et al 2001</xref>] but it is possible that they too could exhibit symptoms as a result of skewed X-chromosome inactivation. (2) Identification of female carriers requires either (a) prior identification of the pathogenic variant in the family or, (b) if an affected male is not available for testing, molecular genetic testing first by sequence analysis, and then, if no variant is identified, using deletion/duplication analysis if available. (3) Enzyme-based carrier testing is not recommended for determining carrier status.</p>
          <p><bold>Carrier testing for relatives</bold>
<bold>at risk for the two subtypes of autosomal recessive PhK deficiency</bold> (caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2)</italic> requires prior identification of the pathogenic variants in the family<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></p>
          <p>Note: (1) Carriers are heterozygotes for these autosomal recessive disorders and are not at risk of developing the disorders. (2) Enzyme-based carrier testing is not recommended for determining carrier status.</p>
          <p><bold>Prenatal diagnosis and preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)</bold> for at-risk pregnancies require prior identification of the pathogenic variant(s) in the family<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="gsd9.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p><bold>Liver phosphorylase kinase (PhK) deficiency.</bold> With increasing understanding of liver PhK deficiency it is clear that clinical severity varies significantly. Although it has been considered to be a mild condition, more severe involvement has been documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.morava.2005.703">Morava et al 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>; Author, personal experience]. See also <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</xref>.</p>
          <p>Typically, an affected child presents in the first years of life with hepatomegaly and growth retardation. Hyperketotic hypoglycemia, if present, is usually mild but can be severe and recurrent. It is also possible that blood glucose concentrations are maintained within normal limits when moderate to large ketosis results from increased fatty acid oxidation and gluconeogenesis is upregulated.</p>
          <p>Mild delays in gross motor development are often seen in early childhood. Hypotonia and muscle weakness have been observed in some individuals, regardless of which gene is mutated.</p>
          <p>Cognitive and/or speech delays have been reported in a few individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1998a.423">Burwinkel et al 1998a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>; Author, personal observation]. At this time, it is not clear whether these delays are directly related to PhK deficiency or are coincidental.</p>
          <p>Growth retardation is most pronounced in childhood, after which catch-up growth occurs; most adults reach normal height [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.willems.1990.268">Willems et al 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.schippers.2003.43">Schippers et al 2003</xref>].</p>
          <p>Puberty may be delayed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.willems.1990.268">Willems et al 1990</xref>].</p>
          <p>Liver fibrosis can occur and in rare instances progress to cirrhosis (typically associated with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>). Liver adenoma appears to be very rare.</p>
          <p>Renal tubular acidosis has been reported in some individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1998a.423">Burwinkel et al 1998a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>].</p>
          <p>Polycystic ovaries are common in females with liver PhK deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.lee.1995.462">Lee &#x00026; Leonard 1995</xref>].</p>
          <p>Cardiac manifestations have not been reported in individuals with liver PhK deficiency.</p>
          <p>Symptoms and biochemical abnormalities improve with age in most individuals with liver PhK deficiency. Most adults are practically asymptomatic despite persistent PhK deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.willems.1990.268">Willems et al 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1998.919">Hendrickx et al 1998</xref>]. However, long-term effects in older persons have not been studied extensively. It is possible that long-term issues could emerge as affected individuals are followed longitudinally.</p>
          <p><bold>Muscle PhK deficiency</bold> presents any time from childhood to adulthood with a broad range of symptoms including exercise intolerance, muscle cramps, myalgia, myoglobinuria, and progressive muscle weakness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.chen.2001">Chen 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.kishnani.2010">Kishnani &#x00026; Chen 2010</xref>]. Serious impairment seems to be the exception and may take years to develop [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.wehner.1994.1983">Wehner et al 1994</xref>]. Heart and liver do not seem to be involved.</p>
          <p>One adult male with asymptomatic myopathy and cognitive impairment has been reported, suggesting wide variability in the clinical findings associated with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.echanizlaguna.2010.125">Echaniz-Laguna et al 2010</xref>]. However, it is possible that another cause exists for the cognitive impairment in this person.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> result in muscle glycogenosis; pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> cause liver glycogenosis; pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> cause liver and muscle glycogenosis (muscle signs are variably present).</p>
          <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic></bold>. No correlation is observed between the type of pathogenic variant, residual muscle PhK activity, and age of onset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.wuyts.2005.82">Wuyts et al 2005</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic></bold>. Symptoms range from mild to severe but no correlation has been observed between genotype and clinical severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>]. Even persons with the same pathogenic variant can have significantly different clinical symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hirono.1998.846">Hirono et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1999.1541">Hendrickx et al 1999</xref>, personal communication].</p>
          <p>Regarding correlation between genotype and biochemical phenotype, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1999.1541">Hendrickx et al [1999]</xref> suggested that:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> variants resulting in reduced amounts of alpha subunit protein (e.g., nonsense and frameshift variants or missense variants that destabilize the protein) cause detectable PhK deficiency in vitro (XLG1 biochemical subtype)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> variants that disrupt activation of PhK enzyme activity (e.g., missense variants or small in-frame insertions or deletions affecting regulatory sites of the enzyme) can result in the normal PhK activity that is observed in vitro in some affected persons (XLG2 biochemical subtype).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>These subtle changes may allow normal amounts of PhK to be made; however, they:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Differentially affect the interaction of the enzyme PhK with exogenous and endogenous substrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.maire.1991.169">Maire et al 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1994.620">Hendrickx et al 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1996.653">Burwinkel et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1996.649">Hendrickx et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997b.170">Burwinkel et al 1997b</xref>];</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Have an effect on in vivo regulation that cannot be detected in vitro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1998.919">Hendrickx et al 1998</xref>];</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Enhance protease sensitivity of PhK (which activates PhK) in a cell-type specific manner;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Affect tissue-specific interaction of subunit isoforms that affect activity differently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1998a.423">Burwinkel et al 1998a</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.carri_re.2008.664">Carri&#x000e8;re et al [2008]</xref> showed that <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> missense variants and small in-frame deletions/insertions are concentrated into two domains of the protein:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>In the N-terminal glucoamylase domain, pathogenic variants (principally leading to XLG2) are clustered within the predicted glycoside-binding site, suggesting that they may have a direct effect on a possible hydrolytic activity of the PhK alpha subunit.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In the C-terminal calcineurin B-like domain (domain D), pathogenic variants (principally leading to XLG1) are clustered in a region predicted to interact with the regulatory region of the PhK catalytic subunit and in a region covering this interaction site.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Further studies are needed to determine the molecular basis of the XLG1 and XLG2 biochemical subtypes. Of note, the same <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> variant (p.Arg295His) has been associated with normal and deficient PhK activity in vitro, suggesting that other factors, such as handling of the specimen and laboratory methodologies, can also affect the biochemical phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1999.1541">Hendrickx et al 1999</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic></bold><italic toggle="yes">.</italic> The few <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> variants reported have been associated with a particularly mild clinical and biochemical phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>]. No genotype/phenotype correlation has been reported for pathogenic variants in this gene.</p>
          <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic></bold>. Mutation of <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> appears to result in more severe disease with an increased risk of liver fibrosis and cirrhosis, although persons with a milder course have been observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.maichele.1996.337">Maichele et al 1996</xref>; Author, personal experience]. No correlation appears to exist between the type of <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> variant and disease severity.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>Assay of enzyme activity has identified liver PhK deficiency in asymptomatic males following diagnosis of another family member [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.willems.1990.268">Willems et al 1990</xref>]. However, it is unclear whether these individuals were adults at the time of the study (and therefore findings had resolved) or whether findings (e.g., hepatomegaly or short stature in childhood) had ever been present. Presenting symptoms can be variable. For example, one child with a pathogenic splice site variant in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> had only short stature and no hepatomegaly or biochemical abnormalities at age 6.8 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hirono.1998.846">Hirono et al 1998</xref>]. Further family studies are required to fully determine variability and penetrance of presenting findings.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p><bold>Liver PhK deficiency</bold>. Historically, the numeric classification of liver PhK deficiency has ranged from GSD type VIa and VIb to GSD VIII to GSD IX.</p>
          <p>Note: (1) Deficiency of the enzyme glycogen phosphorylase that causes GSD V (muscle specific) or GSD VI (liver specific) is distinct from deficiency of the enzyme PhK that causes GSD IX. However, confusion may have arisen in the past re-classification of these types of GSD: because the enzyme PhK activates the enzyme glycogen phosphorylase, PhK deficiency can also result in phosphorylase deficiency. (2) The classification GSD VIII no longer exists: in the past GSD VIII was used to describe some cases of PhK deficiency.</p>
          <p>Liver PhK deficiency has been further subclassified into:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>GSD IXa, now known as <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2-</italic>related glycogen storage disease type IX;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>GSD IXb, now known as <italic toggle="yes">PHKB-</italic>related glycogen storage disease type IX;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>GSD IXc, now known as <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2-</italic>related glycogen storage disease type IX.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Muscle PhK deficiency</bold> has been called GSD Vb and GSD IXd.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>Liver PhK deficiency is thought to account for about 25% of all GSDs with an estimated prevalence of one in 100,000 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.maichele.1996.337">Maichele et al 1996</xref>]. However, the disorder may be underdiagnosed as a result of the variable presentation and challenges with diagnostic confirmation.</p>
          <p>Muscle PhK deficiency appears to be rare, but could be underdiagnosed because of the milder muscle symptoms.</p>
          <p>No populations are known to have an increased prevalence of PhK deficiency.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disorde">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No other phenotypes are known to be associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1, PHKA2, PHKB, or PHKG2.</italic></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>The following disorders have features in common with <bold>liver PhK deficiency:</bold></p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="gsd6" document-type="chapter"><bold>Glycogen storage disease type VI</bold></related-object> (GSD VI) is caused by deficiency of liver glycogen phosphorylase, the enzyme activated by liver phosphorylase b kinase (PhK). It is not possible to distinguish GSD VI and liver PhK deficiency by clinical findings alone. Furthermore, liver glycogen phosphorylase activity can be low in in vitro assays in persons with liver PhK deficiency. The two disorders can be distinguished by enzymatic and molecular genetic testing.</p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="gsd1" document-type="chapter"><bold>Glycogen storage disease type I</bold></related-object> (GSD I) is characterized by growth retardation, hepatomegaly, and hypoglycemia, usually without ketosis. Although hypoglycemia tends to be more severe in GSD I than in liver PhK deficiency, on occasion severe hypoglycemia can occur in individuals with liver PhK deficiency. Elevated serum concentrations of lactate and uric acid, characteristic of GSD I, are usually not seen in liver PhK deficiency. Individuals with GSD Ib also have recurrent bacterial infections caused by neutropenia and impaired neutrophil function. Inheritance is autosomal recessive.</p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="gsd3" document-type="chapter"><bold>Glycogen storage disease type III</bold></related-object> (GSD III) presents with hepatomegaly, hypoglycemia, and growth retardation that improves with age. In GSD IIIa, muscle weakness and elevated serum creatine kinase (CK) are often present. Cardiomyopathy may also occur. Inheritance is autosomal recessive.</p>
        <p>The following disorders have features in common with <bold>muscle PhK deficiency</bold>:</p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="gsd5" document-type="chapter"><bold>Glycogen storage disease type V</bold></related-object> (GSD V, McArdle disease) is caused by deficiency of muscle glycogen phosphorylase (myophosphorylase), the enzyme activated by muscle PhK. GSD V and muscle PhK deficiency have similar findings, including exercise-induced muscle cramps, episodes of myoglobinuria, and excess glycogen in muscle. Age of onset and clinical findings vary widely. However, the &#x0201c;second wind&#x0201d; phenomenon, noted in persons with GSD V, is not observed in those with muscle PhK deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF._rngreen.2008.1876">&#x000d8;rngreen et al 2008</xref>]. X-linked inheritance of such findings suggests muscle PhK deficiency caused by a <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> pathogenic variant. Inheritance of GSD V is autosomal recessive.</p>
        <p><bold>Glycogen storage disease type VII</bold> (GSD VII, Tarui disease, phosphofructokinase deficiency) causes severe exercise intolerance, usually appearing in childhood and associated with nausea, vomiting, and severe muscle pain; vigorous exercise can cause severe muscle cramps and myoglobinuria. Other features include compensated hemolysis, hyperuricemia, and absence of spontaneous second-wind phenomenon. Inheritance is autosomal recessive.</p>
        <p><bold>Other disorders</bold> with clinical features overlapping muscle PhK deficiency include: mitochondrial myopathy (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mt-overview" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial Disorders Overview</related-object>); myodenylate deaminase deficiency; <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="cpt2" document-type="chapter">carnitine palmitoyl transferase II deficiency</related-object>; phosphoglycerate kinase deficiency; phosphoglycerate mutase deficiency (GSD X); lactate dehydrogenase deficiency (GSD XI); <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="vlcad" document-type="chapter">VLCAD deficiency</related-object>; and long-chain 3-hydroxyacyl-CoA dehydrogenase (LCHAD) / mitochondrial trifunctional protein deficiency.</p>
        <p>Severe infantile PhK deficiency in muscle with findings ranging from fatal arthrogryposis to severe muscular hypotonia, but without organomegaly, have also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.ohtani.1982.833">Ohtani et al 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.shin.1994.153">Shin et al 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.sahin.1998.48">Sahin et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.b_hrer.2000.104">B&#x000fc;hrer et al 2000</xref>]. No molecular genetic testing has been performed on these infants and it is not clear whether PhK deficiency is the primary cause of their findings or if they are secondary.</p>
        <p><bold>Fanconi-Bickel syndrome</bold>. PhK deficiency may also occur as a secondary phenomenon in Fanconi-Bickel syndrome, caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">GLUT2</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1999.240">Burwinkel et al 1999</xref>.</p>
        <p><bold>Isolated cardiac PhK deficiency.</bold> Rare instances of heart-specific PhK deficiency present early in life with severe isolated cardiomyopathy. Diagnosis of PhK deficiency isolated to cardiac tissue requires biopsy of heart tissue. Pathogenic variants in the genes encloding the PhK subunits (<italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PHKG1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">CALM1, CALM2, or CALM3-3</italic>) have not be associated with this phenotype, but pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PRKAG2</italic> (which encodes the regulatory subunit of AMP-activated protein kinase) have been identified in some persons with this phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2005.1034">Burwinkel et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.akman.2007.499">Akman et al 2007</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="gsd9.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diagn">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs of an individual diagnosed with <bold>liver PhK deficiency</bold>, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Measurement of blood glucose concentration (normal &#x0003e;70 mg/dL) for two to three days: upon waking in the morning; prior to meals and night time supplementation with oral cornstarch; and after activity</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Measurement of blood ketone levels for two to three days: upon waking in the morning; prior to meals and night time supplementation with oral cornstarch; and after activity. Elevated blood ketones (beta-hydroxybutyrate &#x0003e;1.0 mmol/L) could be an indicator of suboptimal metabolic control and pending hypoglycemia.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Liver imaging, if not performed in the past year. The type of liver imaging (ultrasound, MRI, or CT) is determined by factors such as age and underlying liver status (such as liver cirrhosis).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Basic metabolic panel including liver enzymes (AST, ALT, and alkaline phosphatase)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Prothrombin time</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Lipid panel (cholesterol and triglyceride concentrations)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Serum creatine kinase measurement (Some individuals with liver PhK deficiency can have muscle involvement)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Baseline echocardiogram (Although cardiac problems have not been reported to occur in PhK deficiency [due to paucity of systematic investigation and lack of knowledge], baseline echocardiogram may be done as a precaution.)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs of an individual diagnosed with <bold>muscle PhK deficiency</bold>, the following evaluations are suggested:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical therapy evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Serum creatine kinase measurement</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <sec id="gsd9.Liver_PhK_Deficiency_1">
            <title>Liver PhK Deficiency</title>
            <p><bold>Hypoglycemia</bold>
<bold>can be prevented</bold> with frequent daytime feedings that are high in complex carbohydrates and protein.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>The dose of cornstarch can range from 0.6 to 2.5 g/kg every six hours based on clinical symptoms.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Protein should be given as 15% to 25% of total calories (tailored to the patient&#x02019;s age) as long as renal function is normal. Protein provides an alternative source of glucose via intact gluconeogenesis.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>For signs of</bold>
<bold>hypoglycemia or ketosis</bold>, Polycose<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> or fruit juice should be given orally (if oral intake is tolerated) followed by a snack high in complex carbohydrates and protein. Blood glucose and ketone concentrations should be monitored periodically to ensure that they return to normal. If oral intake is not tolerated, an IV should be started. An initial glucose bolus (D50, or D10 if D50 not available) may be needed to maintain blood glucose concentrations above 70 mg/dL. The bolus can then be followed by 10% dextrose by IV.</p>
            <p>Symptomatic management of liver manifestations such as cirrhosis, liver failure, portal hypertension is appropriate.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="gsd9.Muscle_PhK_Deficiency_1">
            <title>Muscle PhK Deficiency</title>
            <p>Signs and symptoms should be managed as with other muscle GSDs, such as <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="gsd3" document-type="chapter">GSD III</related-object> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.kishnani.2010.446">Kishnani et al 2010</xref>].</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Physical therapy evaluation and intervention based on physical status and function</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Coordination with a metabolic nutritionist regarding monitoring and optimizing blood glucose concentrations based on levels of exercise and activity</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Prevention_of_Primary_Manifestation">
          <title>Prevention of Primary Manifestations</title>
          <sec id="gsd9.Liver_PhK_Deficiency_2">
            <title>Liver PhK Deficiency</title>
            <p><bold>Hypoglycemia.</bold> Frequent feedings high in complex carbohydrates and protein are given to prevent hypoglycemia. In some individuals, no additional treatment is required to prevent hypoglycemia. However, some persons with liver PhK deficiency have severe and recurrent hypoglycemia which can be prevented by ingestion of uncooked cornstarch (range of cornstarch dose 0.6 to 2.5 g/kg) one to four times per day, depending on the severity of the condition. Some individuals may require cornstarch only before bedtime. Requirements for cornstarch tend to lessen with age.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="gsd9.Muscle_PhK_Deficiency_2">
            <title>Muscle PhK Deficiency</title>
            <p>Little published information is available on prevention of primary manifestations in individuals with muscle PhK deficiency; however, regular moderate aerobic exercise may be beneficial. Intense exercise should be avoided as it may promote rhabdomyolysis and muscle cramping.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complicatio">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p><bold>Liver PhK deficiency.</bold> Perioperative care for elective procedures should include IV glucose infusion preoperatively which should start as soon as the patient is made NPO. Continue with intraoperative and postoperative IV glucose infusion to prevent hypoglycemia. IV glucose should be tapered off gradually as the patient tolerates the usual diet. Abrupt discontinuation of fluids could result in hypoglycemia.</p>
          <p>If general anesthesia is required, <bold>malignant hyperthermia precautions</bold> should be taken as individuals with liver PhK deficiency may have increased CK levels and myopathy [Author, personal experience]. (See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mhs" document-type="chapter">Malignant Hyperthermia Susceptibility</related-object>).</p>
          <p>During childhood, <bold>routine immunizations</bold> should be given on the recommended schedule. Any immunizations that may prevent illness, such as influenza leading to hypoglycemia, should be offered.</p>
          <p><bold>Muscle PhK deficiency.</bold> Lipid-lowering drugs (e.g., statins) that can worsen or unmask myopathy should be used cautiously.</p>
          <p>If general anesthesia is required, <bold>malignant hyperthermia precautions</bold> should be taken as individuals with muscle PhK deficiency have increased CK levels and myopathy. (See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mhs" document-type="chapter">Malignant Hyperthermia Susceptibility</related-object>).</p>
          <p>During childhood, <bold>routine immunizations</bold> should be given on the recommended schedule.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Liver PhK deficiency</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular evaluation by a <bold>metabolic physician</bold> familiar with liver PhK deficiency to monitor medical issues and a <bold>metabolic nutritionist</bold> to give dietary recommendations and monitor cornstarch requirement</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular monitoring of blood glucose concentration and ketones, as recommended by a metabolic physician and nutritionist. Blood glucose concentrations and ketones should also be measured during times of stress including illness, intense activity, rapid growth, puberty, and pregnancy; and at any time in which intake of food is reduced or meal and/or cornstarch dose or scheduling is altered. Note: It is possible that blood glucose concentrations may be normal when moderate to large ketosis in liver PhK deficiency results from increased fatty acid oxidation and upregulated gluconeogenesis. The role of ketone monitoring in this setting as a marker of metabolic control requires further systematic investigation.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Liver imaging.</bold> In children younger than age 18 years, liver ultrasound examination every 12 to 24 months. With increasing age, consideration of CT or MRI using intravenous contrast to evaluate for complications of liver disease</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Follow-up echocardiogram.</bold> No guidelines established. Follow up approximately every two years or earlier if symptoms are present</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Muscle PhK deficiency</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular evaluation by a <bold>metabolic physician</bold> familiar with liver PhK deficiency to monitor medical issues and a <bold>metabolic nutritionist</bold> to give dietary recommendations and monitor cornstarch requirement.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular evaluation by a <bold>physical therapist</bold> to look for progression in symptoms and to guide exercise program</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p><bold>Liver PhK deficiency.</bold> Affected Individuals with should avoid the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Large amounts of simple sugars as they will increase liver storage of glycogen.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Prolonged fasting</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>High impact contact sports if significant (moderate to massive) hepatomegaly is present. The final decision is based on clinician judgment.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Drugs known to cause hypoglycemia such as insulin and insulin secretagogues (the sulfonylureas); though there are no reports in the literature of drugs precipitating hypoglycemia in children with liver PhK deficiency</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Alcohol, as this may predispose to hypoglycemia.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Hypoglycemic events in adults with liver PhK deficiency are relatively uncommon; however, caution should be used with drugs causing potential hypoglycemia, particularly in persons with impaired liver function.</p>
          <p>M<bold>uscle PhK deficiency.</bold> Affected individuals should avoid the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Vigorous exercise</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Medications that can cause rhabdomyolysis (e.g., succinylcholine)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing (if the family-specific variants are known) and/or evaluation by a metabolic physician during the first year of life (if the family-specific variants are not known) allows for early diagnosis and treatment for sibs at increased risk for liver PhK deficiency.</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>Ideally, women with PhK deficiency consult with their health care team and maintain optimal metabolic control before conception.</p>
          <p>It is extremely important that euglycemia is maintained throughout pregnancy to avoid upregulation of counterregulatory hormones which would result in lipolysis and ketosis, with risk of fetal demise. The appropriate diet during pregnancy is unique to each individual. For some, this may only require following a regular healthy diet, but for many it may mean increasing snacks to include more complex carbohydrates and protein and/or adding or increasing the amount of corn starch. Blood glucose concentrations and ketones should also be measured during pregnancy on a regular basis to ensure euglycemia. Adequate amounts of protein are necessary to provide an alternate source of glucose via gluconeogenesis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>The improved and modified version of cornstarch, called Superstarch<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, is under investigation for prevention of hypoglycemia in GSDs in general.</p>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ClinicalTrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="gsd9.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>-related liver PhK deficiency and <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic>-related muscle PhK deficiency are inherited in an X-linked manner.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>-related liver and muscle PhK deficiency and <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>-related liver PhK deficiency are inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Risk_To_Family_Members__Xlinked_Inh">
          <title>Risk To Family Members &#x02014; X-linked Inheritance</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The father of an affected male will not have the disease nor will he be a carrier of the family-specific pathogenic variant.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In a family with more than one affected individual, the mother of an affected male is an obligate carrier. Note: If a woman has more than one affected child and no other affected relatives and if the family-specific variant cannot be detected in her leukocyte DNA, she has germline mosaicism. No data are available on the possibility or frequency of germline mosaicism in X-linked muscle or liver PhK deficiency</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a male is the only affected family member (i.e., a simplex case), the mother may be a carrier, or the affected male may have a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant, in which case the mother is not a carrier. The frequency of <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> is unknown. No <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> cases have been documented.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to sibs depends on the carrier status of the mother.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the mother is a carrier, the chance of transmitting the pathogenic variant in each pregnancy is 50%. Males who inherit the variant will be affected; females who inherit the variant will be carriers. No symptoms have been reported in female carriers of a <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> pathogenic variant, although development of symptoms may occur, in theory, if skewed X-chromosome inactivation is present. Female carriers of a <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> pathogenic variant may be unaffected, have mild hepatomegaly, or (rarely) have more severe symptoms depending on the pattern of X-chromosome inactivation [Author, personal observation].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the affected male is a simplex case (i.e., a single occurrence in a family) and if the pathogenic variant cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of his mother, the risk to sibs is low but greater than that of the general population because of the possibility of maternal germline mosaicism.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a male proband.</bold> Affected males pass the pathogenic variant to all of their daughters and none of their sons.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> An affected male&#x02019;s maternal aunts may be at risk of being carriers and the aunts&#x02019; offspring, depending on their gender, may be at risk of being carriers or of being affected.</p>
          <p>Note: Molecular genetic testing may be able to identify the family member in whom a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant arose, information that could help determine genetic risk status of the extended family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Carrier_Detection">
          <title>Carrier Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk female relatives is possible if the pathogenic variant in the family has been identified.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Risk_To_Family_Members__Autosomal_R">
          <title>Risk To Family Members &#x02014; Autosomal Recessive Inheritance</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected child are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one mutated allele).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Once an at-risk sib is known to be unaffected, the risk of his/her being a carrier is 2/3.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> The offspring of an individual with autosomal recessive PhK deficiency are obligate heterozygotes (carriers) for a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Carrier_Detection_1">
          <title>Carrier Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk family members is possible if the pathogenic variants in the family have been identified.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk of being carriers or of being affected.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantatio">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the pathogenic variant(s) have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal diagnosis and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for a pregnancy at increased risk for PhK deficiency are possible options.</p>
          <p>Requests for prenatal testing for conditions which (like PhK deficiency) do not affect intellect and have some treatment available are not common. Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although decisions about prenatal testing are the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="gsd9.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>The enzyme phosphorylase kinase (PhK) activates liver glycogen phosphorylase and muscle glycogen phosphorylase in response to neuronal and hormonal stimuli and thus is a key regulatory enzyme in glycogen breakdown. In liver PhK deficiency, the inability to break down glycogen results in risk for hypoglycemia and glycogen accumulation in the liver, which in turn causes hepatomegaly and liver damage.</p>
          <p>Muscle PhK deficiency caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> appears to cause myopathy by causing a defect in glycogen availability during submaximal exercise (oxidative metabolism; e.g., cycle test) presumably because PhK is required to activate glycogen phosphorylase under these conditions. Interestingly, anaerobic glycogenolysis is normal, suggesting that other regulatory factors are involved in phosphorylase activation in this situation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF._rngreen.2008.1876">&#x000d8;rngreen et al 2008</xref>].</p>
          <p>PhK is a multi-subunit enzyme composed of four copies each of four subunits (&#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, &#x003b3;, and &#x003b4;). The gamma (&#x003b3;) subunit contains the catalytic activity and is regulated by the alpha (&#x003b1;), beta (&#x003b2;), and delta (&#x003b4;) subunits. The inhibitory effect of the alpha and beta subunits is modulated by phosphorylation (phosphorylation removes the inhibitory effect); calcium levels modulate the regulatory effect of the delta subunit (calmodulin).</p>
          <p>Each PhK subunit is encoded by at least one gene: <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> encode the muscle and liver isoforms of the alpha subunit, respectively; <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> encodes the liver and muscle beta subunits; <italic toggle="yes">PHKG1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> encode the muscle and liver isoforms of the gamma subunit, respectively; and the delta subunit, calmodulin, is encoded by three genes, <italic toggle="yes">CALM1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">CALM2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">CALM3</italic>. Further complexity is introduced by tissue-specific alternative splicing. The complexity of the enzyme PhK explains to some degree the clinical and biochemical heterogeneity of PhK deficiency.</p>
          <sec id="gsd9.PHKA1">
            <title>
              <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic>
            </title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> Alternatively spliced transcript variants encoding different isoforms have been identified in this gene. The longest transcript (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_002637.3">NM_002637.3</ext-link>) consists of 32 exons and is transcribed into a 6-kb cDNA. <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> spans approximately 133 kb of genomic DNA. A pseudogene, <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1P1</italic>, has been found on chromosome 1p22.2. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="gsd9" object-id="gsd9.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> To date, six predicted pathogenic variants have been reported in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic>, each of which was found in only one individual. Pathogenic variants include missense (2), small deletions inducing frameshifts (2), nonsense (1), and splice site (1) changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.wehner.1994.1983">Wehner et al 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.bruno.1998.648">Bruno et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003a.516">Burwinkel et al 2003a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.wuyts.2005.82">Wuyts et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF._rngreen.2008.1876">&#x000d8;rngreen et al 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.echanizlaguna.2010.125">Echaniz-Laguna et al 2010</xref>].</p>
            <p>A frameshift variant in mouse ortholog <italic toggle="yes">Phka1</italic> causes PhK deficiency in the I-strain mouse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.schneider.1993.381">Schneider et al 1993</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> encodes the muscle isoform of the alpha subunit of PhK, a 1223-amino acid protein (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_002628.2">NP_002628.2</ext-link>).</p>
            <p>Two alternatively spliced transcript variants encoding different isoforms have been identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.harmann.1991.15631">Harmann et al 1991</xref>]; alpha-FM is the predominant form in fast-twitch skeletal muscle and is also expressed in brain while alpha-prime is the predominant form in slow-twitch skeletal muscle. Alpha-prime has an internal deletion of 59 amino acids (amino acids 654-712) when compared to alpha-FM.</p>
            <p>The degree of phosphorylation of the alpha subunit regulates the activity of PhK; the greater the phosphorylation the less the inhibitory effect.</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> No studies have been done to determine how <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> pathogenic variants cause PhK deficiency. Complete lack of PHKA1 protein is predicted to affect formation or stability of PhK holoenzyme. Production of an altered PHKA1 protein, resulting from missense variants, may affect its ability to interact with other subunits or to activate PhK activity.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="gsd9.PHKA2">
            <title>
              <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>
            </title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> The gene contains 33 exons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1999.1541">Hendrickx et al 1999</xref>] and spans 91.3 kb of DNA. Alternatively spliced transcript variants have been reported, but the full-length nature of these variants has not been determined. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="gsd9" object-id="gsd9.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
            <p><bold>Benign allelic variants.</bold> An amino acid polymorphism, p.Glu38Gln (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/SNP/snp_ref.cgi?rs=17313469">rs17313469</ext-link>) has been identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>]. Two intronic changes, c.718-3C&#x0003e;T and c.1715-50G&#x0003e;C, were each found in one affected individual but are not thought to be pathogenic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> About 50 different pathogenic variants have been reported in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic>. Most of them are missense or nonsense variants or small deletions causing frameshifts. The pathogenic variants are distributed throughout the gene.</p>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> encodes the liver alpha subunit of PhK. A 5325-bp mRNA is translated into a 1235-amino acid protein with high expression in liver and brain, but not in muscle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1993.583">Hendrickx et al 1993</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> is highly homologous to <italic toggle="yes">PHKA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>.</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Two biochemical subtypes of X-linked glycogenosis (XLG) are caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKA2</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1994.620">Hendrickx et al 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1996.653">Burwinkel et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1996.649">Hendrickx et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1998a.423">Burwinkel et al 1998a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1999.1541">Hendrickx et al 1999</xref>]:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>XLG1, the more common form, in which in vitro PhK activity is deficient in peripheral blood cells and liver.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>XLG2, in which in vitro PhK activity in peripheral blood cells is normal or even elevated and activity in liver is variable</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>While not yet fully understood, there are various theories as to how different pathogenic variants in PHKA2 could result in these different biochemical subtypes (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="gsd9.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">Genotype/Phenotype Correlation</xref>).</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="gsd9.PHKB">
            <title>
              <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>
            </title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> Alternatively spliced transcript variants encoding different isoforms have been identified in this gene. The longer transcript variant, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000293.2">NM_000293.2</ext-link>, is composed of 33 exons spanning 239 kb of genomic DNA. Exons 26 and 27 are two homologous, mutually exclusively spliced exons that encode muscle and non-muscle PHKB respectively; exon 2 is a facultatively used cassette exon encoding an alternative N-terminus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.w_llrichschmoll.1996.374">W&#x000fc;llrich-Schmoll &#x00026; Kilimann 1996</xref>]. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="gsd9" object-id="gsd9.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
            <p><bold>Benign allelic variants.</bold> c.2309A&#x0003e;G (p.Tyr770Cys) is found in 2%-3% of the normal population and is predicted to be non-pathogenic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.van_den_berg.1997.539">van den Berg et al 1997</xref>]. However, it is unclear whether this change in any way contributed to muscle PhK deficiency in two persons in whom it was found [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003a.516">Burwinkel et al 2003a</xref>].</p>
            <p>A restriction fragment length polymorphism (deletion of ATTA at the end of intron 20 that abolishes an <italic toggle="yes">Asn</italic>I restriction site) has an allele frequency of 35% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997a.1109">Burwinkel et al 1997a</xref>].</p>
            <p>Two processsed pseudogenes have been identified: <italic toggle="yes">PHKBP1</italic> on chromosome 20p12.3-20p12.2 and <italic toggle="yes">PHKBP2</italic> on chromosome 14q13.3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.w_llrichschmoll.1996.374">W&#x000fc;llrich-Schmoll &#x00026; Kilimann 1996</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> Fourteen variants suspected or known to be pathogenic have been reported in <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic>. These include nonsense (5), missense (3), splice site (3), small insertion (1), small deletion (1), and gross deletion (1) changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997b.170">Burwinkel et al 1997b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.van_den_berg.1997.539">van den Berg et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003a.516">Burwinkel et al 2003a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>]. Two of the missense changes (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000293.2">NM_000293.2</ext-link>:c.555G&#x0003e;T (p.Met185Ile) and NM_000293.2:c.1969C&#x0003e;A (p.Gln657Lys) were identified in heterozygotes in whom no other pathogenic variant was identified and, thus, the significance is unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997a.1109">Burwinkel et al 1997a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003a.516">Burwinkel et al 2003a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>].</p>
            <p>Another missense change (p.Tyr975His) was found in association with two nonsense variants, suggesting that it may be non-pathogenic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997a.1109">Burwinkel et al 1997a</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> encodes the beta subunit of liver of muscle PhK. The degree of phosphorylation of the beta subunit determines the activity of the enzyme PhK.</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> It is not known exactly how <italic toggle="yes">PHKB</italic> pathogenic variants result in PhK deficiency. Lack of PHKB protein would affect formation of the normal PhK holoenzyme and an abnormal PHKB protein would presumably affect its interaction with other PhK subunits and its regulatory function. Biochemical evidence suggests that an alpha-gamma-delta complex may form in the absence of the beta subunit, explaining the residual enzyme activity seen in some patients and the mild clinical features [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997a.1109">Burwinkel et al 1997a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.brushia.1999.d618">Brushia &#x00026; Walsh 1999</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="gsd9.PHKG2">
            <title>
              <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic>
            </title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> Alternatively spliced transcript variants encoding different isoforms have been identified in this gene. The <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> longer transcript isoform <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000294.2">NM_000294.2</ext-link> comprises ten exons spanning 9 kb of genomic DNA. A complex microsatellite repeat has been identified at the beginning of intron 2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1998b.149">Burwinkel et al 1998b</xref>]. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="gsd9" object-id="gsd9.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> Thirteen predicted pathogenic variants have been reported in <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> including missense (7), nonsense (2), splice site (1), small deletion (2), and small insertion (1) changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.maichele.1996.337">Maichele et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.van_beurden.1997.544">van Beurden et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1998b.149">Burwinkel et al 1998b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2000.376">Burwinkel et al 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003b.834">Burwinkel et al 2003b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">Beauchamp et al 2007</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> encodes the catalytic gamma subunit of liver PhK, a 406-amino acid protein, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_000285.1">NP_000285.1</ext-link>. Alternative splicing creates a variant of 374 amino acids with a different C-terminus.</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PHKG2</italic> are expected to affect the catalytic ability of the gamma subunit either by resulting in production of no protein or affecting the stability or confirmation of the protein.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="gsd9.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="gsd9.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.akman.2007.499">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Akman</surname>
                    <given-names>HO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sampayo</surname>
                    <given-names>JN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ross</surname>
                    <given-names>FA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scott</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wilson</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Benson</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bruno</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shanske</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hardie</surname>
                    <given-names>DG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dimauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Fatal infantile cardiac glycogenosis with phosphorylase kinase deficiency and a mutation in the gamma2-subunit of AMP-activated protein kinase.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Res</source>
                <volume>62</volume>
                <fpage>499</fpage>
                <lpage>504</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17667862</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.bak.2001.286">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bak</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cordato</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carey</surname>
                    <given-names>WF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Milder</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>Adult-onset exercise intolerance due to phosphorylase b kinase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Neurosci</source>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>286</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11386811</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.baussan.1981.107">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baussan</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moatti</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Odievre</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lemonnier</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1981</year>
                <article-title>Liver glycogenosis caused by a defective phosphorylase system: hemolysate analysis.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatrics.</source>
                <volume>67</volume>
                <fpage>107</fpage>
                <lpage>12</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6787554</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.beauchamp.2007.88">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beauchamp</surname>
                    <given-names>NJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dalton</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ramaswami</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Niinikoski</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mention</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kenny</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kolho</surname>
                    <given-names>KL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raiman</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Walter</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Treacy</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tanner</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sharrard</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Glycogen storage disease type IX: High variability in clinical phenotype.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab</source>
                <volume>92</volume>
                <fpage>88</fpage>
                <lpage>99</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17689125</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.bruno.1998.648">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bruno</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Manfredi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Andreu</surname>
                    <given-names>AL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shanske</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Krishna</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ilse</surname>
                    <given-names>WK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998</year>
                <article-title>A splice junction mutation in the alpha(M) gene of phosphorylase kinase in a patient with myopathy.</article-title>
                <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
                <volume>249</volume>
                <fpage>648</fpage>
                <lpage>51</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9731190</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.brushia.1999.d618">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brushia</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Walsh</surname>
                    <given-names>DA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Phosphorylase kinase: the complexity of its regulation is reflected in the complexity of its structure.</article-title>
                <source>Front Biosci.</source>
                <volume>4</volume>
                <fpage>D618</fpage>
                <lpage>41</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10487978</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.b_hrer.2000.104">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>B&#x000fc;hrer</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Landeghem</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Br&#x000fc;ck</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Felderhoff-M&#x000fc;ser</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vorgerd</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Obladen</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>Fetal-onset severe skeletal muscle glycogenosis associated with phosphorylase-b kinase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Neuropediatrics.</source>
                <volume>31</volume>
                <fpage>104</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10832587</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1998a.423">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Amat</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gray</surname>
                    <given-names>RG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsuo</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Muroya</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Narisawa</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sokol</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vilaseca</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998a</year>
                <article-title>Variability of biochemical and clinical phenotype in X-linked liver glycogenosis with mutations in the phosphorylase kinase PHKA2 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>102</volume>
                <fpage>423</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9600238</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003a.516">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hu</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schroers</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clemens</surname>
                    <given-names>PR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moses</surname>
                    <given-names>SW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shin</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pongratz</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vorgerd</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003a</year>
                <article-title>Muscle glycogenosis with low phosphorylase kinase activity: mutations in PHKA1, PHKG1 or six other candidate genes explain only a minority of cases.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>516</fpage>
                <lpage>26</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12825073</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997a.1109">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maichele</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aagenaes</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bakker</surname>
                    <given-names>HD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lerner</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shin</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Strachan</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997a</year>
                <article-title>Autosomal glycogenosis of liver and muscle due to phosphorylase kinase deficiency is caused by mutations in the phosphorylase kinase beta subunit (PHKB).</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                <volume>6</volume>
                <fpage>1109</fpage>
                <lpage>15</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9215682</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1997b.170">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moses</surname>
                    <given-names>SW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997b</year>
                <article-title>Phosphorylase-kinase-deficient liver glycogenosis with an unusual biochemical phenotype in blood cells associated with a missense mutation in the beta subunit gene (PHKB).</article-title>
                <source>Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>101</volume>
                <fpage>170</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9402963</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2003b.834">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rootwelt</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kvittingen</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
                    <given-names>PK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003b</year>
                <article-title>Severe phenotype of phosphorylase kinase-deficient liver glycogenosis with mutations in the PHKG2 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Res</source>
                <volume>54</volume>
                <fpage>834</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12930917</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1999.240">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sanjad</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Sabban</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Abbad</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>A mutation in GLUT2, not in phosphorylase kinase subunits, in hepato-renal glycogenosis with Fanconi syndrome and low phosphorylase kinase activity.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>105</volume>
                <fpage>240</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10987651</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2005.1034">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scott</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>B&#x000fc;hrer</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Landeghem</surname>
                    <given-names>FK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cox</surname>
                    <given-names>GF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wilson</surname>
                    <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grahame Hardie</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Fatal congenital heart glycogenosis caused by a recurrent activating R531Q mutation in the gamma 2-subunit of AMP-activated protein kinase (PRKAG2), not by phosphorylase kinase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>76</volume>
                <fpage>1034</fpage>
                <lpage>49</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15877279</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1996.653">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shin</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bakker</surname>
                    <given-names>HD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Deutsch</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lozano</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maire</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>Mutation hotspots in the PHKA2 gene in X-linked liver glycogenosis due to phosphorylase kinase deficiency with atypical activity in blood cells (XLG2).</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                <volume>5</volume>
                <fpage>653</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8733134</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.1998b.149">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shiomi</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al Zaben</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998b</year>
                <article-title>Liver glycogenosis due to phosphorylase kinase deficiency: PHKG2 gene structure and mutations associated with cirrhosis.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                <volume>7</volume>
                <fpage>149</fpage>
                <lpage>54</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9384616</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.burwinkel.2000.376">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tanner</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>Phosphorylase kinase deficient liver glycogenosis: progression to cirrhosis in infancy associated with PHKG2 mutations (H144Y and L225R).</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>37</volume>
                <fpage>376</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10905889</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.carri_re.2008.664">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carri&#x000e8;re</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jonic</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mornon</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Callebaut</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>3D mapping of glycogenosis-causing mutations in the large regulatory alpha subunit of phosphorylase kinase.</article-title>
                <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
                <volume>1782</volume>
                <fpage>664</fpage>
                <lpage>70</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18950708</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.chen.2001">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Chen YT. Glycogen storage diseases. In: Scriver CR, Beaudet AL, Sly WS, Valle D, Childs B, Kinzler KW, Vogelstein B, eds. <italic toggle="yes">The Metabolic and Molecular Bases of Inherited Disease</italic>. 8 ed. Chapter 71. New York: McGraw-Hill; 2001:1521-51. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ommbid.mhmedical.com/">online</ext-link>. Accessed 5-2-16.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.dunger.1982.384">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dunger</surname>
                    <given-names>DB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leonard</surname>
                    <given-names>JV</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1982</year>
                <article-title>Value of the glucagon test in screening for hepatic glycogen storage disease.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Dis Child.</source>
                <volume>57</volume>
                <fpage>384</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6953931</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.echanizlaguna.2010.125">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Echaniz-Laguna</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Akman</surname>
                    <given-names>HO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mohr</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tranchant</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Talmant-Verbist</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rolland</surname>
                    <given-names>MO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dimauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010</year>
                <article-title>Muscle phosphorylase b kinase deficiency revisited.</article-title>
                <source>Neuromuscul Disord</source>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>125</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080404</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.fukao.2007.179">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fukao</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aoki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arai</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Teramoto</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaneko</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sugie</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kondo</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Identification of Alu-mediated, large deletion-spanning introns 19-26 in PHKA2 in a patient with X-linked liver glycogenosis (hepatic phosphorylase kinase deficiency).</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <volume>92</volume>
                <fpage>179</fpage>
                <lpage>82</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17581768</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.gray.1983.107">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gray</surname>
                    <given-names>RG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kumar</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Whitfield</surname>
                    <given-names>AE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1983</year>
                <article-title>Glycogen phosphorylase b kinase deficiency in three siblings.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <volume>6</volume>
                <fpage>107</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6422139</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.haller.2008.1872">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haller</surname>
                    <given-names>RG</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Fueling around with glycogen: the implications of muscle phosphorylase b kinase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology.</source>
                <volume>70</volume>
                <fpage>1872</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18474841</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.harmann.1991.15631">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harmann</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zander</surname>
                    <given-names>NF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1991</year>
                <article-title>Isoform diversity of phosphorylase kinase alpha and beta subunits generated by alternative RNA splicing.</article-title>
                <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                <volume>266</volume>
                <fpage>15631</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1874721</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1998.919">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hendrickx</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bosshard</surname>
                    <given-names>NU</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Willems</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gitzelmann</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998</year>
                <article-title>Clinical, biochemical and molecular findings in a patient with X-linked liver glycogenosis followed for 40 years.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>
                <volume>157</volume>
                <fpage>919</fpage>
                <lpage>23</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9835437</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1993.583">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hendrickx</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bossuyt</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wauters</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raeymaekers</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marchau</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smit</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stolte</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sardharwalla</surname>
                    <given-names>IB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berthelot</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>X-linked liver glycogenosis: localization and isolation of a candidate gene.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
                <year>1993</year>
                <volume>2</volume>
                <fpage>583</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8518797</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1994.620">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hendrickx</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hors-Cayla</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smit</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shin</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Deutsch</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smeitink</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berger</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1994</year>
                <article-title>Localization of a new type of X-linked liver glycogenosis to the chromosomal region Xp22 containing the liver alpha-subunit of phosphorylase kinase (PHKA2).</article-title>
                <source>Genomics</source>
                <volume>21</volume>
                <fpage>620</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7959740</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1996.649">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hendrickx</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dams</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Willems</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>X-linked liver glycogenosis type II (XLG II) is caused by mutations in PHKA2, the gene encoding the liver alpha subunit of phosphorylase kinase.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                <volume>5</volume>
                <fpage>649</fpage>
                <lpage>52</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8733133</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.hendrickx.1999.1541">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hendrickx</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Keating</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carton</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sardharwalla</surname>
                    <given-names>IB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tuchman</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baussan</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Willems</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Complete genomic structure and mutational spectrum of PHKA2 in patients with x-linked liver glycogenosis type I and II.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>64</volume>
                <fpage>1541</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10330341</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.hirono.1998.846">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hirono</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shoji</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takahashi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sato</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takeda</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishijo</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kuroda</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishigaki</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Inui</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takada</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutational analyses in four Japanese families with X-linked liver phosphorylase kinase deficiency type 1.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <year>1998</year>
                <volume>21</volume>
                <fpage>846</fpage>
                <lpage>52</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9870210</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.keating.1985.609">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Keating</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brown</surname>
                    <given-names>BI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>White</surname>
                    <given-names>NH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>X-linked glycogen storage disease. A cause of hypotonia, hyperuricemia, and growth retardation.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Dis Child.</source>
                <year>1985</year>
                <volume>139</volume>
                <fpage>609</fpage>
                <lpage>13</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3859203</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.kishnani.2010">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Kishnani P, Chen YT. Defects in metabolism of carbohydrates. In: Kliegman RM, Stanton BMD, St. Geme J, Schor N, Behrman RE, eds. <italic toggle="yes">Nelson Textbook of Pediatrics</italic>. 19 ed. Amsterdam, Netherlands: Elsevier; 2010.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.kishnani.2010.446">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kishnani</surname>
                    <given-names>PS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Austin</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arn</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bali</surname>
                    <given-names>DS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boney</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Case</surname>
                    <given-names>LE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chung</surname>
                    <given-names>WK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Desai</surname>
                    <given-names>DM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>El-Gharbawy</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haller</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smit</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hobson-Webb</surname>
                    <given-names>LD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wechsler</surname>
                    <given-names>SB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Weinstein</surname>
                    <given-names>DA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Watson</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010</year>
                <article-title>Glycogen storage disease type III diagnosis and management guidelines.</article-title>
                <source>Genet Med</source>
                <volume>12</volume>
                <fpage>446</fpage>
                <lpage>63</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20631546</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.lee.1995.462">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leonard</surname>
                    <given-names>JV</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1995</year>
                <article-title>The hepatic glycogen storage diseases--problems beyond childhood.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <volume>18</volume>
                <fpage>462</fpage>
                <lpage>72</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7494404</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.maichele.1996.337">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maichele</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burwinkel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maire</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sovik</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in the testis/liver isoform of the phosphorylase kinase gamma subunit (PHKG2) cause autosomal liver glycogenosis in the gsd rat and in humans.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>337</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8896567</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.maire.1991.169">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maire</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baussan</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moatti</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mathieu</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lemonnier</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1991</year>
                <article-title>Biochemical diagnosis of hepatic glycogen storage diseases: 20 years French experience.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Biochem</source>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>169</fpage>
                <lpage>78</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1645631</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.morava.2005.703">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morava</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wortmann</surname>
                    <given-names>SB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Essen</surname>
                    <given-names>HZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liebrand van Sambeek</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wevers</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Diggelen</surname>
                    <given-names>OP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Biochemical characteristics and increased tetraglucoside excretion in patients with phosphorylase kinase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>28</volume>
                <fpage>703</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16151901</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.ohtani.1982.833">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ohtani</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsuda</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iwamasa</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tamari</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Origuchi</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miike</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1982</year>
                <article-title>Infantile glycogen storage myopathy in a girl with phosphorylase kinase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology.</source>
                <volume>32</volume>
                <fpage>833</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6285226</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF._rngreen.2008.1876">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>&#x000d8;rngreen</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schelhaas</surname>
                    <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jeppesen</surname>
                    <given-names>TD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Akman</surname>
                    <given-names>HO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wevers</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Andersen</surname>
                    <given-names>ST</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>ter Laak</surname>
                    <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Diggelen</surname>
                    <given-names>OP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vissing</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Is muscle glycogenolysis impaired in X-linked phosphorylase b kinase deficiency?</article-title>
                <source>Neurology</source>
                <volume>70</volume>
                <fpage>1876</fpage>
                <lpage>82</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18401027</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.sahin.1998.48">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sahin</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>G&#x000fc;ng&#x000f6;r</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rettwitz-Volk</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schlote</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shin</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Podskarbi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sewell</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998</year>
                <article-title>Infantile muscle phosphorylase-b-kinase deficiency. A case report.</article-title>
                <source>Neuropediatrics.</source>
                <volume>29</volume>
                <fpage>48</fpage>
                <lpage>50</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9553951</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.schippers.2003.43">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schippers</surname>
                    <given-names>HM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smit</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rake</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Visser</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Characteristic growth pattern in male X-linked phosphorylase-b kinase deficiency (GSD IX).</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis</source>
                <volume>26</volume>
                <fpage>43</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12872839</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.schneider.1993.381">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schneider</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Davidson</surname>
                    <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wullrich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1993</year>
                <article-title>Phosphorylase kinase deficiency in I-strain mice is associated with a frameshift mutation in the alpha subunit muscle isoform.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>5</volume>
                <fpage>381</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8298647</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.shin.1994.153">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shin</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pl&#x000f6;chl</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Podskarbi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Muss</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pilz</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Puttinger</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1994</year>
                <article-title>Fatal arthrogryposis with respiratory insufficiency: a possible case of muscle phosphorylase b-kinase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <volume>17</volume>
                <fpage>153</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8051930</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.tuchman.1986.627">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tuchman</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brown</surname>
                    <given-names>BI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burke</surname>
                    <given-names>BA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ulstrom</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Clinical and laboratory observations in a child with hepatic phosphorylase kinase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Metabolism</source>
                <year>1986</year>
                <volume>35</volume>
                <fpage>627</fpage>
                <lpage>33</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3459948</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.van_beurden.1997.544">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Beurden</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Graaf</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wendel</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gitzelmann</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berger</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van den Berg</surname>
                    <given-names>IE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>Autosomal recessive liver phosphorylase kinase deficiency caused by a novel splice-site mutation in the gene encoding the liver gamma subunit (PHKG2).</article-title>
                <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source>
                <volume>236</volume>
                <fpage>544</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9245685</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.van_den_berg.1990.442">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van den Berg</surname>
                    <given-names>IE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berger</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1990</year>
                <article-title>Phosphorylase b kinase deficiency in man: a review.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <volume>13</volume>
                <fpage>442</fpage>
                <lpage>51</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2122111</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.van_den_berg.1997.539">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van den Berg</surname>
                    <given-names>IE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Beurden</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Klerk</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Diggelen</surname>
                    <given-names>OP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malingr&#x000e9;</surname>
                    <given-names>HE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boer</surname>
                    <given-names>MM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berger</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>Autosomal recessive phosphorylase kinase deficiency in liver, caused by mutations in the gene encoding the beta subunit (PHKB).</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>1997</year>
                <volume>61</volume>
                <fpage>539</fpage>
                <lpage>46</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9326319</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.wehner.1994.1983">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wehner</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clemens</surname>
                    <given-names>PR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Engel</surname>
                    <given-names>AG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1994</year>
                <article-title>Human muscle glycogenosis due to phosphorylase kinase deficiency associated with a nonsense mutation in the muscle isoform of the alpha subunit.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                <volume>3</volume>
                <fpage>1983</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7874115</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.willems.1990.268">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Willems</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gerver</surname>
                    <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berger</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1990</year>
                <article-title>The natural history of liver glycogenosis due to phosphorylase kinase deficiency: a longitudinal study of 41 patients.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>
                <volume>149</volume>
                <fpage>268</fpage>
                <lpage>71</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2303074</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.w_llrichschmoll.1996.374">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>W&#x000fc;llrich-Schmoll</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kilimann</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>Structure of the human gene encoding the phosphorylase kinase beta subunit (PHKB).</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Biochem.</source>
                <volume>238</volume>
                <fpage>374</fpage>
                <lpage>80</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8681948</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="gsd9.REF.wuyts.2005.82">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wuyts</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reyniers</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ceuterick</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Storm</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Barsy</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martin</surname>
                    <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Myopathy and phosphorylase kinase deficiency caused by a mutation in the PHKA1 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A</source>
                <volume>133A</volume>
                <fpage>82</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15637709</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="gsd9.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="gsd9.Acknowledgments">
          <title>Acknowledgments</title>
          <p>We would like to thank Dr. YT Chen, Denise Petersen, Keri Fredrickson, and Dr. Catherine Rehder for their useful discussions and professional contributions to increasing the understanding and knowledge of this complicated disorder.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="gsd9.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>31 May 2011 (me) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>7 September 2010 (db) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="gsd9.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Phosphorylase kinase subnunit expression</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gsd9-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
