<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="helpadvsearch" content-type="appendix" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="appendix" indexed="no">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">helpadvsearch</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title><italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> Advanced Search Help</title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2013-06-03" date-type="created">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="authors" document-type="appendix">GeneReviews Authors</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss" document-type="appendix"><italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic><sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="helpadvsearch.How_to_Use_the_GeneReviews">
        <title>How to Use the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> Advanced Search</title>
        <p>Enter your search term in the appropriate search field (Disorder, Gene Symbol, etc.). You may search on one field, or multiple fields using AND, OR, or NOT. </p>
        <sec id="helpadvsearch.Search_Options_for_GeneRev">
          <title>Search Options for <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic></title>
          <p><bold>Disorder</bold> returns any <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapter for which the search term is:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The title </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A synonym of the disorder that is recognized by <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> (e.g., <bold>Hunter syndrome</bold> &#x02013; a synonym for mucopolysaccharidosis type II &#x02013; will return the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapter Mucopolysaccharidosis Type II) </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A disorder included in the scope of a <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> (e.g., <bold>fragile X syndrome</bold> will return the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapter <italic toggle="yes">FMR1</italic>-Related Disorders, which includes fragile X syndrome)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>This search can be used in two ways: </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Auto-complete</bold>. Begin typing and then select the desired disorder from the drop-down options. Note: The <bold>drop-down list is limited to 20 items</bold> and includes <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> synonyms and included disorders as well as titles. As a result, the auto-complete option may not allow you to see all the possible <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> matches. Consider using the <bold>For broader search results</bold> option (see following bullet). See also <xref ref-type="sec" rid="helpadvsearch.GeneReviews_Advanced_Sea_2">Advanced Search Hints</xref>.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
<bold>For broader search results.</bold> Type part of a disorder name (e.g., <bold>ataxia</bold>) and click &#x02018;Search,&#x02019; ignoring the drop-down list.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Gene Symbol</bold> returns the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapter(s) associated with changes in the specified gene. Use the <bold>auto-complete</bold> feature to guarantee a search result: begin typing, and then select the desired gene symbol from the drop-down options that appear. Partial gene symbols will not return results.</p>
          <p>Note: Gene symbol nomenclature used in <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genenames.org/index.html">HGNC</ext-link>.</p>
          <p><bold>Author</bold> returns any <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapter(s) by a <bold>current author</bold> whose surname is an exact match for the search term. This search can be used in two ways:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Auto-complete</bold>. Begin typing, and then select the desired author (surname + initials) from the drop-down options that appear.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>For broader search results.</bold> Type a full surname and click &#x02018;Search,&#x02019; ignoring the drop-down list; your results will include all <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> by any current author with that surname.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>All Fields</bold> (found on the advanced search page as well as the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK1116/">home page</ext-link>) is useful for identifying <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> that discuss disorders that share specific characteristics. For example, a search on <bold>deafness &#x000a0; eye &#x000a0; x-linked </bold>(in any order) returns <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapters in which any (or any combination) of these terms is found. Note: For technical details on this search option, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK45615/#search.Advanced_Search">Searching Bookshelf</ext-link>. </p>
          <p><bold>Full Text</bold> is useful for finding an exact phrase in a <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; (e.g., a search on <bold>liver transplant</bold> yields only those <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> in which this phrase appears verbatim).</p>
          <p><bold>Protein Name</bold> returns <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapters associated with changes in a specific protein. This search can be used in two ways: </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Auto-complete</bold>. Begin typing, and then select the desired protein name from the drop-down options that appear. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>For broader search results.</bold> Type part of a protein name and click &#x02018;Search,&#x02019; ignoring the drop-down list. Note: Partial protein names may not return results. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: Protein nomenclature used in <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org">UniProt</ext-link>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="helpadvsearch.Overviews_Only">
          <title>Overviews Only</title>
          <p><bold>View overviews only.</bold> To see a list of all <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> overviews, select &#x02018;Only Overviews,&#x02019; leave all search fields blank, and click &#x02018;Search.&#x02019;</p>
          <p><bold>Search overviews only</bold>. To perform an &#x02018;All Fields&#x02019; or &#x02018;Full Text&#x02019; search of overviews only, select &#x02018;Only Overviews&#x02019; and then proceed with your search. </p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="helpadvsearch.GeneReviews_Advanced_Sea_2">
        <title><italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> Advanced Search Hints </title>
        <p><bold>In searching by &#x02018;Disorder,&#x02019; the auto-complete option is not always the best choice</bold>.</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>If you are searching on a general term (e.g., ataxia, cardiomyopathy, neuropathy) the number of possible matches (i.e., <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> titles plus any synonyms and included disorders) will likely exceed the <bold>maximum number that can be shown in the drop-down list (20)</bold> &#x02013; in which case there is no way to know how many more possible matches there are. To circumvent this limitation and obtain a search result that includes all relevant <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic>, enter your general search term and click &#x02018;Search,&#x02019; ignoring the drop-down list. </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>If you are looking for a specific disorder and do not see the disorder name in the drop-down list, try one of the following: </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Type in more of the disorder name until a match appears in the drop-down list.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Use the &#x02018;All Fields&#x02019; search (see following hint).</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>Try the &#x02018;All Fields&#x02019; search if you are not receiving what you expect from another search type</bold>.</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Since &#x02018;All Fields&#x02019; has fewer limitations than the specific search categories, it may return results where other options do not.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>If &#x02018;All Fields&#x02019; yields too many results, try entering more than one term in the search field (e.g., <bold>epilepsy</bold> yields &#x0003e;130 results, while <bold>epilepsy &#x000a0; adult-onset</bold> yields ~30).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>
          <bold>The display of your search results can be altered by clicking on &#x02018;Display Settings&#x02019; at the top of the results page.</bold>
        </p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Order of results.</bold> Search results display in order of relevance (based on the number of times a term is found in each <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapter). To see the titles of the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> in your search result in alphabetical order, change <bold>Sort by</bold> from &#x02018;Relevance&#x02019; to &#x02018;Title.&#x02019;</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Items per page.</bold> You can also increase or decrease the number of search results shown on a page.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="helpadvsearch.GeneReviews_Advanced_Sea_3">
        <title><italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> Advanced Search Questions </title>
        <p>
          <bold>Q: I searched on and selected a specific disorder name using the &#x02018;Disorder&#x02019; search drop-down list, and I got a <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> with a completely different title. </bold>
        </p>
        <p><bold>A:</bold> Two possible explanations:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Your search term may be a synonym for the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> title (e.g., a search for GM2 gangliosidosis will return the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapter titled Hexosaminidase A Deficiency, for which GM2 gangliosidosis is a recognized synonym.) Note: Synonyms are listed at the top of the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapter, following the title.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Many <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapter titles are based on a specific gene (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">MED12</italic>-Related Disorders). In this case, your search term is likely a disorder included in the scope of the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> (e.g., a search for Lujan syndrome will yield <italic toggle="yes">MED12</italic>-Related Disorders as a result, as Lujan syndrome is one of the disorders included in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>
          <bold>Q: I know the name of one of the authors on the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> I&#x02019;m trying to find, but when I search on the author&#x02019;s name, I don&#x02019;t get any results.</bold>
        </p>
        <p><bold>A:</bold> Two possible explanations:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>You may be spelling the name incorrectly. Type the first few letters of the author&#x02019;s surname and select from the auto-complete options that appear.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>The author whose name you are searching on may not be <bold>current</bold> (i.e., he/she may have elected not to participate in the most recent update of the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> in question). Check the <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="authors" document-type="appendix">Author List</related-object>, which includes both current and former authors and provides links to their <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic>.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>
          <bold>Q: I entered search information in more than one category, and I don&#x02019;t get any results.</bold>
        </p>
        <p><bold>A:</bold> The default setting for the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> Advanced Search combines terms using &#x02018;AND.&#x02019; With &#x02018;AND,&#x02019; each additional search term further limits your results (e.g., Disorder &#x02018;ataxia&#x02019; AND Author &#x02018;Bird TD&#x02019; yields only those <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> that feature (1) the word &#x02018;ataxia&#x02019; in the title or synonyms AND (2) Bird TD as an author). </p>
        <p>You can change this default in the &#x02018;AND&#x02019; box to &#x02018;OR&#x02019; or &#x02018;NOT&#x02019;:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>A search of Disorder &#x02018;ataxia&#x02019; OR Author &#x02018;Bird TD&#x02019; returns all <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapters that have either Ataxia within the title or synonyms OR Bird TD as the author; this will be a longer list.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Using the same example with the &#x02018;NOT&#x02019; option (Disorder &#x02018;ataxia&#x02019; NOT Author &#x02018;Bird TD&#x02019;) returns <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> chapters with &#x02018;ataxia&#x02019; in the title or synonyms for which Bird TD is not an author.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>For further explanation of Boolean operators, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK3827/#pubmedhelp.Combining_search_ter">Combining search terms with Boolean operators (AND, OR, NOT)</ext-link>.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>Q: I entered a search term, and I don&#x02019;t get any results.</bold>
        </p>
        <p><bold>A:</bold> You may have entered only part of a word, in which case a match will not always be found (e.g., a Gene Symbol search on BRCA will locate neither <italic toggle="yes">BRCA1</italic> nor <italic toggle="yes">BRCA2</italic>). If you are searching by Gene Symbol, Author, or Protein Name, the <bold>auto-complete</bold> feature is the best way to ensure a successful result; if you do not see your search term in the drop-down list, it is not in the <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> database.</p>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
