<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="kos" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">kos</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Kaufman Oculocerebrofacial Syndrome</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: Blepharophimosis-Ptosis-Intellectual Disability (BPID) Syndrome</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Basel-Vanagaite</surname>
            <given-names>Lina</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Schneider Children&#x02019;s Medical Center<break/>Petah Tikva, Israel</aff>
          <email>basel@post.tau.ac.il</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Borck</surname>
            <given-names>Guntram</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>University of Ulm<break/>Ulm, Germany</aff>
          <email>guntram.borck@uni-ulm.de</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="kabuki" document-type="chapter">Kabuki Syndrome</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="kindler" document-type="chapter">Kindler Syndrome</related-object>
      <abstract id="kos.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome (KOS) is characterized by severe intellectual disability and distinctive craniofacial features. Most affected children have prenatal-onset microcephaly, failure to thrive, hypotonia, and short stature. Eye abnormalities are common and can include structural abnormalities (microcornea or microphthalmia, coloboma, optic nerve hypoplasia), refractive errors (myopia &#x000b1; astigmatism, hyperopia), strabismus, and entropion. Less common findings can include: unilateral or bilateral conductive hearing loss or mixed conductive-sensorineural hearing loss of variable severity; congenital heart defects; breathing problems; feeding difficulties; urogenital abnormalities; and/or skeletal abnormalities.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of KOS is established in a proband with developmental delay/intellectual disability and biallelic <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Educational intervention and speech therapy beginning in infancy; early intervention as needed for feeding problems; routine management of ophthalmologic findings, hearing loss, congenital heart defects, urogenital abnormalities, and skeletal abnormalities.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> At least annual assessment of growth, developmental progress, vision, and hearing and examination for evidence of contractures and/or scoliosis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>KOS is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Once the <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, carrier testing for at-risk relatives, prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk, and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="kos.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>No formal diagnostic criteria have been published for Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome (KOS).</p>
        <sec id="kos.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome (KOS) <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following clinical and supportive laboratory findings.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Clinical findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Severe intellectual disability</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A typical and recognizable pattern of craniofacial features* (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="kos.F1">Figure 1</xref>):</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Eyebrows: highly arched, laterally broad with flaring (medial or lateral)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Telecanthus, blepharophimosis with epicanthal folds, ptosis, upslanted palpebral fissures</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Ears: often apparently low-set with overfolded helices and small lobes; variably seen: cupped ears, underdeveloped crus helix, preauricular tags</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Narrow nasal bridge, wide nasal base, anteverted nares</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Flat zygomata</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Long, flat philtrum</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Narrow mouth, thin vermilion of the upper lip with absent cupid's bow</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Micrognathia</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>*With age, the face becomes more elongated, the zygomata become flatter and the palpebral fissures more upslanted, and the alae nasi thicken [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>]. Micrognathia also becomes less prominent with age. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="kos.F1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
          <p>Note: In rare instances individuals with no or only mild characteristic facial features have biallelic <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Supportive laboratory findings.</bold> Low serum concentration of cholesterol (performed as part of routine laboratory testing) in some individuals</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with developmental delay/intellectual disability and biallelic <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants.</p>
          <p>Molecular testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold>, use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>, and <bold>more comprehensive</bold>
<bold>genomic testing</bold>:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> is performed first. Although gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis could be considered if only one pathogenic variant is found, to date no <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> deletion has been reported in individuals with a firm clinical diagnosis of KOS, unexplained KOS, or KOS-like syndrome [G Borck, personal observation].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="kos.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of the condition at the most reasonable cost. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing based tests.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>More comprehensive genomic testing</bold> (when available) including exome sequencing and genome sequencing may be considered if single-gene testing (and/or use of a multi-gene panel that includes <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic>) fails to confirm a diagnosis in an individual with features of KOS. Such testing may provide or suggest a diagnosis not previously considered (e.g., mutation of a different gene or genes that results in a similar clinical presentation). For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="kos.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Kaufman Oculocerebrofacial Syndrome</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_kos.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_kos.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_kos.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Pathogenic Variant&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/11&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="kos.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="kos" object-id="kos.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="kos.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="kos.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="kos.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="kos.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.pedurupillay.2015.657">Pedurupillay et al [2015]</xref> and references therein</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="kos.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kos.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="kos.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome (KOS) was described in 1971 as a distinct clinical entity characterized by severe developmental delay combined with a distinct pattern of ocular and other craniofacial abnormalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.kaufman.1971.135">Kaufman et al 1971</xref>]. This report was followed by more reports of individuals with the combination of clinical features compatible with KOS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.jurenka.1979.15">Jurenka &#x00026; Evans1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.garciacruz.1988.152">Garcia-Cruz et al 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.figuera.1993.98">Figuera et al 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.briscioli.1995.21">Briscioli et al 1995</xref>].</p>
          <p>Subsequently, biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> have been described in individuals with KOS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2012.998">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.flex.2013.493">Flex et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.pedurupillay.2015.657">Pedurupillay et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p>Some individuals clinically diagnosed with Toriello-Carey syndrome (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/217980">217980</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.toriello.2003.84">Toriello et al 2003</xref>] and an individual with a syndrome described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.buntinx.1990.273">Buntinx &#x00026; Majewski [1990]</xref> have later been found to have biallelic <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p>As of September 2016, 14 individuals (from 11 families) with KOS and biallelic <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants have been reported; it is anticipated that as more individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis are identified more details about this rare disorder will emerge.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Neurologic abnormalities/cognitive development</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Most affected children have prenatal microcephaly or a small occipitofrontal head circumference (OFC) at birth (&#x0003c;10<sup>th</sup> centile) which persists postnatally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>]. Microcephaly is often moderate with OFC -2 to -3 SD; it is not currently known to worsen with age. The OFC of the oldest individual with biallelic <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants was at the 75<sup>th</sup> centile at age 33 years; his father also had a large OFC. Note, however, that only a small number of affected persons have been reported thus far.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hypotonia and delayed motor milestones are universal findings.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The onset of independent ambulation varies; in most it is achieved by age four to five years. Gait is frequently described as unsteady.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Intellectual disability is severe to profound in the individuals reported to date; rare affected individuals develop limited speech.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Seizures are observed occasionally, usually fever related.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Structural central nervous system abnormalities include absent or hypoplastic corpus callosum; Chiari 1 malformation has been reported in one individual.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Growth</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Most affected children have failure to thrive and short stature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Stature is usually below the 10<sup>th</sup> centile or -2 to -3 SD; however, the number of reported individuals is small.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Ectodermal abnormalities</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Sparse scalp hair, thin skin, dry skin, and hyperkeratosis are noted in some infants. The appearance of the scalp hair improves with age.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Small teeth and nail dysplasia have also been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Ocular abnormalities</bold> (not universally present) can include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Structural abnormalities (microcornea or microphthalmia, coloboma, optic nerve hypoplasia);</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Refractive errors (myopia with or without astigmatism, hyperopia);</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Abnormal alignment of the eyes (strabismus);</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Entropion (inward turning of the lower eyelid).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Hearing loss</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Hearing impairment, if present, includes unilateral or bilateral conductive hearing loss or mixed conductive-sensorineural hearing loss of variable severity.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Two affected individuals had cholesteatoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Congenital heart malformations,</bold> observed in some, include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Pulmonary artery stenosis and septal hypertrophy;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Atrial septal defect;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ventricular septal defect;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Aortic coarctation.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Respiratory tract abnormalities</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Breathing problems include tracheomalacia, subglottic stenosis, laryngomalacia, and obstructive sleep apnea.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Tracheostomy is needed in some instances.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Gastrointestinal tract abnormalities</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Feeding difficulties are manifest as failure to thrive, poor suck, and gastroesophageal reflux. Feeding by gastric tube is needed in some individuals.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Constipation has been present in several individuals.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>One individual had intestinal malrotation.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Urogenital abnormalities</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Genital abnormalities (more frequent in females than males) include hypoplastic labia majora and/or minora or clitoromegaly.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Micropenis was described in some males.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Renal abnormalities include vesicoureteral reflux up to grade V and duplicated renal pelvis.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Skeletal abnormalities</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Chest is abnormal in shape (bell-shaped thorax, pectus carinatum).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Fingers and toes are long and slender. Other findings include bilateral postaxial polydactyly, fifth finger clinodactyly, hypoplastic distal phalanges, and metatarsus adductus.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Congenital hip dysplasia or coxa valga has been observed in several affected individuals.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>An additional skeletal finding is scoliosis.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Endocrine abnormalities</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Approximately half of affected individuals have abnormal cholesterol levels including low total cholesterol, low HDL, low LDL levels, or a combination of any of these.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Transiently elevated TSH, reduced thyroid gland volume, and low GH and ACTH were observed occasionally.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Pregnancy and birth</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Congenital structural malformations or polyhydramnios may be detected on prenatal ultrasound examination.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Affected infants are usually born at term with borderline low or normal birth weight.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic alleles identified in individuals with typical KOS are missense substitutions in highly conserved amino acid residues of the HECT domain or frameshift and nonsense variants that are predicted to lead to nonsense-mediated mRNA decay and/or protein truncation. These variants presumably completely abolish the E3 ligase enzyme activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2012.998">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p>One individual with mild craniofacial dysmorphism but without blepharophimosis was homozygous for two missense variants (both carried by both parents) each affecting a conserved amino acid residue outside the IQ and HECT domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>Prior to the identification of causative biallelic <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants, the following phenotypes (now known to be Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome) were thought to be distinct disorders:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Blepharophimosis-ptosis-intellectual disability (BPID) syndrome</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Phenotype seen in a subset of patients clinically diagnosed with Toriello-Carey syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.toriello.2003.84">Toriello et al 2003</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Phenotype described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.buntinx.1990.273">Buntinx &#x00026; Majewski [1990]</xref></p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>The prevalence of Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome (KOS) is unknown.</p>
          <p>As of September 2016, 14 individuals (from 11 families) with KOS and biallelic <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants have been reported from different geographic/ethnic origins. While it may be underdiagnosed, KOS is estimated to be very rare.</p>
          <p>It is not currently known whether the disease is more prevalent in certain regions (e.g., due to a founder variant).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kos.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disorder">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic>.</p>
        <p>Of note, in a cohort of individuals with autism, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.chahrour.2012.e1002635">Chahrour et al [2012]</xref> identified monozygotic twins homozygous for a <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> missense variant that was predicted to be pathogenic. Because no clinical data were provided, it is not possible to determine if these twins had KOS with autistic features or nonsyndromic autism.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kos.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome (KOS) has a relatively uniform, clinically recognizable phenotype mainly due to the characteristic dysmorphic features combined with severe intellectual disability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>]. Because of the co-occurrence of blepharophimosis and intellectual disability, the differential diagnosis mainly includes &#x02013; besides small chromosomal deletions or duplications identified by chromosomal microarray analysis &#x02013; other Mendelian blepharophimosis-intellectual disability syndromes; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe">Table 2</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Disorders to Consider in the Differential Diagnosis of Kaufman Oculocerebrofacial Syndrome (KOS)</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_1">Disorder</th>
                <th id="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_2">Gene</th>
                <th id="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_3" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_3">MOI</th>
                <th id="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Clinical Features</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4" id="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Overlapping with KOS</th>
                <th headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4" id="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distinguishing from KOS</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome 3pter-p25 deletion syndrome (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/613792">613792</ext-link>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intellectual disability; blepharophimosis; growth retardation; postaxial polydactyly</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trigonocephaly</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ohdo syndrome (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/249620">249620</ext-link>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_2 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">See footnote 1</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intellectual disability; blepharophimosis; congenital heart disease; ptosis; hypoplastic teeth</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal nasal shape is not a characteristic feature.<break/>Normal growth; no limb defects</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="kat6b-dis" document-type="chapter">Say-Barber-Biesecker variant of Ohdo syndrome</related-object> (also known as Say-Barber-Biesecker/Young-Simpson syndrome)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">KAT6B</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart defects; hearing loss; optic atrophy; cleft palate; dental anomalies, including small &#x00026; pointed teeth</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distinctive facial features&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup>; joint limitations; hypothyroidism.<break/>Individuals with this syndrome and the allelic disorder genitopatellar syndrome (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/606170">606170</ext-link>) have patellar hypoplasia.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maat-Kievit-Brunner syndrome or X-linked Ohdo syndrome (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/300895">300895</ext-link>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">MED12</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XL</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intellectual disability; constipation; hypotonia</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distinctive facial features&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blepharophimosis w/facial &#x00026; genital anomalies &#x00026; intellectual disability, Verloes type (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/604314">604314</ext-link>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_2 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">See footnote 4</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe microcephaly; cleft palate</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypsarrhythmia; adducted thumbs; abnormal genitalia</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="slo" document-type="chapter">Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">DHCR7</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth retardation; microcephaly; moderate-to-severe intellectual disability; cleft palate; cardiac defects</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_1_4 hd_h_kos.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_diffe_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic facial features <sup>5</sup>; underdeveloped external genitalia in males; 2-3 syndactyly of the toes</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>MOI = mode of inheritance</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AD = autosomal dominant</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AR = autosomal recessive</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>XL = X-linked</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="kos.TF.2.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>The molecular cause of this syndrome is unknown; cryptic chromosomal rearrangement has not been excluded in the original family described by Ohdo.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="kos.TF.2.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>Bulbous nasal tip, dysplastic ears, mask-like facial appearance and retrognathia</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="kos.TF.2.3">
              <label>3. </label>
              <p>Triangular and coarse facies with thick alae nasi</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="kos.TF.2.4">
              <label>4. </label>
              <p>The genetic basis of this presumably autosomal recessive syndrome is unknown.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="kos.TF.2.5">
              <label>5. </label>
              <p>Epicanthal folds, ptosis, short nose with anteverted nares</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kos.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="kos.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diagno">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome (KOS), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Developmental assessment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Growth assessment, including assessment of feeding and nutrition</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ophthalmologic evaluation for microcornea, cataract, ptosis, coloboma</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hearing evaluation for sensorineural or mixed sensorineural/conductive hearing impairment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Echocardiogram for congenital heart defects</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation for laryngomalacia if respiratory issues are present</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation for the presence of gastrointestinal reflux, bowel malrotation if indicated</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation of males for cryptorchidism</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Renal ultrasound examination for structural renal abnormalities and vesicoureteral reflux</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hip ultrasound examination to evaluate for femoral head dislocation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation of thyroid function; other hormone levels if clinically indicated</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>The following treatment recommendations are appropriate:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Developmental.</bold> Educational intervention and speech therapy beginning in infancy</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Failure to thrive.</bold> Intervention for feeding problems as needed in infancy and childhood</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Eyes.</bold> Cataract and ptosis surgery if indicated</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Hearing loss.</bold> Hearing aids or cochlear implant if needed</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Cardiac</bold> Function assessment and treatment if needed</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Genital anomalies.</bold> Orchidopexy in males with undescended testes</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Renal anomalies.</bold> Treatment of vesicoureteral reflux if indicated</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Skeletal.</bold> Referral to an orthopedist if joint dislocations or scoliosis is present, early referral to physical therapy</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Endocrine.</bold> Thyroid hormone replacement as needed</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Other facial.</bold> Cleft palate repair if present</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>The following should be assessed at least annually:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Growth</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Developmental progress</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Vision, hearing</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Contractures and/or scoliosis</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="kos.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kos.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="kos.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome (KOS) is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected child are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variant). (<italic toggle="yes">De novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants, although possible, have not been reported to date.)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Individuals with KOS are not known to reproduce.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier of a <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Carrier_Heterozygote_Detection">
          <title>Carrier (Heterozygote) Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants in the family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are carriers or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kos.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantation">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased and preimplantation genetic diagnosis risk for KOS are possible.</p>
          <p>Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions about prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kos.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kos.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="kos.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>The primary protein sequence and domain architecture of UBE3B predict an E3 ligase function. The <italic toggle="yes">C. elegans</italic> ortholog of UBE3B is indeed involved in protein degradation by the ubiquitin proteasome system under oxidative stress conditions. It is therefore likely that human UBE3B also functions as an ubiquitin ligase in vivo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2012.998">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2012</xref>]. However, specific ubiquitination targets of UBE3B have not been identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.gong.2003.143">Gong et al 2003</xref>].</p>
          <p>In mice, predominant expression of <italic toggle="yes">Ube3b</italic> has been observed prenatally in the developing central nervous system including the ventricular zone of the cerebral cortex and the hippocampal anlage. Postnatally, prominent <italic toggle="yes">Ube3b</italic> expression is observed in the cerebral cortex, the cerebellum, and the hippocampus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2012.998">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2012</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Ube3b<sup>-/-</sup></italic> mice have severely reduced body weight, small body size, smaller brain, reduced grip strength, lower low-density lipoprotein (LDL) levels, mild hearing impairment, and corneal abnormalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2012.998">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2012</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> has five transcript variants:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Two encode longer transcripts (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_130466.3">NM_130466.3</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_183415.2">NM_183415.2</ext-link>), which comprise 28 exons and encode an 1,068 amino acid protein isoform (~123 kd)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Three encode shorter transcript variants (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001270449.1">NM_001270449.1</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001270451.1">NM_001270451.1</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001270450.1">NM_001270450.1</ext-link>), which comprise nine exons and are predicted to encode a 244-amino acid protein.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="hops" object-id="hops.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product</bold>. <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> encodes the protein ubiquitin-protein ligase E3B, containing an N-terminal IQ domain and a C-terminal HECT domain. The HECT domain in the C-terminus of the longer isoform of this protein is the likely catalytic site of ubiquitin transfer and forms a complex with E2 conjugating enzyme. Shorter isoforms of this protein lack the C-terminal HECT domain and, if produced, are unlikely to interact with E2 enzymes.</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Most <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants in individuals with KOS affect the HECT domain or are expected to result in nonsense-mediated mRNA decay and/or protein truncation, leading to a loss of function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2012.998">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.flex.2013.493">Flex et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.pedurupillay.2015.657">Pedurupillay et al 2015</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kos.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="kos.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="kos.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2012.998">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Basel-Vanagaite</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dallapiccola</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ramirez-Solis</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Segref</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thiele</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Edwards</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arends</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mir&#x000f3;</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>White</surname>
                    <given-names>JK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>D&#x000e9;sir</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abramowicz</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dentici</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lepri</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hofmann</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Har-Zahav</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ryder</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Karp</surname>
                    <given-names>NA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Estabel</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gerdin</surname>
                    <given-names>AK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Podrini</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ingham</surname>
                    <given-names>NJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Altm&#x000fc;ller</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>N&#x000fc;rnberg</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frommolt</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abdelhak</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pasmanik-Chor</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Konen</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kelley</surname>
                    <given-names>RI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shohat</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>N&#x000fc;rnberg</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Flint</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steel</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoppe</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kubisch</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adams</surname>
                    <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Borck</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Deficiency for the ubiquitin ligase UBE3B in a blepharophimosis-ptosis-intellectual-disability syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>91</volume>
                <fpage>998</fpage>
                <lpage>1010</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23200864</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Basel-Vanagaite</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yilmaz</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tang</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reuter</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rahner</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grange</surname>
                    <given-names>DK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mortenson</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koty</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feenstra</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Farwell Gonzalez</surname>
                    <given-names>KD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sticht</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boddaert</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>D&#x000e9;sir</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Anyane-Yeboa</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zweier</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reis</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kubisch</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jewett</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeng</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Borck</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Expanding the clinical and mutational spectrum of Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome with biallelic UBE3B mutations.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>133</volume>
                <fpage>939</fpage>
                <lpage>49</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24615390</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.briscioli.1995.21">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Briscioli</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Manoukian</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Selicorni</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Livini</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lalatta</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome in a girl of 15 years.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>1995</year>
                <volume>58</volume>
                <fpage>21</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7573151</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.buntinx.1990.273">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Buntinx</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Majewski</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Blepharophimosis, iris coloboma, microgenia, hearing loss, postaxial polydactyly, aplasia of corpus callosum, hydroureter, and developmental delay.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
                <year>1990</year>
                <volume>36</volume>
                <fpage>273</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1694631</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.chahrour.2012.e1002635">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chahrour</surname>
                    <given-names>MH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yu</surname>
                    <given-names>TW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lim</surname>
                    <given-names>ET</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ataman</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coulter</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hill</surname>
                    <given-names>RS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stevens</surname>
                    <given-names>CR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schubert</surname>
                    <given-names>CR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <collab>ARRA Autism Sequencing Collaboration</collab>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Greenberg ME, Gabriel SB, Walsh CA. Whole-exome sequencing and homozygosity analysis implicate depolarization-regulated neuronal genes in autism.</article-title>
                <source>PLoS Genet.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>e1002635</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22511880</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.figuera.1993.98">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Figuera</surname>
                    <given-names>LE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Cruz</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez-Due&#x000f1;as</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rivera-Robles</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cant&#x000f9;</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome: report of two new cases and further delineation.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Genet.</source>
                <year>1993</year>
                <volume>44</volume>
                <fpage>98</fpage>
                <lpage>101</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8275567</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.flex.2013.493">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Flex</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ciolfi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Caputo</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fodale</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leoni</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Melis</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bedeschi</surname>
                    <given-names>MF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mazzanti</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pizzuti</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tartaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zampino</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Loss of function of the E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase UBE3B causes Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>50</volume>
                <fpage>493</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23687348</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.garciacruz.1988.152">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garcia-Cruz</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arreola</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sanchez-Corona</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garcia-Cruz</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Renteria</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Villar</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gonzalez</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vargas-Moyeda</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cantu</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome: a corroborative report.</article-title>
                <source>Dysmorph Clin Genet.</source>
                <year>1988</year>
                <volume>1</volume>
                <fpage>152</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.gong.2003.143">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gong</surname>
                    <given-names>TW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Warner</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lomax</surname>
                    <given-names>MI</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Characterization of the human UBE3B gene: structure, expression, evolution, and alternative splicing.</article-title>
                <source>Genomics.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>82</volume>
                <fpage>143</fpage>
                <lpage>52</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12837265</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.jurenka.1979.15">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jurenka</surname>
                    <given-names>SB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Evans</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome: case report.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>1979</year>
                <volume>3</volume>
                <fpage>15</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">112864</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.kaufman.1971.135">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaufman</surname>
                    <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rimoin</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prensky</surname>
                    <given-names>AL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sly</surname>
                    <given-names>WS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>An oculocerebrofacial syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Birth Defects Orig Artic Ser.</source>
                <year>1971</year>
                <volume>7</volume>
                <fpage>135</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5006210</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.pedurupillay.2015.657">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pedurupillay</surname>
                    <given-names>CR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bar&#x000f8;y</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Holmgren</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blomhoff</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vigeland</surname>
                    <given-names>MD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sheng</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frengen</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Str&#x000f8;mme</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Misceo</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Kaufman oculocerebrofacial syndrome in sisters with novel compound heterozygous mutation in UBE3B.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>167A</volume>
                <fpage>657</fpage>
                <lpage>63</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25691420</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kos.REF.toriello.2003.84">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Toriello</surname>
                    <given-names>HV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carey</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Addor</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Allen</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burke</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chun</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dobyns</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elias</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallagher</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hordijk</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoyme</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Irons</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jewett</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>LeMerrer</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lubinsky</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martin</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McDonald-McGinn</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Neumann</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Newman</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pauli</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seaver</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsai</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wargowsky</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zackai</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Toriello-Carey syndrome: delineation and review.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>123A</volume>
                <fpage>84</fpage>
                <lpage>90</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14556252</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kos.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="kos.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>20 October 2016 (bp) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>25 January 2016 (lbv) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="kos.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Facial dysmorphism associated with KOS caused by biallelic <italic toggle="yes">UBE3B</italic> pathogenic variants. See text for a detailed description of dysmorphic features. Affected individuals pictured are individuals 1, 2, 3, 4, and 6 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kos.REF.baselvanagaite.2014.939">Basel-Vanagaite et al [2014]</xref>.Photographs published with permission of the families</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="kos-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
