<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="myhre" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">myhre</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Myhre Syndrome</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: Laryngotracheal Stenosis, Arthropathy, Prognathism, and Short Stature (LAPS) Syndrome; Myhre-LAPS Syndrome</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Starr</surname>
            <given-names>Lois J</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>University of Nebraska Medical Center<break/>Omaha, Nebraska</aff>
          <email>lstarr@unmc.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Lindor</surname>
            <given-names>Noralane M</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Mayo Clinic<break/>Phoenix, Arizona</aff>
          <email>nlindor@mayo.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Angela E</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>MassGeneral Hospital for Children<break/>Boston, Massachusetts</aff>
          <email>lin.angela@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="edm" document-type="chapter">Multiple Epiphyseal Dysplasia, Recessive</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="myo-dystonia" document-type="chapter">Myoclonus-Dystonia</related-object>
      <abstract id="myhre.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Myhre syndrome is a connective tissue disorder with multisystem involvement, progressive and proliferative fibrosis that may occur spontaneously or following trauma or surgery, mild-to-moderate intellectual disability, and in some instances, autistic-like behaviors. Organ systems primarily involved include: cardiovascular (congenital heart defects, long- and short-segment stenosis of the aorta and peripheral arteries, pericardial effusion, constrictive pericarditis, restrictive cardiomyopathy, and hypertension); respiratory (choanal stenosis, laryngotracheal narrowing, obstructive airway disease, or restrictive pulmonary disease), gastrointestinal (pyloric stenosis, duodenal strictures, severe constipation); and skin (thickened particularly on the hands and extensor surfaces). Additional findings include distinctive craniofacial features and skeletal involvement (intrauterine growth restriction, short stature, limited joint range of motion). To date, 55 individuals with molecularly confirmed Myhre syndrome have been reported.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of Myhre syndrome is established by detecting a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> heterozygous pathogenic variant in a proband with characteristic clinical findings.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Symptomatic treatment (with attention to limiting tissue trauma by minimizing instrumentation during diagnosis and management) by specialty experts of the following involvement: cardiovascular, respiratory (including tracheostomy when tracheal stenosis is recurrent or complete), and GI; routine management of speech and language delay, intellectual disability, behavioral problems.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> Limiting of tissue trauma given the apparent increased risk for proliferative fibrosis following otherwise uncomplicated endotracheal intubation and surgical procedures. When possible, alternative noninvasive approaches should be pursued during diagnosis and management</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Cardiovascular: echocardiogram every one to three years in asymptomatic individuals with a normal echocardiogram at the time of initial diagnosis; in individuals with abnormal cardiac findings at the time of diagnosis, more extensive imaging (including possible cardiac MRI) may be considered. Respiratory: oxygen saturation in children with monitoring as needed for symptoms suggestive of restrictive/obstructive pulmonary disease; annual pulmonary function studies in children oldert than age six years if able to cooperate; evaluation of laryngotracheal stenosis based on symptoms. Annual ophthalmology and audiology evaluations.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Smoking; tissue trauma.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>Myhre syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. All probands with Myhre syndrome reported to date have the disorder as a result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant. If the <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, the risk to sibs is presumed to be slightly greater than that of the general population (though still &#x0003c;1%) because of the theoretic possibility of parental germline mosaicism. To date, individuals with Myhre syndrome are not known to reproduce and fertility has not been assessed. Once the <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at theoretic increased risk for Myhre syndrome and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="myhre.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Formal diagnostic criteria have not been published for Myhre syndrome.</p>
        <sec id="myhre.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Myhre syndrome <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following clinical and radiographic findings.</p>
          <sec id="myhre.Clinical">
            <title>Clinical</title>
            <p>
              <bold>Cardiovascular</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Arterial obstruction: juxtaductal coarctation of the aorta, long- and short-segment descending thoracic and abdominal aortic obstruction, and peripheral arteries in various locations; infrequently, branch pulmonary artery stenosis</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Congenital heart defects:</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Atrial and ventricular septal defects, patent ductus arteriosus</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Valvular stenosis: aortic and mitral valves; infrequently, tricuspid and pulmonic valves</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Pericardial involvement: ranges from effusion to constrictive pericarditis; often chronic and severe</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Restrictive cardiomyopathy (can be rapidly progressive)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Hypertension: systemic and pulmonary</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Respiratory (congenital or acquired)</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Laryngotracheal narrowing (including subglottic stenosis)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Choanal stenosis</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Obstructive airway disease</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Restrictive pulmonary disease (which appears to increase with age)</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Gastrointestinal</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Congenital or acquired pyloric stenosis</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Later onset:</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Duodenal strictures</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Severe constipation</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Skin</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Stiff and thickened overall, but particularly on the hands and extensor surfaces</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Facial creases fewer than expected for age</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Proliferative fibrosis/scarring</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>May occur spontaneously or following trauma or surgery</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>May involve the serosal surfaces of the heart, airway and lungs, and gastrointestinal tract as well as the skin</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Neuropsychiatric</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Mild-to-moderate intellectual disability</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Autistic-like behaviors in some</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Craniofacial</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Characteristic facial features including short palpebral fissures, deeply set eyes, maxillary underdevelopment, short philtrum, narrow mouth, thin vermilion of the upper lip, and prognathism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F1">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F2">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F3">Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F4">Figure 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F5">Figure 5</xref>). Facial characteristics can progress over time; although classic coarsening of features is not present, mandibular elongation is notable. Note: Craniofacial features can vary considerably.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Cleft lip and/or palate and velopharyngeal insufficiency reported in 13% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al 2016</xref>]</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Skeletal</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Infants typically have intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Short stature (height is significantly less than that predicted by parental heights) with compact body habitus</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Range of motion of the joints can be limited</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="myhre.Radiographic">
            <title>Radiographic</title>
            <p>Findings include the following:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Thickened calvarium</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Shortened long bones</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Brachydactyly</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Broad ribs</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Enlarged vertebrae with shortened pedicles; vertebral fusion</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Hypoplastic iliac wings</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F6">Figure 6</xref>.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of Myhre syndrome <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with characteristic clinical findings and a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> heterozygous pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> detected by molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing approaches can include a combination of <bold>gene-targeted testing</bold> (multi-gene panel or single-gene testing) and <bold>genomic testing</bold> (comprehensive genome sequencing).</p>
          <p>Gene-targeted testing requires the clinician to determine which gene(s) are likely involved, whereas genomic testing may not. Persons with the distinctive findings described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Suggestive_Findings">Suggestive Findings</xref> are likely to be diagnosed using gene-targeted testing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Option_1">Option 1</xref>), whereas those in whom a specific diagnosis has been elusive are more likely to be diagnosed using genomic testing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Option_2">Option 2</xref>).</p>
          <sec id="myhre.Option_1">
            <title>Option 1</title>
            <p>When the phenotypic and radiographic findings suggest the diagnosis of Myhre syndrome, molecular genetic testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold> or use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> is performed first. If no pathogenic variant is found, gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis may be considered; to date, however, no exon or whole-gene deletions have been reported.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of the condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting secondary findings. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing based tests.</p>
                <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="myhre.Option_2">
            <title>Option 2</title>
            <p>When the diagnosis of Myhre syndrome has not been considered, <bold>genomic testing</bold> (comprehensive genome sequencing) is likely to be the diagnostic modality selected. Comprehensive genome sequencing (when clinically available) includes exome sequencing and genome sequencing. For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            <table-wrap id="myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 1. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Myhre Syndrome</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                    <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Pathogenic Variant&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55/55&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
              <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn id="myhre.TF.1.1">
                  <label>1. </label>
                  <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="myhre" object-id="myhre.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="myhre.TF.1.2">
                  <label>2. </label>
                  <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="myhre.TF.1.3">
                  <label>3. </label>
                  <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="myhre.TF.1.4">
                  <label>4. </label>
                  <p>54 patients summarized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al [2016]</xref> and one patient reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.bassett.2016.54">Bassett et al [2016]</xref></p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="myhre.TF.1.5">
                  <label>5. </label>
                  <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="myhre.TF.1.6">
                  <label>6. </label>
                  <p>No data on detection rate of gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis are available.</p>
                </fn>
              </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="myhre.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="myhre.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Myhre syndrome is a multisystem connective tissue disorder involving: the cardiovascular system, respiratory system, gastrointestinal tract, and skin; progressive and proliferative fibrosis that may occur spontaneously or following trauma or surgery, often resulting in significant complications; mild-to-moderate intellectual disability; and behavioral issues in some. Additional findings include distinctive craniofacial features and skeletal involvement.</p>
          <p>Myhre syndrome was first described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.myhre.1981.1">Myhre et al [1981]</xref> in two unrelated males. Since 2011, when heterozygosity for a <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant was found to be causative, 55 affected individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis of Myhre syndrome have been reported. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al [2016]</xref> reported four affected individuals and summarized findings in 50 previously reported individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.le_goff.2011.85">Le Goff et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.al_ageeli.2012.541">Al Ageeli et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.asakura.2012.1982">Asakura et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.caputo.2012.161">Caputo et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lindor.2012.1520">Lindor et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.picco.2013.1164">Picco et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.ishibashi.2014.300">Ishibashi et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.kenis.2014.e253">Kenis et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.michot.2014.1272">Michot et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.hawkes.2015.84">Hawkes &#x00026; Kini 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.oldenburg.2015.636">Oldenburg et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>]. Subsequently <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.bassett.2016.54">Bassett et al [2016]</xref> reported one additional affected individual.</p>
          <p>Note: Unless otherwise noted, the following findings are reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al [2016]</xref>.</p>
          <p><bold>Infancy and progression of findings.</bold> In infancy, characteristic facial features are usually present, but more difficult to recognize than in an older child (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Suggestive_Findings">Suggestive Findings</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F1">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F2">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F3">Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F4">Figure 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F5">Figure 5</xref>). Short stature and hearing loss develop over time as well as the highly distinctive (and often severe) findings of Myhre syndrome: joint stiffness, restrictive lung and cardiovascular disease, progressive and proliferative fibrosis, and thickening of the skin.</p>
          <p><bold>Cardiovascular.</bold> Of 54 individuals with a confirmed molecular diagnosis of Myhre syndrome, 70% had a cardiovascular abnormality including structural heart defects (63%); pericardial disease (17%), restrictive cardiomyopathy (9%), and systemic hypertension (15%).</p>
          <p>Cardiovascular abnormalities include the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Atrial septal defect (4%) and ventricular septal defect (6%)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Patent ductus arteriosus (which can be large) (20%)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Obstructive defects of the left heart, such as juxtaductal aortic coarctation (15%), long-segment aorta narrowing (6%), aortic valve stenosis (15%), and mitral valve stenosis (2%). These are more common than obstructive defects of the right-side, such as valvar and branch pulmonary artery stenosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.michot.2014.1272">Michot et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.hawkes.2015.84">Hawkes &#x00026; Kini 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Peripheral vascular stenoses (in celiac and/or renal arteries) (7%)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Of note, complex congenital heart defects are not observed.</p>
          <p>Pericardial disease (reported in 17%) can present as a short-term or recurrent effusion or as chronic or progressive constrictive pericarditis that may require surgical intervention (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Management">Management</xref>).</p>
          <p>Restrictive cardiomyopathy, a lethal condition, is the least common form of cardiomyopathy in the general population and can be overlooked unless cardiac catheterization documents the characteristic hemodynamics.</p>
          <p>While constrictive pericarditis and restrictive cardiomyopathy can present with similar hemodynamics, they differ in pathogenesis and treatment (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Management">Management</xref>).</p>
          <p>Pulmonary hypertension has been infrequently reported; however, this may reflect limited evaluation and/or bias toward ascertainment and/or reporting of younger patients (as underlying causes of pulmonary hypertension resulting from involvement of the lungs and cardiovascular circulation may evolve with age).</p>
          <p>Progressive cardiovascular issues can appear at any age; those with onset in childhood may worsen following instrumentation: two patients with restrictive cardiomyopathy who were treated with heart and heart/lung transplantation did not survive postoperative complications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Respiratory.</bold> Respiratory issues can be multifactorial. Airway stenosis, typically involving the larynx and trachea, has included subglottic stenosis (17%) that can be recurrent and severe. Less common is upper airway obstruction due to choanal stenosis (11%).</p>
          <p>Restrictive and obstructive pulmonary disease are major causes of morbidity at all ages. Interstitial lung disease has been described. Severe pulmonary fibrosis has been noted on autopsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Gastrointestinal involvement</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Duodenal atresia 3/54 (6%)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Late-onset pyloric stenosis [L Starr, personal observation]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Protein-losing enteropathy (Patient 1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al 2016</xref>])</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Severe constipation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.michot.2014.1272">Michot et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Cutaneous.</bold> Generalized thickening/stiffness of the skin is seen in nearly all individuals with Myhre syndrome. Various terms used to describe the skin include thick, stiff, firm, rough, keratotic, and inelastic. Additional findings are minimal creasing of the facial skin and fibrous and keloid-like scar formation.</p>
          <p>Skin changes may not be apparent in infancy; they are often first noted on extensor surfaces, palms, and soles. The changes progress with age.</p>
          <p><bold>Neuropsychiatric.</bold> Data are limited. Mild-to-moderate intellectual disability and global developmental delay are common; however, cognition can be within the normal range. Of note, acquired and unrecognized hearing loss may also contribute to speech delay and academic and social challenges.</p>
          <p>Findings of autism spectrum disorder have been noted in a minority of affected individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.michot.2014.1272">Michot et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Skeletal.</bold> The majority of affected infants have intrauterine growth restriction (41/49; 84%). Short stature with compact body habitus (with normal head circumference) becomes more apparent over time. Adult height is expected to be more than two standard deviations below what is predicted by parental heights.</p>
          <p>Small hands and feet with brachydactyly is usually notable (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F3">Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F4">Figure 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F5">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
          <p>Posture may be distinct with flexed elbows and bending forward at the hips (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="myhre.F3">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.ishibashi.2014.300">Ishibashi et al [2014]</xref>, Figure 1).</p>
          <p>Reduced range of motion of large and small joints is characteristic and is exacerbated with age. Walking on tiptoes is common.</p>
          <p><bold>Immune system.</bold> Recurrent infections (especially otitis media and pneumonia) have been reported in 19 of 34 individuals. Increased susceptibility to infection has been associated with immunoglobulin deficiency in three affected individuals; IVIG was utilized with reported benefit in one affected individual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>]. At this point, it is unknown if immune deficiency is associated with Myhre syndrome or if it is an incidental finding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.michot.2014.1272">Michot et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Ophthalmologic.</bold> At least one abnormal eye finding was reported in 53% (26/49) of affected individuals:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Strabismus 13/53 (24%)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Refractive errors in 17/53 (31%)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Other. Cataracts, astigmatism, and optic nerve sheath meningioma</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Hearing loss</bold> is observed in most (83%) individuals with Myhre syndrome.</p>
          <p>Hearing loss is predominantly conductive, but can be sensorineural and mixed. The underlying etiology of the hearing loss is often unclear or unknown; most often patients have a history of bilateral myringotomy tube placement.</p>
          <p>Of note, most infants pass their newborn hearing screen. In the authors&#x02019; experience hearing loss usually becomes evident in early childhood and is typically present in adults.</p>
          <p><bold>Endocrine.</bold> Puberty has been reported to be normal, premature, or delayed. Secondary amenorrhea has been reported.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Neoplasia</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Endometrial carcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lindor.2012.1520">Lindor et al 2012</xref>], optic nerve sheath meningioma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>], and mesencephalic glioma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al 2016</xref>] have each been reported once.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Telangiectasias and juvenile polyps, reported in heterozygotes for a <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> loss-of-function pathogenic variant, have not been reported in Myhre syndrome; however, information to date is limited.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>The gain-of-function <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variants that cause Myhre syndrome involve only two protein residues (codons 496 and 500). To date, no clear genotype-phenotype correlations are evident in affected individuals with either codon abnormality.</p>
          <p>Of note, although the three individuals reported with the p.Arg496C variant do not have cardiovascular involvement and are taller in stature &#x02013; two on the growth curve (2<sup>nd</sup>-25<sup>th</sup> centile) and one &#x0003c;1<sup>st</sup> centile [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.michot.2014.1272">Michot et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.caputo.2014.1835">Caputo et al 2014</xref>] &#x02013; the data are too limited to draw any conclusions about genotype-phenotype correlations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>Penetrance appears to be complete; however, no familial cases of Myhre syndrome have been reported.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>LAPS (<italic toggle="yes">l</italic>aryngotracheal stenosis, <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>rthropathy, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>rognathism, and <italic toggle="yes">s</italic>hort stature) syndrome was determined to be a phenotypic variant of Myhre syndrome with pathogenic variants in the same codons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lindor.2012.1520">Lindor et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.picco.2013.1164">Picco et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.michot.2014.1272">Michot et al 2014</xref>]; the term is no longer in use.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>The prevalence is unknown.</p>
          <p>Since 2011 when a heterozygous pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> was discovered to be the cause of Myhre syndrome, 55 affected individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis have been reported worldwide with no apparent ethnic or sex predilection (54 summarized in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al [2016]</xref> and one reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.bassett.2016.54">Bassett et al [2016]</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="myhre.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disord">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>Other phenotypes known to be associated with germline pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic>:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="jps" document-type="chapter">Juvenile polyposis syndrome</related-object> (JPS)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hht" document-type="chapter">Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia</related-object> (HHT)</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Whereas Myhre syndrome is caused by heterozygous gain-of-function <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variants (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>), JPS and HHT are caused by heterozygous loss-of-function <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="myhre.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>The disorders that most closely resemble Myhre syndrome are the other acromelic dysplasias: geleophysic dysplasia, acromicric dysplasia, and Weill-Marchesani syndrome, which share the findings of thickened skin, short stature, short hands, and stiff joints. MULIBREY nanism should also be considered.</p>
        <table-wrap id="myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Disorders to Consider in the Differential Diagnosis of Myhre Syndrome</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_1">Disorder</th>
                <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_2">Gene(s)</th>
                <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_3" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_3">MOI</th>
                <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Clinical Features of the Disorder</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4" id="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Overlapping with Myhre Syndrome</th>
                <th headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4" id="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distinguishing from Myhre Syndrome</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acromicric dysplasia<break/>(OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/102370">102370</ext-link>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">FBN1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4 hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>IUGR</p></list-item><list-item><p>Short stature</p></list-item><list-item><p>Brachydactyly</p></list-item><list-item><p>Joint stiffness</p></list-item><list-item><p>Thickened skin</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4 hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Characteristic external notch of the fifth metacarpal and internal notch of the femoral head</p></list-item><list-item><p>Absence of hearing loss</p></list-item><list-item><p>Less frequent cardiac anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Absence of calvarial thickening</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="geleophys-dysp" document-type="chapter">Geleophysic dysplasia</related-object>&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ADAMTSL2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4 hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>IUGR</p></list-item><list-item><p>Short stature</p></list-item><list-item><p>Short hands and feet</p></list-item><list-item><p>Progressive joint limitation and contractures</p></list-item><list-item><p>Progressive cardiac valvar thickening</p></list-item><list-item><p>Thickened skin</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4 hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Hepatomegaly</p></list-item><list-item><p>Characteristic facies</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">FBN1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="weill-ms" document-type="chapter">Weill-Marchesani syndrome</related-object>&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ADAMTS10</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">LTPBP2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4 hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>IUGR</p></list-item><list-item><p>Short stature</p></list-item><list-item><p>Brachydactyly</p></list-item><list-item><p>Joint stiffness</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4 hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Distinctive lens abnormalities&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></p></list-item><list-item><p>Lack of hearing loss</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">FBN1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MULIBREY nanism<break/>(OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/253250">253250</ext-link>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">TRIM37</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4 hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>IUGR</p></list-item><list-item><p>Short stature</p></list-item><list-item><p>Relatively large head</p></list-item><list-item><p>Constrictive pericarditis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Restrictive cardiomyopathy</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_1_4 hd_h_myhre.T.disorders_to_consider_in_the_dif_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Shorter stature</p></list-item><list-item><p>Small tongue</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>MOI = mode of inheritance</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AD = autosomal dominant</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AR = autosomal recessive</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>XL = X-linked</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>IUGR = intrauterine growth restriction</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="myhre.TF.2.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p><bold>Geleophysic dysplasia.</bold> Major findings are likely to be present in the first year of life. Cardiac and respiratory involvement result in death before age five years in approximately 33% of individuals with geleophysic dysplasia 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="myhre.TF.2.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p><bold>Weill-Marchesani syndrome.</bold> The ocular problems, typically recognized in childhood, include microspherophakia (small spherical lens), myopia secondary to the abnormal shape of the lens, ectopia lentis (abnormal position of the lens), and glaucoma, which can lead to blindness.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="myhre.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="myhre.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diag">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with Myhre syndrome, the following are recommended (if not completed previously as part of the diagnostic evaluation).</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Cardiovascular</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Upper- and lower-extremity blood pressure measurements</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Two-dimensional echocardiography with Doppler</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>For those with abnormal findings, more extensive imaging if indicated including cardiac catheterization to document the characteristic hemodynamics of restrictive cardiomyopathy</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Respiratory</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment for airway stenosis by the least invasive means possible with assessment for signs of upper-airway obstruction including noisy breathing, work of breathing, and oxygen saturation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of pulmonary function and oxygen saturation for evidence of obstructive or restrictive lung disease</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Gastrointestinal.</bold> Based on clinical indication (by least invasive means possible), evaluate for evidence of stenosis.</p>
          <p><bold>Neuropsychiatric.</bold> Neuropsychometric evaluation may be indicated for individuals with autistic behaviors and/or cognitive involvement.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Other</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Ophthalmology evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Speech evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Audiology evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Treatment is largely symptomatic and may include the following.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Cardiovascular</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Management by a cardiologist trained in congenital heart disease, including pericardial disease and restrictive cardiomyopathy. At present, no evidence suggests that in Myhre syndrome management of specific lesions would differ from standard care in current clinical practice, except that any unnecessary instrumentation should be avoided as associated tissue trauma may induce stenosis and the scarring-type tissue response unique to Myhre syndrome.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Affected individuals who are in heart failure should be under the care of a cardiovascular specialist with access to a transplant center.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Maximize all medical treatment and minimize instrumentation for all cardiac studies and therapies.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Medical treatment of systemic hypertension and pulmonary hypertension (based on underlying cause).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Respiratory</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Affected individuals have required long-term tracheostomy due to complete and recurrent tracheal stenosis following multiple and/or traumatic intubations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.mcgowan.2011.e553">McGowan et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.oldenburg.2015.636">Oldenburg et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>]. To avoid traumatic intubation, consider using a size-smaller uncuffed endotracheal tube. Elective tracheal surgery/intubation should be avoided; tracheal resection is contraindicated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.oldenburg.2015.636">Oldenburg et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Symptomatic treatment of restrictive lung disease</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Oxygen supplementation as necessary</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Gastrointestinal</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Minimal instrumentation of the gastrointestinal tract is advised because post-operative adhesions can be fatal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lindor.2012.1520">Lindor et al 2012</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Endoscopy should be approached with caution to avoid airway manipulation which increases the risk for tracheal/laryngeal scarring/stenosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.oldenburg.2015.636">Oldenburg et al 2015</xref>]. Noninvasive 3D imaging may be preferred.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Aggressive management of constipation (through dietary means or medication if necessary) is indicated.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Neuropsychiatric.</bold> The following information represents typical management recommendations for individuals with developmental delay/intellectual disability in the United States; standard recommendations may vary from country to country.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Global developmental disability/intellectual disability educational issues</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>Ages 0-3 years.</bold> Referral to an early intervention program is recommended for access to occupational, physical, speech, and feeding therapy. In the United States, early intervention is a federally funded program available in all states.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>Ages 3-5 years.</bold> In the United States, developmental preschool through the local public school district is recommended. Before placement, an evaluation is made to determine needed services and therapies and an individualized education plan (IEP) is developed.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>Ages 5-21 years.</bold> In the United States, an IEP based on the individual&#x02019;s level of function should be developed by the local public school district. Affected children are permitted to remain in the public school district until age 21.</p>
                  <p>Discussion about transition plans including financial, vocation/employment, and medical arrangements should begin at age 12 years. Developmental pediatricians can provide assistance with transition to adulthood.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>All ages.</bold> Consultation with a developmental pediatrician is recommended to ensure the involvement of appropriate community, state, and educational agencies and to support parents in maximizing quality of life. Some issues to consider:</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Private supportive therapies based on the affected individual&#x02019;s needs may be considered. Specific recommendations regarding type of therapy can be made by a developmental pediatrician.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>In the United States, Developmental Disabilities Administration (DDA) enrollment is recommended. DDA is a public agency that provides services and support to qualified individuals. Eligibility differs by state but is typically determined by diagnosis and/or associated cognitive/adaptive disabilities.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>In the United States, families with limited income and resources may also qualify for supplemental security income (SSI) for their child with a disability.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Social/behavioral issues</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Children may qualify for and benefit from interventions used in treatment of autism spectrum disorder, including applied behavior analysis (ABA). ABA therapy is individualized therapy targeted to each child&#x02019;s behavioral, social, and adaptive strengths and weaknesses and is typically performed one on one with a board-certified behavior analyst.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Consultation with a developmental pediatrician may be helpful in guiding parents through appropriate behavioral management strategies or providing prescription medications when necessary.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Individualized behavioral therapy or pharmacologic treatment for anxiety, depression, or other psychological manifestations as per current clinical practice is appropriate.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Hearing</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Hearing loss.</bold> Appropriate hearing augmentation (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="deafness-overview" document-type="chapter">Deafness and Hereditary Hearing Loss Overview</related-object>)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Persistent middle ear effusions.</bold> Myringotomy tubes as needed</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Craniofacial</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Individuals with orofacial clefting or velopharyngeal insufficiency should be referred to a craniofacial clinic with pediatric experience. These individuals benefit most from a multidisciplinary approach to care.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A craniofacial clinic associated with a major pediatric medical center usually includes a surgical team (craniofacial surgeon and neurosurgeon), clinical geneticist, ophthalmologist, otolaryngologist, pediatrician, radiologist, psychologist, multiple dental specialists, audiologist, speech therapist, and social worker.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Skeletal</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Consider physical therapy to keep joints mobile (no study has been done on efficacy). Note: It is not known if passive range of motion exercises help maintain flexibility.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A systematic study of growth hormone treatment for short stature has not been done. One affected individual has been noted to have anecdotal improvement in growth velocity; however, it is unknown if adult height would be affected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Ophthalmology.</bold> Routine treatment of strabismus and refractive errors. Note: Complications from surgical repair have not been reported.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complicati">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Limiting tissue trauma appears to be the single most important preventive measure: The literature suggests increased risk of proliferative fibrosis following otherwise uncomplicated endotracheal intubation and surgical procedures. When possible, alternative noninvasive approaches should be pursued during diagnosis and management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.oldenburg.2015.636">Oldenburg et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Extreme care with intubation and use of an endotracheal tube without a cuff (or careful monitoring of pressures with a cuff) may help prevent airway stenosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.oldenburg.2015.636">Oldenburg et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Minimize abdominal and pelvic procedures as extensive adhesions may develop postoperatively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lindor.2012.1520">Lindor et al 2012</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hysterectomy should be an option of last resort for treatment of menorrhagia as post-surgical fibrosis is highly likely.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Cardiovascular</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>After normal baseline evaluations of upper- and lower-extremity blood pressure measurements, two-dimensional echocardiography with Doppler, and cardiology evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In asymptomatic individuals with a normal echocardiogram at the time of <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diag">initial diagnosis</xref>, repeat echocardiogram every 1-3 years. Note that pericardial effusion and restrictive cardiomyopathy may occur at any age and may be clinically asymptomatic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.garavelli.2016.1307">Garavelli et al 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al 2016</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In individuals with abnormal findings at the time of <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diag">initial diagnosis</xref>, more extensive imaging may be indicated given the progressive nature of the disorder (e.g., MRI to evaluate for pericardial thickening or effusion).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Respiratory</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Consider oxygen saturation in children, with monitoring as needed for symptoms suggestive of restrictive/obstructive pulmonary disease and annual pulmonary function studies in children older than age six years if able to cooperate with test maneuvers.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation for upper airway stenosis (e.g., laryngotracheal stenosis) should be considered based on symptoms.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Other</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Annual ophthalmologic and audiology evaluations</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Monitoring of physical skill development and joint mobility</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Patients should be aggressively counseled not to smoke.</p>
          <p>Limiting tissue trauma appears to be the single most important preventive concept in this disorder to communicate to all health care providers involved in their care (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complicati">Prevention of Secondary Findings</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="myhre.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="myhre.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Myhre syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>All probands with Myhre syndrome reported to date have the disorder as a result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.bassett.2016.54">Bassett et al [2016]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al [2016]</xref> and references therein).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recommendations for the evaluation of parents of a proband with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant include molecular genetic testing.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> If the <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, the risk to sibs is presumed to be slightly greater than that of the general population (though still &#x0003c;1%) because of the theoretic possibility of parental germline mosaicism.</p>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> To date, individuals with Myhre syndrome are not known to reproduce and fertility has not been assessed.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> The risk to other family members is presumed to be low given that all probands with Myhre syndrome reported to date have the disorder as a result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant (i.e., no familial cases of Myhre syndrome have been reported).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to parents of affected individuals.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantati">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at theoretic increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for Myhre syndrome are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="myhre.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="myhre.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="myhre.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>Myhre syndrome is caused by a heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> gain-of-function pathogenic variant that confers stability on the abnormal SMAD4 protein due to an apparent decrease in mono-ubiquitination. This disrupts TGF&#x003b2; signaling, thus altering expression of downstream target genes encoding TGF&#x003b2; and bone morphogenic proteins (BMP), resulting in abnormal development of the axial and appendicular skeleton, cardiac muscle, and central nervous system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.caputo.2012.161">Caputo et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.le_goff.2014.503">Le Goff et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p>In contrast, heterozygosity for a <bold>loss</bold>-of-function <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant has been well established as the cause of a spectrum of acquired cardiac diseases, including cardiac fibrosis and hypertrophy, aortopathies, atherogenesis, and pulmonary artery hypertension.</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> The coding exons 2-12 of <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> constitute a 552-residue protein composed of two domains. Exon 1 is noncoding.</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> The four pathogenic variants reported to date are missense variants that are restricted to residues 496 and 500 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus">Table 3</xref>). No inactivating deletions or duplications have been reported in individuals with Myhre syndrome.</p>
          <p>Since 2011, when heterozygosity for a <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> pathogenic variant was found to be causative, 55 affected individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis of Myhre syndrome have been reported. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al [2016]</xref> reported four affected individuals and summarized findings in 50 previously reported individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.le_goff.2011.85">Le Goff et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.al_ageeli.2012.541">Al Ageeli et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.asakura.2012.1982">Asakura et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.caputo.2012.161">Caputo et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lindor.2012.1520">Lindor et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.picco.2013.1164">Picco et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.ishibashi.2014.300">Ishibashi et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.kenis.2014.e253">Kenis et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.michot.2014.1272">Michot et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.hawkes.2015.84">Hawkes &#x00026; Kini 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.oldenburg.2015.636">Oldenburg et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">Starr et al 2015</xref>]. Subsequently <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.bassett.2016.54">Bassett et al [2016]</xref> reported one additional affected individual.</p>
          <table-wrap id="myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> Pathogenic Variants Discussed in This <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic></p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1486C&#x0003e;T</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg496Cys</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_3" rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_005359.5">NM_005359.5</ext-link>
                    <break/>
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_005350.1">NP_005350.1</ext-link>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1498A&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ile500Val</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1499T&#x0003e;C</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ile500Thr</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1500A&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_myhre.T.smad4_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ile500Met</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The three functional classes of SMADs are:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> that encodes a SMAD protein known as the co-mediator of the SMADs;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>SMAD1, SMAD2, SMAD3, SMAD5, and SMAD8 that are the receptor-regulated SMADs (or R-SMADs);</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>SMAD6 and SMAD7 that are inhibitory SMADs.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>SMAD4 (mothers against decapentaplegic homolog 4) forms heterodimers with the receptor-regulated SMADs, which are translocated to the nucleus of the cell, which then (via an unclear mechanism) regulates the expression of TGB&#x003b2; and BMP pathway genes.</p>
          <p>The 11 coding exons of <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> constitute a 552-residue protein composed of two domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.shi.2003.685">Shi &#x00026; Massague 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.le_goff.2011.85">Le Goff et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.caputo.2012.161">Caputo et al 2012</xref>]:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Mad homology 1 (MH1), which contributes to DNA binding</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Mad homology 2 (MH2), which activates transcription</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Codons 496 and 500 are in the Mad homology 2 domain; pathogenic variants in these codons confer a gain of function to the protein. The work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.le_goff.2011.85">Le Goff et al [2011]</xref> indicated that defective transcriptional regulation during development plays a significant role in the disorder.</p>
          <p><bold>Cancer and benign tumors.</bold> Although germline <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> loss-of-function (inactivating) pathogenic variants predispose to hamartomatous polyps in the gastrointestinal track (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="jps" document-type="chapter">Juvenile Polyposis Syndrome</related-object>), the gain-of-function pathogenic variants associated with Myhre syndrome show no such associations (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="myhre.Clinical_Description">Clinical Description</xref>, <bold>Neoplasia</bold>).</p>
          <p>Note that somatic inactivation of <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4,</italic> a gastrointestinal malignancy-specific tumor suppressor gene, is found in one third of colorectal cancer specimens and half of pancreatic tumors. See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.chen.2014.181">Chen et al [2014]</xref> and references therein.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="myhre.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="myhre.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="myhre.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="myhre.REF.al_ageeli.2012.541">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al Ageeli</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mignot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Afenjar</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Whalen</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dorison</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayer</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Esteva</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dubern</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Momtchilova</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Gargasson</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bursztyn</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heron</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Retinal involvement in two unrelated patients with Myhre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Med Genet</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>55</volume>
                <fpage>541</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22683461</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.asakura.2012.1982">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Asakura</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Muroya</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sato</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kurosawa</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishimaura</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adachi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>First case of a Japanese girl with Myhre syndrome due to a heterozygous SMAD4 mutation.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet Part A.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>158A</volume>
                <fpage>1982</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22711472</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.bassett.2016.54">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bassett</surname>
                    <given-names>JK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Douzgou</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kerr</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Severe constipation in a patient with Myhre syndrome: a case report.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Dysmorph</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>25</volume>
                <fpage>54</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26636501</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.caputo.2014.1835">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Caputo</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bocchinfuso</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castori</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Traversa</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pizzuti</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stella</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grammatico</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tartaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Novel SMAD4 mutation causing Myhre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>164A</volume>
                <fpage>1835</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24715504</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.caputo.2012.161">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Caputo</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cianetti</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Niceta</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carta</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ciolfi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bocchinfuso</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrani</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dentici</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Biamino</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Belligni</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garavelli</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boccone</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Melis</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Andria</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gelb</surname>
                    <given-names>BD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stella</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Silengo</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dallapiccola</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tartaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A restricted spectrum of mutations in the SMAD4 tumor-suppressor gene underlies Myhre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>90</volume>
                <fpage>161</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22243968</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.chen.2014.181">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>YW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hsiao</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Weng</surname>
                    <given-names>CC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kuo</surname>
                    <given-names>KK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kuo</surname>
                    <given-names>TL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wu</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hung</surname>
                    <given-names>WC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cheng</surname>
                    <given-names>KH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>SMAD4 loss triggers the phenotypic changes of pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma cells.</article-title>
                <source>BMC Cancer.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>181</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24625091</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.garavelli.2016.1307">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garavelli</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maini</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baccilieri</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ivanovski</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pollazzon</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rosato</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iughetti</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Unger</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Superti-Furga</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tartaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Natural history and life-threatening complications in Myhre syndrome and review of the literature.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>175</volume>
                <fpage>1307</fpage>
                <lpage>15</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27562837</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.hawkes.2015.84">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hawkes</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kini</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Myhre syndrome with facial paralysis and branch pulmonary stenosis.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Dysmorph.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>84</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25486016</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.ishibashi.2014.300">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ishibashi</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sasaki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Asakura</surname>
                    <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Myhre syndrome: a rare craniofacial disorder.</article-title>
                <source>Cranio</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>32</volume>
                <fpage>300</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25252769</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.kenis.2014.e253">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kenis</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Verstreken</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gieraerts</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Foer</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van der Aa</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Offeciers</surname>
                    <given-names>EF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Casselman</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Bilateral otospongiosis and a unilateral vestibular schwannoma in a patient with Myhre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Otol Neurotol</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>35</volume>
                <fpage>e253</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24841914</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.le_goff.2014.503">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Goff</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Michot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cormier-Daire</surname>
                    <given-names>V.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Myhre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Genet.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>85</volume>
                <fpage>503</fpage>
                <lpage>13</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24580733</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.le_goff.2011.85">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Goff</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mahaut</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abhyankar</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Goff</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Serre</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Afenjar</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Destr&#x000e9;e</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>di Rocco</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>H&#x000e9;ron</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jacquemont</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marlin</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Simon</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tolmie</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Veroles</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Casanova</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munnich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cormier-Daire</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations at a single codon in Mad homology 2 domain of SMAD4 cause Myhre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>44</volume>
                <fpage>85</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22158539</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lin</surname>
                    <given-names>AE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Michot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cormier-Daire</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>L'Ecuyer</surname>
                    <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matherne</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barnes</surname>
                    <given-names>BH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Humberson</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Edmondson</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zackai</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>O'Connor</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaplan</surname>
                    <given-names>JD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ebeid</surname>
                    <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Krier</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Krieg</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ghoshhajra</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindsay</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Gain-of-function mutations in SMAD4 cause a distinctive repertoire of cardiovascular phenotypes in patients with Myhre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>170</volume>
                <fpage>2617</fpage>
                <lpage>31</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27302097</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.lindor.2012.1520">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindor</surname>
                    <given-names>NM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gunawardena</surname>
                    <given-names>SR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thibodeau</surname>
                    <given-names>SN</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations of SMAD4 account for both LAPS and Myhre syndromes.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet Part A.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>158A</volume>
                <fpage>1520</fpage>
                <lpage>1</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22585601</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.mcgowan.2011.e553">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McGowan</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gulati</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McHenry</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cooke</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Butler</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Teik Keng</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Murday</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Whiteford</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dikkers</surname>
                    <given-names>FG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sikkema-Raddatz</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Essen</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tolmie</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Clinical features and respiratory complications in Myhre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>54</volume>
                <fpage>e553</fpage>
                <lpage>e559</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816239</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.michot.2014.1272">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Michot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Goff</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mahaut</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Afenjar</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brooks</surname>
                    <given-names>AS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Campeau</surname>
                    <given-names>PM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Destree</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Di Rocco</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Donnai</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hennekam</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heron</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jacquemont</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kannu</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lin</surname>
                    <given-names>AE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Manouvrier-Hanu</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mansour</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marlin</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McGowan</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Murphy</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raas-Rothchild</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rio</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Simon</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stolte-Dijkstra</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stone</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Szanjer</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tolmie</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Touraine</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ende</surname>
                    <given-names>JVD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van der Aa</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Essen</surname>
                    <given-names>TV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Verloes</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munnich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Comier-Daire</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Myhre and LAPS syndromes: clinical and molecular review of 32 patients.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>22</volume>
                <fpage>1272</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24424121</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.myhre.1981.1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Myhre</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ruvalcaba</surname>
                    <given-names>RH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Graham</surname>
                    <given-names>CB</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A new growth deficiency syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Genet</source>
                <year>1981</year>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>1</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7296942</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.oldenburg.2015.636">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oldenburg</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frisch</surname>
                    <given-names>CD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindor</surname>
                    <given-names>NM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Edell</surname>
                    <given-names>ES</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kasperbauer</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                    <given-names>EK</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Myhre-LAPs syndrome and intubation related airway stenosis: keys to diagnosis and critical therapeutic interventions.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Otolaryngol.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>36</volume>
                <fpage>636</fpage>
                <lpage>41</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25940662</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.picco.2013.1164">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Picco</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Naselli</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pala</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marsciani</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Buoncompagni</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martini</surname>
                    <given-names>A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Recurrent pericarditis in Myhre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet Part A</source>
                <volume>161A</volume>
                <year>2013</year>
                <fpage>1164</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23610053</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.shi.2003.685">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shi</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Massague</surname>
                    <given-names>J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mechanisms of TGF-&#x003b2; signaling from cell membrane to the nucleus.</article-title>
                <source>Cell</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>113</volume>
                <fpage>685</fpage>
                <lpage>700</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12809600</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="myhre.REF.starr.2015.2893">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Starr</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grange</surname>
                    <given-names>DK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Delaney</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yetman</surname>
                    <given-names>AT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hammel</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sanmann</surname>
                    <given-names>JN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Perry</surname>
                    <given-names>DA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                    <given-names>GB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Olney</surname>
                    <given-names>AH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Myhre syndrome: Clinical features and restrictive cardiopulmonary complications.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>167A</volume>
                <fpage>2893</fpage>
                <lpage>901</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26420300</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="myhre.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="myhre.Acknowledgments">
          <title>Acknowledgments</title>
          <p>The authors are indebted to the people living with Myhre syndrome and their families who have provided consent, motivation, contributions, and advocacy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="myhre.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>13 April 2017 (bp) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>11 July 2016 (ljs) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="myhre.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Female with Myhre syndrome at ages seven months, four years, and 16 years. Note the short palpebral fissures, thin upper vermilion border and maxillary underdevelopment. She required tracheostomy subsequent to traumatic intubations that resulted in complete tracheal stenosis.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="myhre-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="myhre.F2" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Female with Myhre syndrome at ages newborn, 12 months, 3.5 years, and seven years. Note the short palpebral fissures, thin upper vermilion border, and progression of mild prognathism.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="myhre-Image002" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="myhre.F3" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 3. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Female with Myhre syndrome at ages three years, ten years (standing), and 21 years (face, posterior hairline, and hands). Note the short palpebral fissures, broad mid-upper nasal bridge, downward pointing nasal tip, thin upper vermilion border, broad and short neck, contracted joints (elbows are fully extended in photos), brachydactyly, and compact habitus.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="myhre-Image003" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="myhre.F4" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 4. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Male with Myhre syndrome at age 12 years. Note the mild facial features (mild maxillary underdevelopment and thin upper vermilion border) and finger contractures (hands are on a flat surface).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="myhre-Image004" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="myhre.F5" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 5. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Female with Myhre syndrome at age five years. Note the short palpebral fissures, thin upper and lower vermilion borders, left-sided facial palsy, and brachydactyly with otherwise mild features. Facial palsy is observed in 4% of individuals with Myhre syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="myhre.REF.lin.2016.2617">Lin et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="myhre-Image005" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="myhre.F6" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 6. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Radiographs of a female age 14 yearsA. Thickened calvaria and anterior cervical vertebral fusion (arrow) of C2 and C3.B. Note the broad ribs and vertebrae. This patient has 11 rib pairs.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="myhre-Image006" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
