<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="nail-ps" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">nail-ps</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Nail-Patella Syndrome</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: Fong Disease, Hereditary Osteo-Onychodysplasia</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sweeney</surname>
            <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="nail-ps.AFF1"/>
          <degrees>MB ChB, FRCP, DRCOG, MD</degrees>
          <email>Elizabeth.Sweeney@lwh.nhs.uk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hoover-Fong</surname>
            <given-names>Julie E</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="nail-ps.AFF2"/>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <email>Jhoover2@jhmi.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>McIntosh</surname>
            <given-names>Iain</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="nail-ps.AFF3"/>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <email>imcintosh@aucmed.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="nail-ps.AFF1">Consultant Clinical Geneticist, Liverpool Women&#x02019;s Hospital<break/>Liverpool, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="nail-ps.AFF2">Director, Greenberg Center for Skeletal Dysplasias<break/>Institute of Genetic Medicine<break/>Johns Hopkins University<break/>Baltimore, Maryland</aff>
      <aff id="nail-ps.AFF3">Professor of Medical Genetics<break/>Department of Molecular &#x00026; Cell Biology<break/>American University of the Caribbean<break/>St Maarten, Netherlands Antilles</aff>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2003-05-31" date-type="created">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>05</month>
          <year>2003</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2014-11-13" date-type="updated">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="nsdhl-dis" document-type="chapter">
<italic toggle="yes">NSDHL</italic>-Related Disorders</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="nem" document-type="chapter">Nemaline Myopathy</related-object>
      <abstract id="nail-ps.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Nail-patella syndrome (NPS) involves a classic clinical tetrad of changes in the nails, knees, and elbows, and the presence of iliac horns. Nail changes are the most constant feature of NPS. Nails may be absent, hypoplastic, or dystrophic; ridged longitudinally or horizontally; pitted; discolored; separated into two halves by a longitudinal cleft or ridge of skin; and thin or (less often) thickened. The patellae may be small, irregularly shaped, or absent. Elbow abnormalities may include limitation of extension, pronation, and supination; cubitus valgus; and antecubital pterygia. Iliac horns are bilateral, conical, bony processes that project posteriorly and laterally from the central part of the iliac bones of the pelvis. Renal involvement, first manifest as proteinuria with or without hematuria, occurs in 30%-50% of affected individuals; end-stage renal disease (ESRD) occurs in about 5% of affected individuals. Primary open-angle glaucoma and ocular hypertension occur at increased frequency and at a younger age than in the general population. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of nail-patella syndrome is based on clinical findings. <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> is the only gene in which pathogenic variants are known to cause NPS. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations</italic>: Orthopedic problems may be helped by analgesics, physiotherapy, splinting, bracing, or surgery; MRI of joints to identify abnormal anatomy is important prior to surgery so that appropriate surgical treatment can be planned in advance; ACE inhibitors to control blood pressure and possibly to slow progression of proteinuria; renal transplantation as needed; glaucoma is treated as in the general population.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance</italic>: Annual monitoring for hypertension and renal disease; screening for glaucoma as soon as a child is compliant. </p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid</italic>: Chronic use of NSAIDs because of the detrimental effect on kidney function.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Pregnancy management</italic>: The risk of developing preeclampsia may be increased in pregnant women with NPS; hence frequent urinalysis and blood pressure measurement is recommended during pregnancy. For women taking an ACE inhibitor, transitioning to an alternative treatment ideally prior to pregnancy, or at least as soon as pregnancy is recognized, is recommended to avoid potential adverse effects of ACE inhibitors on the developing fetus.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>Nail-patella syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Eighty-eight percent of individuals with NPS have an affected parent. Twelve percent of affected individuals have a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> mutation. The offspring of an affected individual are at a 50% risk of inheriting NPS. Prenatal diagnosis for pregnancies at increased risk is possible if the pathogenic variant in the family has been identified. </p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="nail-ps.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>No clinical diagnostic criteria for nail-patella syndrome (NPS) exist; however, the combination of clinical features seen in this condition is characteristic.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>Diagnosis of nail-patella syndrome (NPS) should be suspected in individuals with:</bold>
        </p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Nail changes.</bold> See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nail-ps.F1">Figure 1</xref>. Nail changes are the most constant feature of NPS (98%). Nails may be absent, hypoplastic, or dystrophic; ridged longitudinally or horizontally; pitted; discolored; separated into two halves by a longitudinal cleft or ridge of skin; and thin or (less often) thickened. The nail changes may be limited to triangular lunules (lunulae), a characteristic feature of NPS. Nail changes may be observed at birth and are most often bilateral and symmetric. The thumbnails are the most severely affected; the severity of the nail changes tends to decrease from the index finger toward the little finger. Each individual nail is usually more severely affected on its ulnar side. Dysplasia of the toenails is usually less marked and less frequent than that of the fingernails; if the toenails are involved, it is often the little toenail that is affected. </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Knee involvement.</bold> The patellae may be small, irregularly shaped, or absent. Patella involvement may be asymmetric. Recurrent subluxation or dislocation of the patella is common in NPS and may be associated with poor development of the vastus medialis muscle. The displacement of the patella is lateral and superior; the hypoplastic patella is often located laterally and superiorly even when not actually dislocated. There may be prominent medial femoral condyles, hypoplastic lateral femoral condyles, and prominent tibial tuberosities. These changes together with a hypoplastic or absent patella give the knee joint a flattened profile. Symptoms of knee involvement were apparent in 74% of cases in one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Elbow involvement.</bold> Elbow abnormalities may include limitation of extension, pronation, and supination; cubitus valgus; and antecubital pterygia. Elbow abnormalities may be asymmetric. Typical radiologic findings include dysplasia of the radial head, hypoplasia of the lateral epicondyle and capitellum, and prominence of the medial epicondyle. These abnormalities may result in dislocation of the radial head, usually posteriorly. Approximately 70% of individuals with NPS exhibit some degree of elbow involvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Iliac horns.</bold> Iliac horns are bilateral, conical, bony processes that project posteriorly and laterally from the central part of the iliac bones of the pelvis. They are present in about 70% of individuals with NPS and are considered pathognomonic of NPS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. Pelvic x-ray is usually necessary for their detection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="nail-ps.F2">Figure 2</xref>). Although large horns may be palpable, they are asymptomatic. Iliac horns may be seen on third-trimester ultrasound scanning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.feingold.1998.854">Feingold et al 1998</xref>], on x-ray at birth, and by bone scan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.goshen.2000.476">Goshen et al 2000</xref>]. In children, iliac horns may have an epiphysis at the apex. </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>The diagnosis of nail-patella syndrome (NPS) is established in a proband</bold> with at least one but usually more than one of the manifestations listed above, with nail changes being present in 98% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. In cases where the clinical diagnosis is uncertain the identification of a heterozygous pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> is diagnostic. </p>
        <p><bold>One genetic testing strategy</bold> is molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B.</italic>
</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Sequence analysis should be performed first. All point mutations reported to date have been in exons 2-6, thus analysis of these exons should be prioritized. </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>If no pathogenic variant is identified by sequence analysis, then deletion/duplication analysis should be considered next.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>An alternative genetic testing strategy</bold> is use of a multi-gene panel that includes <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="nail-ps.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>). Note: The genes included and the methods used in multi-gene panels vary by laboratory and over time. </p>
        <p><bold>Cytogenetic testing.</bold> Chromosomal translocations disrupting the gene have also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.silahtaroglu.1999.68">Silahtaroglu et al 1999</xref>] but represent a rare pathogenic mechanism. </p>
        <p><bold>Gene.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> is the only gene in which pathogenic variants are known to cause NPS. </p>
        <p><bold>Clinical testing</bold>
</p>
        <table-wrap id="nail-ps.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Nail-Patella Syndrome</p>
          </caption>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_b_nail-ps.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                <th id="hd_b_nail-ps.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                <th id="hd_b_nail-ps.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Pathogenic Variant Detectable by This Method</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>2,&#x000a0;3</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85%&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10%&#x000a0;<sup>6,&#x000a0;7</sup></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="nail-ps.TF.1">
              <label>1.</label>
              <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="naip-ps" object-id="naip-ps.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="nail-ps.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics </xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene. </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nail-ps.TF.1.1">
              <label>2.</label>
              <p>Sequence variants exons 2 through 6</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nail-ps.TF.1.2">
              <label>3.</label>
              <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of unknown significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exonic or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nail-ps.TF.1.3">
              <label>4.</label>
              <p>Proportion of affected individuals with pathogenic variants identified by sequence analysis of exons 2-6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.clough.1999.459">Clough et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nail-ps.TF.1.4">
              <label>5.</label>
              <p>Testing that identifies exonic or whole-gene deletions/duplications not detectable by sequence analysis of the coding and flanking intronic regions of genomic DNA. Included in the variety of methods that may be used are: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and chromosomal microarray (CMA) that includes this gene/chromosome segment.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nail-ps.TF.1.5">
              <label>6.</label>
              <p>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.bongers.2008.1240">Bongers et al [2008]</xref>
              </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="nail-ps.TF.1.6">
              <label>7.</label>
              <p>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.dunston.2004.565">Dunston et al [2004]</xref>
              </p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p><bold>Confirmation of the diagnosis in a proband</bold> may require molecular genetic testing if the phenotype is atypical or cytogenetic testing if signs and symptoms beyond the typical NPS phenotype are present. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.Clinical_Description">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Natural_History">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>The classic clinical tetrad of nail-patella syndrome (NPS) involves changes in the nails, knees, and elbows, and the presence of iliac horns (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="nail-ps.Diagnosis">Diagnosis</xref>). Many other features may be seen in NPS, and involvement of other body systems such as the kidneys and eyes is well documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. The clinical manifestations are extremely variable in both frequency and severity, with inter- and intrafamilial variability. Individuals may be severely affected by one aspect of NPS but have much milder or no manifestations elsewhere. Males and females are affected equally. Although the diagnosis may be made at birth, it is common for families to remain undiagnosed for several generations despite having been seen by doctors from a variety of disciplines.</p>
          <p><bold>Digital changes.</bold> In NPS, a reduction in flexion of the distal interphalangeal (DIP) joints is associated with loss of the creases in the skin overlying the dorsal surface of the DIP joints of the fingers. The gradient of severity is the same as seen in the nails; therefore, the index fingers are the most affected. Hyperextension of the proximal interphalangeal (PIP) joints with flexion of the DIP joints (resulting in "swan-necking") and fifth finger clinodactyly may be seen. </p>
          <p><bold>Knee involvement.</bold> In addition to the previously mentioned patellar abnormalities, tight hamstring muscles may cause flexion contractures of the knees. There may also be osteochondritis dissecans, synovial plicae, and absence of the anterior cruciate ligament. Early degenerative arthritis is common. Symptoms associated with knee abnormalities in NPS include pain, instability, locking, clicking, patella dislocation, and inability to straighten the knee joint. </p>
          <p><bold>Involvement of the ankles and feet.</bold> Talipes equinovarus, calcaneovarus, calcaneovalgus, equinovalgus, and hyperdorsiflexion of the foot may occur. Tight Achilles tendons are common, contributing to talipes equinovarus and to toe-walking. Pes planus is common. </p>
          <p><bold>Spinal and chest wall problems.</bold> Back pain occurs in half of individuals with NPS. There may be an increased lumbar lordosis, scoliosis (usually mild), spondylolisthesis, spondylolysis, or pectus excavatum. </p>
          <p><bold>Osteoporosis.</bold> Bone mineral density (BMD) is reduced by 8%-20% in the hips of individuals with NPS. An increased rate of fractures has also been reported.</p>
          <p><bold>General appearance.</bold> A lean body habitus may be associated with NPS and affected individuals often have difficulty putting on weight (particularly muscle) despite adequate dietary intake and exercise. In particular, muscle mass in the upper arms and upper legs tend to be decreased. The tendency to be very lean is most evident in adolescents and young adults and becomes less apparent after middle age. </p>
          <p>Increased lumbar lordosis may make the buttocks appear prominent. </p>
          <p>The high forehead and hairline, particularly at the temples, resembles a receding male pattern hairline when seen in women. </p>
          <p><bold>Renal involvement.</bold> Renal involvement occurs in 30%-50% of individuals with NPS; end-stage renal disease (ESRD) occurs in approximately 5% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. </p>
          <p>The first sign of renal involvement is usually proteinuria, with or without hematuria. Proteinuria may present at any age from birth onwards and may be intermittent. Renal problems may present, or be exacerbated, during pregnancy. Once proteinuria is present, it may remit spontaneously, remain asymptomatic, or progress to nephrotic syndrome and occasionally to ESRD. Progression to renal failure may appear to occur rapidly or after many years of asymptomatic proteinuria. The factors responsible for this progression are yet to be identified. Nephritis may also occur in NPS. </p>
          <p>Ultrastructural (electron microscopic) renal abnormalities are the most specific histologic changes seen in NPS and include irregular thickening of the glomerular basement membrane with electron-lucent areas giving a mottled "moth-eaten" appearance, and the presence of collagen-like fibers within the basement membrane and the mesangial matrix. </p>
          <p><bold>Ophthalmologic findings.</bold> Primary open-angle glaucoma and ocular hypertension occur at increased frequency in NPS and at a younger age than in the general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.lichter.1997.506">Lichter et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. Congenital and normal-tension glaucoma have been reported in individuals with NPS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.lichter.1997.506">Lichter et al 1997</xref>].</p>
          <p>Iris pigmentary changes (termed Lester's sign) consisting of a zone of darker pigmentation shaped like a cloverleaf or flower around the central part of the iris are seen frequently. </p>
          <p><bold>Gastrointestinal involvement.</bold> One third of individuals with NPS have problems with constipation (often from birth) or irritable bowel syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. </p>
          <p><bold>Neurologic problems.</bold> Many individuals with NPS exhibit reduced sensation to pain and temperature in the hands and feet, most likely because of the inability of A&#x003b4; and C fibers to connect with interneurons in the dorsal spinal cord [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.dunston.2005.330">Dunston et al 2005</xref>]. Some affected individuals report intermittent numbness, tingling, and burning sensations in the hands and feet, with no obvious precipitant. Rarely, these symptoms may be secondary to local orthopedic problems or neurologic compromise from the spine or cervical ribs. In most cases, however, the paresthesia follows a glove and stocking pattern rather than the distribution of a particular dermatome or peripheral nerve. </p>
          <p>Epilepsy was reported in 6% of affected individuals in one large study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. </p>
          <p><bold>Vasomotor problems.</bold> Some individuals have symptoms of a poor peripheral circulation, such as very cold hands and feet, even in warm weather. Some may be diagnosed with Raynaud's phenomenon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. </p>
          <p><bold>Dental problems.</bold> Dental problems may include weak, crumbling teeth and thin dental enamel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>One study has suggested that individuals with a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> that is located in the LMX1 homeodomain showed significantly more frequent and higher values of proteinuria compared to those with pathogenic variants affecting LMX1 LIM domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.bongers.2005.935">Bongers et al 2005</xref>]. No clear genotype-phenotype association was apparent for extrarenal manifestations of NPS.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>NPS is fully penetrant, although the range and severity of symptoms may be extremely variable.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Anticipation">
          <title>Anticipation</title>
          <p>Anticipation does not occur in NPS.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>Nail-patella syndrome is the most accepted term but has the disadvantage of implying that nail and patellar dysplasia are the most important features. Hereditary onycho-osteodysplasia (HOOD) may be more accurate, but is rarely used. Perhaps hereditary onycho-osteodysplasia with nephropathy and glaucoma would be the best term. The terms Fong's disease and Turner syndrome* have also been used.</p>
          <p>* Note: Referring to JW Turner and not HH Turner, who described the phenotype associated with a 45,X karyotype</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>The prevalence of NPS has been roughly estimated at one in 50,000 but may be higher because of undiagnosed individuals with a mild phenotype.</p>
          <p>NPS has been reported in a wide variety of ethnic groups.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Diso">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>Pathogenic variants involving the same codon in <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> were identified in three families with focal segmental glomerulosclerosis without the extrarenal or ultrastructural manifestations of NPS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.boyer.2013.1216">Boyer et al 2013</xref>]. No amino acid substitutions of this codon have been reported in individuals with NPS, suggesting that this codon is involved more specifically in binding to promoters of podocyte-expressed genes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <table-wrap id="nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Table 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Differential Diagnoses of Nail-Patella Syndrome</p>
          </caption>
          <table>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndrome</th>
                <th id="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similarities</th>
                <th id="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differences</th>
                <th id="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small patella syndrome<break/>(ischiopatellar dysplasia, coxo-podo-patellar syndrome, Scott-Taor syndrome)</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small or absent patellae<break/>Recurrent patella dislocations<break/>Pelvic anomalies</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Defective ossification at the ischiopubic junction <break/>Ischial hypoplasia <break/>Infra-acetabular "axe-cut" notch <break/>No nail changes <break/>No elbow changes <break/>No renal involvement <break/>No ocular involvement </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/entry/147891?search=147891">147891</ext-link>,<break/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.bongers.2004.1239">Bongers et al [2004]</xref>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patella aplasia-hypoplasia (PTLAH)</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolated aplasia OR<break/>Hypoplasia of the patella </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No nail changes <break/>No elbow changes <break/>No renal involvement <break/>No ocular involvement </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/entry/168860?search=168860">168860</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Familial recurrent dislocation of the patella</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Familial tendency toward patella dislocation </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/entry/169000?search=169000">169000</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meier-Gorlin syndrome</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent patellae<break/>Dislocation of the radial head</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microtia <break/>Markedly short stature <break/>Delayed bone age <break/>Characteristic facial appearance <break/>Autosomal recessive inheritance </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/entry/224690?search=224690">224690</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="kat6b-dis" document-type="chapter">Genitopatellar syndrome</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent patellae<break/>Renal anomalies<break/>Flexion deformities of the knees and hips<break/>Club foot</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypoplasia of the ischia and iliac bones <break/>Genital anomalies <break/>Facial dysmorphism <break/>Microcephaly <break/>Intellectual disability<break/>Structural (multicystic kidneys or hydronephrosis) rather than functional abnormalities <break/>Renal manifestations </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/entry/606170?search=606170">606170</ext-link>, <break/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.cormierdaire.2000.520">Cormier-Daire et al [2000]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DOOR syndrome (deafness, onychodystrophy, osteodystrophy, mental retardation, and seizures syndrome)</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent or poorly formed nails</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long thumbs and big toes, often with triphalangy <break/>Other fingers and toes short as the result of an absent or hypoplastic distal phalanx <break/>Bilateral ptosis <break/>Short broad nose with a broad nasal tip and large nostrils <break/>Structural renal tract abnormalities <break/>Cataracts <break/>Optic atrophy <break/>Dandy-Walker malformation <break/>Seizures <break/>Autosomal recessive inheritance </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/entry/220500?search=220500">220500</ext-link>, <break/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.winter.2000.1">Winter &#x00026; Baraitser [2000]</xref>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trisomy 8 mosaicism</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent or hypoplastic patellae <break/>Limited elbow supination <break/>Abnormal nails </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant learning difficulties <break/>Variable facial dysmorphism <break/>Camptodactyly and progressive joint restriction, usually of the fingers and toes </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.jones.1997.1">Jones [1997]</xref>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="coffin-siris" document-type="chapter">Coffin-Siris syndrome</related-object>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence or hypoplasia of the nails and patellae <break/>Elbow dislocation </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nail hypoplasia, usually affecting the little finger nails <break/>Facial dysmorphism </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/entry/135900?search=135900">135900</ext-link>, <break/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.winter.2000.1">Winter &#x00026; Baraitser [2000]</xref>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAPADILINO syndrome (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rts" document-type="chapter">Rothmund-Thomson Syndrome</related-object>, Genetically Related Disorders) </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radial defects<break/>Absent or hypoplastic patellae<break/>Dislocated joints</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleft palate <break/>Facial dysmorphism <break/>Short stature <break/>Radial defects, including absent or hypoplastic thumbs and radii <break/>Autosomal recessive inheritance </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/entry/266280?search=266280">266280</ext-link>, <break/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.winter.2000.1">Winter &#x00026; Baraitser [2000]</xref>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_1" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior syndrome (Brachymorphism-onychodysplasia-dysphalangism syndrome)</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small nails</td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic facial appearance <break/>Short stature <break/>Mild intellectual impairment </td>
                <td headers="hd_b_nail-ps.T.differential_diagnoses_of_nail_1_1_1_4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/entry/113477?search=113477">113477</ext-link>
</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Di">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with nail-patella syndrome (NPS), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Blood pressure measurement and urinalysis to screen for renal disease, plus a urine albumin:creatinine ratio on a first-morning urine. The latter is a more sensitive measure of renal disease than urinalysis as it corrects for urine concentration. If any abnormalities are detected, the individual should then be referred to a nephrologist. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Screening for glaucoma as soon as a child is able to cooperate with the examination. The examination should include measurement of intraocular pressure, examination of the optic disc, and assessment of visual fields in order to detect normal pressure glaucoma. If any abnormalities are detected, individuals should be referred to an ophthalmologist. Any infant or young child found to have an abnormal or absent red reflex on eye examination by a primary care physician should be referred to an ophthalmologist immediately. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>History and physical examination to detect orthopedic problems </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>History to identify gastrointestinal, neurologic, or vasomotor abnormalities </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Before surgery or intensive physiotherapy for orthopedic complaints, investigation via MRI for possible bone/soft tissue anatomic abnormalities</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>History and examination to detect dental anomalies</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consideration of formal quantification of bone mineral density (BMD) via dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) as indicator of fracture propensity based on reported low BMD and increased fracture risk in NPS</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>DEXA norms are readily available in most clinical settings for adults and may be pursued in all young adults (age &#x0003e;18 years) at least once. </p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Pediatric DEXA norms are often less readily available, but may be obtained via local pediatric endocrinologist or machine manufacturer. No formal recommendations for DEXA scanning of pediatric patients exist at this time, but DEXA should be pursued if fractures or unexplained skeletal pain occurs with additional clinical evaluation.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Medical genetics consultation</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Hypertension and renal disease are treated as in the general population. When renal transplantation is necessary, results are usually favorable. ACE inhibitors are useful in slowing progression of proteinuria, but their use should be monitored carefully in children. </p>
          <p>Orthopedic problems may be helped by analgesics, physiotherapy, splinting, bracing, or surgery. Because of the abnormal joint anatomy that may be present in individuals with NPS, MRI of joints to identify abnormal anatomy is important prior to surgery, so that appropriate surgical treatment can be planned in advance.</p>
          <p>Treatment as in the general population for: </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Glaucoma </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Constipation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Dental problems </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Annual measurement of the following is appropriate:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Measurement of blood pressure </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Urinalysis </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Urine albumin:creatinine ratio on a first-morning urine. If any abnormalities are detected, the individual should be referred to a nephrologist. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Screening for glaucoma from the time that a child is compliant with the examination </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Dental examination is indicated at least every six months. </p>
          <p>DEXA scanning frequency in adults is based on clinical symptoms, abnormalities detected on previous evaluations, and standard practice in peri- and post-menopausal females and older males. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Chronic use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) should be avoided because of their detrimental effect on kidney function.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>Early diagnosis of NPS in at-risk family members allows for ophthalmologic and renal screening, especially in individuals with mild-moderate skeletal involvement who may not otherwise come to clinical attention. Molecular genetic testing can be used if the pathogenic variant in the family is known; otherwise, monitor renal findings (i.e., blood pressure, urinalysis, and urine albumin:creatinine ratio on a first-morning urine) and screen for glaucoma. </p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="nail-ps.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issue">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management </title>
          <p>Renal problems may present during (or be exacerbated by) pregnancy and in one study 29% of pregnant women with NPS developed preeclampsia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. Hence, frequent urinalysis and blood pressure measurement is recommended in pregnant women with NPS. Medication used to treat renal disease, such as ACE inhibitors, should be reviewed ideally prior to pregnancy, or at least as soon as pregnancy is recognized, so that transition to an alternative treatment can be considered in order to avoid potential adverse effects of ACE inhibitors on the developing fetus. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Nail-patella syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p><bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Eighty-eight percent of individuals diagnosed with NPS have an affected parent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A proband with NPS may have the disorder as the result of <italic toggle="yes">de novo LMX1B</italic> mutation; 12% of affected individuals have a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> mutation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">Sweeney et al 2003</xref>]. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recommendations for the evaluation of parents of a proband with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> mutation include physical examination and molecular genetic testing if the family mutation is known, as mild symptoms may be overlooked. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: If the parent is the individual in whom the pathogenic variant first occurred, s/he may have somatic mosaicism for the variant and may be mildly/minimally affected. </p>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to the sibs of the proband depends on the genetic status of the proband's parents. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband is affected, the risk to the sibs is 50%. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When the parents are clinically unaffected, the risk to the sibs of a proband appears to be low. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, the risk to sibs is low but greater than that of the general population because of the possibility of germline mosaicism. Evidence of somatic and germline mosaicism has been reported in unaffected parents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.marini.2010.431">Marini et al 2010</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Each child of an individual with NPS has a 50% chance of inheriting the <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Other family members of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to other family members depends on the status of the proband's parents. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent is affected, his or her family members are at risk. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issue">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="nail-ps.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p><bold>Considerations in families with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> mutation.</bold> When neither parent of a proband with NPS has the pathogenic variant or clinical evidence of the disorder, the <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> mutation is likely <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>. However, possible non-medical explanations including alternate paternity or maternity (e.g., with assisted reproduction) or undisclosed adoption could also be explored. </p>
          <p><bold>Family planning</bold>
</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Prenatal_Testing">
          <title>Prenatal Testing</title>
          <p><bold>Molecular genetic testing.</bold> If the <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk may be available from a clinical laboratory that offers either testing of this gene or custom prenatal testing. </p>
          <p>Requests for prenatal testing for conditions which (like NPS) do not affect intellect and have some treatment available are not common. Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions about prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
          <p><bold>Ultrasound examination.</bold> Talipes equinovarus, other identifiable limb anomalies, or large iliac horns may be detected on fetal ultrasound examination in the third trimester of pregnancy. </p>
          <p><bold>Preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)</bold> may be an option for some families in which the <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified. </p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> comprises eight exons covering more than 90 kb, transcribed and spliced to an approximately 7-kb mRNA. <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> is a member of the LIM-homeodomain family. Alternative splicing of 21 bp at the 3' end of exon 7 has been observed; the biologic significance of this event remains to be determined. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="nail-ps" object-id="nail-ps.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
        <p><bold>Benign allelic variants.</bold> A series of single-nucleotide normal variants has been identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.clough.1999.459">Clough et al 1999</xref>]. </p>
        <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> More than 130 pathogenic variants have been identified. Nonsense, frameshift, splice site, and missense mutations have all been reported, as well as partial- and whole-gene deletions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.dunston.2004.565">Dunston et al 2004</xref>]. All amino acid substitutions that have been observed cause NPS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.dunston.2004.565">Dunston et al 2004</xref>]. Missense mutations are concentrated within the homeodomain and the residues in the LIM domains essential for maintaining the zinc finger structures. A series of recurrent mutations within the homeodomain accounts for approximately 30% of all <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic> pathogenic variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.clough.1999.459">Clough et al 1999</xref>]. No pathogenic variants have been identified in the terminal third of the gene. </p>
        <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The predicted protein comprises 395 or 402 amino acids (depending on alternative splicing of 21 bp at the 3' end of exon 7). </p>
        <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> NPS is the result of heterozygous loss-of-function mutations within the gene encoding the transcription factor. Because all types of mutations (including large deletions and translocations) result in the same phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.dunston.2004.565">Dunston et al 2004</xref>], it is believed that NPS is the result of haploinsufficiency for <italic toggle="yes">LMX1B</italic>. There is no evidence that transcripts bearing nonsense or frameshift mutations escape nonsense-mediated mRNA decay and cause any dominant-negative effects on the normal gene product. Missense mutations within the homeodomain reduce or eliminate DNA binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.dreyer.1998.47">Dreyer et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.mcintosh.1998.1651">McIntosh et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.dreyer.2000.1067">Dreyer et al 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.bongers.2002.703">Bongers et al 2002</xref>]. Missense mutations within the LIM domains are believed to affect the secondary structure of the zinc fingers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.mcintosh.1998.1651">McIntosh et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="nail-ps.REF.clough.1999.459">Clough et al 1999</xref>]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="nail-ps.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.bongers.2004.1239">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bongers</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Duijf</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Beersum</surname>
                    <given-names>SE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schoots</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Kampen</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burckhardt</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamel</surname>
                    <given-names>BC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Losan</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoefsloot</surname>
                    <given-names>LH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yntema</surname>
                    <given-names>HG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knoers</surname>
                    <given-names>NV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Bokhoven</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in the human TBX4 gene cause small patella syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>74</volume>
                <fpage>1239</fpage>
                <lpage>48</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15106123</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.bongers.2002.703">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bongers</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gubler</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knoers</surname>
                    <given-names>NV</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Nail-patella syndrome. Overview on clinical and molecular findings.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Nephrol</source>
                <year>2002</year>
                <volume>17</volume>
                <fpage>703</fpage>
                <lpage>12</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12215822</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.bongers.2005.935">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bongers</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huysmans</surname>
                    <given-names>FT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Levtchenko</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Rooy</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blickman</surname>
                    <given-names>JG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Admiraal</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cruysberg</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Toolens</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prins</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Krabbe</surname>
                    <given-names>PF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Borm</surname>
                    <given-names>GF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schoots</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Bokhoven</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Remortele</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoefsloot</surname>
                    <given-names>LH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Kampen</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knoers</surname>
                    <given-names>NV</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Genotype-phenotype studies in nail-patella syndrome show that LMX1B mutation location is involved in the risk of developing nephropathy.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>13</volume>
                <fpage>935</fpage>
                <lpage>46</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15928687</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.bongers.2008.1240">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bongers</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Wijs</surname>
                    <given-names>IJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marcelis</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoefsloot</surname>
                    <given-names>LH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knoers</surname>
                    <given-names>NVAM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Identification of entire LMX1B gene deletions in nail patella syndrome: evidence for haploinsufficiency as the main pathogenic mechanism underlying dominant inheritance in man.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>16</volume>
                <fpage>1240</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18414507</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.boyer.2013.1216">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boyer</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Woerner</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oakeley</surname>
                    <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Linghu</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gribouval</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>T&#x000ea;te</surname>
                    <given-names>M-J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Duca</surname>
                    <given-names>JS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Klickstein</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Damask</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Szustakowski</surname>
                    <given-names>JD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heibel</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matignon</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baudouin</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chantrel</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Champigneulle</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martin</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nitschk&#x000e9;</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gubler</surname>
                    <given-names>M-C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                    <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chibout</surname>
                    <given-names>S-D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Antignac</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>LMX1B mutations cause hereditary FSGS without extrarenal involvement.</article-title>
                <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>1216</fpage>
                <lpage>22</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23687361</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.clough.1999.459">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clough</surname>
                    <given-names>MV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamlington</surname>
                    <given-names>JD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McIntosh</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Restricted distribution of loss-of-function mutations within the LMX1B genes of nail-patella syndrome patients.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>459</fpage>
                <lpage>65</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10571942</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.cormierdaire.2000.520">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cormier-Daire</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chauvet</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lyonnet</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Briard</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munnich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Merrer</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Genitopatellar syndrome: a new condition comprising absent patellae, scrotal hypoplasia, renal anomalies, facial dysmorphism, and mental retardation.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <year>2000</year>
                <volume>37</volume>
                <fpage>520</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882755</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.dreyer.2000.1067">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dreyer</surname>
                    <given-names>SD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morello</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>German</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zabel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Winterpacht</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lunstrum</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horton</surname>
                    <given-names>WA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oberg</surname>
                    <given-names>KC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>LMX1B transactivation and expression in nail-patella syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                <year>2000</year>
                <volume>9</volume>
                <fpage>1067</fpage>
                <lpage>74</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10767331</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.dreyer.1998.47">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dreyer</surname>
                    <given-names>SD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhou</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baldini</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Winterpacht</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zabel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cole</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                    <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in LMX1B cause abnormal skeletal patterning and renal dysplasia in nail patella syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <year>1998</year>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>47</fpage>
                <lpage>50</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9590287</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.dunston.2004.565">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dunston</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamlington</surname>
                    <given-names>JD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zaveri</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sweeney</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sibbring</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tran</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malbroux</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>O'Neill</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mountford</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McIntosh</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The human LMX1B gene: transcription unit, promoter, and pathogenic mutations.</article-title>
                <source>Genomics</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>84</volume>
                <fpage>565</fpage>
                <lpage>76</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15498463</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.dunston.2005.330">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dunston</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reimschisel</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ding</surname>
                    <given-names>YQ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sweeney</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                    <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>ZF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McIntosh</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A neurological phenotype in nail patella syndrome (NPS) patients illuminated by studies of murine Lmx1b expression.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>13</volume>
                <fpage>330</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15562281</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.feingold.1998.854">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feingold</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Itzchak</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goodman</surname>
                    <given-names>RM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Ultrasound prenatal diagnosis of the nail-patella syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Prenat Diagn</source>
                <year>1998</year>
                <volume>18</volume>
                <fpage>854</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9742578</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.goshen.2000.476">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goshen</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schwartz</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zilka</surname>
                    <given-names>LR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zwas</surname>
                    <given-names>ST</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Bilateral accessory iliac horns: pathognomonic findings in nail-patella syndrome. Scintigraphic evidence on bone scan.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Nucl Med</source>
                <year>2000</year>
                <volume>25</volume>
                <fpage>476</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10836702</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.jones.1997.1">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Jones KL. Trisomy 8 syndrome. In: Jones KL, ed. <italic toggle="yes">Smith's Recognizable Patterns of Human Malformation.</italic> 5 ed. Philadelphia, PA: WB Saunders; 1997:24-7.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.lichter.1997.506">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lichter</surname>
                    <given-names>PR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Richards</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Downs</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stringham</surname>
                    <given-names>HM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boehnke</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Farley</surname>
                    <given-names>FA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Cosegregation of open-angle glaucoma and the nail-patella syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
                <year>1997</year>
                <volume>124</volume>
                <fpage>506</fpage>
                <lpage>15</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9323941</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.marini.2010.431">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marini</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bocciardi</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gimelli</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Di Duca</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Divizia</surname>
                    <given-names>MT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baban</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gaspar</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mammi</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garavelli</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cerone</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Emma</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bedeschi</surname>
                    <given-names>MF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tenconi</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sensi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Salmaggi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bengala</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mari</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Colussi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Szczaluba</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Antonarakis</surname>
                    <given-names>SE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seri</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lerone</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ravazzolo</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A spectrum of LMX1B mutations in Nail-Patella syndrome: new point mutations, deletion, and evidence of mosaicism in unaffected parents.</article-title>
                <source>Genet Med.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>12</volume>
                <fpage>431</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20531206</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.mcintosh.1998.1651">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McIntosh</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dreyer</surname>
                    <given-names>SD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clough</surname>
                    <given-names>MV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dunston</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eyaid</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roig</surname>
                    <given-names>CM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Montgomery</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ala-Mello</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaitila</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Winterpacht</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zabel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frydman</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cole</surname>
                    <given-names>WG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Francomano</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutation analysis of LMX1B gene in nail-patella syndrome patients.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <year>1998</year>
                <volume>63</volume>
                <fpage>1651</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9837817</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.silahtaroglu.1999.68">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Silahtaroglu</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hol</surname>
                    <given-names>FA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jensen</surname>
                    <given-names>PK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Erdel</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Duba</surname>
                    <given-names>HC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Geurds</surname>
                    <given-names>MP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knoers</surname>
                    <given-names>NV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mariman</surname>
                    <given-names>EC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tumer</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Utermann</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wirth</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bugge</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tommerup</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Molecular cytogenetic detection of 9q34 breakpoints associated with nail patella syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>7</volume>
                <fpage>68</fpage>
                <lpage>76</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10094193</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.sweeney.2003.153">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sweeney</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fryer</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mountford</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Green</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McIntosh</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Nail patella syndrome: a review of the phenotype aided by developmental biology.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>40</volume>
                <fpage>153</fpage>
                <lpage>62</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12624132</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.winter.2000.1">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Winter R, Baraitser M. <italic toggle="yes">London Dysmorphology Database</italic>. Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press; 2000.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Suggested_Reading">
          <title>Suggested Reading</title>
          <ref-list id="nail-ps.Suggested_Reading.reflist0">
            <ref id="nail-ps.REF.mcintosh.2005.349">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McIntosh</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dunston</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoover-Fong</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sweeney</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Nail patella syndrome revisited: 50 years after linkage.</article-title>
                <source>Ann Hum Genet</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>69</volume>
                <fpage>349</fpage>
                <lpage>63</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15996164</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="nail-ps.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>13 November 2014 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>28 July 2009 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>26 July 2005 (me) Comprehensive update posted to live Web site </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>31 May 2003 (me) Review posted to live Web site </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>14 April 2003 (im) Original submission </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="nail-ps.1.11" sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig id="nail-ps.F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Typical presentation of thumb nails (a) and finger nails (b) in nail-patella syndrome. The arrow points to the index finger. Note decrease in severity of nail involvement from second to fifth finger and lack of creases over the distal interphalangeal joints. </p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="nailpsFig1ab" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="nail-ps.F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Iliac horns (arrows) in an individual with nail-patella syndrome</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Picture_3" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
