<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="slc6a3-dtds" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">slc6a3-dtds</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>-Related Dopamine Transporter Deficiency Syndrome</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: DAT Deficiency</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kurian</surname>
            <given-names>Manju A</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MA, MBBChir, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Developmental Neurosciences Programme<break/>UCL Institute of Child Health<break/>London, United Kingdom</aff>
          <email>manju.kurian@ucl.ac.uk</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="slc39a14-def" document-type="chapter">SLC39A14 Deficiency</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="sost" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">SOST</italic>-Related Sclerosing Bone Dysplasias</related-object>
      <abstract id="slc6a3-dtds.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome (DTDS) is a complex movement disorder with a continuum that ranges from classic early-onset DTDS (in the first 6 months) to atypical later-onset DTDS (in childhood, adolescence, or adulthood).</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">Classic DTDS</italic>. Infants typically manifest nonspecific findings (irritability, feeding difficulties, axial hypotonia, and/or delayed motor development) followed by a hyperkinetic movement disorder (with features of chorea, dystonia, ballismus, orolingual dyskinesia). Over time, affected individuals develop parkinsonism-dystonia characterized by bradykinesia (progressing to akinesia), dystonic posturing, distal tremor, rigidity, and reduced facial expression. Limitation of voluntary movements leads to severe motor delay. Episodic status dystonicus, exacerbations of dystonia, and secondary orthopedic, gastrointestinal, and respiratory complications are common. Many affected individuals appear to show relative preservation of intellect with good cognitive development.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">Atypical DTDS</italic>. Normal psychomotor development in infancy and early childhood is followed by later-onset manifestations of parkinsonism-dystonia with tremor, progressive bradykinesia, variable tone, and dystonic posturing. The long-term outcome of this form is currently unknown.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS is established in a proband with characteristic clinical, laboratory, and imaging findings and biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> identified by molecular genetic testing.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Treatment to control chorea and dyskinesia in early stages of the disease includes tetrabenazine and benzodiazepines. Dystonia is more difficult to control and treatment often includes pramipexole and ropinirole as first-line agents; adjuncts such as trihexyphenidyl, baclofen, gabapentin, and clonidine for severe dystonia; and chloral hydrate and benzodiazepines for exacerbations of dystonia or status dystonicus.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> Regular physiotherapy to reduce the risk of contractures; early referral for management of feeding difficulties; use of influenza vaccine, prophylactic antibiotics, and chest physiotherapy for patients prone to chest infections, especially in the winter months.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Evaluation every six to 12 months for early evidence of hip dislocation and/or spinal deformity; regular assessment of swallowing to evaluate risk for aspiration; regular nutrition assessment to ensure adequate caloric intake.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Although the dopamine agonists bromocriptine and pergolide could be considered, the associated increased risk of pulmonary, retroperitoneal, and pericardial fibrosis makes them less desirable than the newer dopamine agonists. Drugs with anti-dopaminergic side effects (e.g., some antihistamines, sedatives, and dimenhydrinate) may exacerbate the movement disorder. For the treatment of vomiting, anti-emetics such as the anti-serotoninergic agents (e.g., ondansetron) potentially have fewer side effects than other agents.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Once the <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, carrier testing for at-risk relatives and prenatal testing or preimplantation genetic diagnosis for pregnancies at increased risk are options that can be considered.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.GeneReview_Scope">
        <title><italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> Scope</title>
        <table-wrap id="slc6a3-dtds.Tc" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.Tc_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>-Related Dopamine Transporter Deficiency Syndrome: Included Phenotypes</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.Tc_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Classic early-onset dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome (DTDS)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Atypical later-onset DTDS</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome (DTDS) is a complex movement disorder in which the disease continuum comprises two phenotypes with overlapping clinical features:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Classic early-onset DTDS</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Atypical later-onset DTDS</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Classic early-onset and atypical later-onset <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>-related dopamine transporter deficiency (DTDS) syndrome <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following clinical and laboratory findings.</p>
          <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Clinical_Findings">
            <title>Clinical Findings</title>
            <p><bold>Classic</bold>
<bold>early-onset DTDS</bold></p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>
                  <bold>Predominant features in infancy</bold>
                </p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Onset usually within the first six months of life</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Early nonspecific clinical findings of irritability and difficulty feeding</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Axial hypotonia</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Delay in motor milestones</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Hyperkinetic movement disorder (chorea, ballismus, dystonia, orolingual dyskinesia) typically evident in infancy and early childhood; may persist into late childhood and adolescence</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Eye movement disorders including recurrent oculogyric crisis, saccade initiation failure, ocular flutter, and eyelid myoclonus (which is thought to be non-epileptic)</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>
                  <bold>Predominant features in childhood/adolescence</bold>
                </p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Parkinsonism-dystonia including dystonic postures, resting and action tremor, difficulty initiating movements, bradykinesia, paucity of facial expression, and rigidity</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Severe delay in motor milestones</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Eye movement disorder (see classic early-onset DTDS)</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Atypical later-onset DTDS: Predominant features</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Onset from childhood to adulthood (4th decade)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Resting and action tremor</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Dysarthria</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Parkinsonism-dystonia</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Laboratory_Findings">
            <title>Laboratory Findings</title>
            <p><bold>CSF neurotransmitter analysis.</bold> To date, all individuals with classic early-onset <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS have a distinct pattern:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Raised homovanillic acid level (HVA, metabolite derived from dopamine) with normal 5-hydroxyindoleacetic acid level (5-HIAA, metabolite derived from serotonin). The HVA:5-HIAA ratio in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS is &#x0003e;4.0 (range 5.0-13.0) (normal range 1.0-4.0)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Normal pterin profile</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>SPECT imaging using the ligand ioflupane (DaTScan).</bold> To date, all individuals with <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS who were evaluated had very abnormal results with absent/reduced tracer uptake in the basal nuclei.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with characteristic clinical findings (especially parkinsonism-dystonia), CSF HVA:5-HIAA ratio &#x0003e;4.0, DaTScan showing reduced tracer uptake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">Kurian et al 2011b</xref>], and biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> identified by molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing approaches can include a combination of <bold>gene-targeted testing</bold> (multi-gene panel or single-gene testing) and <bold>genomic testing</bold> (comprehensive genome sequencing) depending on the phenotype.</p>
          <p>Gene-targeted testing requires the clinician to broadly determine clinical phenotype and the gene(s) likely to be involved, whereas genomic testing does not. Children with the distinctive early-onset findings described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc6a3-dtds.Suggestive_Findings">Suggestive Findings</xref> are likely to be diagnosed using gene-targeted testing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc6a3-dtds.Option_1">Option 1</xref>) but may also be identified by genomic testing. Individuals with later-onset disease in which the phenotype may show overlap with other inherited neurologic disorders (ADHD, tremor, dysarthria, and/or parkinsonism-dystonia) may be identified through gene-targeted panels but may also be diagnosed using genomic testing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc6a3-dtds.Option_2">Option 2</xref>).</p>
          <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Option_1">
            <title>Option 1</title>
            <p>When the phenotypic and laboratory findings suggest the diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS, molecular genetic testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold> or use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> is performed first. Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis should be considered if only one or no pathogenic variant is found. To date, the majority of variants are intragenic single-nucleotide variants, insertions, or deletions detectable by Sanger sequencing. Two larger deletions that were detectable by deletion/duplication analysis have been identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">Kurian et al 2011b</xref>; Kurian, personal communication 2016].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc6a3-dtds.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of a condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting secondary findings.</p>
                <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Option_2">
            <title>Option 2</title>
            <p>When the phenotype is indistinguishable from many other inherited disorders characterized by ADHD, tremor, dysarthria, and/or parkinsonism-dystonia, molecular genetic testing approaches can include (when clinically available) genomic testing (<bold>comprehensive genome sequencing</bold>). Comprehensive genome sequencing includes exome sequencing and genome sequencing.</p>
            <p>For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            <table-wrap id="slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 1. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>-Related Dopamine Transporter Deficiency Syndrome</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                    <th id="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Pathogenic Variant&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Most <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> pathogenic variants reported to date</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc6a3-dtds.T.summary_of_molecular_genet_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See footnote 5</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
              <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn id="slc6a3-dtds.TF.1.1">
                  <label>1. </label>
                  <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="slc6a3-dtds" object-id="slc6a3-dtds.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="slc6a3-dtds.TF.1.2">
                  <label>2. </label>
                  <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc6a3-dtds.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="slc6a3-dtds.TF.1.3">
                  <label>3. </label>
                  <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="slc6a3-dtds.TF.1.4">
                  <label>4. </label>
                  <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="slc6a3-dtds.TF.1.5">
                  <label>5. </label>
                  <p>Two individuals with deletions detectable by deletion/duplication analysis have been reported (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc6a3-dtds.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenes">Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</xref>, <bold>Pathogenic variants</bold>).</p>
                </fn>
              </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome (DTDS) typically presents in infancy and atypically later in childhood, adolescence, or adulthood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hansen.2014.3107">Hansen et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014a.1107">Ng et al 2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2015">Kurian &#x00026; Assmann 2015</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS is rare, with fewer than 30 affected individuals (from ~21 families) identified to date [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2009.1595">Kurian et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">Kurian et al 2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hansen.2014.3107">Hansen et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014a.1107">Ng et al 2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.yildiz.2017.49">Yildiz et al 2017</xref>].</p>
          <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Classic_EarlyOnset_DTDS">
            <title>Classic Early-Onset DTDS</title>
            <p>Typically, infants present between birth and age six months [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2009.1595">Kurian et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">Kurian et al 2011b</xref>]. In the early stages, children manifest the nonspecific findings of irritability, feeding difficulties, axial hypotonia, and delayed motor development. In infancy a heterogeneous movement disorder is prominent, with features of chorea, dystonia, dystonia-parkinsonism, ballismus, and orolingual dyskinesia. Many infants also develop an eye movement disorder, which may manifest as recurrent oculogyric crises, saccade initiation failure, ocular flutter, or eyelid myoclonus. At this early age hyperkinetic features predominate.</p>
            <p>The early hyperkinesia often becomes less prominent over time, with subsequent development of parkinsonism-dystonia. Bradykinesia progressing to akinesia is common, as well as dystonic posturing, distal tremor, rigidity, and hypomimia (reduced facial expression). Voluntary movements become limited, leading to severe motor delay.</p>
            <p>During the first years of life some children have episodic status dystonicus. Prolonged periods of crying and irritability &#x02013; without discernable triggers &#x02013; are also described. Disrupted sleep patterns are common. Exacerbations of dystonia are also common, often related to intercurrent illness, infection, and/or dehydration.</p>
            <p>Although more data are needed, it appears that many affected individuals show relative preservation of intellect with good cognitive development.</p>
            <p>Secondary orthopedic, gastrointestinal, and respiratory complications are common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2015">Kurian &#x00026; Assmann 2015</xref>].</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Many develop spinal deformities, often necessitating surgery. Fixed limb contractures, osteoporotic bone fractures, and hip dislocation are also described.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Alternative feeding strategies using nasogastric tubes or percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy become necessary due to progressive bulbar dysfunction.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Reduced axial tone, spinal abnormalities, and bulbar dysfunction compromise respiratory function, leading to an increased risk for recurrent chest infections and aspiration pneumonia.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>The majority develop anarthria, and need alternative and augmentative communication devices for effective communication.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>A number of children with infantile-onset <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS die in late childhood / early adolescence from unexplained sudden death in sleep or respiratory complications.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Atypical_LaterOnset_DTDS">
            <title>Atypical Later-Onset DTDS</title>
            <p>To date, four individuals with atypical later-onset DTDS have been described. They had normal psychomotor development in infancy and early childhood, attaining independent ambulation and spoken language [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hansen.2014.3107">Hansen et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014a.1107">Ng et al 2014a</xref>]. Later in childhood, adolescence, or adulthood, they developed manifestations of parkinsonism-dystonia with tremor, progressive bradykinesia, variable tone, and dystonic posturing.</p>
            <p>Manifestations of ADHD in childhood have been reported.</p>
            <p>Identification of additional individuals with later-onset DTDS will aid understanding of this atypical presentation.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.GenotypePhenotype_Correlatio">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>It is not yet clear whether genotype-phenotype correlations exist for <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS.</p>
          <p>From published functional data on pathogenic missense variants, children with classic, severe early-onset disease have lower levels of residual transporter activity than those with the later-onset atypical phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hansen.2014.3107">Hansen et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014a.1107">Ng et al 2014a</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS shows complete penetrance with no discernible gender differences.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS is rare, with fewer than 30 affected individuals (from ~21 families) currently identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2009.1595">Kurian et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">Kurian et al 2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hansen.2014.3107">Hansen et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014a.1107">Ng et al 2014a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.yildiz.2017.49">Yildiz et al 2017</xref>].</p>
          <p>Affected individuals have been reported from a wide variety of ethnic backgrounds.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Genetically_Related_Allelic">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>Rare missense variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> have been reported in individuals with bipolar disorder, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, and autism spectrum disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hayden.2006.85">Hayden &#x00026; Nurnberger 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hamilton.2013.1315">Hamilton et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.bowton.2014.e464">Bowton et al 2014</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc6a3-dtds.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>, <bold>Pathogenic variants</bold>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>The following groups of disorders can present clinically with the manifestations of classic early-onset and atypical later onset <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS.</p>
        <p><bold>Cerebral palsy.</bold> The early hyperkinetic features of classic early-onset <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS can mimic dyskinetic cerebral palsy and later features may be reminiscent of spastic/dystonic cerebral palsy. Details of the pre- and perinatal history as well as MRI, as well as the diagnostic testing specific for <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS, may be helpful in differentiating these conditions.</p>
        <p><bold>Neurotransmitter disorders.</bold> The clinical features of progressive parkinsonism-dystonia, eye movement disorder, axial hypotonia, and delayed motor development may be similar to those seen in other neurotransmitter disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011a.721">Kurian et al 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2015.567">Ng et al 2015</xref>], including autosomal recessive pterin defects (e.g., <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="spr-def" document-type="chapter">sepiapterin reductase deficiency</related-object> and autosomal recessive GTP cyclohydrolase deficiency [OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/233910">233910</ext-link>]), <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="thdrd" document-type="chapter">tyrosine hydroxylase deficiency</related-object>, aromatic L-amino acid decarboxylase deficiency (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/107930">107930</ext-link>), and brain serotonin-dopamine deficiency caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">SLC18A2</italic>.</p>
        <p><bold>Mitochondrial diseases.</bold> The phenotypic features of the mitochondriocytopathies (including those caused by pathogenic variants in <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="alpers" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic></related-object><italic toggle="yes">,</italic> pyruvate dehydrogenase deficiency (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/312170">312170</ext-link>), and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pdc" document-type="chapter">pyruvate carboxylase deficiency</related-object>) overlap with <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.garciacazorla.2008.273">Garcia-Cazorla et al 2008</xref>]. In some mitochondrial disorders increased HVA levels are also observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.pineda.2006.394">Pineda et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hasselmann.2010.58">Hasselmann et al 2010</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold>Metabolic syndromes</bold> including lysosomal storage diseases, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="npc" document-type="chapter">Niemann-Pick disease type C</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="gm1-ganglio" document-type="chapter">GM1 gangliosidosis</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="lns" document-type="chapter">Lesch-Nyhan syndrome</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="homocystinuria" document-type="chapter">homocystinuria</related-object>, and untreated <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pku" document-type="chapter">phenylketonuria</related-object> can mimic <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.garciacazorla.2014.627">Garcia-Cazorla &#x00026; Duarte 2014</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold>Monogenic movement disorders associated with infantile-onset dyskinesia/hyperkinesia.</bold> Early disease manifestations of classic early-onset DTDS may be reminiscent of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK263441/"><italic toggle="yes">ADCY5</italic>-related dyskinesia</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK1430/">glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome</ext-link>, <italic toggle="yes">PRRT2</italic>-related infantile convulsions choreoathetosis (ICCA; see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" document-type="chapter">Dystonia Overview</related-object>), <italic toggle="yes">FOXG1-</italic>related syndrome (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/613454">613454</ext-link>), <italic toggle="yes">SYT1-</italic>related disorder (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/185605">185605</ext-link>), <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rapid-odp" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">ATP1A3</italic>-related neurologic disorders</related-object> and <italic toggle="yes">GNAO1</italic>-related diseases (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/615473">615473</ext-link>).</p>
        <p><bold>Monogenic juvenile parkinsonism syndromes</bold> due to mutation of the following genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.garciacazorla.2014.627">Garcia-Cazorla &#x00026; Duarte 2014</xref>] may mimic classic early-onset and atypical later-onset DTDS:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">PARK2</italic> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="jpd" document-type="chapter">Parkin Type of Early-Onset Parkinson Disease</related-object>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">PINK1</italic> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pink1-pd" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">PINK1</italic> Type of Young-Onset Parkinson Disease</related-object>)<italic toggle="yes">,</italic></p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">DJ1</italic> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" document-type="chapter">Dystonia Overview</related-object>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>ATXN2 (SCA2) (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="sca2" document-type="chapter">SCA2</related-object>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>ATXN3 (SCA3) (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="sca3" document-type="chapter">SCA3</related-object>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">ATP1A3</italic> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" document-type="chapter">Dystonia Overview</related-object>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">PRKRA</italic> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" document-type="chapter">Dystonia Overview</related-object>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">FBXO7</italic> (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/260300">260300</ext-link>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">SPG11</italic> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="spg11" document-type="chapter">Spastic Paraplegia 11</related-object>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">DNAJC6</italic> (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/608375">608375</ext-link>)</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>Disorders of brain metal accumulation.</bold>
<related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="wilson" document-type="chapter">Wilson disease</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nbia-ov" document-type="chapter">neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation</related-object> (NBIA), and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hmdpc" document-type="chapter">dystonia/parkinsonism, hypermanganesemia, polycythemia, and chronic liver disease</related-object> may mimic <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS. Brain MRI can assist in the diagnosis of these disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.tuschl.2012.457">Tuschl et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.bandmann.2015.103">Bandmann et al 2015</xref>]; see also <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nbia-ov" document-type="chapter">Neurodegeneration with Brain Iron Accumulation</related-object>.</p>
        <p><bold>Other.</bold> Meningoencephalitis, autoimmune, hypoxia, drug-induced, post-infectious and monogenic causes of striatal necrosis, tumors, and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rett" document-type="chapter">Rett syndrome</related-object> should be considered as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.garciacazorla.2014.627">Garcia-Cazorla &#x00026; Duarte 2014</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Evaluations_Following_Initia">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with a <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome (DTDS), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Neurologic assessment of the movement disorder</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ophthalmology assessment of vision and eye movements</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation of caloric intake and feeding by a nutritionist</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Speech and language therapy assessment of communication and swallowing</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Physiotherapy evaluation of postural issues and tone</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Occupational therapy to provide suitable aids for communication, mobility, and home adaptations</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hip and spine x-rays to evaluate for hip dislocation and spinal deformity</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Orthopedic review of any fixed contractures / joint dislocations</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Pediatric physician-led care for evaluation of general issues such as drooling, gastroesophageal reflux disease, constipation, disturbed sleeping, and pressure sores</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>A multidisciplinary approach to the long-term management of this progressive disorder is optimal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014b.275">Ng et al 2014b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2015">Kurian &#x00026; Assmann 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p>As first principle, risk factors that exacerbate the movement disorder should be avoided, including patient discomfort, poor body positioning, and pain (e.g., from constipation, urinary retention, pressure sores, undetected fractures). Early referral for nasogastric feeding or percutaneous gastrostomy is appropriate if oral feeding becomes problematic.</p>
          <p><bold>Treatment for the palliative control of symptoms</bold> includes the following [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014b.275">Ng et al 2014b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2015">Kurian &#x00026; Assmann 2015</xref>]:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Tetrabenazine and benzodiazepines may be useful in controlling chorea and dyskinesia in early stages of the disease. Chloral hydrate may also help during exacerbations or to aid sleep.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Dystonia is more difficult to control and treatment often includes pramipexole and ropinirole as first-line agents (as few patients respond to levodopa/carbidopa and any response is usually modest and not sustained).</p>
              <p>Adjuncts, such as the anticholinergic trihexyphenidyl, are often needed. Baclofen, gabapentin, and clonidine may also be tried for severe dystonia.</p>
              <p>Benzodiazepines and chloral hydrate can be useful for exacerbations of dystonia or status dystonicus. Although the role of atypical tranquilizers (e.g., zopiclone) is not yet established, they have been used successfully in individual cases.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Surgical interventions such as intrathecal baclofen and deep brain stimulation have been used on rare occasions late in the disease course when dystonia is severe; therapeutic benefit is limited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2009.1595">Kurian et al 2009</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Optimum management of tone with medical therapies and regular physiotherapy evaluation reduce risk of contracture development. Focal botulinum toxin may be considered for emerging limb contractures and to prevent hip dislocation.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>For the treatment of vomiting, anti-emetics such as the anti-serotoninergic agents (e.g., ondansetron) potentially have fewer side effects than other agents.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Treatment of status dystonicus.</bold> Standard protocols are used in an intensive care setting. Anesthetic agents, GABA-ergic medication (including GABA-A receptor agonists such as benzodiazepines, GABA-enhancing medications such as gabapentin or phenobarbitone, and GABA-B receptor agonists like baclofen), further anticholinergics, and alpha adrenergic agents such as clonidine may be used. For severe life-threatening or medically intractable status dystonicus, intrathecal baclofen and pallidal deep brain stimulation may be considered.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Prevention_of_Secondary_Comp">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Consider influenza vaccine, prophylactic antibiotics, and chest physiotherapy for patients prone to chest infections especially during winter months</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>The following are appropriate:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation every six to 12 months for early evidence of hip dislocation and/or spinal deformity</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular swallowing assessment to evaluate risk for aspiration</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular assessment by a dietitian/nutritionist to ensure adequate caloric intake</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Although dopamine agonists are used as first-line treatment of dystonia in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS, bromocriptine and pergolide are generally avoided due to increased risk of pulmonary, retroperitoneal, and pericardial fibrosis.</p>
          <p>Drugs with anti-dopaminergic side effects (e.g., some antihistamines, sedatives, and dimenhydrinate) may exacerbate the movement disorder.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_R">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc6a3-dtds.Related_Genetic_Counseling_I">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Therapies_Under_Investigatio">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome (DTDS) is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected child are usually obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> pathogenic variant).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Offspring of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>To date, there are no reports of individuals with <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>-related DTDS having children, but this may be a theoretic possibility for those with the atypical form of disease.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The offspring of an individual with <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>-related DTDS would be obligate heterozygotes (carriers) for a pathogenic variant (based on the assumption that the offspring&#x02019;s partner is not a carrier).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier of an <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Carrier_Heterozygote_Detecti">
          <title>Carrier (Heterozygote) Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> pathogenic variants in the family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Related_Genetic_Counseling_I">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected, are carriers, or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimpl">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenes">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>To date, functional investigations indicate that <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS results from loss of transporter function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2009.1595">Kurian et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">Kurian et al 2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hansen.2014.3107">Hansen et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014a.1107">Ng et al 2014a</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> encodes the dopamine transporter (DAT) that is expressed predominantly within the substantia nigra (projecting to the striatum) and in the midbrain ventral tegmental area (projecting to the hippocampus, nucleus accumbens, and corticolimbic areas). The transporter has a crucial role in mediating reuptake of dopamine from the synaptic cleft, thereby controlling dopamine homeostasis by regulating the duration and amplitude of synaptic dopaminergic transmission.</p>
          <p>A number of nonsense variants, splice site changes, and deletions have been reported in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3-</italic>related DTDS, and it is likely that for these pathogenic variants nonsense-mediated decay or absent/truncated protein are mechanistic factors in disease. Reported missense substitutions result in mutated proteins which impair transporter function through a number of mechanisms including (i) reduced transporter activity, (ii) impaired dopamine recognition and/or binding affinity, (iii) decreased cell surface expression of the transporter, and (iv) abnormal posttranslational protein modification with impaired glycosylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2009.1595">Kurian et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">Kurian et al 2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hansen.2014.3107">Hansen et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014a.1107">Ng et al 2014a</xref>]. Abnormal DAT protein folding and transporter oligomerization are also postulated to play a role.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> pathogenic variants therefore impair the normal physiologic recycling of dopamine leading to presynaptic dopamine depletion. Excess dopamine in the synaptic cleft is metabolized to HVA, which can be detected on CSF analysis. High levels of synaptic dopamine may have downstream signaling effects on postsynaptic dopamine receptors, and are also likely to suppress tyrosine hydroxylase activity through action on D2 autoreceptors, thereby inhibiting presynaptic dopamine synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.blackstone.2009.1455">Blackstone 2009</xref>].</p>
          <p>A DAT knockout mouse model shows a number of features described in humans, including reduced growth, early hyperkinesia, and difficulties with feeding. Over time they develop abnormal clasping and kyphosis with progressive bradykinesia, reminiscent of the parkinsonism-dystonia phenotype in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.giros.1996.606">Giros et al 1996</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> The protein-coding transcript <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001044.4">NM_001044.4</ext-link> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org/Homo_sapiens/Transcript/Summary?g=ENSG00000142319;r=5:1392790-1445430;t=ENST00000270349">ENST00000270349</ext-link>) comprises 15 exons in total, 14 of which are coding.</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> To date, 20 individuals have been identified with biallelic (i.e., homozygous or compound heterozygous) pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3.</italic></p>
          <p>Pathogenic variants have been identified throughout the entire coding region and flanking splice sites. No mutation hot spots or recurrent/common pathogenic variants have been identified. In these 20 individuals, 41 pathogenic variants including 27 missense changes, one pathogenic nonsense variant, seven splice site variants, and four intra-exon small deletions have been described. Large deletions have been described: a homozygous multiexon deletion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">Kurian et al 2011b</xref>] and a microdeletion/translocation encompassing <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> [Kurian, personal communication 2016].</p>
          <p>Note that rare missense variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic> have been reported in individuals with bipolar disorder, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, and autism spectrum disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hayden.2006.85">Hayden &#x00026; Nurnberger 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hamilton.2013.1315">Hamilton et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.bowton.2014.e464">Bowton et al 2014</xref>] leading to the proposal that &#x02013; through currently unknown mechanisms &#x02013; this gene may confer risk for multiple complex psychiatric disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.bowton.2014.e464">Bowton et al 2014</xref>]. However, parents of individuals with DTDS have not manifested attention deficit disorder or psychiatric diseases.</p>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The gene transcript encodes a protein of 620 amino acids (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_001035.1">NP_001035.1</ext-link>). The dopamine transporter (DAT) is one of the solute carrier 6 (SLC6) transporters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.br_er.2012.256">Br&#x000f6;er &#x00026; Gether 2012</xref>]. Based on the crystal structure of a prokaryotic homolog [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.singh.2007.952">Singh et al 2007</xref>], DAT comprises 12 transmembrane helices connected by a series of interconnecting extracellular and intracellular loops from the N- to C-terminus. The protein undergoes posttranslational modification prior to being expressed at the cell surface of the presynaptic membrane. Its role in the translocation of dopamine requires tandem transport of sodium and chloride ions across the cell membrane.</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Pathogenic variants in the gene are postulated to lead to loss of transporter function and a number of pathogenic variants reported in the literature are pathogenic nonsense variants, splice site variants, or deletions.</p>
          <p>Functional studies indicate that for pathogenic missense variants, mutated DAT displays impaired transporter function through a number of mechanisms including (i) reduced transporter activity, (ii) impaired dopamine recognition and binding affinity, (iii) decreased cell surface expression of the transporter, and (iv) abnormal posttranslational protein modification with impaired glycosylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2009.1595">Kurian et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">Kurian et al 2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hansen.2014.3107">Hansen et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014a.1107">Ng et al 2014a</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <ref-list id="slc6a3-dtds.References.reflist0">
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.bandmann.2015.103">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bandmann</surname>
                  <given-names>O</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Weiss</surname>
                  <given-names>KH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kaler</surname>
                  <given-names>SG</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2015</year>
              <article-title>Wilson's disease and other neurological copper disorders.</article-title>
              <source>Lancet Neurol.</source>
              <volume>14</volume>
              <fpage>103</fpage>
              <lpage>13</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25496901</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.blackstone.2009.1455">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Blackstone</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2009</year>
              <article-title>Infantile parkinsonism-dystonia: a dopamine "transportopathy".</article-title>
              <source>J Clin Invest.</source>
              <volume>119</volume>
              <fpage>1455</fpage>
              <lpage>8</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19504720</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.bowton.2014.e464">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bowton</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Saunders</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Reddy</surname>
                  <given-names>IA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Campbell</surname>
                  <given-names>NG</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hamilton</surname>
                  <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Henry</surname>
                  <given-names>LK</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Coon</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sakrikar</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Veenstra-VanderWeele</surname>
                  <given-names>JM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Blakely</surname>
                  <given-names>RD</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sutcliffe</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Matthies</surname>
                  <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Erreger</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Galli</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2014</year>
              <article-title>SLC6A3 coding variant Ala559Val found in two autism probands alters dopamine transporter function and trafficking.</article-title>
              <source>Transl Psychiatry.</source>
              <volume>4</volume>
              <fpage>e464</fpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25313507</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.br_er.2012.256">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Br&#x000f6;er</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gether</surname>
                  <given-names>U</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2012</year>
              <article-title>The solute carrier 6 family of transporters.</article-title>
              <source>Br J Pharmacol.</source>
              <volume>167</volume>
              <fpage>256</fpage>
              <lpage>78</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22519513</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.garciacazorla.2008.273">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Garcia-Cazorla</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Duarte</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Serrano</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nascimento</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ormazabal</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Carrilho</surname>
                  <given-names>I</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Briones</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Montoya</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Garesse</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sala-Castellvi</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Pineda</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Artuch</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2008</year>
              <article-title>Mitochondrial diseases mimicking neurotransmitter defects.</article-title>
              <source>Mitochondrion.</source>
              <volume>8</volume>
              <fpage>273</fpage>
              <lpage>8</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18558519</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.garciacazorla.2014.627">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Garcia-Cazorla</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Duarte</surname>
                  <given-names>ST</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2014</year>
              <article-title>Parkinsonism and inborn errors of metabolism.</article-title>
              <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
              <volume>37</volume>
              <fpage>627</fpage>
              <lpage>42</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24906253</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.giros.1996.606">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Giros</surname>
                  <given-names>B</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jaber</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jones</surname>
                  <given-names>SR</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wightman</surname>
                  <given-names>RM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Caron</surname>
                  <given-names>MG</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>1996</year>
              <article-title>Hyperlocomotion and indifference to cocaine and amphetamine in mice lacking the dopamine transporter.</article-title>
              <source>Nature.</source>
              <volume>379</volume>
              <fpage>606</fpage>
              <lpage>12</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8628395</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hamilton.2013.1315">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hamilton</surname>
                  <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Campbell</surname>
                  <given-names>NG</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sharma</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Erreger</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Herborg Hansen</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Saunders</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Belovich</surname>
                  <given-names>AN</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sahai</surname>
                  <given-names>MA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cook</surname>
                  <given-names>EH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gether</surname>
                  <given-names>U</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>McHaourab</surname>
                  <given-names>HS</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Matthies</surname>
                  <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sutcliffe</surname>
                  <given-names>JS</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Galli</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <etal/>
              </person-group>
              <year>2013</year>
              <article-title>De novo mutation in the dopamine transporter gene associates dopamine dysfunction with autism spectrum disorder.</article-title>
              <source>Mol Psychiatry.</source>
              <volume>18</volume>
              <fpage>1315</fpage>
              <lpage>23</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23979605</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hansen.2014.3107">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hansen</surname>
                  <given-names>FH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Skj&#x000f8;rringe</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Yasmeen</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Arends</surname>
                  <given-names>NV</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sahai</surname>
                  <given-names>MA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Erreger</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Andreassen</surname>
                  <given-names>TF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Holy</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hamilton</surname>
                  <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Neergheen</surname>
                  <given-names>V</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Karlsborg</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Newman</surname>
                  <given-names>AH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Pope</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Heales</surname>
                  <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Friberg</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Law</surname>
                  <given-names>I</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Pinborg</surname>
                  <given-names>LH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sitte</surname>
                  <given-names>HH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Loland</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Shi</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Weinstein</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Galli</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hjermind</surname>
                  <given-names>LE</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>M&#x000f8;ller</surname>
                  <given-names>LB</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gether</surname>
                  <given-names>U</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2014</year>
              <article-title>Missense dopamine transporter mutations associate with adult parkinsonism and ADHD.</article-title>
              <source>J Clin Invest.</source>
              <volume>124</volume>
              <fpage>3107</fpage>
              <lpage>20</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24911152</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hasselmann.2010.58">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hasselmann</surname>
                  <given-names>O</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Blau</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ramaekers</surname>
                  <given-names>VT</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Quadros</surname>
                  <given-names>EV</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sequeira</surname>
                  <given-names>JM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Weissert</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2010</year>
              <article-title>Cerebral folate deficiency and CNS inflammatory markers in Alpers disease.</article-title>
              <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
              <volume>99</volume>
              <fpage>58</fpage>
              <lpage>61</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19766516</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.hayden.2006.85">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hayden</surname>
                  <given-names>EP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nurnberger</surname>
                  <given-names>JI</given-names>
                  <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2006</year>
              <article-title>Molecular genetics of bipolar disorder.</article-title>
              <source>Genes Brain Behav.</source>
              <volume>5</volume>
              <fpage>85</fpage>
              <lpage>95</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16436192</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2015">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Kurian MA, Assmann BE. The monoamine &#x0201c;transportopathies&#x0201d;: Dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome and vesicular monoamine transporter deficiency. In: Hoffmann G, Blau N, eds. <italic toggle="yes">Congenital Neurotransmitter Disorders: A Clinical Approach</italic>. New York: Nova Science Publishers Inc; 2015:81-91.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011a.721">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kurian</surname>
                  <given-names>MA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gissen</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Smith</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Heales</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                  <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Clayton</surname>
                  <given-names>PT</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2011a</year>
              <article-title>The monoamine neurotransmitter disorders: an expanding range of neurological syndromes.</article-title>
              <source>Lancet Neurol.</source>
              <volume>10</volume>
              <fpage>721</fpage>
              <lpage>33</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21777827</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2011b.54">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kurian</surname>
                  <given-names>MA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Li</surname>
                  <given-names>Y</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Zhen</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Meyer</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hai</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Christen</surname>
                  <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hoffmann</surname>
                  <given-names>GF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jardine</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>von Moers</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mordekar</surname>
                  <given-names>SR</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>O'Callaghan</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wassmer</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wraige</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dietrich</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lewis</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hyland</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Heales</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                  <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sanger</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gissen</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Assmann</surname>
                  <given-names>BE</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Reith</surname>
                  <given-names>ME</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Maher</surname>
                  <given-names>ER</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2011b</year>
              <article-title>Clinical and molecular characterisation of hereditary dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome: an observational cohort and experimental study.</article-title>
              <source>Lancet Neurol.</source>
              <volume>10</volume>
              <fpage>54</fpage>
              <lpage>62</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21112253</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.kurian.2009.1595">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kurian</surname>
                  <given-names>MA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Zhen</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cheng</surname>
                  <given-names>SY</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Li</surname>
                  <given-names>Y</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mordekar</surname>
                  <given-names>SR</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jardine</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Morgan</surname>
                  <given-names>NV</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Meyer</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tee</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Pasha</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wassmer</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Heales</surname>
                  <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gissen</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Reith</surname>
                  <given-names>ME</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Maher</surname>
                  <given-names>ER</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2009</year>
              <article-title>Homozygous loss-of-function mutations in the gene encoding the dopamine transporter are associated with infantile parkinsonism-dystonia.</article-title>
              <source>J Clin Invest.</source>
              <volume>119</volume>
              <fpage>1595</fpage>
              <lpage>603</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19478460</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2015.567">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ng</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Papandreou</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Heales</surname>
                  <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kurian</surname>
                  <given-names>MA</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2015</year>
              <article-title>Monoamine neurotransmitter disorders-clinical advances and future perspectives.</article-title>
              <source>Nat Rev Neurol.</source>
              <volume>11</volume>
              <fpage>567</fpage>
              <lpage>84</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26392380</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014a.1107">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ng</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Zhen</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Meyer</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Erreger</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Li</surname>
                  <given-names>Y</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kakar</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ahmad</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Thiele</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kubisch</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rider</surname>
                  <given-names>NL</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Morton</surname>
                  <given-names>DH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Strauss</surname>
                  <given-names>KA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Puffenberger</surname>
                  <given-names>EG</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>D'Agnano</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Anikster</surname>
                  <given-names>Y</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Carducci</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hyland</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rotstein</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Leuzzi</surname>
                  <given-names>V</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Borck</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Reith</surname>
                  <given-names>ME</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kurian</surname>
                  <given-names>MA</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2014a</year>
              <article-title>Dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome: phenotypic spectrum from infancy to adulthood.</article-title>
              <source>Brain.</source>
              <volume>137</volume>
              <fpage>1107</fpage>
              <lpage>19</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24613933</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.ng.2014b.275">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ng</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Heales</surname>
                  <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kurian</surname>
                  <given-names>MA</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2014b</year>
              <article-title>Clinical features and pharmacotherapy of childhood monoamine neurotransmitter disorders.</article-title>
              <source>Paediatr Drugs.</source>
              <volume>16</volume>
              <fpage>275</fpage>
              <lpage>91</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25011953</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.pineda.2006.394">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Pineda</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ormazabal</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Gallardo</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nascimento</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Solano</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Herrero</surname>
                  <given-names>MD</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Vilaseca</surname>
                  <given-names>MA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Briones</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ib&#x000e1;&#x000f1;ez</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Montoya</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Artuch</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2006</year>
              <article-title>Cerebral folate deficiency and leukoencephalopathy caused by a mitochondrial DNA deletion.</article-title>
              <source>Ann Neurol.</source>
              <volume>59</volume>
              <fpage>394</fpage>
              <lpage>8</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16365882</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.tuschl.2012.457">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tuschl</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Clayton</surname>
                  <given-names>PT</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gospe</surname>
                  <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gulab</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Singhi</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Aulakh</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
                  <given-names>RT</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Barsottini</surname>
                  <given-names>OG</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Zaki</surname>
                  <given-names>MS</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Del Rosario</surname>
                  <given-names>ML</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dyack</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Price</surname>
                  <given-names>V</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rideout</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gordon</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wevers</surname>
                  <given-names>RA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chong</surname>
                  <given-names>WK</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mills</surname>
                  <given-names>PB</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2012</year>
              <article-title>Syndrome of hepatic cirrhosis, dystonia, polycythemia, and hypermanganesemia caused by mutations in SLC30A10, a manganese transporter in man.</article-title>
              <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
              <volume>90</volume>
              <fpage>457</fpage>
              <lpage>66</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22341972</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.singh.2007.952">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Singh</surname>
                  <given-names>SK</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Yamashita</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gouaux</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <year>2007</year>
              <article-title>Antidepressant binding site in a bacterial homologue of neurotransmitter transporters.</article-title>
              <source>Nature.</source>
              <volume>448</volume>
              <fpage>952</fpage>
              <lpage>6</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17687333</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="slc6a3-dtds.REF.yildiz.2017.49">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Yildiz</surname>
                  <given-names>Y</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Pektas</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tokatli</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Haliloglu</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Hereditary dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome: challenges in diagnosis and treatment.</article-title>
              <source>Neuropediatrics.</source>
              <year>2017</year>
              <volume>48</volume>
              <fpage>49</fpage>
              <lpage>52</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27690368</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>Dr Manju KurianDevelopmental Neurosciences, UCL Institute of Child Health, LondonWeb: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=MKURI59">iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=MKURI59</ext-link></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Acknowledgments">
          <title>Acknowledgments</title>
          <p>The author would like to thank and acknowledge the families and patients with DTDS. MAK is funded by a Wellcome Trust Intermediate Clinical Fellowship and receives funding from Rosetrees Trust.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc6a3-dtds.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>27 July 2017 (bp) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>30 June 2015 (mak) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
