<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="sucla2-def" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">sucla2-def</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Encephalomyopathic Form with Methylmalonic Aciduria</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: SUCLA2 Deficiency</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>El-Hattab</surname>
            <given-names>Ayman W</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, FAAP, FACMG</degrees>
          <aff>Medical Genetics and Metabolic Consultant, Division of Clinical Genetics and Metabolic Disorders<break/>Pediatric Department<break/>Tawam Hospital<break/>Al-Ain, United Arab Emirates</aff>
          <email>elhattabaw@yahoo.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Scaglia</surname>
            <given-names>Fernando</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, FAAP, FACMG</degrees>
          <aff>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics<break/>Baylor College of Medicine<break/>Houston, Texas</aff>
          <email>fscaglia@bcm.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="revised">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="stxbp1-ee" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">STXBP1</italic> Encephalopathy with Epilepsy</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="suclg1-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Encephalomyopathic Form with Methylmalonic Aciduria</related-object>
      <abstract id="sucla2-def.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) depletion syndrome, encephalomyopathic form with methylmalonic aciduria is characterized by onset of the following features in infancy or childhood (median age of onset 2 months; range of onset birth to 6 years): psychomotor retardation, hypotonia, dystonia, muscular atrophy, sensorineural hearing impairment, postnatal growth retardation, and feeding difficulties. Other less frequent features include distinctive facial features, contractures, kyphoscoliosis, gastroesophageal reflux, ptosis, choreoathetosis, ophthalmoplegia, and epilepsy (infantile spasms or generalized convulsions). The median survival is 20 years; approximately 30% of affected individuals succumb during childhood. Affected individuals may have hyperintensities in the basal ganglia, cerebral atrophy, and leukoencephalopathy on head MRI. Elevation of methylmalonic acid (MMA) in the urine and plasma is found in a vast majority of affected individuals, although at levels that are far below those typically seen in individuals with classic methylmalonic aciduria.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome is established in a proband by the identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> on molecular genetic testing.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Physical therapy to maintain muscle function and prevent joint contractures; antiepileptic drugs for seizures; nasogastric or gastrostomy tube as needed to assure adequate caloric intake; chest physiotherapy, aggressive antibiotic treatment of chest infections, and respiratory aids such as assisted nasal ventilation or use of a tracheostomy and ventilator when indicated; bracing to treat scoliosis or kyphosis; blepharoplasty for significant ptosis; and hearing aids/cochlear implantation for sensorineural hearing loss.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Routine monitoring of development, growth, and hearing; periodic ophthalmologic evaluations; routine skeletal evaluations for kyphoscoliosis and joint contractures.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Carrier testing for at-risk relatives and prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk are possible once the pathogenic variants in the family have been identified.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) depletion syndrome, encephalomyopathic form with methylmalonic aciduria typically manifests during early infancy and <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with a combination of the following clinical, brain MRI, and supportive laboratory and muscle biopsy findings:</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Clinical features</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Psychomotor retardation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hypotonia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Sensorineural hearing impairment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Dystonia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Feeding difficulties</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Growth retardation/failure to thrive (FTT)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Muscular atrophy</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Brain MRI findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Basal ganglia hyperintensities</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Cerebral atrophy</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Leukoencephalopathy</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Supportive laboratory findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Urine organic acid analysis</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Elevation of methylmalonic acid (MMA) in the vast majority of affected children. However, the MMA level is considerably less pronounced than in classic methylmalonic aciduria and can be only marginally elevated or even normal on rare occasions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.lamperti.2012.403">Lamperti et al 2012</xref>].</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Several other metabolites may be elevated in urine, including methylcitrate, 3-methylglutaconic acid, 3-hydroxyisovaleric acid, and Krebs cycle intermediates such as succinate, fumarate, and 2-ketoglutarate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Plasma MMA level</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Elevation has been reported in all affected individuals analyzed, including those with marginally elevated urine MMA level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Plasma MMA level may be more sensitive in identifying <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome than urine organic acid analysis.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Acylcarnitine profile.</bold> Elevated C3; thus, this condition can potentially be detected by newborn screening.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Plasma and CSF lactate levels.</bold> Elevated in most affected individuals</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Muscle biopsy findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Increased fiber size variability, atrophic fibers, intracellular lipid accumulation, and COX-deficient fibers</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Approximately 20% of affected individuals will have normal muscle histology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In some cases, structurally altered mitochondria with abnormal cristae on electron microscopy</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In the majority of individuals, abnormal electron transport chain activity</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>The most common abnormalities are combined complex I and IV deficiencies, combined complex I, III, and IV deficiencies, and isolated complex IV deficiency.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Electron transport chain activity has been reported to be normal in approximately 10% of affected individuals who underwent this test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Mitochondrial DNA content in muscle tissue of affected individuals typically reduced to 20%-60% of tissue- and age-matched controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.elpeleg.2005.1081">Elpeleg et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2007.862">Carrozzo et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.ostergaard.2007.853">Ostergaard et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome <bold>is established</bold> in a proband by the identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> on molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold>, use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>, and <bold>more comprehensive</bold>
<bold>genomic testing</bold>.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> is performed first and followed by gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis if only one or no pathogenic variant is found.</p>
              <p>Note: Targeted analysis for the c.534+1G&#x0003e;A pathogenic founder variant can be performed first in individuals of Faroese ancestry (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sucla2-def.Prevalence">Prevalence</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sucla2-def.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of the condition at the most reasonable cost. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing based tests.</p>
              <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>More comprehensive genomic testing</bold> (when available) including exome sequencing, mitochondrial sequencing, and genome sequencing may be considered if single-gene testing (and/or use of a multi-gene panel that includes <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>) fails to confirm a diagnosis in an individual with features of <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome. Such testing may provide or suggest a diagnosis not previously considered (e.g., mutation of a different gene or genes that results in a similar clinical presentation). For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Encephalomyopathic Form with Methylmalonic Aciduria</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with Pathogenic Variants&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46/50&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/50&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="sucla2-def.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="sucla2-def" object-id="sucla2-def.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="sucla2-def.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sucla2-def.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="sucla2-def.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice-site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="sucla2-def.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.matilainen.2015.325">Matilainen et al [2015]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al [2016]</xref></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="sucla2-def.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>To date 50 individuals with <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.elpeleg.2005.1081">Elpeleg et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2007.862">Carrozzo et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.ostergaard.2007.853">Ostergaard et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.morava.2009.438">Morava et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.lamperti.2012.403">Lamperti et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.navarrosastre.2012.409">Navarro-Sastre et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.jaberi.2013.526">Jaberi et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.matilainen.2015.325">Matilainen et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.nogueira.2015.228">Nogueira et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>]. The clinical description here is based on what has been reported in these 50 individuals. The common clinical manifestations are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati">Table 2</xref> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <table-wrap id="sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 2. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Common Clinical Manifestations of <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Encephalomyopathic Form with Methylmalonic Aciduria</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manifestations</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;75%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Dystonia</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hypotonia</p></list-item><list-item><p>Psychomotor retardation</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sensorineural hearing impairment</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%-75%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Feeding difficulties</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25%-50%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Growth retardation / failure to thrive</p></list-item><list-item><p>Muscular atrophy</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;25%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.common_clinical_manifestati_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Choreoathetosis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Distinctive facial features including brachycephaly, epicanthus, upslanted palpebral fissures</p></list-item><list-item><p>Epilepsy</p></list-item><list-item><p>Gastroesophageal reflux disease</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hyperhidrosis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hypertonia</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hypoglycemia</p></list-item><list-item><p>Joint contractures</p></list-item><list-item><p>Kyphoscoliosis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ophthalmoplegia</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ptosis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Strabismus</p></list-item><list-item><p>Recurrent respiratory infections</p></list-item><list-item><p>Recurrent vomiting</p></list-item><list-item><p>Respiratory distress</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </table-wrap>
          <p>Affected children with <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome typically have an uncomplicated prenatal course and birth. Birth weight and birth length are typically within the normal range. The median age of onset of manifestations is two months, with a range from birth to six years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Neurocognitive.</bold> The vast majority of affected children present during infancy with hypotonia and psychomotor retardation. Dystonia and muscle atrophy also occur commonly. Other less frequent neurologic manifestations include hypertonia, choreoathetosis, ptosis, ophthalmoplegia, strabismus, and epilepsy (including infantile spasms and generalized convulsions). Brain MRI typically shows basal ganglia hyperintensities (70%), cerebral atrophy (70%), and leukoencephalopathy (15%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Hearing.</bold> Most affected children develop sensorineural hearing impairment; some benefit from a cochlear implant.</p>
          <p><bold>Growth.</bold> Postnatal growth retardation with low weight and length/height is a common feature of this condition. Feeding difficulties, often necessitating tube feeding, occur commonly, while recurrent vomiting and gastroesophageal reflux disease occasionally occur. The feeding difficulties, recurrent vomiting, and gastroesophageal reflux disease can lead or contribute to failure to thrive in affected infants.</p>
          <p><bold>Distinctive facial features</bold> including brachycephaly, epicanthus, and upslanted palpebral fissures, have been reported.</p>
          <p><bold>Respiratory.</bold> Recurrent respiratory infections occur occasionally. Respiratory distress due to muscle weakness, obstructive sleep apnea, tracheomalacia, and abnormal breathing has also been reported.</p>
          <p><bold>Skeletal.</bold> Progressive kyphoscoliosis has been reported occasionally and may require treatment. Joint contractures can develop in extremities secondary to decreased movement.</p>
          <p><bold>Other.</bold> Hyperhidrosis and neonatal hypoglycemia have occasionally been reported. Other rare manifestations:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Anemia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Acquired dislocation of hip and shoulder</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Irritability</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Sleep disturbance</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Life span</bold> is shortened, with median survival of 20 years in individuals with <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome. Approximately 30% of affected individuals reportedly died during childhood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.GenotypePhenotype_Correlation">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>Pathogenic missense variants can result in some residual enzyme activity, and hence a milder phenotype. Survival in affected individuals with biallelic pathogenic missense variants was significantly longer than in those with biallelic loss-of-function variants (deletions, frameshift and nonsense variants) (median survival age 21 years vs 15 years) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome is rare; the exact prevalence is unknown. To date, 50 individuals of different ethnic origins have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.elpeleg.2005.1081">Elpeleg et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2007.862">Carrozzo et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.ostergaard.2007.853">Ostergaard et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.morava.2009.438">Morava et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.lamperti.2012.403">Lamperti et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.navarrosastre.2012.409">Navarro-Sastre et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.jaberi.2013.526">Jaberi et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.matilainen.2015.325">Matilainen et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.nogueira.2015.228">Nogueira et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <p>A founder pathogenic variant in families of Faroese origin has been identified (<xref ref-type="table" rid="sucla2-def.T.selected_sucla2_pathogenic">Table 4</xref>); the disorder has a high incidence (1:1700) and a carrier frequency of 1:33 in the Faroe Islands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.ostergaard.2007.853">Ostergaard et al 2007</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.Genetically_Related_Allelic_D">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No other phenotypes are known to be associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome needs to be differentiated from other mtDNA depletion syndromes, a genetically and clinically heterogeneous group of autosomal recessive disorders that are characterized by a severe reduction in mtDNA content leading to impaired energy production in affected tissues and organs.</p>
        <p>Mitochondrial DNA depletion syndromes occur as a result of defects in mtDNA maintenance caused by pathogenic variants in nuclear genes that function in either mitochondrial nucleotide synthesis (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">TK2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">TYMP</italic>) or mtDNA replication (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TWNK</italic>).</p>
        <p>Mitochondrial DNA depletion syndromes are phenotypically classified into myopathic, encephalomyopathic, hepatocerebral, and neurogastrointestinal forms (<xref ref-type="table" rid="sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion">Table 3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.elhattab.2013.186">El-Hattab &#x00026; Scaglia 2013</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold>Myopathic forms</bold> present in infancy or early childhood with hypotonia, proximal muscle weakness, and feeding difficulty. Cognition is usually spared. Typically, there is rapid progression of muscle weakness with respiratory failure and death within a few years of onset.</p>
        <p><bold>Encephalomyopathic mtDNA depletion syndromes</bold> present in infancy with hypotonia and global developmental delay. Depending on the underlying defect, other features, including deafness, movement disorders, Leigh like syndrome, and renal disease, can be observed.</p>
        <p><bold>Hepatocerebral forms</bold> present with early-onset liver dysfunction and neurologic involvement, including developmental delay, abnormal eye movements, and peripheral neuropathy.</p>
        <p><bold>Neurogastrointestinal</bold>
<bold>forms,</bold> the prototype of which is mitochondrial neurogastrointestinal encephalopathy (MNGIE) disease, present in adolescence to early adulthood with progressive gastrointestinal dysmotility, cachexia, and peripheral neuropathy.</p>
        <p>The phenotype of <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome may be difficult to distinguish from <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion. <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome is characterized by psychomotor retardation, hypotonia, muscle atrophy, feeding difficulties, growth retardation, dystonia, hearing loss, lactic acidosis, elevated urine and plasma MMA, and mtDNA depletion. However, hepatopathy and cardiomyopathy occur in <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>-related mtDNA depletion only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">Carrozzo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
        <table-wrap id="sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 3. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndromes</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenotype&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th>
                <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome #, Type</th>
                <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_1" rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Hepatocerebral</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">DGUOK</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, hepatocerebral type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dguok-mtddepl" document-type="chapter">Deoxyguanosine Kinase Deficiency</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4A, Alpers type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="alpers" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic>-Related Disorders</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">MPV17</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6<italic toggle="yes">,</italic> hepatocerebral type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mpv17-mtdep" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">MPV17</italic>-Related Hepatocerebral Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">TWNK</italic><break/>(<italic toggle="yes">C10orf2)</italic></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7, hepatocerebral type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/271245">271245</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">TFAM</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, hepatocerebral type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/617156">617156</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_1" rowspan="6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Encephalo-</bold>
                  <break/>
                  <bold>myopathic</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, encephalomyopathic type w/methylmalonic aciduria</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Encephalomyopathic Form with Methylmalonic Aciduria</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">FBXL4</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13, encephalomyopathic type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fbxl4-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">FBXL4</italic>-Related Encephalomyopathic Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9, encephalomyopathic type with methylmalonic aciduria</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="suclg1-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome, encephalomyopathic form with methylmalonic aciduria</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8A, encephalomyopathic type w/renal tubulopathy</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rrm2b-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>-Related Mitochondrial Disease</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">OPA1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14, encephalocardiomyopathic type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/616896">616896</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ABAT</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encephalomyopathic type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/613163">613163</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Neurogastro-</bold>
                  <break/>
                  <bold>intestinal</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">TYMP</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, MNGIE type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mngie" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial Neurogastrointestinal Encephalopathy Disease</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4B, MNGIE type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="alpers" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic>-Related Disorders</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8B, MNGIE type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rrm2b-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">RRM2B</italic>-Related Mitochondrial Disease</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_1" rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Myopathic</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">TK2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, myopathic type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="tk2-mtddepl" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">TK2</italic>-Related Mitochondrial DNA Depletion Syndrome, Myopathic Form</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">AGK</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10, cardiomyopathic type (Sengers syndrome)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/212350">212350</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">MGME1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11, myopathic type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/615084">615084</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">SLC25A4</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12B, cardiomyopathic type</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.mitochondrial_dna_depletion_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/615418">615418</ext-link></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="sucla2-def.TF.3.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>Within each phenotypic category, mtDNA depletion syndromes are ordered by relative prevalence.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="sucla2-def.TF.3.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>See hyperlinked <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> or OMIM phenotype entry for more information.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Evaluations_Following_Initial">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome, the following evaluations need to be performed (if not already done as part of the initial diagnostic evaluation):</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Comprehensive neurologic examination and developmental/cognitive assessment. The following diagnostic modalities can be used to assess the degree of neurologic involvement:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Neuroimaging (preferably brain MRI) to establish the degree of central nervous system involvement</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>EMG to assess myopathy</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>EEG if seizures are suspected</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Audiology evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ophthalmologic examination</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Nutritional evaluation and swallowing assessment for feeding difficulties and growth failure</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical examination for the back and joints for kyphoscoliosis and joint contractures</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Management should involve a multidisciplinary team including specialists in neurology, audiology, child development, gastroenterology, nutrition, and clinical genetics. Treatments include the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical therapy to help maintain muscle function and prevent joint contractures</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Standard treatment with antiepileptic drugs for seizures</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Nutritional support by a dietitian and the use of a nasogastric tube or gastrostomy tube feedings to address feeding difficulties and failure to thrive</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Chest physiotherapy, aggressive antibiotic treatment of chest infections, and artificial ventilation (including assisted nasal ventilation or intubation and the use of a tracheostomy and ventilator) for respiratory insufficiency</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Bracing for scoliosis and kyphosis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Blepharoplasty for significant ptosis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hearing aids and/or cochlear implantation for sensorineural hearing loss</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>No clinical guidelines for surveillance are available. The following evaluations are suggested, with frequency varying according to the severity of the condition:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Routine developmental and neurologic assessment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Periodic nutritional and growth assessment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Periodic hearing evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Periodic ophthalmologic examination</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Routine physical examination of back and joints for kyphoscoliosis and joint contractures</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Ri">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sucla2-def.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Is">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome, encephalomyopathic form with methylmalonic aciduria is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected child are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> pathogenic variant).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Individuals with <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic>-related mtDNA depletion syndrome are not reported to reproduce.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier of a <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Carrier_Heterozygote_Detectio">
          <title>Carrier (Heterozygote) Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> pathogenic variants in the family.</p>
          <p>In populations with a high carrier rate and/or a high rate of consanguinity, the reproductive partner of the proband may be a carrier. Thus, the risk to offspring is most accurately determined after molecular genetic testing of the proband's reproductive partner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Is">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are carriers or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimpla">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesi">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic> encode subunits of succinyl CoA ligase (SUCL). SUCL is a mitochondrial tricarboxylic acid cycle enzyme that catalyzes the reversible conversion of succinyl-CoA and ADP or GDP to succinate and ATP or GTP. SUCL is composed of an alpha subunit, encoded by <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG1</italic> and a beta subunit, encoded by either <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">SUCLG2</italic>. The alpha subunit forms a heterodimer with either of its beta subunits, resulting in an ADP-forming SUCL and a GDP-forming SUCL, respectively. SUCL also forms a complex with the mitochondrial nucleoside diphosphate kinase, and the lack of this complex formation in SUCL deficiency has been suggested to disturb the kinase function, resulting in decreased mitochondrial nucleotide synthesis and therefore decreased mtDNA synthesis leading to mtDNA depletion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.kowluru.2002.160">Kowluru et al 2002</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> maps to 13q14.2, spans 58 kb, and contains 11 exons. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="sucla2-def" object-id="sucla2-def.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> See <xref ref-type="table" rid="sucla2-def.T.selected_sucla2_pathogenic">Table 4</xref>.</p>
          <table-wrap id="sucla2-def.T.selected_sucla2_pathogenic" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 4. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Selected <italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> Pathogenic Variants</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.selected_sucla2_pathogenic_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.selected_sucla2_pathogenic_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.selected_sucla2_pathogenic_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.selected_sucla2_pathogenic_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.534+1G&#x0003e;A&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.selected_sucla2_pathogenic_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_sucla2-def.T.selected_sucla2_pathogenic_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_003850.2">NM_003850.2</ext-link>
                    <break/>
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_003841.1">NP_003841.1</ext-link>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. GeneReviews staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on nomenclature: GeneReviews follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="sucla2-def.TF.4.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>Founder pathogenic variant in the Faroe Islands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2007.862">Carrozzo et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.ostergaard.2007.853">Ostergaard et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.morava.2009.438">Morava et al 2009</xref>]</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SUCLA2</italic> encodes the 463 amino acids of the &#x003b2; subunit of the ADP-forming SUCL.</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> The pathogenic variants lead to dysfunctional SUCL protein. As SUCL forms a complex with the mitochondrial nucleoside diphosphate kinase, the lack of this complex formation in SUCL deficiency can disturb the kinase function, resulting in decreased mitochondrial nucleotide synthesis and therefore decreased mtDNA synthesis leading to mtDNA depletion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="sucla2-def.REF.kowluru.2002.160">Kowluru et al 2002</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="sucla2-def.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2007.862">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrozzo</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dionisi-Vici</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steuerwald</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lucioli</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Deodato</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Di Giandomenico</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bertini</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Franke</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kluijtmans</surname>
                    <given-names>LA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meschini</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rizzo</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Piemonte</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rodenburg</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santer</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santorelli</surname>
                    <given-names>FM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Rooij</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vermunt-de Koning</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morava</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wevers</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>SUCLA2 mutations are associated with mild methylmalonic aciduria, Leigh-like encephalomyopathy, dystonia and deafness.</article-title>
                <source>Brain.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>130</volume>
                <fpage>862</fpage>
                <lpage>74</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17301081</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.carrozzo.2016.243">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrozzo</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Verrigni</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rasmussen</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Coo</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Amartino</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bianchi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Buhas</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mesli</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Naess</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Born</surname>
                    <given-names>AP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Woldseth</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prontera</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Batbayli</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ravn</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Joensen</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cordelli</surname>
                    <given-names>DM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santorelli</surname>
                    <given-names>FM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tulinius</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Darin</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Duno</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jouvencel</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burlina</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stangoni</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bertini</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Redonnet-Vernhet</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wibrand</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dionisi-Vici</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Uusimaa</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vieira</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Osorio</surname>
                    <given-names>AN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McFarland</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>RW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Holme</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ostergaard</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Succinate-CoA ligase deficiency due to mutations in SUCLA2 and SUCLG1: phenotype and genotype correlations in 71 patients.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>39</volume>
                <fpage>243</fpage>
                <lpage>52</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26475597</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.elhattab.2013.186">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>El-Hattab</surname>
                    <given-names>AW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA depletion syndromes: review and updates of genetic basis, manifestations, and therapeutic options.</article-title>
                <source>Neurotherapeutics.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>186</fpage>
                <lpage>98</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23385875</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.elpeleg.2005.1081">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miller</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hershkovitz</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bitner-Glindzicz</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bondi-Rubinstein</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rahman</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pagnamenta</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eshhar</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saada</surname>
                    <given-names>A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Deficiency of the ADP-forming succinyl-CoA synthase activity is associated with encephalomyopathy and mitochondrial DNA depletion.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>76</volume>
                <fpage>1081</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15877282</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.jaberi.2013.526">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jaberi</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chitsazian</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ali Shahidi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rohani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sina</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Safari</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malakouti Nejad</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houshmand</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Klotzle</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elahi</surname>
                    <given-names>E.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The novel mutation p.Asp251Asn in the &#x003b2;-subunit of succinate-CoA ligase causes encephalomyopathy and elevated succinylcarnitine.</article-title>
                <source>J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>58</volume>
                <fpage>526</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23759946</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.kowluru.2002.160">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kowluru</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tannous</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>HQ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Localization and characterization of the mitochondrial isoform of the nucleoside diphosphate kinase in the pancreatic beta cell: evidence for its complexation with mitochondrial succinyl-CoA synthetase.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Biochem Biophys.</source>
                <year>2002</year>
                <volume>398</volume>
                <fpage>160</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11831846</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.lamperti.2012.403">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lamperti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fang</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Invernizzi</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrara</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moroni</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeviani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ghezzi</surname>
                    <given-names>D.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A novel homozygous mutation in SUCLA2 gene identified by exome sequencing.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>107</volume>
                <fpage>403</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23010432</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.matilainen.2015.325">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matilainen</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Isohanni</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Euro</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>L&#x000f6;nnqvist</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pihko</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kivel&#x000e4;</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knuutila</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Suomalainen</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy and retinoblastoma explained by compound heterozygosity of SUCLA2 point mutation and 13q14 deletion.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>23</volume>
                <fpage>325</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24986829</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.morava.2009.438">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morava</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steuerwald</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrozzo</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kluijtmans</surname>
                    <given-names>LA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Joensen</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santer</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dionisi-Vici</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wevers</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Dystonia and deafness due to SUCLA2 defect; Clinical course and biochemical markers in 16 children.</article-title>
                <source>Mitochondrion.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>9</volume>
                <fpage>438</fpage>
                <lpage>42</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19666145</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.navarrosastre.2012.409">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Navarro-Sastre</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tort</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garcia-Villoria</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pons</surname>
                    <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nascimento</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Colomer</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Campistol</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoldi</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Gallardo</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Montoya</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Unceta</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martinez</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Briones</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ribes</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA depletion syndrome: new descriptions and the use of citrate synthase as a helpful tool to better characterise the patients.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>107</volume>
                <fpage>409</fpage>
                <lpage>15</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22980518</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.nogueira.2015.228">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nogueira</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meschini</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nesti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garcia</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Diogo</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valongo</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Costa</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Videira</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vilarinho</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santorelli</surname>
                    <given-names>FM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A novel SUCLA2 mutation in a Portuguese child associated with &#x0201c;mild&#x0201d; methylmalonic aciduria.</article-title>
                <source>J Child Neurol.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>30</volume>
                <fpage>228</fpage>
                <lpage>32</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24659738</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="sucla2-def.REF.ostergaard.2007.853">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ostergaard</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hansen</surname>
                    <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sorensen</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Duno</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vissing</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Larsen</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Faeroe</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thorgrimsson</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wibrand</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Christensen</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schwartz</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy with elevated methylmalonic acid is caused by SUCLA2 mutations.</article-title>
                <source>Brain.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>130</volume>
                <fpage>853</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17287286</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sucla2-def.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Author_History">
          <title>Author History</title>
          <p>Ayman W El-Hattab, MD, FAAP, FACMG (2016-present)Elsebet Ostergaard, MD, PhD; National University Hospital Rigshospitalet (2009-2016)Fernando Scaglia, MD, FAAP, FACMG (2016-present)</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="sucla2-def.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>18 May 2017 (aa) Revision: <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sucla2-def.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref> updated</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>30 June 2016 (ma) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>26 May 2009 (et) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>16 January 2009 (eo) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
