<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="tef-ov" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">tef-ov</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Esophageal Atresia/Tracheoesophageal Fistula Overview</title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Scott</surname>
            <given-names>Daryl A</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Department of Molecular and Human Genetics<break/>Baylor College of Medicine<break/>Houston, Texas</aff>
          <email>dscott@bcm.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="epp-ar" document-type="chapter">Erythropoietic Protoporphyria, Autosomal Recessive</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="ee" document-type="chapter">Ethylmalonic Encephalopathy</related-object>
      <abstract id="tef-ov.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Esophageal atresia (EA) is a developmental defect of the upper gastrointestinal tract in which the continuity between the upper and lower esophagus is lost. EA can occur with or without tracheoesophageal fistula (TEF), an abnormal connection between the trachea and the esophagus.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>EA may be detected prenatally and postnatally by imaging studies. EA/TEF can be isolated (not associated with other birth defects), syndromic (associated with other birth defects comprising a specific genetic diagnosis), or non-isolated (associated with other defects, but not a specific genetic diagnosis). Diagnosis of syndromic EA/TEF is based on clinical findings with or without molecular confirmation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>If an individual with EA/TEF has a specific genetic syndrome or an inherited or <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> chromosome abnormality, genetic counseling for that condition is indicated. Isolated EA/TEF is generally considered to be inherited in a multifactorial manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Initial postnatal intervention is aimed at minimizing the risk for aspiration pneumonia. Surgical repair consists of closure of the TEF and anastomosis of the esophageal segments. Other abnormalities are treated symptomatically.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="tef-ov.Definition">
        <title>Definition</title>
        <p>Esophageal atresia (EA) is a developmental defect of the upper gastrointestinal tract in which the continuity between the upper and lower esophagus is lost. EA can occur with or without tracheoesophageal fistula (TEF), an abnormal connection between the trachea and the esophagus.</p>
        <p>The following five EA/TEF configurations have been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.clark.1999.910">Clark 1999</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="tef-ov.F1">Figure 1</xref>):</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>EA with a distal TEF, the most common (84%)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Isolated EA (i.e., without TEF) (8%)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>H-type TEF with no EA (4%)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>EA with proximal and distal TEF (3%)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>EA with a proximal TEF (1%)</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Although EA/TEF can occur as an isolated finding, large epidemiologic studies suggest that up to 60% of individuals with EA/TEF have additional anomalies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.shawsmith.2006.545">Shaw-Smith 2006</xref>].</p>
        <p>EA/TEF can occur in the following settings:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Isolated.</bold> Not associated with other birth defects</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Syndromic.</bold> Associated with other birth defects leading to a specific genetic diagnosis</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Non-isolated.</bold> Associated with other defects, but not leading to a specific genetic diagnosis</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>VACTERL association.</bold> Non-random association of <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>ertebral, <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>nal, <italic toggle="yes">c</italic>ardiac, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>racheo<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>sophageal fistula, <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>enal, and <italic toggle="yes">l</italic>imb defects &#x02013; that occur together more often than would be expected by chance but are not known to be caused by a unifying genetic defect (i.e., a subgroup of non-isolated but not syndromic EA/TEF). Approximately 10% of infants with EA/TEF have at least two of the other defects included in VACTERL and can be said to have VACTERL association if a specific diagnosis cannot be reached [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.chittmittrapap.1989.364">Chittmittrapap et al 1989</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Clinical_Manifestations_of_EATEF">
          <title>Clinical Manifestations of EA/TEF</title>
          <p>Infants with congenital forms of EA/TEF usually present shortly after birth with copious oral secretions, coughing, gagging, cyanosis, vomiting, and/or respiratory distress.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Establishing_the_Diagnosis_of_EAT">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis of EA/TEF</title>
          <p>EA/TEF may be suspected prenatally if ultrasound examination reveals polyhydramnios, absence of a fluid-filled stomach, a small abdomen, lower-than-expected fetal weight, and a distended esophageal pouch [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.kronemer.2013">Kronemer &#x00026; Snyder-Warwick 2013</xref>]. Fetal MRI may be used to confirm the presence of EA/TEF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.langer.2001.804">Langer et al 2001</xref>].</p>
          <p>EA may be detected postnatally by:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Failure to pass a nasogastric (NG) tube and radiographs that demonstrate coiling of the NG tube in the pouch</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Tracheal compression and deviation on plain chest radiographs</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Absence of a gastric bubble on plain radiographs, which may suggest EA without a TEF or EA with a proximal TEF</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Three-dimensional CT scanning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.kronemer.2013">Kronemer &#x00026; Snyder-Warwick 2013</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: Administration of barium into the esophagus followed by chest radiographs can confirm the diagnosis but is seldom required.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Differential_Diagnosis_of_EATEF">
          <title>Differential Diagnosis of EA/TEF</title>
          <p><bold>Laryngotracheoesophageal cleft.</bold> Midline defect between the posterior larynx and trachea and the anterior wall of the esophagus. This entity can present prenatally with polyhydramnios and a small or absent stomach bubble and postnatally with aspiration after feeding. Laryngotracheoesophageal clefts are commonly associated with other anomalies including TEF.</p>
          <p><bold>Esophageal webs/rings.</bold> Circumferential partial obstruction of the esophageal lumen caused by membranous or diaphragmatic tissue that can be associated with TEF. Many cases are asymptomatic. Symptomatic esophageal webs/rings typically present with recurrent vomiting, dysphagia (solid&#x0003e;liquids), and sometimes aspiration. These symptoms tend to occur later in life than those caused by EA.</p>
          <p><bold>Esophageal stricture.</bold> A narrowing of the esophageal lumen caused by a variety of intrinsic and extrinsic disease processes. Congenital esophageal strictures typically present after the newborn period in a manner similar to that seen in esophageal webs/rings.</p>
          <p><bold>Esophageal diverticulum.</bold> A sack or pouch arising from the esophagus. Esophageal diverticula can be present at birth but most often arise and/or become symptomatic in adulthood, presenting with a history of dysphagia, chest pain, vomiting, and sometimes aspiration pneumonia.</p>
          <p><bold>Tubular esophageal</bold>
<bold>duplications</bold><bold>.</bold> Tubular channels that lie parallel to the esophagus and often connect to the main esophageal lumen or the stomach. These lesions are often asymptomatic and are most commonly identified serendipitously at autopsy. Symptoms typically result from inflammation and/or distention secondary to food entrapment and typically involve intermittent dysphagia.</p>
          <p><bold>Congenital short esophagus.</bold> An abnormally short esophagus accompanied by an intrathoracic location of part of the stomach. Symptoms are often present at birth and include gastroesophageal reflux and vomiting.</p>
          <p><bold>Tracheal agenesis/atresia.</bold> Lack of communication between the larynx and the alveoli of the lungs. This can be associated with other anomalies including TEF. Prenatal findings can include hyperechoic lungs, flattened diaphragms, oligo- or polyhydramnios, and large breathing movements. Postnatal symptoms include severe respiratory distress, cyanosis, absent cry, and failure to ventilate despite tracheal intubation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Prevalence_of_EATEF">
          <title>Prevalence of EA/TEF</title>
          <p>The incidence of EA/TEF is approximately 1:3500 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.shawsmith.2006.545">Shaw-Smith 2006</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="tef-ov.Causes_of_EATEF">
        <title>Causes of EA/TEF</title>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Environmental_Acquired_Causes">
          <title>Environmental (Acquired) Causes</title>
          <p>Although exposure to certain medications and infections during pregnancy have been proposed as possible risk factors for development of esophageal atresia/tracheoesophageal fistula (EA/TEF), no external factor has been consistently linked to the development of EA/TEF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.felix.2007.163">Felix et al 2007</xref>].</p>
          <p>Exposure to methimazole during pregnancy has been postulated to cause a specific embryopathy, which includes EA/TEF, but data supporting this association remain anecdotal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.clementi.1999.43">Clementi et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.di_gianantonio.2001.262">Di Gianantonio et al 2001</xref>].</p>
          <p>Maternal diabetes mellitus has been suggested as a possible risk factor for development of VACTERL association [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.castori.2008.169">Castori et al 2008</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Heritable_Causes">
          <title>Heritable Causes</title>
          <sec id="tef-ov.Chromosomal_Causes">
            <title>Chromosomal Causes</title>
            <p>Chromosome anomalies have been reported in approximately 6%-10% of individuals with EA/TEF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.felix.2007.163">Felix et al 2007</xref>].</p>
            <p>EA/TEF is found in the following aneuploidy syndromes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.felix.2007.163">Felix et al 2007</xref>]:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Trisomy 21 (~0.5%-1.0% of affected individuals)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Trisomy 18 (~25% of affected individuals)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Trisomy 13</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>(Mosaic) trisomy X</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>A review of published chromosomal deletions/duplications associated with EA/TEF reveals that they are distributed in a non-random pattern with several regions of the genome being recurrently affected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.felix.2007.163">Felix et al 2007</xref>].</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Recurrent duplications of 3p25-pter and 5q34-qter suggest that these regions may harbor one or more genes in which overexpression causes or predisposes to the development of EA/TEF.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Recurrent deletions of 2q37.2-qter, 4q35-qter, 5p15-pter, 6q13-q15, 14q32.3-qter, and 17q22-q23 suggest that haploinsufficiency or decreased expression of one or more genes in these regions may cause or predispose to the development of EA/TEF.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Recurrent deletions of 13q34-qter and 22q11 are also associated with EA/TEF but typically are associated with findings consistent with VACTERL association [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.walsh.2001.137">Walsh et al 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.felix.2007.163">Felix et al 2007</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="tef-ov.SingleGene_Causes">
            <title>Single-Gene Causes</title>
            <p>
              <bold>Autosomal dominant syndromic EA/TEF (</bold>
              <xref ref-type="table" rid="tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea">
                <bold>Table 1</bold>
              </xref>
              <bold>)</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Anophthalmia-esophageal-genital (AEG) syndrome is characterized by anophthalmia/microphthalmia, EA with our without TEF, and urogenital anomalies such as cryptorchidism, hypospadias, and micropenis. Heterozygous pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SOX2</italic> are causative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.williamson.2006.1413">Williamson et al 2006</xref>] (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="sox2" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">SOX2</italic>-Related Eye Disorders</related-object>).</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="charge" document-type="chapter"><bold>CHARGE syndrome</bold></related-object><bold>.</bold> Although EA/TEF is not a major criterion for diagnosis of CHARGE syndrome (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>oloboma of the eye, <italic toggle="yes">h</italic>eart anomaly; <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>tresia of the choanae, <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>etardation of mental and somatic development, <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>enital hypoplasia, and <italic toggle="yes">e</italic>ar abnormalities and/or hearing loss), it is present in approximately 15%-20% of infants with this disorder. Approximately 60% of individuals with CHARGE syndrome have a heterozygous pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">CHD7</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.vissers.2004.955">Vissers et al 2004</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="feingold" document-type="chapter"><bold>Feingold syndrome</bold></related-object> is characterized by variable combinations of esophageal and duodenal atresias, microcephaly, learning disabilities, syndactyly, and cardiac defects. Heterozygous pathogenic variants and whole-gene deletions of <italic toggle="yes">MYCN</italic> are causative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.van_bokhoven.2005.465">van Bokhoven et al 2005</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="phs" document-type="chapter"><bold>Pallister-Hall syndrome</bold></related-object> is characterized by hypothalamic hamartoma, central and postaxial polydactyly, imperforate anus, renal anomalies, bifid epiglottis, and tracheal clefts. Heterozygous pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">GLI3</italic> cause Pallister-Hall syndrome. A <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> heterozygous sequence variant in the N-terminal region of <italic toggle="yes">GLI3</italic> (c.332T&#x0003e;C, p.Met111Thr) has been described in one individual with esophageal atresia and hemivertebrae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.yang.2014">Yang et al 2014</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <table-wrap id="tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 1. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Autosomal Dominant Syndromic EA/TEF</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndrome</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical Findings</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_4" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selected OMIM Links</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="sox2" document-type="chapter">Anophthalmia-esophageal-genital syndrome</related-object>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">SOX2</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Anophthalmia/microphthalmia</p></list-item><list-item><p>EA/TEF</p></list-item><list-item><p>Urogenital anomalies</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/184429">184429</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="charge" document-type="chapter">CHARGE syndrome</related-object>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">CHD7</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Coloboma of the eye</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cardiac anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Choanal atresia</p></list-item><list-item><p>Intellectual disability</p></list-item><list-item><p>Growth retardation</p></list-item><list-item><p>Genital anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ear anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hearing loss</p></list-item><list-item><p>EA/TEF</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/608892">608892</ext-link>
                      <break/>
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/214800">214800</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="feingold" document-type="chapter">Feingold syndrome</related-object>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">MYCN</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Esophageal and duodenal atresias</p></list-item><list-item><p>Microcephaly</p></list-item><list-item><p>Learning disabilities</p></list-item><list-item><p>Syndactyly</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cardiac defects</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/164840">164840</ext-link>
                      <break/>
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/164280">164280</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="phs" document-type="chapter">Pallister-Hall syndrome</related-object>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">GLI3</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Hypothalamic hamartoma</p></list-item><list-item><p>Central and postaxial polydactyly</p></list-item><list-item><p>Imperforate anus</p></list-item><list-item><p>Renal anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Bifid epiglottis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Tracheal clefts</p></list-item><list-item><p>EA/TEF (rare)</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_dominant_syndromic_ea_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/165240">165240</ext-link>
                      <break/>
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/146510">146510</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>
              <bold>Autosomal recessive syndromic EA/TEF (</bold>
              <xref ref-type="table" rid="tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy">
                <bold>Table 2</bold>
              </xref>
              <bold>)</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fa" document-type="chapter"><bold>Fanconi anemia</bold></related-object> is characterized by bone marrow failure, an increased risk for malignancies, and a wide variety of physical abnormalities that can include short stature, abnormal skin pigmentation, radial ray defects, eye anomalies, renal anomalies, cardiac defects, abnormal ears, central nervous system anomalies, hearing loss, and developmental delay. Gastrointestinal anomalies are common and can include EA/TEF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.berrebi.2006.e11">Berrebi et al 2006</xref>]. Fifteen of the 16 Fanconi anemia complementation groups are associated with autosomal recessive inheritance. The exception is complementation group B, which has X-linked inheritance. Autosomal recessive EA/TEF has been described in individuals with biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">FANCA,</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">FANCC,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ERCC4</italic>.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <table-wrap id="tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 2. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Autosomal Recessive Forms of Syndromic EA/TEF</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndrome</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genes</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical Findings</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selected OMIM Links</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_1" rowspan="16" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                      <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fa" document-type="chapter">Fanconi anemia</related-object>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCA</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_3" rowspan="16" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Bone marrow failure</p></list-item><list-item><p>Malignancies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Short stature</p></list-item><list-item><p>Abnormal skin pigmentation</p></list-item><list-item><p>Radial ray defects</p></list-item><list-item><p>Eye anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Renal anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cardiac defects</p></list-item><list-item><p>Abnormal ears</p></list-item><list-item><p>Central nervous system anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hearing loss</p></list-item><list-item><p>Developmental delay</p></list-item><list-item><p>Gastrointestinal anomalies including EA/TEF</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/227650">227650</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCB</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/300514">300514</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCC</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/227645">227645</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">BRCA2</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/605724">605724</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCD2</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/227646">227646</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCE</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/600901">600901</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCF</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/603467">603467</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCG</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/614082">614082</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCI</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/609053">609053</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">BRIP1</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/609054">609054</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCL</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/614083">614083</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCM</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/614087">614087</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">PALB2</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/610832">610832</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">RAD51C</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/613390">613390</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">SLX4</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/613951">613951</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">ERCC4</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.autosomal_recessive_forms_of_sy_1_1_1_4" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/615272">615272</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>
              <bold>X-linked syndromic EA/TEF (</bold>
              <xref ref-type="table" rid="tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate">
                <bold>Table 3</bold>
              </xref>
              <bold>)</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="opitz" document-type="chapter"><bold>X-linked Opitz G/BBB syndrome</bold></related-object> is characterized by midline abnormalities including cleft lip, heart defects, hypospadias, agenesis of the corpus callosum, and laryngeal clefts. Rare individuals exhibit EA/TEF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.de_falco.2003.222">De Falco et al 2003</xref>]. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">MID1</italic> are causative of X-linked Opitz G/BBB syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.quaderi.1997.285">Quaderi et al 1997</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>VACTERL association with hydrocephalus (VACTERL-H)</bold> is characterized by vertebral anomalies, anal atresia, cardiac malformations, TEF, renal anomalies, limb anomalies, and hydrocephalus. Pathogenic variants in the <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fa" document-type="chapter">Fanconi anemia</related-object> complementation group B gene, <italic toggle="yes">FANCB,</italic> have been identified in males with this phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.holden.2006.750">Holden et al 2006</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <table-wrap id="tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 3. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>X-Linked Forms of Syndromic EA/TEF</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndrome</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical Findings</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selected OMIM Links</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="opitz" document-type="chapter">X-linked Opitz G/BBB syndrome</related-object>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">MID1</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Midline abnormalities including:</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cleft lip</p></list-item><list-item><p>Laryngeal cleft</p></list-item><list-item><p>Heart defects</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hypospadias</p></list-item><list-item><p>Agenesis of the corpus callosum</p></list-item><list-item><p>EA/TEF (rare)</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/300552">300552</ext-link>
                      <break/>
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/300000">300000</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VACTERL-H</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">FANCB</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Vertebral anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Anal atresia</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cardiac malformations</p></list-item><list-item><p>Tracheoesophageal fistula</p></list-item><list-item><p>Renal anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Limb anomalies</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hydrocephalus</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_tef-ov.T.xlinked_forms_of_syndromic_eate_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/300515">300515</ext-link>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="tef-ov.Multifactorial_Inheritance">
            <title>Multifactorial Inheritance</title>
            <p>The inheritance pattern of EA/TEF for which a specific genetic diagnosis cannot be made is generally considered to be multifactorial.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Unknown_Cause">
          <title>Unknown Cause</title>
          <p>It is not known in what proportion of individuals with EA/TEF the cause is unknown.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="tef-ov.Evaluation_Strategy">
        <title>Evaluation Strategy</title>
        <p>Once the diagnosis of esophageal atresia/tracheoesophageal fistula (EA/TEF) has been established in an individual, the following evaluations may help determine if the EA/TEF is isolated, syndromic, or non-isolated. These evaluations may also provide information that can be used in discussions of prognosis and recurrence risk counseling.</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Family history.</bold> A three-generation family history to determine the inheritance pattern in the family and to look for findings in other relatives that could suggest a specific etiology and/or mode of inheritance</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Physical examination</bold> to look for additional anomalies including limb defects and anal anomalies</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Imaging studies</bold> to identify additional anomalies of the skeleton, heart, and/or kidneys</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <bold>Testing</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Molecular genetic testing.</bold> When a genetic syndrome is suspected, the gene(s) responsible can be tested individually or as part of a multi-gene panel (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="tef-ov.Causes_of_EATEF">Causes</xref>). Alternatively, exome or genome approaches can be used to identify deleterious sequence changes in genes associated with EA/TEF.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Array-based copy number detection assays and/or a chromosome analysis.</bold> These tests may be ordered if a specific chromosomal disorder is suspected or as a screening test for chromosomal anomalies associated with EA/TEF.</p>
                <p>Note: Because array-based copy number detection assays are able to detect small chromosomal deletions and duplications that are undetectable using chromosome analysis, an array-based copy number detection assay should typically be ordered unless a balanced chromosomal rearrangement or aneuploidy is suspected.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="tef-ov.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Esophageal atresia/tracheoesophageal fistula (EA/TEF) can occur as an isolated finding, as part of a genetic syndrome, or as part of a non-isolated (but not syndromic) set of findings.</p>
          <p>If an affected individual is found to have an inherited or <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> chromosome abnormality, or a specific syndrome or association with EA/TEF, genetic counseling for that condition is indicated.</p>
          <p>Nonsyndromic EA/TEF is generally considered to be inherited in a multifactorial manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Empiric_Risks_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Empiric Risks to Family Members &#x02013; TEF</title>
          <p>Most individuals with EA/TEF represent simplex cases (i.e., the only affected member of the family). A small subset of families are multiplex (i.e., two or more relatives have EA/TEF).</p>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> For individuals with isolated EA/TEF without a clear etiology, recurrence risk for sibs is likely to be approximately 1% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.shawsmith.2006.545">Shaw-Smith 2006</xref>]. The twin concordance rate for EA/TEF is also low (~2.5%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.robert.1993.405">Robert et al 1993</xref>]. Note: No data for recurrence risks for isolated vs non-isolated EA/TEF are available.</p>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> In individuals with EA/TEF without a clear etiology, recurrence risk to offspring for EA/TEF and/or malformations in the VACTERL association is likely to be between 2% and 4% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.shawsmith.2006.545">Shaw-Smith 2006</xref>]. Note: Since these estimates were generated by studying the offspring of individuals with both isolated and non-isolated EA/TEF, the risk to offspring in isolated cases may be lower.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Empiric_Risks_to_Family_Members_1">
          <title>Empiric Risks to Family Members &#x02013; Non-Isolated EA/TEF</title>
          <p>Recurrence risk counseling for individuals with non-isolated EA/TEF &#x02013; in whom additional anomalies have been identified and for whom a specific genetic disorder is not recognized &#x02013; is problematic.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Some cases of non-isolated EA/TEF are probably caused by <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> autosomal dominant mutations, and therefore, pose a low recurrence risk to the sibs of the proband.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Some are probably unrecognized or private autosomal recessive conditions.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Some may be multifactorial disorders with a low recurrence risk.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Non-genetic causes are possible as well, including stochastic events, epigenetic modifications, or teratogenic/environmental exposures.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Thus, counseling in this setting should be as for other multiple congenital anomaly disorders of unknown etiology. Specifically, the estimated recurrence risk to sibs is "low&#x0201d;; however, this estimate represents an averaging of a negligible, or very low, recurrence risk in the majority of families together with a higher recurrence risk (&#x02264;25%-50%) in the minority of families.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Prenatal_Testing">
          <title>Prenatal Testing</title>
          <p>If the pathogenic variant(s) have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk may be available from a clinical laboratory that offers either testing of this gene or custom prenatal testing.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Ultrasound examination</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Prenatal ultrasound examination of a fetus affected by EA/TEF may reveal an absent or small fetal stomach bubble in combination with maternal polyhydramnios [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.houben.2008.667">Houben &#x00026; Curry 2008</xref>]. The diagnostic accuracy is increased if an anechoic area is present in the middle of the fetal neck because it can help differentiate EA from diseases with possible swallowing impairments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.kronemer.2013">Kronemer &#x00026; Snyder-Warwick 2013</xref>]. In one study of 87 fetuses with a small (n = 53) or absent stomach bubble (n = 34), the positive predictive value of an absent stomach bubble and polyhydramnios was 56% and the sensitivity of prenatal sonography in the diagnosis of EA was 42% based on the outcome of all fetuses scanned during the same period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.stringer.1995.1258">Stringer et al 1995</xref>]. The positive predictive value is likely to be even lower among fetuses with multiple anomalies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.choudhry.2007.608">Choudhry et al 2007</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The presence of a dilated blind-ending esophageal pouch on a sonogram is suggestive of EA; it is the most reliable sonographic sign indicative of EA and has been seen in cases with and without TEF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.kronemer.2013">Kronemer &#x00026; Snyder-Warwick 2013</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Polyhydramnios can be seen in a wide variety of disorders and alone is a poor indicator of EA: only one in 12 fetuses with polyhydramnios has EA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.kronemer.2013">Kronemer &#x00026; Snyder-Warwick 2013</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When EA/TEF is suspected on routine prenatal ultrasound examination:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>A high-resolution ultrasound examination is indicated;</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Fetal MRI should be considered to help confirm the diagnosis of EA/TEF and to evaluate for additional structural anomalies;</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Chromosome analysis, an array-based copy number detection assay, and/or molecular testing using fetal cells/DNA should be considered.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>All fetuses suspected of having EA/TEF should be evaluated for the presence of additional major malformations that could be part of an underlying syndrome because such malformations and/or the underlying diagnosis may significantly affect the prognosis. Involvement of a medical geneticist in the evaluation of these families can be helpful.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="tef-ov.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="tef-ov.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Dia">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>After an individual has been diagnosed with esophageal atresia/tracheoesophageal fistula (EA/TEF), the following evaluations should be considered as a means of identifying associated anomalies:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>X-ray evaluation for vertebral anomalies</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Echocardiogram</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Renal ultrasound examination</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Initial postnatal intervention, aimed at minimizing the risk of aspiration pneumonia, typically includes the elimination of oral feeds, placement of a suction catheter to allow continuous drainage of secretions, and elevation of the head of the bed to minimize reflux [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.clark.1999.910">Clark 1999</xref>]. Intravenous (IV) glucose and fluids should be provided; supplemental oxygen should be administered as needed. When intubation cannot be avoided, a possible complication is the collection of air in the stomach, which in severe cases can only be removed by gastrostomy.</p>
          <p>Surgical repair consists of closure of the TEF and anastomosis of the esophageal segments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.sharma.2012">Sharma &#x00026; Duerksen 2012</xref>]. Surgical repair may need to be delayed in infants with low birth weight, pneumonia, or other major congenital anomalies. When surgical repair is delayed, infants may be treated with parenteral nutrition, gastrostomy tube placement, and upper pouch suctioning until they become surgical candidates.</p>
          <p>The most common complications after surgical repair include leakage at the site of the anastomosis, recurrent fistula, structure formation, and gastroesophageal reflux [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.clark.1999.910">Clark 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.sharma.2012">Sharma &#x00026; Duerksen 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="tef-ov.REF.kronemer.2013">Kronemer &#x00026; Snyder-Warwick 2013</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="tef-ov.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="tef-ov.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="tef-ov.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.berrebi.2006.e11">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berrebi</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lebras</surname>
                    <given-names>MN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Belarbi</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Couturier</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fattet</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Faye</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peuchmaur</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Lagausie</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Bilateral adrenal neuroblastoma and nephroblastoma occurring synchronously in a child with Fanconi's anemia and VACTERL syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr Surg</source>
                <volume>41</volume>
                <fpage>e11</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16410081</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.castori.2008.169">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castori</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rinaldi</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Capocaccia</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roggini</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grammatico</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>VACTERL association and maternal diabetes: a possible causal relationship?</article-title>
                <source>Birth Defects Res A Clin Mol Teratol</source>
                <volume>82</volume>
                <fpage>169</fpage>
                <lpage>72</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18181216</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.chittmittrapap.1989.364">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chittmittrapap</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spitz</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kiely</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brereton</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1989</year>
                <article-title>Oesophageal atresia and associated anomalies.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
                <volume>64</volume>
                <fpage>364</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2705799</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.choudhry.2007.608">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Choudhry</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boyd</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chamberlain</surname>
                    <given-names>PF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lakhoo</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Prenatal diagnosis of tracheo-oesophageal fistula and oesophageal atresia.</article-title>
                <source>Prenat Diagn</source>
                <volume>27</volume>
                <fpage>608</fpage>
                <lpage>10</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17457956</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.clark.1999.910">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clark</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Esophageal atresia and tracheoesophageal fistula.</article-title>
                <source>Am Fam Physician</source>
                <volume>59</volume>
                <fpage>910</fpage>
                <lpage>6, 919-20</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10068713</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.clementi.1999.43">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clementi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Di Gianantonio</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pelo</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mammi</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Basile</surname>
                    <given-names>RT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tenconi</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Methimazole embryopathy: delineation of the phenotype.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>83</volume>
                <fpage>43</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10076883</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.de_falco.2003.222">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Falco</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cainarca</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Andolfi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ferrentino</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rodriguez Criado</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rittinger</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dennis</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Odent</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rastogi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liebelt</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chitayat</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Winter</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jawanda</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ballabio</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Franco</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meroni</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>X-linked Opitz syndrome: novel mutations in the MID1 gene and redefinition of the clinical spectrum.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A</source>
                <volume>120A</volume>
                <fpage>222</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12833403</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.di_gianantonio.2001.262">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Di Gianantonio</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mastroiacovo</surname>
                    <given-names>PP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cournot</surname>
                    <given-names>MP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Benedicenti</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reuvers</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Occupati</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robert</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bellemin</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Addis</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arnon</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clementi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>Adverse effects of prenatal methimazole exposure.</article-title>
                <source>Teratology</source>
                <volume>64</volume>
                <fpage>262</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11745832</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.felix.2007.163">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Felix</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tibboel</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Klein</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Chromosomal anomalies in the aetiology of oesophageal atresia and tracheo-oesophageal fistula.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>50</volume>
                <fpage>163</fpage>
                <lpage>75</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17336605</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.houben.2008.667">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houben</surname>
                    <given-names>CH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Curry</surname>
                    <given-names>JI</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Current status of prenatal diagnosis, operative management and outcome of esophageal atresia/tracheo-esophageal fistula.</article-title>
                <source>Prenat Diagn</source>
                <volume>28</volume>
                <fpage>667</fpage>
                <lpage>75</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18302317</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.holden.2006.750">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Holden</surname>
                    <given-names>ST</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cox</surname>
                    <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kesterton</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thomas</surname>
                    <given-names>NS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carr</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Woods</surname>
                    <given-names>CG</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Fanconi anaemia complementation group B presenting as X linked VACTERL with hydrocephalus syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>43</volume>
                <fpage>750</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16679491</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.kronemer.2013">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="web">Kronemer KA, Snyder-Warwick A. Esophageal atresia/tracheoesophageal fistula. Medscape. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/414368-overview#showall">online</ext-link>. 2013. Accessed 2-22-17</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.langer.2001.804">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Langer</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hussain</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khan</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Minkes</surname>
                    <given-names>RK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gray</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Siegel</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ryan</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>Prenatal diagnosis of esophageal atresia using sonography and magnetic resonance imaging.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr Surg</source>
                <volume>36</volume>
                <fpage>804</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11329594</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.quaderi.1997.285">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Quaderi</surname>
                    <given-names>NA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schweiger</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gaudenz</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Franco</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rugarli</surname>
                    <given-names>EI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berger</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feldman</surname>
                    <given-names>GJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Volta</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Andolfi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gilgenkrantz</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marion</surname>
                    <given-names>RW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hennekam</surname>
                    <given-names>RC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Opitz</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Muenke</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ropers</surname>
                    <given-names>HH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ballabio</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>Opitz G/BBB syndrome, a defect of midline development, is due to mutations in a new RING finger gene on Xp22.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>17</volume>
                <fpage>285</fpage>
                <lpage>91</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9354791</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.robert.1993.405">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robert</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mutchinick</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mastroiacovo</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knudsen</surname>
                    <given-names>LB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Daltveit</surname>
                    <given-names>AK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castilla</surname>
                    <given-names>EE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lancaster</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>K&#x000e4;ll&#x000e9;n</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cocchi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1993</year>
                <article-title>An international collaborative study of the epidemiology of esophageal atresia or stenosis.</article-title>
                <source>Reprod Toxicol</source>
                <volume>7</volume>
                <fpage>405</fpage>
                <lpage>21</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8274816</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.sharma.2012">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="web">Sharma S, Duerksen D. Tracheoesophageal fistula. Medscape. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/186735-overview#showall">online</ext-link>. 2012. Accessed 2-22-17.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.shawsmith.2006.545">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shaw-Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Oesophageal atresia, tracheo-oesophageal fistula, and the VACTERL association: review of genetics and epidemiology.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>43</volume>
                <fpage>545</fpage>
                <lpage>54</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16299066</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.stringer.1995.1258">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stringer</surname>
                    <given-names>MD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McKenna</surname>
                    <given-names>KM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goldstein</surname>
                    <given-names>RB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Filly</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adzick</surname>
                    <given-names>NS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harrison</surname>
                    <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1995</year>
                <article-title>Prenatal diagnosis of esophageal atresia.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr Surg</source>
                <volume>30</volume>
                <fpage>1258</fpage>
                <lpage>63</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8523220</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.van_bokhoven.2005.465">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Bokhoven</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celli</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Reeuwijk</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rinne</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glaudemans</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Beusekom</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rieu</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Newbury-Ecob</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chiang</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brunner</surname>
                    <given-names>HG</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>MYCN haploinsufficiency is associated with reduced brain size and intestinal atresias in Feingold syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>37</volume>
                <fpage>465</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15821734</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.vissers.2004.955">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vissers</surname>
                    <given-names>LE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Ravenswaaij</surname>
                    <given-names>CM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Admiraal</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hurst</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Vries</surname>
                    <given-names>BB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Janssen</surname>
                    <given-names>IM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van der Vliet</surname>
                    <given-names>WA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huys</surname>
                    <given-names>EH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Jong</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamel</surname>
                    <given-names>BC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schoenmakers</surname>
                    <given-names>EF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brunner</surname>
                    <given-names>HG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Veltman</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Kessel</surname>
                    <given-names>AG</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in a new member of the chromodomain gene family cause CHARGE syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>36</volume>
                <fpage>955</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15300250</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.walsh.2001.137">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Walsh</surname>
                    <given-names>LE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vance</surname>
                    <given-names>GH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Weaver</surname>
                    <given-names>DD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>Distal 13q Deletion Syndrome and the VACTERL association: case report, literature review, and possible implications.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>98</volume>
                <fpage>137</fpage>
                <lpage>44</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11223849</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.williamson.2006.1413">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Williamson</surname>
                    <given-names>KA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hever</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rainger</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rogers</surname>
                    <given-names>RC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Magee</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fiedler</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Keng</surname>
                    <given-names>WT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sharkey</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McGill</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hill</surname>
                    <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schneider</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Messina</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Turnpenny</surname>
                    <given-names>PD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fantes</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Heyningen</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>FitzPatrick</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in SOX2 cause anophthalmia-esophageal-genital (AEG) syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                <volume>15</volume>
                <fpage>1413</fpage>
                <lpage>22</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16543359</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="tef-ov.REF.yang.2014">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang L, Shen C, Mei M, Zhan G, Zhao Y, Wang H, Huang G, Qiu Z, Lu W, Zhou W. De novo GLI3 mutation in esophageal atresia: Reproducing the phenotypic spectrum of Gli3 defects in murine models. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2014;1842:1755-61.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="tef-ov.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>Author&#x02019;s <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bcm.edu/departments/molecular-and-human-genetics/?pmid=11041">Web page</ext-link></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="tef-ov.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>12 June 2014 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>12 March 2009 (me) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>14 October 2008 (das) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="tef-ov.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>EA/TEF configurations and their frequencies</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tef-ov-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
