<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="vodi" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">vodi</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Hepatic Veno-Occlusive Disease with Immunodeficiency</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: VODI</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Roscioli</surname>
            <given-names>Tony</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MBBS, FRACP, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Clinical Geneticist, School of Women&#x02019;s and Children&#x02019;s Health<break/>University of New South Wales<break/>Sydney Children&#x02019;s Hospital<break/>Sydney, Australia</aff>
          <email>t.roscioli@garvan.org.au</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ziegler</surname>
            <given-names>John B</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MBBS, FRACP, MD</degrees>
          <aff>Clinical Immunologist, Sydney Children's Hospital<break/>Sydney, Australia</aff>
          <email>j.ziegler@unsw.edu.au</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Buckley</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MBChB, PhD, FRCPA, FHGSA</degrees>
          <aff>Director, SEALS Molecular and Cytogenetics Laboratory<break/>Prince of Wales Hospital<break/>Sydney, Australia</aff>
          <email>michael.buckley@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wong</surname>
            <given-names>Melanie</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MBBS, FRACP, FRCPA, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Clinical Immunologist and Immunopathologist, Children's Hospital Westmead<break/>Sydney, Australia</aff>
          <email>melanie.wong@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="hemo-b" document-type="chapter">Hemophilia B</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="hep" document-type="chapter">Hepatoerythropoietic Porphyria</related-object>
      <abstract id="vodi.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Hepatic veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency (VODI) is characterized by: (1) primary immunodeficiency; and (2) terminal hepatic lobular vascular occlusion and hepatic fibrosis manifest as hepatomegaly and/or hepatic failure. Onset is usually before age six months. The immunodeficiency comprises severe hypogammaglobulinemia, clinical evidence of T-cell immunodeficiency with normal numbers of circulating T cells, absent lymph node germinal centers, and absent tissue plasma cells. Bacterial and opportunistic infections including <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> infection, mucocutaneous candidiasis, and enteroviral or cytomegalovirus infections occur. In the past the prognosis for affected individuals was poor, with 100% mortality in the first year of life if unrecognized and untreated with intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) and <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> prophylaxis. However, with early recognition and treatment there is a marked improvement in prognosis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of VODI is established in a proband with the following clinical diagnostic criteria:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Clinical evidence of primary immunodeficiency</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hepatomegaly or evidence of hepatic failure in a proband or a first-degree relative</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Onset usually before age six months</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Family history consistent with autosomal recessive inheritance</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> on molecular genetic testing establishes the diagnosis if clinical features are inconclusive.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> IVIG and <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> prophylaxis as soon as the diagnosis of VODI is established; appropriate, prompt treatment of infections; consider hepatic transplantation, although rate of complications may be high; bone marrow transplantation may be efficacious with appropriate conditioning therapy.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of primary manifestations:</italic> IVIG and <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> prophylaxis.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Regular monitoring of hepatic function, platelet count, and hemoglobin level; routine monitoring of serum and urine electrolytes as the syndrome of inappropriate anti-diuretic hormone (SIADH) may occur; measurement of immunoglobulin concentrations prior to IVIG infusions; broncho-alveolar lavage to diagnose <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> infection; viral cultures or lung function studies as needed; cerebrospinal imaging to diagnose leukodystrophy when clinically indicated.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Agents known to predispose to hepatic veno-occlusive disease (hVOD) including cyclophosphamide and senecio alkaloids/bush teas.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> If both pathogenic variants in the family are known, molecular genetic testing of sibs of a proband who are younger than age 12 months to allow for early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>VODI is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. The parents of an affected child are obligate heterozygotes (carriers) and therefore carry one pathogenic variant. Heterozygotes are asymptomatic. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Carrier testing for at-risk relatives and prenatal diagnosis for pregnancies at increased risk are possible if both pathogenic variants in a family are known.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="vodi.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="vodi.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Hepatic veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency (VODI) <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Clinical diagnostic criteria</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Clinical evidence of immunodeficiency with bacterial and opportunistic infections including <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> infection, mucocutaneous candidiasis, and enteroviral or cytomegalovirus infections</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hepatomegaly or evidence of hepatic failure, not explained by other factors, in the affected individual or a first degree relative (hepatic veno-occlusive disease is usually present and pathognomonic but may not be found, or may have resolved)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Onset usually before age six months</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Family history consistent with autosomal recessive inheritance</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Laboratory features</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Low serum concentrations of IgA, IgM, and IgG</p>
              <p>Note: Immunoglobulin levels are age specific and laboratory specific and thus should be compared against appropriate local reference ranges.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Normal lymphocyte numbers and CD4 and CD8 percentages</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Normal lymphocyte proliferative responses to mitogens</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Low intracellular cytokine production</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Radiographic features</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Hepatic ultrasonography. Features consistent with hepatic veno-occlusive disease (hVOD) may include hepatosplenomegaly, gallbladder wall thickening, increased portal vein diameter, reduced hepatic vein diameter, ascites, and re-canalization of the <italic toggle="yes">ligamentum teres</italic>.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Doppler ultrasound examination. Features consistent with hVOD may include reduced portal venous flow, flow in the para-umbilical vein, and increased resistance in the hepatic artery.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Histopathologic features</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>hVOD (also known as sinusoidal obstruction syndrome) may include fibrous concentric narrowing of zone 3 terminal hepatic venules, centrilobular hepatocyte necrosis, and sinusoidal congestion (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vodi.F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Note: If hepatic biopsy is contraindicated, hepatic ultrasonography and Doppler ultrasonography may provide supportive evidence of hVOD.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of VODI <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with the above clinical diagnostic criteria. Identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> on molecular genetic testing establishes the diagnosis if clinical features are inconclusive (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold>, use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>, and <bold>more comprehensive genomic testing</bold>.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> is performed first and followed by gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis if only one or no pathogenic variant is found.</p>
              <p>Targeted analysis for the <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss">c.642delC</xref> pathogenic variants can be performed first in individuals of Lebanese ancestry.</p>
              <p>Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> may be performed in a tiered approach beginning with exons 2, 4, 5 and 8 (reference sequence: LRG_109). Sequencing of the entire coding region of 19 exons and an alternatively spliced exon 15 in the Sp110c isoform is performed if neither or only one pathogenic variant is identified in exons 2, 4, 5 and 8.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="vodi.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of the condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting secondary findings. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing based tests.</p>
              <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>More comprehensive genomic testing</bold> (when available) including exome sequencing and genome sequencing may be considered if single-gene testing (and/or use of a multi-gene panel that includes <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic>) fails to confirm a diagnosis in an individual with features of VODI. Such testing may provide or suggest a diagnosis not previously considered (e.g., mutation of a different gene or genes that results in a similar clinical presentation). For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Hepatic Veno-Occlusive Disease with Immunodeficiency</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with Pathogenic Variants&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/13 (100%)&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="vodi" object-id="vodi.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See Molecular Genetics for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>All pathogenic variants identified to date are in exons 2, 4, 5 and 8 with the most common being the c.642delC found in the Lebanese population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.ruga.2006">Ruga et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.wang.2012.102">Wang et al 2012</xref>].</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used can include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.1.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>No data on detection rate of gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis are available</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="vodi.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="vodi.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Hepatic veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency (VODI) is a primary immunodeficiency associated with terminal hepatic lobular vascular occlusion and hepatic lobule zone 3 fibrosis. All children in the cohort from Sydney, Australia presented prior to age six months, the majority with sequelae of the immunodeficiency either alone or concurrently with features of hepatic veno-occlusive disease (hVOD) (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features">Table 2</xref>).</p>
          <p><bold>Immunodeficiency</bold> is characterized by severe hypogammaglobulinemia, clinical evidence of T-cell immunodeficiency with normal numbers of circulating T and B cells, absent lymph node germinal centers, and absent tissue plasma cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al 2006</xref>]. Bacterial and opportunistic infections including <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> infection, mucocutaneous candidiasis, and enteroviral or cytomegalovirus infections occur.</p>
          <p><bold>Hepatic veno-occlusive disease (hVOD).</bold> Ninety percent of the children with VODI present <italic toggle="yes">ab initio</italic> either with hepatomegaly (83% with preceding infection) or hepatic failure (53% with preceding infection). Typically, an infant has been unwell for several weeks, has become tachypneic, is failing to thrive, is admitted with interstitial pneumonitis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic>, is found to be jaundiced with ascites, has hypogammaglobulinemia and thrombocytopenia, and has evidence of hVOD.</p>
          <p><bold>Neurologic.</bold> Overall, 30% of children with VODI had neurologic involvement; none of the individuals were reported to have veno-occlusive disease of the brain. Four individuals (sister of B II.1 and B II.2 [<xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals">Table 3</xref>] and 3 unrelated children) had multi-organ failure associated with extensive cerebral necrosis on post-mortem examination. A striking finding is the presence of cerebrospinal leukodystrophy in three individuals (20%) with VODI. Individual 5 had a leukodystrophy of unknown etiology and individual 6 developed this complication after a CMV-related gastroenteritis. In individual A II.1, the initial diagnosis of a cerebrovascular accident with a right-sided cerebral white matter lesion &#x02013; presumed to be <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma</italic> or a porencephalic cyst &#x02013; was revised as more consistent with cerebrospinal leukodystrophy. Individual B II.2 remained well on intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) and cotrimoxazole prophylaxis until age 18 years when she suddenly developed paraparesis and urinary retention associated with cerebral lesions. No infective cause or evidence of veno-occlusive disease was found on extensive investigation. There was partial response to high-dose IVIG and steroid therapy, suggesting an inflammatory etiology [MW Lin and M Wong, personal communication].</p>
          <p><bold>Other features.</bold> Infants and children with VODI do not have dysmorphic features. Thrombocytopenia is frequent at presentation but may improve with resolution of the hVOD. One child had the syndrome of inappropriate ADH secretion, presumably as a manifestation of his cerebral leukodystrophy.</p>
          <p><bold>Morbidity/mortality.</bold> VODI is associated with 100% mortality in the first year of life if unrecognized and untreated with IVIG or subcutaneous immunoglobulin (SCIG) replacement and <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> prophylaxis, and a 90% mortality overall by the mid-teenage years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al 2006</xref>]. However, there have been only three deaths among eight recently ascertained affected individuals older than age one year, representing a markedly improved prognosis with early recognition and treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al 2012</xref>]. Should hVOD recovery occur, recurrence of hVOD appears to be prevented by continuation of IVIG and <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">jirovecii</italic> prophylaxis. However, there may be an ongoing risk for neurologic inflammatory complications (B II.2). One child (Individual A II.1, <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals">Table 3</xref>) died following recurrence of hVOD after bone marrow transplantation at age six years. <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features">Table 2</xref> summarizes the clinical and immunologic features of the 20 individuals from Sydney with the clinical diagnosis of VODI (including the 11 individuals who were able to be investigated by molecular analysis confirming the presence of <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variants) and eight newly ascertained individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al 2012</xref>].</p>
          <table-wrap id="vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 2. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Clinical and Immunologic Features of Hepatic Veno-Occlusive Disease with Immunodeficiency</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical Features</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individuals From Sydney w/VODI&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comments</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Newly Ascertained Individuals w/VODI w/Novel Pathogenic Variants&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presenting &#x0003c;6 months</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/20 (100%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatic failure at initial presentation</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/20 (20%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/12 post-HSCT<break/>3/12 no obvious precipitant</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatomegaly at initial presentation</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/20 (45%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/6 <italic toggle="yes">P. jirovecii</italic><break/>2/6 hepatomegaly w/out SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/8<break/>1/8 enterovirus &#x00026; disseminated cytomegalovirus <sup>3</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P. jirovecii</italic> infection</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/20 (60%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/12 proven<break/>5/12 suspected</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/8 suspected&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup><break/>1/8 proven&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mucocutaneous candidiasis</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/20 (10%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other features</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/20 (5%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">By age 19 years</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/8 lung fibrosis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Death</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/20 (95%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/8 (38%)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery from initial SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/20 (20%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 completely well<break/>1 chronic liver disease requiring hepatic transplantation<break/>1 SOS post-HSCT<break/>1 developmental disability, chronic aspiration</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurologic abnormalities</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/20 (35%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/7 cerebral infarction<break/>2/7 leukodystrophy</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/8 leukodystrophy</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panhypogammaglobulinemia</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/19 (100%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/18 loss of normal immunoglobulins at age 4 mos</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5 tested<break/>1/5 low normal levels of IgA &#x00026; IgM after commencing IVIG</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal number of lymphocytes</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/11 (92%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal NK cells</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/12 (100%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/3&#x000a0;<sup>3,&#x000a0;4,&#x000a0;5</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreased intracytoplasmic IFN-&#x003b3;, IL-2, IL-4, IL-10</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5 (80%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low levels at 4 hrs, normal/increased levels at 48 hrs</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreased number of memory T &#x00026; B cells</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4 (75%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_and_immunologic_features_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/3&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>HSCT = hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>IVIG = intravenous immunoglobulin</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>SOS = sinusoidal obstruction syndrome</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.2.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>Table modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al [2006]</xref></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.2.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al [2012]</xref>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.2.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals">Table 3</xref>, Affected individual 1</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.2.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals">Table 3</xref>, Affected individual 4</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.2.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals">Table 3</xref>, Affected individual 2</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.2.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>Memory T and B cells were present in affected individual 1 (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals">Table 3</xref>)</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals">Table 3</xref> outlines clinical features in individuals with identified homozygous <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.wang.2012.102">Wang et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.ganaiem.2013.250">Ganaiem et al 2013</xref>].</p>
          <table-wrap id="vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Clinical Features of Individuals Homozygous for <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> Pathogenic Variants</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Affected Individual</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> (LRG_109) Pathogenic Variant</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Presentation</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum Igs</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Memory T/B Cells</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T Cell Cytokines</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical Findings</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deceased</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A II.1&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">c.642delC<break/>in exon 5</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 5 mos: immunodeficiency, thrombocytopenia, SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left hemiparesis&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup>, recurrent hVOD with GVHD post-HSCT</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B II.1&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">Age 7 mos: immunodeficiency</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic lung disease secondary to recurrent aspiration</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (age 19 yrs)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B II.2&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">Age 6 mos: hepatosplenomegaly, ascites, SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Well until 18 yrs (developed paraparesis, urinary retention, cerebral lesions)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C II.1&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">Age 4 mos: hepatosplenomegaly, ascites, SOS, thrombocytopenia, mucocutaneous candidiasis</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic liver disease, portal hypertension post-hepatic transplantation</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D II.1&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">Age 3 mos: hepatosplenomegaly, ascites, SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemophagocytic syndrome post-hepatic transplantation</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.642delC<break/>in exon 5</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 3 mos: hepatosplenomegaly, ascites, SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulmonary hemorrhage, multi-organ failure</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.642delC<break/>in exon 5</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 3 mos, respiratory distress</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIADH, idiopathic cerebrospinal leukodystrophy</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.642delC<break/>in exon 5</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 3 mos: chronic cough, diarrhea<break/>Age 8 yrs: hepatosplenomegaly<break/>Age &#x02265;12 yrs: hVOD</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Idiopathic left frontal lobe calcified cyst, epilepsy, CMV colitis, post-diarrheal encephalomyelitis w/lower limb paralysis, cerebrospinal leukodystrophy, esophageal candidiasis, duodenal lymphocytic infiltrate</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.642delC<break/>presumed&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 2 mos: chronic diarrhea, failure to thrive, middle ear and respiratory infections, hepatosplenomegaly, thrombocytopenia</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microcephaly, hepatic biopsy consistent w/SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, 11 mos from diarrhea leading to septic shock</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.642delC<break/>presumed&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 5 mos: upper respiratory illness<break/>Age 8 mos: chronic diarrhea, hepatomegaly, thrombocytopenia</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatic biopsy consistent w/SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, 3.5 yrs from diarrhea leading to septic shock</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.642delC<break/>presumed&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 2 mos: ascites, hepatomegaly, anemia, thrombocytopenia</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatic biopsy consistent w/SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes, 2.5 mos from otitis, diarrhea, pneumonia</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E I.1&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup><break/>Lebanese</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.40delC<break/>in exon 2</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 3 mos: immunodeficiency, thrombocytopenia, hepatosplenomegaly w/out definite evidence of SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enteroviral and <italic toggle="yes">P. jirovecii</italic> infection</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Hispanic</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.78_79delinsAT (p.Ile27Leu)<break/>in exon 2</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 5 mos: hepatosplenomegaly, fever, respiratory distress, pancytopenia</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stable &#x00026; well</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Italian</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.319_325dup GGTGCTT<break/>in exon 4</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 11 mos: hepatosplenomegaly, disseminated CMV, rotavirus gastroenteritis, vulvar abscesses, SOS</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;initially</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovering from hVOD, well</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Italian</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.667+1dup<break/>exon 5 splice site</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 3 mos: hepatosplenomegaly, failure to thrive, respiratory distress/lung fibrosis, diarrhea</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02193;</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatic biopsy consistent w/sinusoidal dilatation, moderate central vein &#x00026; perivenular subsinusoidal fibrosis; stable w/improvement</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup><break/>Palestinian Arab</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.373del<break/>in exon 4</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age 3 mos: diagnosis of VODI confirmed w/cascade testing prior to illness onset. No hepatomegaly or liver function abnormalities</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stable &#x00026; well</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al [2006]</xref></p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>CMV = cytomegalovirus</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>GVHD = graft-versus-host disease</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>HSCT = hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>hVOD = hepatic veno-occlusive disease</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>SOS = sinusoidal obstruction syndrome</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>SIADH = syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note: Although families A, B, and C are not known to be related, they are believed to have a common ancestor. Individuals included in the initial homozygosity mapping analysis: A II.1, B II.1, B II.2, C II.1, 16 (&#x02018;G&#x02019; in initial analysis), and 5 (&#x02018;J&#x02019; in initial analysis).</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Affected individual designations are those used in the articles cited.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.3.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al [2006]</xref>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.3.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>Secondary to cerebral white matter abnormality</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.3.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>IgA and IgM serum concentrations increased to lower limit of normal while on IVIG.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.3.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al [2012]</xref>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="vodi.TF.3.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>The pathogenic variant listed is a known familial variant. While sequence analysis was not performed on this affected individual, c.642delC is presumed to be the pathogenic variant based on the family history.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>No significant difference in the clinical manifestations of VODI is observed between individuals with different pathogenic variants.</p>
          <p>The one child with an out-of-frame duplication in exon 4 (Individual 1, <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.clinical_features_of_individuals">Table 3</xref>) presented at age 11 months (later than average) with disseminated CMV infection, which has not been noted in other children with VODI. In addition, the numbers of memory T and B cells were normal and intracellular cytokine production was normal &#x02013; findings not observed in other children with VODI.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>Penetrance for the combined B- and T-cell immunodeficiency has been 100% in individuals confirmed to have VODI caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic>. Likewise, hVOD has been described in all probands or their affected sibs.</p>
          <p>Approximately 10% of children with VODI, ascertained at a young age because of an affected sib and treated early in the disease course with IVIG, may manifest immunodeficiency only at presentation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>Hepatic veno-occlusive disease alone was known previously as Jamaican bush tea disease due to a dietary and geographic association. This term is now superseded by hepatic veno-occlusive disease (hVOD) or sinusoidal obstruction syndrome (SOS), terms less limiting given the occurrence of hVOD worldwide and it being secondary to other precipitants. The combination of hVOD and a combined immunodeficiency is termed VODI.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>VODI was described originally in Australians of Lebanese origin by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.mellis.1976.236">Mellis &#x00026; Bale [1976]</xref>. Subsequently, the majority of children reported with VODI have been of Lebanese origin. The prevalence of VODI in the Lebanese population of Sydney, Australia has been calculated at one in 2,500 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al 2006</xref>]. Unpublished data from Australia and Lebanon suggest that VODI associated with the <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> exon 5 pathogenic variant c.642delC is found not infrequently in families of Lebanese background, especially in association with consanguinity. This in turn suggests that the diagnosis has been missed in expatriate Lebanese communities.</p>
          <p>The prevalence of VODI in children of non-Lebanese origin is unknown; however, the following reports suggest that the VODI phenotype is observed in other populations. Additional reports of VODI:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>A simplex case of VODI (i.e., a single occurrence in a family) with humoral and cellular immunodeficiency in the Spanish literature</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Two Italian children with VODI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.ruga.2006">Ruga et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al 2012</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A Hispanic child with VODI from the United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.wang.2012.102">Wang et al 2012</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="vodi.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disorde">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No allelic Mendelian disorders for <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> or contiguous-gene disorders including the <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> region associated with hVOD or immunodeficiency have been described.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="vodi.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Although sinusoidal obstruction syndrome in association with severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID) was described in an individual reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.washington.1993.485">Washington et al [1993]</xref>, and in one post-mortem HIV cohort reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.buckley.1995.398">Buckley &#x00026; Hutchins [1995]</xref>, the lack of a recognized and replicated association of immunodeficiency with hepatic veno-occlusive disease (hVOD) in other classes of immunodeficiency suggests that hVOD may be a primary feature of VODI rather than secondary to an immunodeficiency per se.</p>
        <p>The primary differential diagnosis for hVOD alone would be environmental alkaloid or sinusoidal cell toxicity. However, hVOD has also been reported in association with alcoholic cirrhosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.kishi.1999.47s">Kishi et al 1999</xref>], <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="ataxia-telangiectas" document-type="chapter">ataxia-telangiectasia</related-object> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.srisirirojanakorn.1999.786">Srisirirojanakorn et al 1999</xref>], osteopetrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.corbacioglu.2006.547">Corbacioglu et al 2006</xref>] (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="clcn7" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">CLCN7</italic>-Related Osteopetrosis</related-object>), and hypereosinophilic syndrome (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/607685">OMIM</ext-link>). HIV should also be considered in the differential diagnosis for the immune phenotype.</p>
        <p>Previous case-control studies using single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) have also reported associations between hVOD and SNPs in the carbamoyl phosphate synthetase 1 <italic toggle="yes">(CPS1</italic>) (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="ucd-overview" document-type="chapter">Urea Cycle Disorders Overview</related-object>), <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="factor-v-leiden" document-type="chapter">factor V Leiden</related-object> (FVL), <italic toggle="yes">HFE</italic> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hemochromatosis" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">HFE</italic>-Associated Hereditary Hemochromatosis</related-object>), and glutathione S-transferase <italic toggle="yes">(GSTM1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GSTT1</italic>) genes. Relative risks of 8.6 for the homozygous <italic toggle="yes">HFE</italic> Cys282Tyr allele and 4.12 for the <italic toggle="yes">GSTM1</italic> null allele have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.srivastava.2004.1574">Srivastava et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.kallianpur.2005.1">Kallianpur 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.kallianpur.2005.1155">Kallianpur et al 2005</xref>]. No independent replication of these findings has been performed.</p>
        <p>There has been no report of <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variants in individuals described to have hVOD without immunodeficiency.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="vodi.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="vodi.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diagn">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with hepatic veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency (VODI), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of immune function including serum immunoglobulin levels, T- and B-cell numbers and percentages, and T-cell proliferative response to mitogens</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>More extensive immune testing for number of memory B and T cells and intracellular cytokine (IL2, IL4, IL6, and IFN&#x003b3;) responses to stimulation, if available</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Complete blood count</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of hepatic function (including serum concentrations of aminotransferases, bilirubin, and albumin) and assessment for sequelae of portal hypertension (including anemia and thrombocytopenia)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>A clotting profile and a hepatic Doppler ultrasound examination should be undertaken prior to consideration of hepatic biopsy for a histologic diagnosis of hepatic veno-occlusive disease (hVOD). Evidence of impaired clotting and/or portal hypertension contraindicates hepatic biopsy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p><bold>Hypogammaglobulinemia</bold> is treated via intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG), which should commence at the diagnosis of VODI or in presymptomatic sibs confirmed to have homozygous <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variants. An appropriate dose is 0.4 g/kg every four weeks adjusting the dose to maintain a trough IgG level greater than 6 g/L.</p>
          <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> prophylaxis</bold> with cotrimoxazole pediatric suspension (5 mL = trimethoprim 40 mg and sulfamethoxazole 200 mg) should be ongoing in children with VODI who tolerate this medication. This may be administered as a single daily dose or as a single dose three days per week. The recommended dose is 5 mg trimethoprim per kg (0.625 mL/kg) or 150 mg/M<sup>2</sup> (3.75 mL/M<sup>2</sup>).</p>
          <p><bold>Infections with specific agents</bold> should be treated with appropriate supportive care and antibacterials or antivirals.</p>
          <p><bold>Hepatic transplantation</bold> may be considered, but appears to have a high rate of complications in the VODI cohort studied to date (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="vodi.Other">Other</xref>).</p>
          <p><bold>Bone marrow transplantation.</bold>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.ganaiem.2013.250">Ganaiem et al [2013]</xref> reported that this may be an efficacious treatment modality with appropriate conditioning therapy (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="vodi.Other">Other</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Prevention_of_Primary_Manifestation">
          <title>Prevention of Primary Manifestations</title>
          <p>Initiation of regular IVIG at the time of diagnosis to prevent infection related to severe hypogammaglobulinemia and cotrimoxazole prophylaxis to prevent <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> infection is appropriate (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="vodi.Treatment_of_Manifestations">Treatment of Manifestations</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complicatio">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Some evidence suggests that treatment of immunodeficiency early in VODI may reduce the risk for development or recurrence of hVOD.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>The following are appropriate:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular surveillance of hepatic function, platelet count, and hemoglobin level in children with VODI as hepatic failure and portal hypertension may occur</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Surveillance of serum and urine electrolytes as the syndrome of inappropriate anti-diuretic hormone (SIADH) may occur</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Measurement of immunoglobulin concentrations prior to IVIG infusions</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Broncho-alveolar lavage to diagnose <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> infection; viral cultures or lung function studies as needed</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Cerebrospinal imaging to diagnose leukodystrophy when clinically indicated</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Agents known to predispose to hVOD (e.g., cyclophosphamide and senecio alkaloids/bush teas) should be avoided.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>It is appropriate to evaluate sibs of a proband who are younger than age 12 months in order to identify as early as possible those who would benefit from initiation of treatment and preventive measures. The majority of children with VODI present before age six months; however, as one child presented at age 11 months, testing should be considered in sibs of a proband who are younger than age 12 months.</p>
          <p>Evaluations include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic testing if the pathogenic variants in the family are known;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Serum immunoglobulins, full blood count and liver function tests at birth and repeated at six months if the pathogenic variants in the family are not known.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Penetrance is complete (i.e., 100%) in the individuals with VODI described to date; thus, molecular genetic testing of healthy at-risk sibs of a proband who are older than age 12 months is not recommended.</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="vodi.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>For an affected pregnant woman, ongoing intravenous immunoglobulin to prevent infection related to severe hypogammaglobulinemia and cotrimoxazole prophylaxis to prevent <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> infection is appropriate during pregnancy. There is evidence that early treatment of a baby known to be homozygous for pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variants may result in improved long-term outcomes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Other">
          <title>Other</title>
          <p>Hepatic VOD (hVOD) has been reported in the Australian cohort with VODI following hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT); therefore, individuals with VODI are likely to have at least the population risk for hVOD following HSCT. The first successful HSCT was reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.ganaiem.2013.250">Ganaiem et al [2013]</xref> suggesting that this may be an efficacious treatment modality with appropriate conditioning therapy. Ganaiem et al described a consanguineous Arab family with eight affected individuals; five individuals received HSCT, of which three were successful. All five individuals received matched sib or family member bone marrow (4 individuals) or peripheral stem cells (1 individual). All five individuals received conditioning with fludarabine and serotherapy and an alkylating agent (cyclophosphamide, busulfan, or treosulfan). The two individuals who died also received thiotepa, and following engraftment died with hVOD and multi-organ failure. One child has remained well for two years following uncomplicated HSCT in 2014. She was of consanguineous Lebanese background and presented at age four months with probable herpetic hepatitis which initially responded clinically to acyclovir, but then developed florid hVOD following a transfusion. She responded well to IVIG, prophylactic Bactrim&#x02122;, and defibrotide. She was neurologically normal, but asymptomatic bilateral subdural hematomas were found on routine pre-transplant MRI despite a normal head ultrasound a week prior when coagulation studies and platelets had already normalized. At age six months she underwent an unrelated cord blood transplant with alemtuzumab, fludarabine, treosulfan and antithymocyte globulin conditioning. Defibrotide was prophylactically continued until two months post transplant. She remains neurologically normal and her MRI scan at age two years showed no anatomic abnormality [M Wong, personal communication].</p>
          <p>In 2016, an Australian infant of consanguineous Lebanese background presented at age four months with <italic toggle="yes">Pneumocystis</italic>, CMV infection, and hVOD with hypogammaglobinemia. A homozygous <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variant (c.642delC) was identified on molecular genetic testing. At age five months, after control of pneumonitis and hVOD, he received a haplo-identical paternal HSCT after depletion of &#x003b1;/&#x003b2; TCR and CD19+ cells. He received conditioning with fludarabine, treosulfan, and antithymocyte globulin. Defibrotide was given as hVOD prophylaxis. Two months post-transplant he was well and had engrafted without GVHD or recurrence of hVOD but with moderate CMV hepatitis. Defibrotide was able to be discontinued at day 60. Both the affected individual and donor were CMV positive prior to transplant. Seventy days following HSCT he developed seizures. MRI showed extensive abnormalities throughout the brain and spinal cord, including areas of edema and ring-like enhancing lesions. CT showed widespread calcifications. CMV retinitis was apparent and both CSF and vitreous were CMV PCR positive [T Cole, J Smart, and T Soosay Raj, personal communication].</p>
          <p>Inclusion of defibrotide prophylaxis in the transplant regimen may improve survival. Omission of a second alkylating agent in the conditioning regimen may reduce the risk for transplant-related hVOD.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="vodi.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="vodi.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Hepatic veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency (VODI) is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Penetrance is complete.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected child are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variant).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>An at-risk sib older than age 12 months and known to be unaffected has a 2/3 risk of being a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> The offspring of an individual with hepatic veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency are obligate heterozygotes (carriers) for a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic>.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members of a proband.</bold> Each sib of the proband's parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier of an <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Carrier_Heterozygote_Detection">
          <title>Carrier (Heterozygote) Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variants in the family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="vodi.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives younger than age 12 months for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected, are carriers, or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="vodi.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantatio">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for VODI are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="vodi.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="vodi.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> encodes three major isoforms:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Sp110 isoform A, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_004509.3">NM_004509.3</ext-link> (average mass 78.438 kd; transcript does not include exon 17)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Isoform B, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_004510.3">NM_004510.3</ext-link> (average mass 61.940 kd; transcript includes an alternate exon 15 and terminates within exon 15)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Isoform C, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_080424.2">NM_080424.2</ext-link> (average mass 81.211 kd; full-length transcript including exon 17 and terminating at exon 19)</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> See <xref ref-type="table" rid="vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss">Table 4</xref>. The majority of these pathogenic variants cause a frameshift with consequent protein truncation. The c.642delC pathogenic variant has been identified in multiple probands of Lebanese ancestry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al 2012</xref>].</p>
        <table-wrap id="vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 4. </label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> Pathogenic Variants Discussed in This <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change<break/>(Alias&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup>)</th>
                <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon</th>
                <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
                <th id="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.40delC</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gln14SerfsTer25</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al [2006]</xref>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_5" rowspan="6" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_080424.2">NM_080424.2</ext-link>
                  <break/>
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_536349.2">NP_536349.2</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.78_79delinsAT<break/>(78_79CA&#x0003e;AT)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ile27Leu</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al [2012]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.wang.2012.102">Wang et al [2012]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.319_325dupGGTGCTT</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ser109TrpfsTer5</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.ruga.2006">Ruga et al [2006]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al [2012]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.373delA</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Thr125LeufsTer3</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al [2012]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.ganaiem.2013.250">Ganaiem et al [2013]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.642delC</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Pro214ProfsTer14</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al [2006]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.667+1dupG</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_vodi.T.sp110_pathogenic_variants_discuss_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al [2012]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>NA = not applicable</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="vodi.TF.4.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>Variant designation that does not conform to current naming conventions</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> Sp110 is expressed primarily in leukocytes and spleen; it is induced by interferon gamma and all-trans retinoic acid (ATRA). SP110 isoform B has been described as showing activity as a potent transcriptional co-repressor of retinoic acid receptor alpha (RAR&#x003b1;) perhaps via competitive exclusion of activators at receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.watashi.2003.7498">Watashi et al 2003</xref>].</p>
        <p>The Sp110 nuclear body protein is a member of the Sp100/Sp140 promyelocytic leukemia nuclear body (PML NB) protein family. The protein has an Sp100 domain (amino acids 6-159), which is involved in dimerization with other Sp100 family proteins, a nuclear localization signal (amino acids 288-306) and a nuclear hormone interaction domain (LXXLL type), which may act as an ATRA response element. Other domains that are common features of modular proteins involved in chromatin-mediated gene transcription include a SAND domain (amino acids 452-532), a plant homeobox domain (amino acids 537-577), and a bromodomain (amino acids 606-674) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.bloch.2000.6138">Bloch et al 2000</xref>].</p>
        <p>The Sp110 nuclear body protein is associated with the PML NB, a nuclear macromolecular complex, which is deployed to areas of active host or viral DNA replication, transcription, and repair and has been reported to be involved in apoptosis, cell cycle control, and the immune response.</p>
        <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> EBV-transformed B cells from an individual with VODI and a homozygous inactivating <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> variant have shown an absence of nuclear Sp100-specific immunolabeling in a setting of normal numbers of PML nuclear bodies. This finding is consistent with Sp110 protein having an important role in the immune response without being essential for PML nuclear body formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">Roscioli et al 2006</xref>].</p>
        <p>Most pathogenic variants associated with VODI are loss-of-function variants. The c.78_79delinsAT (p.Ile27Leu) pathogenic variant occurs at the highly conserved p.Ile27 within the highly conserved Sp100 domain (see <bold>Normal gene product</bold>). The c.78_79delinsAT (p.Ile27Leu) pathogenic variant greatly reduces Sp110 stability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">Cliffe et al 2012</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold>Pathophysiology.</bold> It is currently unknown whether the hVOD is a direct manifestation of <italic toggle="yes">SP110</italic> sequence variants, related to altered apoptosis in the hepatic sinusoid, or secondary to infection; however, hVOD appears to develop after infections occur.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="vodi.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="vodi.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="vodi.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="vodi.REF.bloch.2000.6138">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bloch</surname>
                    <given-names>DB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakajima</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gulick</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chiche</surname>
                    <given-names>JD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Orth</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de La Monte</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bloch</surname>
                    <given-names>KD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>Sp110 localizes to the PML-Sp100 nuclear body and may function as a nuclear hormone receptor transcriptional coactivator.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>6138</fpage>
                <lpage>46</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10913195</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.buckley.1995.398">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Buckley</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hutchins</surname>
                    <given-names>GM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1995</year>
                <article-title>Association of hepatic veno-occlusive disease with the acquired immunodeficiency syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Mod Pathol</source>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>398</fpage>
                <lpage>401</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7567938</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.cliffe.2012.735">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cliffe</surname>
                    <given-names>ST</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bloch</surname>
                    <given-names>DB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Suryani</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kamsteeg</surname>
                    <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Avery</surname>
                    <given-names>DT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Palendira</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Church</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wainstein</surname>
                    <given-names>BK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Trizzino</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lefranc</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Akatcherian</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Megarban&#x000e9;</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gilissen</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moshous</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reichenbach</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Misbah</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Salzer</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abinun</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ong</surname>
                    <given-names>PY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stepensky</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ruga</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ziegler</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wong</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tangye</surname>
                    <given-names>SG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindeman</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Buckley</surname>
                    <given-names>MF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roscioli</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Clinical, molecular, and cellular immunologic findings in patients with SP110-associated veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>130</volume>
                <fpage>735</fpage>
                <lpage>742.e6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22621957</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.corbacioglu.2006.547">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Corbacioglu</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Honig</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lahr</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stohr</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berry</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Friedrich</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schulz</surname>
                    <given-names>AS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Stem cell transplantation in children with infantile osteopetrosis is associated with a high incidence of VOD, which could be prevented with defibrotide.</article-title>
                <source>Bone Marrow Transplant</source>
                <volume>38</volume>
                <fpage>547</fpage>
                <lpage>53</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16953210</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.ganaiem.2013.250">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ganaiem</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eisenstein</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tenenbaum</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Somech</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Simanovsky</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roscioli</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Weintraub</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stepensky</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2013</year>
                <article-title>The role of hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in SP110 associated veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Allergy Immunol.</source>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>250</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23448538</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.kallianpur.2005.1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kallianpur</surname>
                    <given-names>AR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Genomic screening and complications of hematopoietic stem cell transplantation: has the time come?</article-title>
                <source>Bone Marrow Transplant</source>
                <volume>35</volume>
                <fpage>1</fpage>
                <lpage>16</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15489868</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.kallianpur.2005.1155">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kallianpur</surname>
                    <given-names>AR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hall</surname>
                    <given-names>LD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yadav</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byrne</surname>
                    <given-names>DW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Speroff</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dittus</surname>
                    <given-names>RS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haines</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Christman</surname>
                    <given-names>BW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Summar</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>The hemochromatosis C282Y allele: a risk factor for hepatic veno-occlusive disease after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation.</article-title>
                <source>Bone Marrow Transplant</source>
                <volume>35</volume>
                <fpage>1155</fpage>
                <lpage>64</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15834437</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.kishi.1999.47s">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kishi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maeyama</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ogata</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koike</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Uchikoshi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Hepatic veno-occlusive lesions in severe alcoholic hepatitis and alcoholic liver cirrhosis: a comparative histopathological study in autopsy cases.</article-title>
                <source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res.</source>
                <volume>23</volume>
                <fpage>47S</fpage>
                <lpage>51S</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10235278</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.mellis.1976.236">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mellis</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bale</surname>
                    <given-names>PM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1976</year>
                <article-title>Familial hepatic venoocclusive disease with probable immune deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr</source>
                <volume>88</volume>
                <fpage>236</fpage>
                <lpage>42</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1249685</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.roscioli.2006.620">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roscioli</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cliffe</surname>
                    <given-names>ST</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bloch</surname>
                    <given-names>DB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bell</surname>
                    <given-names>CG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mullan</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sarris</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Donald</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kirk</surname>
                    <given-names>EP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ziegler</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Salzer</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McDonald</surname>
                    <given-names>GB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wong</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindeman</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Buckley</surname>
                    <given-names>MF</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in the gene encoding the PML nuclear body protein Sp110 are associated with immunodeficiency and hepatic veno-occlusive disease.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>38</volume>
                <fpage>620</fpage>
                <lpage>2</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16648851</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.ruga.2006">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">Ruga EM, Guariso G, Antiga LD, Guido M, Fassan M, Elia RD, Ziegler JB, Roscioli T, Cliffe ST, Buckley MF, Zancan L. Hepatic veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency syndrome: case report. Budapest, Hungary: 12th Meeting of the European Society for Immunodeficiencies. 2006.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.srisirirojanakorn.1999.786">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Srisirirojanakorn</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Finegold</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gopalakrishna</surname>
                    <given-names>GS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Klish</surname>
                    <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Hepatic veno-occlusive disease in ataxia-telangiectasia.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr</source>
                <volume>134</volume>
                <fpage>786</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10356154</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.srivastava.2004.1574">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Srivastava</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Poonkuzhali</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shaji</surname>
                    <given-names>RV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>George</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mathews</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chandy</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Krishnamoorthy</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004</year>
                <article-title>Glutathione S-transferase M1 polymorphism: a risk factor for hepatic venoocclusive disease in bone marrow transplantation.</article-title>
                <source>Blood</source>
                <volume>104</volume>
                <fpage>1574</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15142875</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.wang.2012.102">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ong</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roscioli</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cliffe</surname>
                    <given-names>ST</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Church</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>Hepatic veno-occlusive disease with immunodeficiency (VODI): first reported case in the U.S. and identification of a unique mutation in Sp110.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Immunol</source>
                <volume>145</volume>
                <fpage>102</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22982295</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.washington.1993.485">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Washington</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gossage</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gottfried</surname>
                    <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1993</year>
                <article-title>Pathology of the liver in severe combined immunodeficiency and DiGeorge syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Pathol</source>
                <volume>13</volume>
                <fpage>485</fpage>
                <lpage>504</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8372033</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="vodi.REF.watashi.2003.7498">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Watashi</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hijikata</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tagawa</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Doi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marusawa</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shimotohno</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Modulation of retinoid signaling by a cytoplasmic viral protein via sequestration of Sp110b, a potent transcriptional corepressor of retinoic acid receptor, from the nucleus.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
                <volume>23</volume>
                <fpage>7498</fpage>
                <lpage>509</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14559998</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="vodi.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="vodi.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>12 January 2017 (sw) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>3 July 2013 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>15 September 2009 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>21 February 2007 (me) Review posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>29 November 2006 (mb) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="vodi.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Hepatic biopsy showing vascular obliteration, peri-venular fibrosis, zone 3 fibrosis and hepatocyte dropout from a girl who presented at age five months with hepatomegaly and ascites (Picro-Mallory stain 100x)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="vodi-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
