<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="wss" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">wss</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Woodhouse-Sakati Syndrome</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: Hypogonadism, Alopecia, Diabetes Mellitus, Intellectual Disability, and Extrapyramidal Syndrome</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bohlega</surname>
            <given-names>Saeed A</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, FRCPC, FAAN</degrees>
          <aff>Professor and Consultant, Department of Neurosciences<break/>King Faisal Specialist Hospital and Research Centre<break/>Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</aff>
          <email>boholega@kfshrc.edu.sa</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Alkuraya</surname>
            <given-names>Fowzan S</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD (Hons), ABP, ABMGG</degrees>
          <aff>Professor of Human Genetics<break/>Principal Clinical Scientist/Senior Consultant<break/>Head, Developmental Genetics Unit<break/>King Faisal Specialist Hospital and Research Centre<break/>Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</aff>
          <email>falkuraya@kfshrc.edu.sa</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="whs" document-type="chapter">Wolf-Hirschhorn Syndrome</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="ahc" document-type="chapter">X-Linked Adrenal Hypoplasia Congenita</related-object>
      <abstract id="wss.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Virtually all individuals with Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome (WSS) have the endocrine findings of hypogonadism (evident at puberty) and progressive childhood-onset hair thinning that often progresses to alopecia totalis in adulthood. More than half of individuals have the neurologic findings of progressive extrapyramidal movements (dystonic spasms with dystonic posturing with dysarthria and dysphagia), moderate bilateral post-lingual sensorineural hearing loss, and mild intellectual disability. To date 32 families (including 23 with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis) with a total of 76 affected individuals have been reported.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis is established in a proband with suggestive clinical findings and by identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> (formerly known as <italic toggle="yes">C2orf37</italic>) on molecular genetic testing.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Treatment is symptomatic and should be managed by a multidisciplinary team. Hypogonadism requires hormone replacement therapy to induce secondary sex characteristics and promote bone health at the usual age of puberty. Alopecia is treated symptomatically for cosmetic reasons only. Treatment for dystonia is routine; oral medications are tried first and followed in some instances by botulinum toxin injection and/or deep-brain stimulation. Dysarthria often benefits from consultation with a speech therapist. Those with dysphagia often require measures to reduce oral secretions, use of thickened liquids and pureed foods to avoid aspiration, and eventually a gastrostomy to help maintain caloric intake. Hearing loss, intellectual disability, diabetes mellitus, and hypothyroidism are treated as per routine.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Monitoring for endocrine abnormalities is recommended at the following ages: hypogonadism (12-14 years), diabetes mellitus (in the 20s or later), hypothyroidism (in the 20s or later). Neurologic manifestations should be monitored by a neurologist as well as experts in rehabilitative medicine, speech, and swallowing. Hearing should be monitored annually.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Persons with dystonia should avoid situations in which the risk of falling is increased.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> Molecular genetic testing for the <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variants identified in the proband is appropriate for evaluation of apparently asymptomatic older and younger sibs to identify, as early as possible, those who would benefit from early identification and treatment of potential complications.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>WSS is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Once the pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> variants have been identified in an affected family member, carrier testing for at-risk relatives, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk, and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible options.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="wss.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="wss.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome (WSS) <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following findings.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Endocrine</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Hypogonadism (100% of individuals), hypogonadotropic in males and hypergonadotropic in females</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Primary amenorrhea in females</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Lack of development of secondary sexual characteristics in males and females</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Low insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) (100%)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Adolescent- to young adult-onset diabetes mellitus (66%)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hypothyroidism (30%)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Alopecia.</bold> Hair loss beginning in childhood or adolescence, resulting in partial to complete loss of scalp hair and eyelashes (100%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F1">Figure 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F1">1H</xref>)</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Neurologic</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Adolescent to young adult onset of extrapyramidal findings (56%) including focal (later generalized) dystonia and chorea, dysarthria, and dysphagia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL) with onset in childhood (62%)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Intellectual disability (58%)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <sec id="wss.Supportive_Findings">
            <title>Supportive Findings</title>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>On MRI:</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Variable abnormalities in periventricular white matter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F2">Figure 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F2">2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F2">2D</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.schneider.2008.592">Schneider &#x00026; Bhatia 2008</xref>]</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Rarely, iron deposition in the globus pallidus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F2">Figure 2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F2">2D</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.gregory.2011.254">Gregory &#x00026; Hayflick 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.hdiji.2016.120">Hdiji et al 2016</xref>]</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Parental consanguinity</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with suggestive clinical findings and biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> (formerly known as <italic toggle="yes">C2orf37</italic>) on molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold>, use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>, and <bold>more comprehensive genomic testing</bold>.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> identifies biallelic pathogenic variants in all individuals with typical findings of WSS. <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> exon and whole-gene deletion/duplication variants have not been reported. However, gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis may be useful to confirm homozygosity of a pathogenic variant detected by sequence analysis when parental DNA is not available (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="wss.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>, <bold>Pathogenic variants</bold>).</p>
              <p>For affected individuals who are ethnically Saudi Arabian or Qatari, targeted analysis for pathogenic variants may be performed first: to date, all affected individuals in these populations have been homozygous for the same founder pathogenic variant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="wss.T.dcaf17_variants_discussed_in_this">c.436delC</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alazami.2008.684">Alazami et al 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.benomran.2011.2647">Ben-Omran et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="wss.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of the condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting secondary findings. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing-based tests.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>More comprehensive genomic testing</bold> (when available) including exome sequencing, mitochondrial sequencing, and genome sequencing may be considered if serial single-gene testing (and/or use of a multi-gene panel that includes <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic>) fails to confirm a diagnosis in an individual with features of WSS. Such testing may provide or suggest a diagnosis not previously considered (e.g., mutation of a different gene or genes that results in a similar clinical presentation). For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Woodhouse-Sakati Syndrome</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with Pathogenic Variants&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/32 families</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None reported</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="wss.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="wss" object-id="wss.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="wss.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="wss.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="wss.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="wss.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wss.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="wss.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome (WSS) is characterized by the endocrine findings of hypogonadism, diabetes mellitus, and hypothyroidism; and progressive childhood-onset alopecia along with neurologic findings of progressive extrapyramidal movements, sensorineural hearing loss, and intellectual disability.</p>
          <p>WSS was first described in a few consanguineous Saudi families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.woodhouse.1983.216">Woodhouse &#x00026; Sakati 1983</xref>]. Of note, a review of earlier literature revealed two families that appeared to have similar clinical manifestations &#x02013; one from Lebanon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.slti.1979.428">Slti &#x00026; Salem 1979</xref>] and one from Italy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.bjornstad.1965">Bjornstad 1965</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.crandall.1973.461">Crandall et al 1973</xref>].</p>
          <p>As of July 2016, 32 families (including 23 families with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis) with a total of 76 affected individuals have been reported. While the majority are from the Middle East (i.e., Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates, Qatar, Kuwait, Palestine, Turkey), families from India, Belgium, the Roma population in France, Croatia, Pakistan, Tunisia, and Italy have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alawadi.1985.619">Al-Awadi et al 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.m_garban_.2003.214">M&#x000e9;garban&#x000e9; et al 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.medica.2007.227">Medica et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.tatar.2009.501">Tatar et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.steindl.2010.594">Steindl et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.nanda.2014.83">Nanda et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.abdulla.2015.489">Abdulla et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.hdiji.2016.120">Hdiji et al 2016</xref>, and references cited below in this section].</p>
          <sec id="wss.Endocrine">
            <title>Endocrine</title>
            <p><bold>Hypogonadism,</bold> present in all affected individuals, manifests as delayed puberty with lack of secondary sexual characteristics. The nature of hypogonadism has been difficult to characterize as both hypergonadotropic and hypogonadotropic hypogonadism have been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>]; in about 30% of affected individuals the hormonal profile does not neatly fit either group. Sense of smell is normal.</p>
            <p>Women typically have primary amenorrhea. Detailed endocrine investigation, available in 52 of the women described in the literature, typically revealed severely reduced or absent estradiol and high FSH and LH, consistent with hypergonadotropic hypogonadism. There appears to be decreased hypothalamic-pituitary responsiveness, as the FSH and LH are not as high as expected for the degree of ovarian failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.woodhouse.1983.216">Woodhouse &#x00026; Sakati 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.rachmiel.2011.362">Rachmiel et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p>The ovaries are streak or underdeveloped [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alswailem.2006.116">Al-Swailem et al 2006</xref>] and not visualized by laparotomy, laparoscopy, or autopsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.g_l.2000.123">G&#x000fc;l et al 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.benomran.2011.2647">Ben-Omran et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.rachmiel.2011.362">Rachmiel et al 2011</xref>]. Ovarian biopsy showed fibrous tissue with no identifiable oocysts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.woodhouse.1983.216">Woodhouse &#x00026; Sakati 1983</xref>].</p>
            <p>Men have moderately low testosterone and &#x02013; in contrast to women &#x02013; inappropriately low gonadotropins, consistent with hypogonadotropic hypogonadism which may be of central or central and peripheral etiology. Semen analysis may show azoospermia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.ali.2016.263">Ali et al 2016</xref>]. One male had cryptorchidism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.rachmiel.2011.362">Rachmiel et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            <p>Although the testes are of normal size, testicular biopsy reveals reduced spermatogenesis with predominance of Sertoli cells and few Leydig cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.woodhouse.1983.216">Woodhouse &#x00026; Sakati 1983</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Low insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1).</bold> First described in 12 families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>], low IGF-1 was identified in all subsequently reported cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alazami.2010.585">Alazami et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.benomran.2011.2647">Ben-Omran et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.habib.2011.26">Habib et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.rachmiel.2011.362">Rachmiel et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.ali.2016.263">Ali et al 2016</xref>]. Reduction of IGF1 is more pronounced in females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.benomran.2011.2647">Ben-Omran et al 2011</xref>]. The low IGF-1 levels may reflect the low sex steroids resulting from hypogonadism.</p>
            <p>The growth pattern is normal and growth hormone levels are usually normal; short stature is not a part of this syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Diabetes mellitus.</bold> Type 2 diabetes (either insulin dependent or non-insulin dependent) was reported in 66% of all individuals and 96% of those older than age 25 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Hypothyroidism</bold> of peripheral origin (primary but without evidence of autoimmunity) was found in 30% of individuals, typically around age 20 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Other.</bold> No abnormalities of the corticotropic axis or prolactin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>] have been reported.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="wss.Ectodermal">
            <title>Ectodermal</title>
            <p><bold>Alopecia.</bold> All affected individuals have predominantly frontotemporal alopecia with sparse thin scalp hair. Hair loss begins in childhood and often progresses to alopecia totalis in the third or fourth decade or earlier. Eyelashes and eyebrows are absent or sparse. In men, facial hair is absent or underdeveloped.</p>
            <p>Scanning electron microscopy of the hair shows longitudinal grooves with no specific abnormalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.devriendt.1996.54">Devriendt et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Facial skin</bold> is often wrinkled in advanced stages conferring a progeroid appearance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.woodhouse.1983.216">Woodhouse &#x00026; Sakati 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.schneider.2008.592">Schneider &#x00026; Bhatia 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Anodontia.</bold> Total loss of teeth is rare; when it occurs, it is usually seen at later stage of the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.steindl.2010.594">Steindl et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Nails</bold> appear to be normal.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="wss.Neurologic">
            <title>Neurologic</title>
            <p><bold>Extrapyramidal abnormal movement</bold> was seen in more than 56% of reported individuals. In particular, dystonic spasms with dystonic posturing was seen in the majority, including segmental dystonia affecting the craniocervical region, oromandibular region, or one extremity. Often, the first neurologic manifestation is abnormal posturing movements that typically start insidiously in childhood or the early teens. Dysarthria (often with a high-pitched voice) and dysphagia are common.</p>
            <p>In a majority of individuals, dystonia becomes generalized and disabling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F1">Figure 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F1">1F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F1">1H</xref>). Progressive dystonia of the trunk may lead to severe dystonic scoliosis. As the dystonia progresses, gait difficulties ultimately lead to immobility.</p>
            <p>Inter- and intrafamilial variability is common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.schneider.2008.592">Schneider &#x00026; Bhatia 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.benomran.2011.2647">Ben-Omran et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.ali.2016.263">Ali et al 2016</xref>]. For example, families with the founder <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> (c.436delC) pathogenic variant can have dystonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>] or not [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alazami.2008.684">Alazami et al 2008</xref>]. Of note, although extrapyramidal features were not mentioned in the original report of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.woodhouse.1983.216">Woodhouse and Sakati [1983]</xref>, subsequent follow up in the originally reported families revealed progressive dystonia in a few family members (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F1">Figure 1H</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL).</bold> Moderate bilateral SNHL was noted in 62% of reports. When present, deafness is invariably postlingual, usually starting in adolescence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.woodhouse.1983.216">Woodhouse &#x00026; Sakati 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.schneider.2008.592">Schneider &#x00026; Bhatia 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.benomran.2011.2647">Ben-Omran et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Intellectual disability</bold> is described in 58% of individuals. It is typically mild and usually overshadowed by accompanying severe and disabling dystonia, dysarthria, and SNHL. The authors observed ten individuals who were able to complete their college education and hold permanent manual occupations [Author, personal observation].</p>
            <p><bold>Other.</bold> Seizures with onset in early childhood, tremors, and mild Parkinsonism features were rarely reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">Al-Semari &#x00026; Bohlega 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.schneider.2008.592">Schneider &#x00026; Bhatia 2008</xref>].</p>
            <p>Polyneuropathy with stocking glove sensory loss and diminished deep tendon reflexes but normal strength has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.schneider.2008.592">Schneider &#x00026; Bhatia 2008</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="wss.Other_Findings">
            <title>Other Findings</title>
            <p><bold>Dysmorphic facial features</bold> include a long triangular face, prominent nasal bridge, widely spaced eyes, and sparse eyebrows, creating a characteristic facial appearance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F1">Figure 1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F1">1E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="wss.F1">1G</xref>).</p>
            <p><bold>Bilateral keratoconus</bold> was reported in four individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alswailem.2006.116">Al-Swailem et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.schneider.2008.592">Schneider &#x00026; Bhatia 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.benomran.2011.2647">Ben-Omran et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Electrocardiographic (ECG) abnormalities</bold> (lengthening of the ST segments and T-wave flattening) were described in the original report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.woodhouse.1983.216">Woodhouse &#x00026; Sakati 1983</xref>]; however, they were rarely reported subsequently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.koshy.2008.57">Koshy et al 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.schneider.2008.592">Schneider &#x00026; Bhatia 2008</xref>]. Of note, these ECG abnormalities were asymptomatic and individuals with WSS have no major cardiac manifestations.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>There is no clear genotype-phenotype correlation. Even individuals with the same Saudi Arabian founder <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variant (c.436delC) have displayed marked phenotypic variability.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>From the time of the original description in 1983 to the present (July 2016), 32 families with 76 affected individuals have been reported. Of these, 44 individuals from 23 families have had the diagnosis confirmed molecularly (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="wss.Clinical_Description">Clinical Description</xref>).</p>
          <p>The carrier frequency of the Saudi Arabian founder variant is 0.00243309 [Abouelhoda et al, submitted].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wss.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disorder">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wss.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <table-wrap id="wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Disorders/Phenotypes to Consider in the Differential Diagnosis of Woodhouse-Sakati Syndrome</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disorder / Phenotype</th>
                <th id="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene(s)</th>
                <th id="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOI</th>
                <th id="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distinguishing Clinical Features</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="kms" document-type="chapter">Gonadotropin-releasing hormone deficiency</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See footnote 1</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XL<break/>AD<break/>AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Idiopathic hypogonadotropic hypogonadism w/congenital olfactory deficit w/ataxia, epilepsy &#x00026; congenital paresis of cranial nerves III, IV, VI</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gordon Holmes syndrome (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/212840">212840</ext-link>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">RNF216</italic>
<break/><italic toggle="yes">PNPLA6</italic>&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypogonadism, cerebellar ataxia, white matter lesions; no alopecia</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alopecia, neuropathy, endocrinopathy (ANE) syndrome (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/612079">612079</ext-link>)&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">RBM28</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypogonadotropic hypogonadism, alopecia, adrenal insufficiency and cognitive impairment</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hgps" document-type="chapter">Hutchinson-Gilford progeria syndrome</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">LMNA</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alopecia, aged-looking skin, joint abnormalities, loss of subcutaneous fat</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="cockayne" document-type="chapter">Cockayne syndrome</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ERCC6<break/>ERCC8</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short stature &#x00026; appearance of premature aging</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="ddon" document-type="chapter">Deafness-dystonia-optic neuronopathy syndrome</related-object> (Mohr-Tranebjaerg syndrome)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">TIMM8A</italic>&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XL</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early-onset hearing loss; movement disorder; impaired vision; behavior problems (almost exclusively in males)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nbia-ov" document-type="chapter">Neurodegeneration with brain iron storage disorders</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">PANK2</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">PLA2G6</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">C19orf12</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">FA2H</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">ATP13A2</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">COASY</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">FTL</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">CP</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR<break/>XL<break/>AD&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable phenotype: variable age of onset, dystonia w/postural instability<break/>Brain iron accumulation on MRI</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" document-type="chapter">Dystonia</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See footnote 7</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD<break/>AR<break/>XL</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable phenotype; hypogonadism &#x00026; alopecia not observed</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="deafness-overview" document-type="chapter">Deafness and hereditary hearing loss</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See footnote 8</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD<break/>AR<break/>XL<break/>mtDNA</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable phenotype w/variable age of onset; hypogonadism not a feature</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="perrault" document-type="chapter">Perrault syndrome</related-object> (PRLTS)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">HSD17B4</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">HARS2</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">CLPP</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">LARS2</italic>
                  <break/>
                  <italic toggle="yes">TWNK</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.disordersphenotypes_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterogeneous &#x00026; variable; early deafness, premature ovarian failure, weakness, spasticity</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>MOI = mode of inheritance</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AD = autosomal dominant</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AR = autosomal recessive</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>XL = X-linked</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>mtDNA = mitochondrial DNA</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="wss.TF.2.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="kms" document-type="chapter">Isolated Gonadotropin-Releasing Hormone (GnRH) Deficiency</related-object> for associated genes.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="wss.TF.2.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pnpla6-dis" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">PNPLA6</italic>-Related Disorders</related-object>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="wss.TF.2.3">
              <label>3. </label>
              <p>Only one family reported to date as per OMIM</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="wss.TF.2.4">
              <label>4. </label>
              <p>Almost all individuals with Hutchinson-Gilford progeria syndrome have the disorder as the result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> autosomal dominant pathogenic variant.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="wss.TF.2.5">
              <label>5. </label>
              <p>Deafness-dystonia-optic neuronopathy syndrome occurs as either a single-gene disorder resulting from mutation of <italic toggle="yes">TIMM8A</italic> or a contiguous gene deletion syndrome at Xq22.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="wss.TF.2.6">
              <label>6. </label>
              <p>Eight of the ten genetically defined types of neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation are inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Exceptions are: <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="bpan" document-type="chapter">beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration</related-object>, caused by <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic>, which is inherited in an X-linked manner with suspected male lethality; and neuroferritinopathy, caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">FTL</italic>, which is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="wss.TF.2.7">
              <label>7. </label>
              <p>See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" document-type="chapter">Dystonia Overview</related-object> for associated genes.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="wss.TF.2.8">
              <label>8. </label>
              <p>See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="deafness-overview" document-type="chapter">Deafness and Hereditary Hearing Loss Overview</related-object> for associated genes.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wss.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="wss.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diagno">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome (WSS), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Endocrine.</bold> Evaluation for possible endocrine findings (if not done at the time of diagnosis) relating to: hypogonadism, low IGF-1, diabetes mellitus, hypothyroidism</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Ectodermal.</bold> Assessment of scalp hair</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Neurologic</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Neurologic examination for evidence of dystonia (if not done at the time of diagnosis) (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" document-type="chapter">Dystonia Overview</related-object>)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Speech and language assessment of dysarthria and dysphagia</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Assessment of hearing (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="deafness-overview" document-type="chapter">Hereditary Hearing Loss and Deafness</related-object>)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Assessment of psychomotor development (in young children) or intellectual ability in individuals older than age six years</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Other.</bold> Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>No specific treatment exists for WSS. All treatment is symptomatic.</p>
          <sec id="wss.Endocrine_1">
            <title>Endocrine</title>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Hypogonadism.</bold> Sex hormone replacement therapy at the usual age of puberty to induce and maintain secondary sex characteristics and promote bone health</p>
                <p>Note: Standard replacement hormonal treatment will not promote fertility. It may be possible to stimulate testes with gonadotropins and harvest sperm with assisted reproductive technology.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Low IGF-1.</bold> Treatment with recombinant IGF-1 not recommended: no evidence shows that it improves the clinical features of WSS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">Agopiantz et al 2014</xref>]. Of note, IGF-1 levels may increase with sex hormone replacement therapy.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Diabetes mellitus.</bold> Standard treatment</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Hypothyroidism.</bold> L-thyroxine replacement therapy</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="wss.Ectodermal_1">
            <title>Ectodermal</title>
            <p>Treatment is symptomatic and cosmetic only.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="wss.Neurologic_1">
            <title>Neurologic</title>
            <p>
              <bold>Movement disorders</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Dystonia.</bold> Treatment is aimed at relieving symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.albanese.2015.1547">Albanese et al 2015</xref>]:</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Oral medications are usually tried first:</p>
                    <list list-type="bullet">
                      <list-item>
                        <p>Anticholinergics such as trihexyphenidyl (moderately effective for ~40%-50% of individuals)</p>
                        <p>Trihexyphenidyl can be titrated to high doses (~100 mg/day) in younger individuals.</p>
                        <p>Anticholinergic side effects, particularly cognitive effects, must be monitored closely.</p>
                      </list-item>
                      <list-item>
                        <p>Baclofen (Lioresal<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>)</p>
                      </list-item>
                      <list-item>
                        <p>Benzodiazepines, especially clonazepam</p>
                      </list-item>
                      <list-item>
                        <p>Other medications tried alone or in combination with the above categories: levodopa, carbamazepine, and dopamine depleting agents (reserpine, tetrabenazine)</p>
                      </list-item>
                    </list>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Botulinum toxin injections directly into dystonic muscles are generally the treatment of choice for adult-onset focal dystonias. For individuals with more widespread dystonia in whom specific muscle groups produce disabling symptoms, such injections may also be helpful, and are often used in combination with oral medications.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>If medications fail, surgery to enable deep-brain stimulation (DBS) of the globus pallidus interna (GPi) has been shown to be an effective treatment for some forms of medically refractory primary generalized dystonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.vidailhet.2007.223">Vidailhet et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.crowell.2016.22">Crowell &#x00026; Shah 2016</xref>]. Its use in WSS has not been documented.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Dysarthria.</bold> Consultation with a speech therapist may be helpful.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Dysphagia.</bold> Oral secretions in individuals with bulbar symptoms can be reduced with tricylic antidepressants and anticholinergic agents, thus reducing the need for suctioning. Swallowing difficulties can be alleviated by thickening liquids and pureeing solid food, as well as eventually using a gastrostomy tube to help maintain caloric intake and hydration. Nutritional management by a knowledgeable nutritionist is helpful.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Sensorineural hearing loss.</bold> See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="deafness-overview" document-type="chapter">Hereditary Hearing Loss and Deafness</related-object>.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Monitor for endocrine abnormalities:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Hypogonadism at age 12-14 years</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Diabetes mellitus in the teens and later</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hypothyroidism in the teens and later</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Neurologic manifestations should be monitored by experts in rehabilitative medicine, speech, and swallowing.</p>
          <p>Dystonia may require monitoring by a neurologist.</p>
          <p>Monitor hearing annually.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Persons with dystonia should avoid situations in which the risk of falling is increased.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing for known familial <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variants is appropriate for the evaluation of apparently asymptomatic older and younger sibs of a proband in order to identify as early as possible those who will benefit from early identification and treatment of potential complications.</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="wss.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wss.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="wss.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome (WSS) is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected individual are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variant).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> The offspring of an individual with WSS are obligate heterozygotes (carriers) for a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic>.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier of a <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Carrier_Heterozygote_Detection">
          <title>Carrier (Heterozygote) Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variants in the family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="wss.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected, are carriers, or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="wss.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantation">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for WSS are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wss.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wss.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> Alternate splicing of <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> (formerly known as <italic toggle="yes">C2orf37</italic>) results in multiple transcript variants. The longest transcript variant, NM_025000.3, has 14 exons. In comparison another major variant, NM_001164821.1, lacks two exons in the coding region for a total of 12 exons. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="wss" object-id="wss.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
        <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> Eleven different <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variants (4 small intragenic deletions, 3 nonsense and 3 splice site variants, and 1 small indel) have been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alazami.2010.585">Alazami et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.habib.2011.26">Habib et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.abdulla.2015.489">Abdulla et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.ali.2016.263">Ali et al 2016</xref>]. Pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> missense variants have not been described.</p>
        <p>Of the 23 families with molecularly confirmed WSS, only one with two compound heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variants has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.ali.2016.263">Ali et al 2016</xref>]. The remaining 22 families were homozygous for <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> pathogenic variants. Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis may be useful to confirm apparent homozygosity of a pathogenic variant detected by sequence analysis when parental DNA samples are not available.</p>
        <table-wrap id="wss.T.dcaf17_variants_discussed_in_this" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 3. </label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> Variants Discussed in This <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_wss.T.dcaf17_variants_discussed_in_this_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change</th>
                <th id="hd_h_wss.T.dcaf17_variants_discussed_in_this_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                <th id="hd_h_wss.T.dcaf17_variants_discussed_in_this_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.dcaf17_variants_discussed_in_this_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.436delC&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.dcaf17_variants_discussed_in_this_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ala147HisfsTer9</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_wss.T.dcaf17_variants_discussed_in_this_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_025000.3">NM_025000.3</ext-link>
                  <break/>
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_079276.2">NP_079276.2</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="wss.TF.3.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>This variant has the same nucleotide and protein change designations for either transcript variant <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_025000.3">NM_025000.3</ext-link> or <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001164821.1">NM_001164821.1</ext-link>.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p><bold>Normal gene product</bold>. The transcript variant <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_025000.3">NM_025000.3</ext-link> encodes DDB1- and CUL4-associated factor 17, a 520 amino-acid protein known as the &#x003b1; isoform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_079276.2">NP_079276.2</ext-link>). This is a nucleolar protein of unknown function expressed in various tissues including brain, skin, and liver &#x02013; which correlates to some extent with the multiorgan involvement in individuals with WSS. More than 30 <italic toggle="yes">DCAF17</italic> isoforms have been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="wss.REF.alazami.2008.684">Alazami et al 2008</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> The types of pathogenic variants known to result in WSS predict premature translation termination, missplicing, or nonsense-mediated decay, suggesting that WSS results from loss of DCAF17 function.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wss.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="wss.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="wss.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="wss.REF.abdulla.2015.489">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abdulla</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alazami</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alungal</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koya</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Musambil</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Novel compound heterozygous frameshift mutations of C2orf37 in a familial Indian case of Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Genet.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>94</volume>
                <fpage>489</fpage>
                <lpage>92</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26440089</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.agopiantz.2014.1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Agopiantz</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Corbonnois</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sorlin</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonnet</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Klein</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hubert</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pascal-Vigneron</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jonveaux</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cuny</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leheup</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Weryha</surname>
                    <given-names>G.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Endocrine disorders in Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome: a systematic review of the literature.</article-title>
                <source>J Endocrinol Invest.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>37</volume>
                <fpage>1</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24464444</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.alawadi.1985.619">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Awadi</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Farag</surname>
                    <given-names>TI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Teebi</surname>
                    <given-names>AS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Naguib</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>el-Khalifa</surname>
                    <given-names>MY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kelani</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Ansari</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schimke</surname>
                    <given-names>RN</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Primary hypogonadism and partial alopecia in three sibs with m&#x000fc;llerian hypoplasia in the affected females.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>1985</year>
                <volume>22</volume>
                <fpage>619</fpage>
                <lpage>22</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4061495</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.alazami.2008.684">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alazami</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Saif</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Semari</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bohlega</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zlitni</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alzahrani</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bavi</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaya</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Colak</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khalak</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baltus</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peterlin</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Danda</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schneider</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sakati</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Walsh</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Mohanna</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meyer</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alkuraya</surname>
                    <given-names>FS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in C2orf37, encoding a nucleolar protein, cause hypogonadism, alopecia, diabetes mellitus, mental retardation, and extrapyramidal syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>83</volume>
                <fpage>684</fpage>
                <lpage>91</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19026396</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.alazami.2010.585">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alazami</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schneider</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonneau</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pasquier</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carecchio</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kojovic</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steindl</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Kerdanet</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nezarati</surname>
                    <given-names>MM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Degos</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goh</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alkuraya</surname>
                    <given-names>FS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>C2orf37 mutational spectrum in Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome patients.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Genet.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>78</volume>
                <fpage>585</fpage>
                <lpage>90</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20507343</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.albanese.2015.1547">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Albanese</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Romito</surname>
                    <given-names>LM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calandrella</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Therapeutic advances in dystonia.</article-title>
                <source>Mov Disord.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>30</volume>
                <fpage>1547</fpage>
                <lpage>56</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26301801</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.ali.2016.263">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ali</surname>
                    <given-names>RH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shah</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nasir</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steyaert</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ahmad</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Exome sequencing revealed a novel biallelic deletion in the DCAF17 gene underlying Woodhouse Sakati syndrome (WSS).</article-title>
                <source>Clin Genet.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>90</volume>
                <fpage>263</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26612766</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.alsemari.2007.149">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Semari</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bohlega</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Autosomal-recessive syndrome with alopecia, hypogonadism, progressive extra-pyramidal disorder, white matter disease, sensory neural deafness, diabetes mellitus, and low IGF1.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>143A</volume>
                <fpage>149</fpage>
                <lpage>60</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17167799</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.alswailem.2006.116">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Swailem</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Assiri</surname>
                    <given-names>AA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Torbak</surname>
                    <given-names>AA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Woodhouse Sakati syndrome associated with bilateral keratoconus.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Ophthalmol.</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>90</volume>
                <fpage>116</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16361682</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.benomran.2011.2647">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ben-Omran</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ali</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Almureikhi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alameer</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Saffar</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Walsh</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Felie</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Teebi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Phenotypic heterogeneity in Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome: two new families with a mutation in the C2orf37 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>155A</volume>
                <fpage>2647</fpage>
                <lpage>53</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21964978</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.bjornstad.1965">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">Bjornstad R. Pili torti and sensory-neural loss of hearing. Paper. Copenhagen, Denmark: 17th Combined Scandavian Dermatological Association Meeting. 1965</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.crandall.1973.461">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Crandall</surname>
                    <given-names>BF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Samec</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sparkes</surname>
                    <given-names>RS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wright</surname>
                    <given-names>SW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A familial syndrome of deafness, alopecia, and hypogonadism.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>1973</year>
                <volume>82</volume>
                <fpage>461</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4698933</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.crowell.2016.22">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Crowell</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shah</surname>
                    <given-names>BB</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Surgery for dystonia and tremor.</article-title>
                <source>Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>16</volume>
                <fpage>22</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26838349</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.devriendt.1996.54">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Devriendt</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Legius</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fryns</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Progressive extrapyramidal disorder with primary hypogonadism and alopecia in sibs: a new syndrome?</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>1996</year>
                <volume>62</volume>
                <fpage>54</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8779325</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.gregory.2011.254">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gregory</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Genetics of neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation.</article-title>
                <source>Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>254</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21286947</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.g_l.2000.123">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>G&#x000fc;l</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ozata</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mergen</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Odaba&#x0015f;i</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mergen</surname>
                    <given-names>M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Woodhouse and Sakati syndrome (MIM 241080): report of a new patient.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Dysmorphol.</source>
                <year>2000</year>
                <volume>9</volume>
                <fpage>123</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10826625</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.habib.2011.26">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Habib</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Basit</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khan</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khan</surname>
                    <given-names>MN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ahmad</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A novel splice site mutation in gene C2orf37 underlying Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome (WSS) in a consanguineous family of Pakistani origin.</article-title>
                <source>Gene.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>490</volume>
                <fpage>26</fpage>
                <lpage>31</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21963443</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.hdiji.2016.120">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hdiji</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Turki</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bouzidi</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bouchhima</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Damak</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bohlega</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mhiri</surname>
                    <given-names>C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome: report of the first Tunisian family with C2orf37 gene mutation.</article-title>
                <source>J Mov Disord.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>9</volume>
                <fpage>120</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27240811</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.koshy.2008.57">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koshy</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Danda</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thomas</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mathews</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viswanathan</surname>
                    <given-names>V.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Three siblings with Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome in an Indian family.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Dysmorphol.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>17</volume>
                <fpage>57</fpage>
                <lpage>60</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18049083</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.medica.2007.227">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Medica</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sepci&#x00107;</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peterlin</surname>
                    <given-names>B.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome: case report and symptoms review.</article-title>
                <source>Genet Couns.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>18</volume>
                <fpage>227</fpage>
                <lpage>31</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17710875</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.m_garban_.2003.214">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>M&#x000e9;garban&#x000e9;</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gannag&#x000e9;-Yared</surname>
                    <given-names>MH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khalif&#x000e9;</surname>
                    <given-names>AA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fabre</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Primary hypergonadotropic hypogonadism, partial alopecia, and M&#x000fc;llerian hypoplasia: report of a second family with additional findings.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>119A</volume>
                <fpage>214</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12749067</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.nanda.2014.83">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nanda</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pasternack</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mahmoudi</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ishorst</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grimalt</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Betz</surname>
                    <given-names>RC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Alopecia and hypotrichosis as characteristic findings in Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome: report of a family with mutation in the C2orf37 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Dermatol.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>31</volume>
                <fpage>83</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24015686</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.rachmiel.2011.362">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rachmiel</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bistritzer</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hershkoviz</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khahil</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Epstein</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Parvari</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Woodhouse-Sakati syndrome in an Israeli-Arab family presenting with youth-onset diabetes mellitus and delayed puberty.</article-title>
                <source>Horm Res Paediatr.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>75</volume>
                <fpage>362</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21304230</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.schneider.2008.592">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schneider</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Dystonia in the Woodhouse Sakati syndrome: A new family and literature review.</article-title>
                <source>Mov Disord.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>23</volume>
                <fpage>592</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18175354</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.slti.1979.428">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Slti</surname>
                    <given-names>IS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Salem</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Familial hypogonadotropic hypogonadism with alopecia.</article-title>
                <source>Can Med Assoc J.</source>
                <year>1979</year>
                <volume>121</volume>
                <fpage>428</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">466617</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.steindl.2010.594">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steindl</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alazami</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wuerfel</surname>
                    <given-names>JT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Petersen</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cartolari</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Neri</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Klein</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mongiardo</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alkuraya</surname>
                    <given-names>FS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schneider</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A novel C2orf37 mutation causes the first Italian cases of Woodhouse Sakati syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Genet.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>78</volume>
                <fpage>594</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21044051</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.tatar.2009.501">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tatar</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ocak</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tatar</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yesilyurt</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Borekci</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oztas</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Primary hypogonadism, partial alopecia, and Mullerian hypoplasia: report of a third family and review.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>149A</volume>
                <fpage>501</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19213036</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.vidailhet.2007.223">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vidailhet</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vercueil</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houeto</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Krystkowiak</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lagrange</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yelnik</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bardinet</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Benabid</surname>
                    <given-names>AL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Navarro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dormont</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grand</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blond</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ardouin</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pillon</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dujardin</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hahn-Barma</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Agid</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dest&#x000e9;e</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pollak</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <collab>French SPIDY Study Group</collab>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Bilateral, pallidal, deep-brain stimulation in primary generalised dystonia: a prospective 3 year follow-up study.</article-title>
                <source>Lancet Neurol.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>6</volume>
                <fpage>223</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17303528</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="wss.REF.woodhouse.1983.216">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Woodhouse</surname>
                    <given-names>NJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sakati</surname>
                    <given-names>NA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A syndrome of hypogonadism, alopecia, diabetes mellitus, mental retardation, deafness, and ECG abnormalities.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>1983</year>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>216</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6876115</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wss.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="wss.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>4 August 2016 (bp) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>2 February 2016 (sab) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="wss.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Affected individuals from different families with WSS who have variable degrees of alopecia or hair loss and neurologic involvementA. Male age 23 with flat occiput; temporal and frontal alopecia B. Female age 19 with dystonia involving neck, face, mouth, and tongue, arms, and hands C. Female age 35 with sparse, short hair, flat occiput, low-set ears, and retrocollisD. Male age 14 with sparse hair E. Female age 25 with alopecia and wasting of the facial and temporal muscles F. Male age 17 with dystonic posturing and lack of breast tissue G. Male age 21 with sparse hair with temporal hair loss; long face H. Male age 32 with severe generalized dystonia with alopecia totalis</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="wss-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="wss.F2" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Brain MRI of individuals with WSS. Arrows indicate the following findings:A. Long TR sequence, showing increased signal intensities in the subcortical regions of the centrum semi-oval B. T<sub>2</sub>-weighted image demonstrating marked signal hypointensity of the globi pallidi bilaterallyC. T<sub>2</sub>-weighted image showing multiple white matter foci with confluent lesions affecting the short U-fibersD. T<sub>2</sub>-weighted image showing confluent white matter lesions and abnormal signal intensity of the globi pallidi</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="wss-Image002" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
