<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="xq28-dup" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">xq28-dup</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Xq28 Duplication Syndrome, Int22h1/Int22h2 Mediated</title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>El-Hattab</surname>
            <given-names>Ayman W</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, FAAP, FACMG</degrees>
          <aff>Medical Genetics and Metabolic Consultant, Division of Clinical Genetics and Metabolic Disorders<break/>Pediatric Department<break/>Tawam Hospital<break/>Al-Ain, United Arab Emirates</aff>
          <email>elhattabaw@yahoo.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Schaaf</surname>
            <given-names>Christian P</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD, FACMG</degrees>
          <aff>Assistant Professor, Department of Molecular and Human Genetics<break/>Baylor College of Medicine<break/>Houston, Texas</aff>
          <email>schaaf@bcm.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cheung</surname>
            <given-names>Sau Wai</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD, MBA, FACMG</degrees>
          <aff>Professor, Department of Molecular and Human Genetics<break/>Baylor College of Medicine<break/>Houston, Texas</aff>
          <email>scheung@bcm.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2016-03-10" date-type="created">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="xp" document-type="chapter">Xeroderma Pigmentosum</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="yci" document-type="chapter">Y Chromosome Infertility</related-object>
      <abstract id="xq28-dup.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>The int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome is a recently recognized X-linked intellectual disability syndrome characterized in males by cognitive impairment, behavioral and psychiatric problems, recurrent infections and atopic diseases, obesity, and distinctive facial features. Females heterozygous for this duplication exhibit a milder phenotype (with learning difficulties and distinctive facies) or are clinically unaffected. To date 26 individuals (14 males and 12 females) have been described with this recurrent duplication.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication is established by detection of a 0.5-Mb duplication (hemizygous in males and heterozygous in females) at chromosome Xq28 extending from 154.1 Mb to 154.6 Mb in the reference genome (NCBI Build GRCh37/hg19).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Early intervention with speech and physical therapy for young children with developmental delay; special education programs for school-aged children with intellectual disability. Recurrent bacterial infections are treated with standard antibiotics; recurrent ear infections are treated in the standard manner. Nutritional counseling and regular exercise for obese individuals. Standard management for behavioral and psychiatric problems.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> The following monitoring is recommended: assessment of developmental progress and cognitive abilities; screening for behavioral and psychiatric problems; and routine audiologic and ophthalmologic evaluations.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> Clinically asymptomatic children who have the familial duplication should be assessed and monitored for developmental delay with the goal of early initiation of therapies and support if needed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>The int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication is inherited in an X-linked manner. The father of an affected male will not have the disorder nor will he be hemizygous for this Xq28 duplication. All mothers (tested to date) of individuals with this Xq28 duplication were found to be heterozygous for the duplication. When mothers are heterozygous for this Xq28 duplication, the chance of transmission in each pregnancy is 50%: sons who inherit the duplication will be affected; daughters who inherit the duplication will be heterozygotes and may have a milder phenotype or may be clinically unaffected. Prenatal testing using genomic testing that will detect this Xq28 duplication is possible when the mother is known to be heterozygous for the duplication.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>The int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome <bold>should be suspected in males</bold> with the following clinical findings:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Cognitive impairment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Behavioral and psychiatric problems: aggressiveness, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), autism spectrum disorder, sleep disturbance, anxiety, and psychotic disorders</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recurrent respiratory infections and atopic diseases</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Obesity</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Distinctive facial features: tall forehead, upper eyelid fullness, wide nasal bridge, and thick vermilion of the lower lip (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="xq28-dup.F1">Figure 1A-E</xref>)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>The int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome <bold>should be suspected in females</bold> with the following clinical findings:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Learning difficulties</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Distinctive facial features: tall forehead, upper eyelid fullness, wide nasal bridge, and thick vermilion of the lower lip (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="xq28-dup.F1">Figure 1F-K</xref>)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication is established by detection of a 0.5-Mb duplication (hemizygous in males and heterozygous in females) at chromosome Xq28 extending from 154.1 Mb to 154.6 Mb in the reference genome (NCBI Build GRCh37/hg19).</p>
          <p>The duplicated segment extends from a low copy repeat (LCR) region located within intron 22 of <italic toggle="yes">F8</italic> (known as intron 22 homologous region 1 [int22h1]) and another LCR region situated 0.5 Mb telomeric to the int22h1 region (known as intron 22 homologous region 2 [int22h2]). This duplication is mediated by non-allelic homologous recombination between the int22h1 and int22h2 LCR regions.</p>
          <p>Note: A 0.8-Mb Xq28 duplication that overlaps with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication has been reported in individuals who shared some of the clinical findings of individuals with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Genetically_Related_Disorders">Genetically Related Disorders</xref>).</p>
          <p>The duplicated region between int22h1 and int22h2 includes several genes. The cognitive impairment in individuals with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome is likely due to increased dosage of one or more of these genes; the most likely candidates are <italic toggle="yes">CLIC2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">RAB39B</italic> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>).</p>
          <p><bold>Genomic testing methods</bold> that determine the copy number of sequences can include <bold>chromosomal microarray (CMA)</bold> or <bold>targeted duplication analysis</bold> by quantitative PCR (qPCR), multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), or other targeted quantitative methods. Although <bold>fluorescence <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH)</bold> using metaphase chromosomes is NOT reliable for detecting this duplication, it can be used to determine if the duplicated segment is inserted elsewhere in the genome (insertion translocation). Note: The int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication cannot be identified by routine analysis of G-banded chromosomes or other conventional cytogenetic banding techniques.</p>
          <p><bold>Chromosomal microarray (CMA)</bold> using oligonucleotide arrays or SNP (single nucleotide polymorphism) genotyping arrays can detect the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication. The ability to size the duplication depends on the type of microarray used and the density of probes in the Xq28 region.</p>
          <p>Note: (1) Most individuals with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication are identified by CMA performed for the indication of developmental delay or intellectual disability. (2) Prior to 2011, CMA platforms did not include coverage for this region and thus could not detect this duplication. The earlier BAC (bacterial artificial chromosome)-based arrays could not detect this duplication.</p>
          <p><bold>Targeted duplication analysis.</bold> Quantitative PCR (qPCR), multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA) or other targeted quantitative methods may be used to test relatives of a proband known to have the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication.</p>
          <p>Note: (1) Metaphase FISH is not a reliable method for detecting a duplication of this size; interphase FISH (iFISH) may be used if appropriate control studies are performed. (2) Targeted duplication testing is not appropriate for an individual in whom the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication was not detected by CMA designed to target this region. (3) It is not possible to size the duplication routinely by use of targeted methods.</p>
          <table-wrap id="xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Genomic Testing Used in Xq28 Duplication Syndrome, Int22h1/Int22h2 Mediated</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_1">Duplication&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_2">ISCA ID&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_3" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_3">Region Location&#x000a0;<sup>3,&#x000a0;4</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_4" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_4">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Test Sensitivity<hr/></th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_5" id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Proband</th>
                  <th headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_5" id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">At-risk family members</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">0.5-Mb duplication at Xq28 (hemizygous in males; heterozygous in females)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">Pending</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_3" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">GRCh37/hg19 chrX: 154,124,111-154,564,398</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMA&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup><hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_5 hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup><hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_5 hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup><hr/></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Targeted duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_5 hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not applicable&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_1_5 hd_h_xq28-dup.T.genomic_testing_used_in_xq28_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="xq28-dup.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for details of the duplication.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="xq28-dup.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>Standardized clinical annotation and interpretation for genomic variants from the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicalgenome.org/about/">Clinical Genome Resource (ClinGen) project</ext-link> (formerly the International Standards for Cytogenomic Arrays (ISCA) Consortium).</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="xq28-dup.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Genomic coordinates represent the minimum duplication size associated with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication as designated by ClinGen. Duplication coordinates may vary slightly based on array design used by the testing laboratory. Note that the size of the duplication as calculated from these genomic positions may differ from the expected duplication size due to the presence of segmental duplications near breakpoints.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="xq28-dup.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for genes of interest included in this region.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="xq28-dup.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Chromosomal microarray analysis (CMA) using oligonucleotide arrays or SNP arrays. CMA designs in current clinical use target the Xq28 region. Note: The int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication may not have been detectable by older oligonucleotide or BAC platforms.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="xq28-dup.TF.1.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">El-Hattab et al [2011]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.lannoy.2013.970">Lannoy et al [2013]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.vanmarsenille.2014.377">Vanmarsenille et al [2014]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">El-Hattab et al [2015]</xref></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="xq28-dup.TF.1.7">
                <label>7. </label>
                <p>Targeted duplication analysis methods can include: quantitative PCR (qPCR), multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA) and iFISH as well as other targeted quantitative methods. Targeted duplication analysis is not appropriate for an individual in whom the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication was not detected by CMA designed to target this region.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Evaluating at-risk relatives.</bold> qPCR, iFISH or other quantitative methods of targeted duplication analysis can be used to identify the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication in at-risk relatives of the proband. Testing of maternal samples is important in determining recurrence risk (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Genetic_Counseling">Genetic Counseling</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>The int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome is a recently recognized X-linked intellectual disability syndrome characterized in males by cognitive impairment, behavioral and psychiatric problems, recurrent infections, atopic diseases, obesity, and distinctive facial features. Females heterozygous for this duplication exhibit a milder phenotype (with learning difficulties and distinctive facies) or are clinically unaffected.</p>
          <p>To date 26 individuals (14 males and 12 females) have been described with this recurrent duplication. The clinical description below is based on the clinical phenotype described in these 26 individuals (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26">Table 2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">El-Hattab et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.lannoy.2013.970">Lannoy et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.vanmarsenille.2014.377">Vanmarsenille et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">El-Hattab et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Cognitive impairment.</bold> Cognitive impairment has been reported in all males with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication. Developmental delay is typically observed in early childhood. The majority of affected males require special education. Intellectual disability in the affected males is typically in the mild to moderate range.</p>
          <p>Females heterozygous for this duplication have milder cognitive impairment (i.e., learning difficulties in 6 of 12 affected females) or no cognitive impairment.</p>
          <p><bold>Behavioral and psychiatric problems.</bold> Behavioral problems are common in affected males; they include aggressiveness, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), autism spectrum disorder, and sleep disturbance.</p>
          <p>Only one heterozygous female was reported to have ADHD.</p>
          <p>Additionally, two males and one female were reported to have psychotic disorders including mood disorders and schizophrenia (<xref ref-type="table" rid="xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26">Table 2</xref>).</p>
          <p><bold>Recurrent infections and atopic diseases.</bold> Approximately 70% of males with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication have experienced recurrent infections including otitis media and pneumonia. Atopic diseases, including asthma, eczema, and allergic rhinitis, are also common in these males.</p>
          <p>None of the heterozygous females were reported to have recurrent infections or atopic diseases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26">Table 2</xref>).</p>
          <p><bold>Growth abnormalities.</bold> Obesity was reported in four affected males and one female heterozygous for the Xq28 duplication.</p>
          <p>Tall stature was observed in three affected males and microcephaly in one (<xref ref-type="table" rid="xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26">Table 2</xref>).</p>
          <table-wrap id="xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 2. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Clinical Manifestations in 26 Individuals with the Int22h1/Int22h2-Mediated Xq28 Duplication Syndrome</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manifestation</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males (n=14)</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females (n=12)</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Cognitive impairment</bold>
                    <hr/>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>14 (100%)</bold>
                    <hr/>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <bold>6 (50%)</bold>
                    <hr/>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Behavioral problems</bold><break/>&#x02022; Aggressiveness<break/>&#x02022; ADHD <break/>&#x02022; Autism spectrum disorder<break/>&#x02022; Sleep disturbance <break/>&#x02022; Anxiety<break/>&#x02022; Socialization difficulties<break/>&#x02022; Motor tics<break/>&#x02022; Self-mutilation<hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>9 (64%)</bold><break/>6 (43%)<break/>5 (36%)<break/>2 (14%)<break/>2 (14%)<break/>2 (14%)<break/>1 (7%)<break/>1 (7%)<break/>1 (7%)<hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1 (8%)</bold><break/>&#x02013;<break/>1 (8%)<break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;<hr/></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Psychotic disorders</bold><break/>&#x02022; Depression/bipolar<break/>&#x02022; Schizophrenia<hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2 (14%)</bold><break/>1 (7%)<break/>1 (7%)<hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1 (8%)</bold><break/>1 (8%)<break/>&#x02013;<hr/></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Recurrent infections</bold><break/>&#x02022; Otitis media <break/>&#x02022; Pneumonia<break/>&#x02022; Upper respiratory tract infections<hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10 (71%)</bold><break/>8 (57%)<break/>4 (29%)<break/>1 (7%)<hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02013;</bold><break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;<hr/></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Atopic diseases</bold><break/>&#x02022; Asthma<break/>&#x02022; Allergic rhinitis<break/>&#x02022; Eczema<hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6 (43%)</bold><break/>5 (36%)<break/>4 (29%)<break/>1 (7%)<hr/></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02013;</bold><break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;<hr/></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Growth abnormalities</bold><break/>&#x02022; Obesity<break/>&#x02022; Tall stature<break/>&#x02022; Microcephaly</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6 (43%)</bold><break/>4 (29%)<break/>3 (21%)<break/>1 (7%)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_xq28-dup.T.clinical_manifestations_in_26_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1 (8%)</bold><break/>1 (8%)<break/>&#x02013;<break/>&#x02013;</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">El-Hattab et al [2011]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.lannoy.2013.970">Lannoy et al [2013]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.vanmarsenille.2014.377">Vanmarsenille et al [2014]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">El-Hattab et al [2015]</xref></p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Characteristic facial features.</bold> The most common facial features in both males and females are listed in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Diagnosis">Diagnosis</xref> and represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="xq28-dup.F1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
          <p>Less common facial features are listed in <inline-supplementary-material xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="media" xlink:href="xq28-dup-Table3.pdf" content-type="local-data">Table 3</inline-supplementary-material> (pdf).</p>
          <p><bold>Other infrequent manifestations.</bold> Hand and foot anomalies have been infrequently observed in males with this duplication. Clinodactyly was reported twice; single palmar crease, fetal finger pads, rocker bottom feet, pes valgus, pes planus, metatarsus adductus, sandal gap, 2-3 toe syndactyly, short second toe, and short heel cords were each reported once in a male with this duplication.</p>
          <p>Hearing loss was reported in one affected boy.</p>
          <p>Strabismus, myopia, and astigmatism were each reported once in a male with this duplication.</p>
          <p>Patent ductus arteriosus (PDA), atrial septal defect (ASD), esophageal atresia with tracheoesophageal fistula, Pierre Robin sequence with cleft palate, cryptorchidism, phimosis, hip dysplasia, kyphoscoliosis, and polyhydramnios were each reported once in an affected male.</p>
          <p>Hemihyperplasia, hypothyroidism, and kyphoscoliosis were each reported once in a heterozygous female.</p>
          <p><bold>X-chromosome inactivation in heterozygous females.</bold> X-chromosome inactivation analyses were reported to be skewed in nine of 12 females heterozygous for the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication; however, skewing of X-chromosome inactivation was inconsistent; that is, it was observed with the normal X chromosome and the X chromosome with the duplication. Additionally, no clear correlation between the X-chromosome inactivation pattern and the cognitive phenotypes was evident: random and skewed patterns occurred in both cognitively normal and cognitively impaired females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">El-Hattab et al 2015</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>Int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome is completely penetrant for cognitive impairment in males.</p>
          <p>Cognitive impairment is incompletely penetrant in females heterozygous for this duplication with only 50% reported to have learning difficulties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">El-Hattab et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.lannoy.2013.970">Lannoy et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.vanmarsenille.2014.377">Vanmarsenille et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">El-Hattab et al 2015</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>Int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication has been reported in 26 individuals (14 males and 12 females) to date [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">El-Hattab et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.lannoy.2013.970">Lannoy et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.vanmarsenille.2014.377">Vanmarsenille et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">El-Hattab et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p>The prevalence of this duplication is not known, but has been estimated at 1:1000 among males with intellectual disability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.vanmarsenille.2014.377">Vanmarsenille et al 2014</xref>]; this may, however, be an overestimate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.Genetically_Related_Disorders">
        <title>Genetically Related Disorders</title>
        <p><bold>Other Xq28 duplications.</bold> Three sibs were reported to have a 0.8-Mb Xq28 duplication that extends from 154.4 to 155.2 Mb, overlapping the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication and including the genes <italic toggle="yes">RAB39B</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CLIC2</italic>. These sibs showed some of the features observed in individuals with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome, including cognitive impairment, distinctive facial features (tall forehead, upper-eyelid fullness, wide nasal bridge, thick vermilion of the lower lip), and behavioral problems (autism spectrum disorder, aggressiveness, and ADHD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.andersen.2014.1795">Andersen et al 2014</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold>The reciprocal int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 deletion</bold> has been reported in five females who exhibited skewed X-chromosome inactivation patterns and normal cognition. It has been suggested that this deletion does not have phenotypic effects in females due to inactivation of the X chromosome with the deletion. However, this deletion can be embryonic lethal in males, which can result in higher miscarriage rates in females heterozygous for this deletion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">El-Hattab et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">El-Hattab et al 2015</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mecp2-dup" document-type="chapter"><bold><italic toggle="yes">MECP2 </italic>duplication syndrome</bold></related-object> is a severe neurodevelopmental disorder characterized by infantile hypotonia, delayed psychomotor development leading to severe intellectual disability, poor speech development, progressive spasticity, recurrent respiratory infections, seizures, autistic behaviors, and gastrointestinal dysfunction. Inheritance is X-linked with complete penetrance in males.</p>
        <p>Occasionally females have been described with a <italic toggle="yes">MECP2</italic> duplication and related clinical findings, often associated with concomitant X-chromosomal abnormalities that prevent inactivation of the duplicated region.</p>
        <p>This syndrome is caused by duplications in chromosome Xq28 that include <italic toggle="yes">MECP2</italic> (153.3 Mb) and range from 0.3 to 4 Mb. In contrast, the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome is caused by 0.5-Mb duplication in Xq28 located telomeric to the <italic toggle="yes">MECP2</italic> locus and extending from 154.1 to 154.6 Mb. Cognitive impairment and recurrent infections are common in both syndromes. However, infantile hypotonia, spasticity, and seizures have not been observed in int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome.</p>
        <p><bold>Other.</bold> Differential diagnosis also includes different forms of syndromic X-linked intellectual disability and nonsyndromic X-linked intellectual disability; see OMIM Phenotypic Series: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/phenotypicSeries/PS309510">Mental retardation, X-linked syndromic</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/phenotypicSeries/PS309530">Mental retardation, X-linked nonsyndromic</ext-link> to view genes associated with these phenotypes in OMIM.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Evaluations_Following_Initial_D">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Review of medical history for behavioral and psychiatric problems, recurrent infections, and atopic diseases</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Comprehensive physical examination with emphasis on growth parameters, hands and feet, and possible kyphoscoliosis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Neuropsychological evaluation to assess level of cognitive functioning and for any behavioral problems</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Psychiatric evaluation if psychiatric illness is suspected</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Echocardiogram</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Audiologic evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ophthalmologic examination</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Spine x-ray and orthopedic evaluation if kyphoscoliosis is present</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Nutritional evaluation and counseling if obesity is present</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Early intervention with speech and physical therapy is recommended for young children with developmental delay. Special education programs are subsequently recommended for school-aged children with intellectual disability.</p>
          <p>Recurrent bacterial infections are treated with standard antibiotics. Children with recurrent ear infections should be referred to ENT to assess need for tympanostomy tubes.</p>
          <p>Nutritional counseling and regular exercise are needed when obesity is an issue.</p>
          <p>Standard management is recommended for the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Behavioral and psychiatric problems</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Kyphoscoliosis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Cardiac malformations</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hearing impairment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Eye problems</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>The following routine monitoring is recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of developmental progress and cognitive abilities</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Screening for behavioral and psychiatric problems</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Audiology evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ophthalmologic evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>It is appropriate to clarify the genetic status of apparently asymptomatic children who are relatives of an affected individual by genomic testing for the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication. Clinically asymptomatic children who have the familial duplication should be assessed and monitored for developmental delay with the goal of early initiation of therapies and support if needed.</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issu">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>The int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication is inherited in an X-linked manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The father of an affected male will not have the disorder nor will he be hemizygous for the Xq28 duplication; therefore, he does not require further evaluation/testing.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>All mothers (tested to date) of individuals with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication were found to be heterozygous for the duplication.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In a family with more than one affected individual, the mother of an affected individual is an obligate heterozygote.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In a family with one affected individual (i.e., a simplex case), the mother may be heterozygous for the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication or the affected male may have a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> duplication, in which case the mother is not heterozygous; however, <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplications have not been reported to date.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Testing of maternal samples is important in determining recurrence risk. Evaluation of the mother by genomic testing that will detect the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication present in the proband is recommended.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> The risk to sibs depends on the genetic status of the mother:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>If the mother of the proband has the Xq28 duplication, the chance of transmission in each pregnancy is 50%.</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Males who inherit the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication will be affected.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Females who inherit the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication will be heterozygotes and may have a milder phenotype or may be clinically unaffected (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Clinical_Description">Clinical Description</xref>).</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the proband represents a simplex case (i.e., a single occurrence in a family) and if the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of the mother, the risk to sibs is low but greater than that of the general population because of the possibility of maternal germline mosaicism. However, all mothers (tested to date) of probands with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication were found to be heterozygous for the duplication.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a male proband.</bold> No affected male has been reported to reproduce.</p>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a female proband.</bold> Women with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication have a 50% chance of transmitting the duplication to each child:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Males who inherit the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication will be affected.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Females who inherit the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication will be heterozygotes and may have a milder phenotype or may be clinically unaffected (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Clinical_Description">Clinical Description</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> The risk to other family members depends on the genetic status of the proband&#x02019;s mother. If the mother has the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication, her family members may also have the duplication.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issu">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="xq28-dup.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy. Similarly, decisions about testing to determine the genetic status of family members are best made before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are at risk of having a child with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplant">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p><bold>Pregnancies known to be at increased risk for the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication.</bold> Once the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for a pregnancy at increased risk are possible options.</p>
          <p><bold>Pregnancies not known to be at increased risk for int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication.</bold> Chromosomal microarray (CMA) performed in a pregnancy not known to be at increased risk may detect this duplication.</p>
          <p>Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions about prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>The int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication breakpoints are localized to the directly oriented LCRs int22h1 (located within intron 22 of <italic toggle="yes">F8</italic>) and int22h2 (situated 0.5 Mb telomerically to int22h1). The duplication is mediated by nonallelic homologous recombination between int22h1and int22h2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">El-Hattab et al 2011</xref>]. A third homologous region, int22h3, is located 0.6 Mb telomerically to int22h1. No duplications using the int22h3, which is in opposite orientation to int22h1, have been observed.</p>
          <p>Genomic inversions between int22h1 and either int22h2 or int22h3 are known to disrupt <italic toggle="yes">F8</italic> in nearly half of individuals with severe <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hemo-a" document-type="chapter">hemophilia A</related-object> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.bagnall.2005.2598">Bagnall et al 2005</xref>]. However, int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication does not result in hemophilia A because a complete copy of <italic toggle="yes">F8</italic> is preserved after formation of this duplication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">El-Hattab et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p>The 0.5-Mb duplicated region between int22h1 and int22h2 includes several genes. The cognitive impairment in individuals with the int22h1/int22h2- mediated Xq28 duplication syndrome is likely due to increased dosage of one or more of these genes; the most likely candidates are <italic toggle="yes">RAB39B</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">CLIC2</italic> (see following) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">El-Hattab et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Genes of interest in this region</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">CLIC2</italic></bold> encodes chloride intracellular channel 2 (CLIC2) protein that functions as an intrinsic stabilizer of ryanodine receptors (RyR); therefore, it can modulate calcium signaling through the regulation of RyR channel activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.meng.2009.320">Meng et al 2009</xref>]. A missense pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">CLIC2</italic> was reported in two brothers with cognitive impairment, seizures, and cardiac anomalies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.takano.2012.4497">Takano et al 2012</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">RAB39B</italic></bold> encodes a member of the Rab protein family, which are small GTPases involved in intracellular signaling proteins that coordinate vesicle trafficking during a variety of cellular processes, including neuronal development and signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.ng.2008.236">Ng &#x00026; Tang 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.stenmark.2009.513">Stenmark 2009</xref>]. Loss of-function pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">RAB39B</italic> were identified in families with X-linked intellectual disability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.giannandrea.2010.185">Giannandrea et al 2010</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">RAB39B</italic> overexpression was found in two individuals with the int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication. Overexpression of <italic toggle="yes">Rab39b</italic> in mouse primary hippocampal neurons results in decreased neuronal branching and synapse number, suggesting that the increased dosage of <italic toggle="yes">RAB39B</italic> disturbs neuronal development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.vanmarsenille.2014.377">Vanmarsenille et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="xq28-dup.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.andersen.2014.1795">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Andersen</surname>
                    <given-names>EF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baldwin</surname>
                    <given-names>EE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ellingwood</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lamb</surname>
                    <given-names>AN</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Xq28 duplication overlapping the int22h-1/int22h-2 region and including RAB39B and CLIC2 in a family with intellectual and developmental disability.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>164A</volume>
                <fpage>1795</fpage>
                <lpage>801</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24700761</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.bagnall.2005.2598">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bagnall</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Giannelli</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Green</surname>
                    <given-names>PM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Polymorphism and hemophilia A causing inversions in distal Xq28: a complex picture.</article-title>
                <source>J Thromb Haemost.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>3</volume>
                <fpage>2598</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16241967</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>El-Hattab</surname>
                    <given-names>AW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fang</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jin</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hughes</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gibson</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patel</surname>
                    <given-names>GS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grange</surname>
                    <given-names>DK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Manwaring</surname>
                    <given-names>LP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patel</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stankiewicz</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cheung</surname>
                    <given-names>SW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Int22h-1/int22h-2-mediated Xq28 rearrangements: intellectual disability associated with duplications and in utero male lethality with deletions.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>48</volume>
                <fpage>840</fpage>
                <lpage>50</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21984752</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>El-Hattab</surname>
                    <given-names>AW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaaf</surname>
                    <given-names>CP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fang</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roeder</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kimonis</surname>
                    <given-names>VE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Church</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patel</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cheung</surname>
                    <given-names>SW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Clinical characterization of int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication/deletion: new cases and literature review.</article-title>
                <source>BMC Med Genet.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>16</volume>
                <fpage>12</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25927380</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.giannandrea.2010.185">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Giannandrea</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bianchi</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mignogna</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sirri</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrabino</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>D'Elia</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vecellio</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Russo</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cogliati</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Larizza</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ropers</surname>
                    <given-names>HH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tzschach</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kalscheuer</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oehl-Jaschkowitz</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Skinner</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schwartz</surname>
                    <given-names>CE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gecz</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Esch</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raynaud</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chelly</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Brouwer</surname>
                    <given-names>AP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Toniolo</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>D'Adamo</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in the small GTPase gene RAB39B are responsible for X-linked mental retardation associated with autism, epilepsy, and macrocephaly.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>86</volume>
                <fpage>185</fpage>
                <lpage>95</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20159109</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.lannoy.2013.970">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lannoy</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grisart</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eeckhoudt</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Verellen-Dumoulin</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lambert</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vikkula</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hermans</surname>
                    <given-names>C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Intron 22 homologous regions are implicated in exons 1-22 duplications of the F8 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>21</volume>
                <fpage>970</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23299923</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.meng.2009.320">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meng</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viero</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mi</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Su</surname>
                    <given-names>XD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wagenknecht</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yin</surname>
                    <given-names>CC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>CLIC2-RyR1 interaction and structural characterization by cryo-electron microscopy.</article-title>
                <source>J Mol Biol.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>387</volume>
                <fpage>320</fpage>
                <lpage>34</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19356589</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.ng.2008.236">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ng</surname>
                    <given-names>EL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tang</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Rab GTPases and their roles in brain neurons and glia.</article-title>
                <source>Brain Res Rev.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>58</volume>
                <fpage>236</fpage>
                <lpage>46</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18485483</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.stenmark.2009.513">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stenmark</surname>
                    <given-names>H.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Rab GTPases as coordinators of vesicle traffic.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>513</fpage>
                <lpage>25</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19603039</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.takano.2012.4497">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takano</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tarpey</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallant</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lam</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Witham</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alexov</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chaubey</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stevenson</surname>
                    <given-names>RE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schwartz</surname>
                    <given-names>CE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Board</surname>
                    <given-names>PG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dulhunty</surname>
                    <given-names>AF</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>An X-linked channelopathy with cardiomegaly due to a CLIC2 mutation enhancing ryanodine receptor channel activity.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>21</volume>
                <fpage>4497</fpage>
                <lpage>507</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22814392</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="xq28-dup.REF.vanmarsenille.2014.377">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vanmarsenille</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Giannandrea</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fieremans</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Verbeeck</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Belet</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raynaud</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vogels</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>M&#x000e4;nnik</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>&#x000d5;unap</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jacqueline</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Briault</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Esch</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>D'Adamo</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Froyen</surname>
                    <given-names>G.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Increased dosage of RAB39B affects neuronal development and could explain the cognitive impairment in male patients with distal Xq28 copy number gains.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>35</volume>
                <fpage>377</fpage>
                <lpage>83</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24357492</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="xq28-dup.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="xq28-dup.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>10 March 2016 (bp) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>31 July 2015 (aweh) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="xq28-dup.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Facial features of males (A-E) and females (F-K) with int22h1/int22h2-mediated Xq28 duplication. &#x02022;&#x000a0;A and B are brothers ages 11 and 3 years, respectively. &#x02022;&#x000a0;C, D, and E are ages 3 years, 15 years, and 9 months, respectively. &#x02022;&#x000a0;F, G, and H are sisters ages 4, 6, and 8 years, respectively. &#x02022;&#x000a0;I, J, and K are ages 32, 25, and 47 years respectively. Note the tall forehead, upper eyelid fullness, wide nasal bridge, and thick vermilion of the lower lip in most of these individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2011.840">El-Hattab et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="xq28-dup.REF.elhattab.2015.12">El-Hattab et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="xq28-dup-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
