<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="dfna2" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">dfna2</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>DFNA2 Nonsyndromic Hearing Loss</title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>Richard JH</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Director, Molecular Otolaryngology Research Laboratories <break/>Sterba Hearing Research Professor of Otolaryngology <break/>Professor of Otolaryngology, Pediatrics, and Internal Medicine, Division of Nephrology <break/>Carver College of Medicine <break/>University of Iowa<break/>Iowa City, Iowa</aff>
          <email>richard-smith@uiowa.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hildebrand</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Department of Medicine <break/>University of Melbourne<break/>Melbourne, Australia</aff>
          <email>michael.hildebrand@unimelb.edu.au</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="depdc5-epilepsy" document-type="chapter">
<italic toggle="yes">DEPDC5</italic>-Related Epilepsy</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="dfnx1" document-type="chapter">DFNX1 Nonsyndromic Hearing Loss and Deafness</related-object>
      <abstract id="dfna2.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss is characterized by symmetric, predominantly high-frequency sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL) that is progressive across all frequencies. At younger ages, hearing loss tends to be mild in the low frequencies and moderate in the high frequencies; in older persons, the hearing loss is moderate in the low frequencies and severe to profound in the high frequencies. Although the hearing impairment is often detected during routine hearing assessment of a school-age child, it is likely that hearing is impaired from birth, especially at high frequencies. Most affected persons initially require hearing aids to assist with sound amplification between ages ten and 40 years. By age 70 years, all persons with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss have severe-to-profound hearing impairment.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss is established in an individual with a characteristic audioprofile, a family history consistent with autosomal dominant inheritance, and identification of a deafness-related variant in <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Hearing aids for those with mild-to-moderate hearing loss; consideration of cochlear implants when hearing loss is severe to profound; special assistance in school for hearing-impaired children and adolescents.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> At least annual audiogram to follow progression of hearing loss.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Avoiding exposure to loud noise may reduce the rate of progression of high-frequency SNHL.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> Determining in infancy or early childhood whether a family member of the proband has inherited a deafness-related variant in <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> allows early support and management of the child and family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Most individuals with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss have a parent with hearing loss; the proportion of individuals with a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> deafness-related variant is unknown. Each child of an individual with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss has a 50% chance of inheriting the deafness-related variant. Prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk is possible if the <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> deafness-related variant has been identified in a family member.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="dfna2.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="dfna2.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss <bold>should be suspected</bold> in an individual with:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Symmetric, predominantly high-frequency sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL) that is progressive across all frequencies:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>At younger ages, hearing loss tends to be mild in the low frequencies and moderate in the high frequencies.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>In older persons, the hearing loss is moderate in the low frequencies and severe to profound in the high frequencies.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Normal physical examination</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Family history of hearing loss consistent with autosomal dominant inheritance</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Temporal bone imaging (i.e., CT of the inner ears) is normal. Specifically, abnormalities such as dilation of the vestibular aqueducts (also known as enlarged vestibular aqueducts) and Mondini dysplasia should be absent.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with the above characteristic audioprofile and identification of a heterozygous deafness-related variant in <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> on molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold>, use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>, and <bold>more comprehensive</bold>
<bold>genomic testing</bold>.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> is performed first followed by gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis if no deafness-related variant is found.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfna2.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.kothiyal.2010.10">Kothiyal et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.shearer.2010.21104">Shearer et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.shearer.2015.175">Shearer &#x00026; Smith 2015</xref>]. Note: The genes included and sensitivity of multi-gene panels vary by laboratory and over time.</p>
              <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>More comprehensive genomic testing</bold> (when available) including exome sequencing, mitochondrial sequencing, and genome sequencing may be considered if single-gene testing (and/or use of a multi-gene panel that includes <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic>) fails to confirm a diagnosis in an individual with features of DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss. For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in DFNA2 Nonsyndromic Hearing Loss</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Deafness-Related Variant&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="dfna2.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dfna2" object-id="dfna2.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfna2.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfna2.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfna2.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely deafness-related, or deafness related. Deafness-related variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfna2.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects deafness-related variants in <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> in virtually all individuals with autosomal dominant nonsyndromic sensorineural hearing loss that maps to the DFNA2 locus.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfna2.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used can include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfna2.TF.1.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>No data on detection rate of gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis are available.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfna2.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="dfna2.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>All families with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss have symmetric, predominantly high-frequency hearing loss that is progressive across all frequencies. A comprehensive review of the clinical presentation and prognosis of individuals diagnosed with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss has been provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002a.41">De Leenheer et al [2002a]</xref>.</p>
          <p>Onset of hearing loss is generally reported in early childhood or adolescence; however, it is likely that hearing is impaired from birth, especially at the high frequencies. The hearing loss is often detected during standard hearing assessment of a school-age child or less frequently during the evaluation of a child for delayed speech development.</p>
          <p>In all affected individuals the hearing loss is more severe at the high frequencies, resulting in a characteristic downsloping audioprofile with hearing thresholds between 50 and 90 dB at 500 Hz and between 90 and 120 dB at 2 kHz and 4 kHz by age 50 years. A typical audiogram of an adolescent with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="dfna2.F1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
          <p>Whereas onset age varies within families, deterioration of annual thresholds for families with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss has been calculated at a relatively uniform ~1 dB/year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.coucke.1999.1321">Coucke et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.talebizadeh.1999.493">Talebizadeh et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.ensink.2000.62">Ensink et al 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.van_hauwe.2000.184">Van Hauwe et al 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.akita.2001.355">Akita et al 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002a.41">De Leenheer et al 2002a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002b.267">De Leenheer et al 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.van_camp.2002.15">Van Camp et al 2002</xref>]. Most persons with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss are first fitted with hearing aids to assist with sound amplification between ages ten and 40 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002a.41">De Leenheer et al 2002a</xref>]. By age 70 years, all persons with hearing loss attributed to a deafness-related variant in <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> have severe-to-profound hearing loss.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Other findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Vestibular function.</bold> Thirty percent of individuals in two families with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss (Dutch families 1 and 4; <xref ref-type="table" rid="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v">Table 3</xref>) had increased vestibulo-ocular reflex activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.marres.1997.573">Marres et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002b.267">De Leenheer et al 2002b</xref>]. Vestibular problems have not been observed in any other families with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Speech recognition scores.</bold> When measured in several Dutch families, speech recognition scores were relatively good given the pure-tone thresholds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002b.267">De Leenheer et al 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.van_camp.2002.15">Van Camp et al 2002</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>The phenotype associated with <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> deafness-related missense variants is similar in all families: predominantly high-frequency sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL) that is detectable in childhood and progressive across all frequencies. At younger ages, hearing loss tends to be mild in the low frequencies and moderate in the high frequencies. In older persons, the hearing loss is moderate in the low frequencies and severe to profound in the high frequencies.</p>
          <p>The phenotype associated with <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> truncating variants differs from that associated with <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> deafness-related missense variants. In two families, small frameshift deletions of <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v">c.211_223del</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v">c.211delC</xref>) are predicted to result in a profoundly truncated protein that either does not interact with normal protein translated from the normal allele or may not remain in cells as a result of nonsense-mediated decay. The hearing loss associated with this dosage effect is milder in low and mid-frequencies, more severe in high frequencies, and later in onset than the hearing loss seen with deafness-related missense variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.coucke.1999.1321">Coucke et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.akita.2001.355">Akita et al 2001</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>The penetrance is complete. All individuals with a <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> deafness-related variant exhibit the hearing loss phenotype; onset age and severity are variable.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>No data on prevalence of DFNA2 among families segregating autosomal dominant nonsyndromic hearing loss (ADNSHL) are available. Anecdotally, however, deafness-related variants in <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> are thought to account for up to 5% of ADNSHL [R Smith, personal communication].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfna2.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disord">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with deafness-related variants in <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfna2.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="deafness-overview" document-type="chapter">Deafness and Hereditary Hearing Loss Overview</related-object> for complete differential diagnosis.</p>
        <p>Because variants in <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> are a relatively common cause of high-frequency autosomal dominant nonsyndromic hearing loss (ADNSHL), <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> should be among the first genes tested in families with this type of hearing impairment.</p>
        <p>Variants in the following genes also cause high-frequency ADNSHL:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">GJB3</italic> (<related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dfna3" document-type="chapter">DFNA3</related-object>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">COCH</italic> (DFNA9)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">POU4F3</italic> (DFNA15)</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfna2.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="dfna2.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diag">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of hearing loss and needs in an individual diagnosed with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss, the following are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Audiometry, including bone conduction testing</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>When hearing loss is mild to moderate, fitting of hearing aids to provide improved amplification is warranted.</p>
          <p>When the hearing loss becomes severe to profound, cochlear implants (CIs) can be considered. In individuals with preserved or relatively good low-frequency hearing and severe-to-profound high-frequency loss, a short electrode may be considered. Short electrodes boost the high frequencies while preserving residual low-frequency hearing.</p>
          <p>For school-age children or adolescents, special assistance for the hearing impaired may be warranted and, where available, should be offered.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Audiograms should be obtained on an annual basis to follow progression of hearing loss.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>The rate of progression of high-frequency hearing loss can be reduced by encouraging individuals with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss to avoid exposure to loud noise in the workplace and during recreation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>Determining in infancy or early childhood whether a relative of a person with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss has inherited the <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> deafness-related variant allows for early support and management of the child and the family.</p>
          <p>Evaluations may include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic testing if the deafness-related <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> variant in the family is known.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Audiometry and sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4,</italic> or a multi-gene panel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.kothiyal.2010.10">Kothiyal et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.shearer.2010.21104">Shearer et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.shearer.2015.175">Shearer &#x00026; Smith 2015</xref>] that includes <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> if the deafness-related variant in the family is not known.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfna2.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this condition.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfna2.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="dfna2.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Most individuals diagnosed with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss have a deaf parent.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A proband with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss may have deafness as the result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> variant. The proportion of individuals with a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> deafness-related variant is unknown.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the deafness-related variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, two possible explanations are a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> deafness-related variant in the proband or germline mosaicism in a parent. Although no instances of germline mosaicism have been reported, it remains a possibility.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recommendations for the evaluation of parents of a proband with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> deafness-related variant include audiometry and molecular genetic testing. Evaluation of parents may determine that one has hearing loss but has escaped previous diagnosis because of a milder phenotypic presentation. Therefore, an apparently negative family history cannot be confirmed until appropriate evaluations have been performed.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: (1) Although most individuals diagnosed with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss have a deaf parent, in addition to failure to recognize hearing loss in family members, the family history may appear to be negative because of early death of the parent before the onset of hearing loss or late onset of hearing loss in a parent. (2) If the parent is the individual in whom the deafness-related variant first occurred, s/he may have somatic mosaicism for the deafness-related variant and have mild hearing loss.</p>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> The probability that the sibs of the proband will be deaf depends on the genetic status of the proband's parents:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband is deaf, each sib has a 50% chance of being deaf.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When the parents are hearing, the probability that a sib of the proband will be deaf appears to be low.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the deafness-related variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, the probability that a sib will be deaf is low, but greater than that of the general population because of the possibility of germline mosaicism.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Each child of an individual with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss has a 50% chance of inheriting the deafness-related variant.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members of a proband.</bold> The probability of deafness in other family members depends on the status of the proband's parents: if a parent is deaf, his or her family members may also be deaf or develop deafness.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfna2.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating relatives of a proband for the purpose of early diagnosis and management.</p>
          <p>The following points are noteworthy:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Communication with individuals who are members of the Deaf community and sign requires the services of a skilled interpreter.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Members of the Deaf community may view deafness as a distinguishing characteristic and not as a handicap, impairment, or medical condition requiring a "treatment" or "cure," or to be "prevented."</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Many deaf people are interested in obtaining information about the cause of their own deafness, including information on medical, educational, and social services, rather than information about prevention, reproduction, or family planning.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The use of certain terms is preferred: probability or chance versus risk; deaf and hard-of-hearing versus hearing impaired. Terms such as "abnormal" should be avoided.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Considerations in families with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> variant.</bold> When neither parent of a proband with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss has the deafness-related variant or clinical evidence of deafness, it is likely that the proband has a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> variant. However, possible non-medical explanations could be explored including alternate paternity or maternity (i.e., with assisted reproduction) or undisclosed adoption.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic status and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of the probability that offspring will be deaf and reproductive options) to young adults who have DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and deafness will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of individuals with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantati">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> deafness-related variant has been identified in a family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss are possible.</p>
          <p>Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions about prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfna2.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfna2.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <p>
          <bold>
            <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic>
          </bold>
        </p>
        <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> has a transcript length of 2,335 base pairs. The transcript consists of 14 exons. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dfna2" object-id="dfna2.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
        <p><bold>Variants of uncertain clinical significance.</bold> Two variants that result in synonymous amino acid changes are of uncertain clinical significance (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer">Table 2</xref>). These nucleotide variants were detected on a screen of 185 individuals with nonsyndromic hearing loss. These individuals were reported as having nonsyndromic hearing loss; no information regarding family history was provided.</p>
        <table-wrap id="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Selected <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> Variants of Uncertain Clinical Significance</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change<break/>(Alias&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup>)</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein Domain</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Onset of Symptoms&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.648C&#x0003e;T</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.=&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup><break/>(Arg216Arg)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S4 transmembrane domain</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_4" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">Taiwanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_5" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_6" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.su.2007.20">Su et al [2007]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1503C&#x0003e;T</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.=&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup><break/>(Thr501Thr)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_variants_of_uncer_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal to S6 transmembrane domain</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dfna2.TF.2.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>Variant designation that does not conform to current naming conventions</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dfna2.TF.2.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>Pathology was high-frequency hearing impairment and tissue-specific expression was in cochlear outer hair cells and brain for all deafness-related variants described in the table.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dfna2.TF.2.3">
              <label>3. </label>
              <p>For these variants, "p.=" indicates that no effect on protein level is expected.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> Most deafness-related variants cluster in exons 5, 6, and 7 of <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic>. These exons encode highly conserved amino acid sequences that form the channel pore. The predominant deafness-related variants are missense variants that induce a dominant-negative effect. The p.Trp276Ser deafness-related variant appears to be most common and has been identified in four unrelated families, including three of five Dutch families with DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v">Table 3</xref>). The fourth family is Japanese. Congenital onset of DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss has been reported in one of the Dutch families with the p.Trp276Ser variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002b.267">De Leenheer et al 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.van_camp.2002.15">Van Camp et al 2002</xref>], but not in other families with this deafness-related variant. The high-frequency hearing loss in this family was progressive without substantial loss of speech recognition during the first decades of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002b.267">De Leenheer et al 2002b</xref>].</p>
        <table-wrap id="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 3. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Selected <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> Deafness-Related Variants</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change<break/>(Alias&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup>)</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein Amino Acid Change <break/>(Alias&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup>)</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein Domain</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Onset of Symptoms&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                <th id="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.211_223del13<break/>(211del13)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gln71ProfsTer64 <break/>(Q71fsTer134)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-terminal cytoplasmic</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgian</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adolescence</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.coucke.1999.1321">Coucke et al [1999]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.211delC</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gln71SerfsTer68 <break/>(FS71)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-terminal cytoplasmic</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adolescence</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.kamada.2006.455">Kamada et al [2006]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.ishikawa.2014.557">Ishikawa et al [2014]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.228_229dupGC</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.His77ArgfsTer63</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-terminal cytoplasmic</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.naito.2013.e63231">Naito et al [2013]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.546C&#x0003e;G</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Phe182Leu</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S3 transmembrane domain</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taiwanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.su.2007.20">Su et al [2007]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.667_684del18<break/>(664_681del)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Thr223_Gly228del<break/>(Gly222_Leu227del)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intra-membrane loop</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korean</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.baek.2011.536">Baek et al [2011]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.689T&#x0003e;A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Val230Glu</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S4-S5 linker</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.naito.2013.e63231">Naito et al [2013]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.778G&#x0003e;A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Glu260Lys</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S5 transmembrane domain</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.hildebrand.2008.797">Hildebrand et al [2008]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.785A&#x0003e;T</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Asp262Val</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S5 transmembrane domain</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.hildebrand.2008.797">Hildebrand et al [2008]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.725G&#x0003e;A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Trp242Ter</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S5 transmembrane domain</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.hildebrand.2008.797">Hildebrand et al [2008]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">c.806_808delCCT</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">p.Ser269del</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">Between S5 domain and pore helix</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canadian</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.abdelfatah.2013.1112">Abdelfatah et al [2013]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adulthood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.watabe.2013.475">Watabe et al [2013]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.808T&#x0003e;C</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Tyr270His</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pore helix</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congenital</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.namba.2012.145">Namba et al [2012]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.821T&#x0003e;A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Leu274His</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-loop</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dutch</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.van_hauwe.2000.184">Van Hauwe et al [2000]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.de_heer.2011.243">de Heer et al [2011]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.823T&#x0003e;C</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Trp275Arg</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-loop</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Han Chinese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.wang.2014.e103133">Wang et al [2014]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.827G&#x0003e;C</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Trp276Ser</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-loop</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dutch, Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.coucke.1999.1321">Coucke et al [1999]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.van_camp.2002.15">Van Camp et al [2002]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.topsakal.2005.52">Topsakal et al [2005]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.842T&#x0003e;C</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Leu281Ser</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-loop</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.talebizadeh.1999.493">Talebizadeh et al [1999]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.853G&#x0003e;T</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly285Cys</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-loop</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.coucke.1999.1321">Coucke et al [1999]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.853G&#x0003e;A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly285Ser</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-loop</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Northern European, Han Chinese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.kubisch.1999.437">Kubisch et al [1999]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.wang.2014.e103133">Wang et al [2014]</xref></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.859G&#x0003e;C</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly287Arg</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-loop</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.arnett.2011.54">Arnett et al [2011]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.871C&#x0003e;T</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Pro291Ser</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Channel pore</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adulthood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.naito.2013.e63231">Naito et al [2013]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.872C&#x0003e;T</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Pro291Leu</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Channel pore</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adolescence</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.naito.2013.e63231">Naito et al [2013]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.886G&#x0003e;A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly296Ser</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Channel pore</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spanish</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.menc_a.2008.41">Menc&#x000ed;a et al [2008]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.891G&#x0003e;T</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg297Ser</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S6 transmembrane domain</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.naito.2013.e63231">Naito et al [2013]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.961G&#x0003e;A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly321Ser</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S6 transmembrane domain</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dutch</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.coucke.1999.1321">Coucke et al [1999]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1044_1051del8</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ala349ProfsTer19</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-terminal cytoplasmic</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.wasano.2015.582">Wasano et al [2015]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.2039C&#x0003e;T</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ser680Phe</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C-terminal cytoplasmic</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Han Chinese</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.wu.2013.e57369">Wu et al [2013]</xref>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Reference sequences for <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic>: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_004700.2">NM_004700.2</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/viewer.fcgi?db=protein&#x00026;id=26638653">NP_004691.2</ext-link></p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dfna2.TF.3.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>Variant designation that does not conform to current naming conventions</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dfna2.TF.3.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>Pathology was high-frequency hearing impairment and tissue-specific expression was in cochlear outer hair cells and brain for all deafness-related variants described in the table.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The protein encoded by <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> is 695 amino acids in length. The protein forms a potassium channel that consists of six transmembrane domains and a P-loop region that forms the channel pore. A highly conserved glycine-tyrosine-glycine (GYG) signature sequence within the P-loop comprises the selectivity filter that provides discrimination of potassium ions for selective transport [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.kubisch.1999.437">Kubisch et al 1999</xref>]. Deafness-related variants have been shown to cluster in the channel pore region and some directly affect this selectivity filter (i.e., <xref ref-type="table" rid="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v">p.Gly285Ser</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v">p.Gly285Cys</xref>).</p>
        <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Most deafness-related <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> variants are missense alterations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="dfna2.T.selected_kcnq4_deafnessrelated_v">Table 3</xref>) that cause hearing loss via a dominant-negative effect. These alleles are typically associated with progressive hearing loss with childhood or adolescent onset. Initially, high frequencies are predominately affected; later in life, hearing loss can become severe to profound across all frequencies. The phenotype reflects the consequence of defective KCNQ4 protein in the inner ear. This protein assembles as a tetramer to form a potassium channel made of four subunits. In a person with a deafness-related missense variant in one allele, half of the total amount of encoded protein is defective and consequently only one of every 16 channels comprises four normal protein subunits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.kubisch.1999.437">Kubisch et al 1999</xref>]. Over time the result is hypothesized to be progressive loss in potassium recycling in the inner ear. Because potassium ions are crucial for hair cell transduction, the inability to recycle these ions results in hearing loss. These deafness-related variants affect amino acids located within or close to the channel pore. The presence of an abnormal protein subunit interferes with the assembly and/or function of the tetrameric channel protein in the inner ear. Some DFNA2-causing variants in <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> are deletions that result in haploinsufficiency. As a result, cells of the inner ear produce insufficient functional KCNQ4 protein and over time auditory function is compromised.</p>
        <p><bold>Evidence for locus heterogeneity.</bold> Initial reports of <italic toggle="yes">GJB3</italic> (encoding gap junction protein &#x003b2;-3, or connexin 31) variants as causative of DFNA2 nonsyndromic hearing loss have not been substantiated. No additional families with DFNA2 caused by <italic toggle="yes">GJB3</italic> variants have been reported since the original Chinese families in 1998.</p>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">GJB3</italic> was suggested as a deafness-associated gene at the DFNA2 locus based on two different <italic toggle="yes">GJB3</italic> sequence variants identified in two small Chinese families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfna2.REF.xia.1998.370">Xia et al 1998</xref>]. Individuals from both families had bilateral sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL) characterized by a gently downsloping audiogram from normal hearing thresholds below 1,000 Hz to a moderate hearing loss in the high frequencies.</p>
        <p>However, the evidence associating the <italic toggle="yes">GJB3</italic> variants with the hearing loss is neither substantial nor convincing:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>In both families, other individuals with normal hearing had the reported deafness-related variants, a finding inconsistent with complete penetrance, which is observed in virtually all types of autosomal dominant SNHL.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>It is doubtful that <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> deafness-related variants have been excluded in these two families reported in 1998, as <italic toggle="yes">KCNQ4</italic> deafness-related variants were not implicated in autosomal dominant SNHL until 1999.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>No other families with autosomal dominant SNHL have been reported to segregate <italic toggle="yes">GJB3</italic> deafness-related variants.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Specific deafness-related variants in <italic toggle="yes">GJB3</italic> cause erythrokeratodermia variabilis.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfna2.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="dfna2.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="dfna2.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.abdelfatah.2013.1112">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abdelfatah</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McComiskey</surname>
                    <given-names>DA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Doucette</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Griffin</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moore</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Negrijn</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hodgkinson</surname>
                    <given-names>KA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>King</surname>
                    <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Larijani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houston</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stanton</surname>
                    <given-names>SG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Young</surname>
                    <given-names>TL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2013</year>
                <article-title>Identification of a novel in-frame deletion in KCNQ4 (DFNA2A) and evidence of multiple phenocopies of unknown origin in a family with ADSNHL.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>21</volume>
                <fpage>1112</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23443030</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.akita.2001.355">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Akita</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abe</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shinkawa</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kimberling</surname>
                    <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Usami</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>Clinical and genetic features of nonsyndromic autosomal dominant sensorineural hearing loss: KCNQ4 is a gene responsible in Japanese.</article-title>
                <source>J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>46</volume>
                <fpage>355</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11450843</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.arnett.2011.54">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arnett</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Emery</surname>
                    <given-names>SB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kim</surname>
                    <given-names>TB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boerst</surname>
                    <given-names>AK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leal</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lesperance</surname>
                    <given-names>MM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Autosomal dominant progressive sensorineural hearing loss due to a novel mutation in the KCNQ4 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>
                <volume>137</volume>
                <fpage>54</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21242547</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.baek.2011.536">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baek</surname>
                    <given-names>JI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Park</surname>
                    <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Park</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Choi</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>KY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yi</surname>
                    <given-names>JH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Friedman</surname>
                    <given-names>TB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Drayna</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shin</surname>
                    <given-names>KS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kim</surname>
                    <given-names>UK</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Pathogenic effects of a novel mutation (c.664_681del) in KCNQ4 channels associated with auditory pathology.</article-title>
                <source>Biochim Biophys Acta.</source>
                <volume>1812</volume>
                <fpage>536</fpage>
                <lpage>43</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20832469</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.coucke.1999.1321">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Hauwe</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kelley</surname>
                    <given-names>PM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kunst</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schatteman</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Velzen</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meyers</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ensink</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Verstreken</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Declau</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marres</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kastury</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhasin</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McGuirt</surname>
                    <given-names>WT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>CW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van de Heyning</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Willems</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>SD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Camp</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in the KCNQ4 gene are responsible for autosomal dominant deafness in four DFNA2 families.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>1321</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10369879</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.de_heer.2011.243">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Heer</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schraders</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oostrik</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoefsloot</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>CW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Audioprofile-directed successful mutation analysis in a DFNA2/KCNQ4 (p.Leu274His) family.</article-title>
                <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
                <volume>120</volume>
                <fpage>243</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21585154</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002a.41">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Leenheer</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ensink</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kunst</surname>
                    <given-names>HP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marres</surname>
                    <given-names>HA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Talebizadeh</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Declau</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>SD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Usami</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van de Heyning</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Camp</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>CW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002a</year>
                <article-title>DFNA2/KCNQ4 and its manifestations.</article-title>
                <source>Adv Otorhinolaryngol</source>
                <volume>61</volume>
                <fpage>41</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12408061</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.de_leenheer.2002b.267">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Leenheer</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Admiraal</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Camp</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>CW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002b</year>
                <article-title>Longitudinal and cross-sectional phenotype analysis in a new, large Dutch DFNA2/KCNQ4 family.</article-title>
                <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
                <volume>111</volume>
                <fpage>267</fpage>
                <lpage>74</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11915881</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.ensink.2000.62">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ensink</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Hauwe</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>CW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Camp</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>A Dutch family with progressive sensorineural hearing impairment linked to the DFNA2 region.</article-title>
                <source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source>
                <volume>257</volume>
                <fpage>62</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10784363</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.hildebrand.2008.797">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hildebrand</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tack</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McMordie</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DeLuca</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hur</surname>
                    <given-names>IA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishimura</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Casavant</surname>
                    <given-names>TL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Audioprofile-directed screening identifies novel mutations in KCNQ4 causing hearing loss at the DFNA2 locus.</article-title>
                <source>Genet Med</source>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>797</fpage>
                <lpage>804</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18941426</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.ishikawa.2014.557">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ishikawa</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Naito</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishio</surname>
                    <given-names>SY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iwasa</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakamura</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Usami</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ichimura</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>A Japanese family showing high-frequency hearing loss with KCNQ4 and TECTA mutations.</article-title>
                <source>Acta Otolaryngol</source>
                <volume>134</volume>
                <fpage>557</fpage>
                <lpage>63</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24655070</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.kamada.2006.455">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kamada</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kure</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kudo</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Suzuki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oshima</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ichinohe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kojima</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Niihori</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kanno</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Narumi</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Narisawa</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kato</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aoki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ikeda</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsubara</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>A novel KCNQ4 one-base deletion in a large pedigree with hearing loss: implication for the genotype-phenotype correlation.</article-title>
                <source>J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>51</volume>
                <fpage>455</fpage>
                <lpage>60</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16596322</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.kothiyal.2010.10">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kothiyal</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cox</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ebert</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Husami</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kenna</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Greinwald</surname>
                    <given-names>JH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aronow</surname>
                    <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rehm</surname>
                    <given-names>HL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010</year>
                <article-title>High-throughput detection of mutations responsible for childhood hearing loss using resequencing microarrays.</article-title>
                <source>BMC Biotechnol</source>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>10</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20146813</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.kubisch.1999.437">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kubisch</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schroeder</surname>
                    <given-names>BC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Friedrich</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lutjohann</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>El-Amraoui</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marlin</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Petit</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jentsch</surname>
                    <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>KCNQ4, a novel potassium channel expressed in sensory outer hair cells, is mutated in dominant deafness.</article-title>
                <source>Cell</source>
                <volume>96</volume>
                <fpage>437</fpage>
                <lpage>46</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10025409</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.marres.1997.573">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marres</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Ewijk</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kunst</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Camp</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Willems</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>Inherited nonsyndromic hearing loss. An audiovestibular study in a large family with autosomal dominant progressive hearing loss related to DFNA2.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>
                <volume>123</volume>
                <fpage>573</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9193215</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.menc_a.2008.41">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Menc&#x000ed;a</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gonzalez-Nieto</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Modamio-Hoybjor</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Etxeberria</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aranguez</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Salvador</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Del Castillo</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Villarroel</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moreno</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barrio</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moreno-Pelayo</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>A novel KCNQ4 pore-region mutation (p.G296S) causes deafness by impairing cell-surface channel expression.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>123</volume>
                <fpage>41</fpage>
                <lpage>53</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18030493</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.naito.2013.e63231">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Naito</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishio</surname>
                    <given-names>SY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iwasa</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yano</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kumakawa</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abe</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ishikawa</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kojima</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Namba</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oshikawa</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Usami</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Comprehensive genetic screening of KCNQ4 in a large autosomal dominant nonsyndromic hearing loss cohort: genotype-phenotype correlations and a founder mutation.</article-title>
                <source>PLoS One</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>e63231</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23717403</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.namba.2012.145">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Namba</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mutai</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaneko</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hashimoto</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsunaga</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>In silico modeling of the pore region of a KCNQ4 missense mutant from a patient with hearing loss.</article-title>
                <source>BMC Res Notes</source>
                <volume>5</volume>
                <fpage>145</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22420747</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.shearer.2010.21104">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shearer</surname>
                    <given-names>AE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DeLuca</surname>
                    <given-names>AP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hildebrand</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>KR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gurrola</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                    <suffix>2nd</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scherer</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scheetz</surname>
                    <given-names>TE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010</year>
                <article-title>Comprehensive genetic testing for hereditary hearing loss using massively parallel sequencing.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                <volume>107</volume>
                <fpage>21104</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21078986</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.shearer.2015.175">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shearer</surname>
                    <given-names>AE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2015</year>
                <article-title>Massively Parallel Sequencing for Genetic Diagnosis of Hearing Loss: The New Standard of Care.</article-title>
                <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>
                <volume>153</volume>
                <fpage>175</fpage>
                <lpage>82</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26084827</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.su.2007.20">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Su</surname>
                    <given-names>CC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shieh</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Su</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>SY</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Identification of novel mutations in the KCNQ4 gene of patients with nonsyndromic deafness from Taiwan.</article-title>
                <source>Audiol Neurootol</source>
                <volume>12</volume>
                <fpage>20</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17033161</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.talebizadeh.1999.493">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Talebizadeh</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kelley</surname>
                    <given-names>PM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Askew</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beisel</surname>
                    <given-names>KW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>SD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Novel mutation in the KCNQ4 gene in a large kindred with dominant progressive hearing loss.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat</source>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>493</fpage>
                <lpage>501</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10571947</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.topsakal.2005.52">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Topsakal</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pennings</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>te Brinke</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kremer</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>CW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Phenotype determination guides swift genotyping of a DFNA2/KCNQ4 family with a hot spot mutation (W276S).</article-title>
                <source>Otol Neurotol</source>
                <volume>26</volume>
                <fpage>52</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15699719</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.van_camp.2002.15">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Camp</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Akita</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fransen</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abe</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Leenheer</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>CW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Usami</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>A mutational hot spot in the KCNQ4 gene responsible for autosomal dominant hearing impairment.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat</source>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>15</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12112653</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.van_hauwe.2000.184">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Hauwe</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ensink</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huygen</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>CW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Camp</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in the KCNQ4 K+ channel gene, responsible for autosomal dominant hearing loss, cluster in the channel pore region.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>93</volume>
                <fpage>184</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10925378</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.wang.2014.e103133">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhao</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yi</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gao</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lan</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Guan</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yin</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Han</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhao</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zong</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Xiong</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yu</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Song</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yi</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Petit</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>Targeted high-throughput sequencing identifies pathogenic mutations in KCNQ4 in two large Chinese families with autosomal dominant hearing loss.</article-title>
                <source>PLoS One</source>
                <volume>9</volume>
                <fpage>e103133</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25116015</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.wasano.2015.582">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wasano</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mutai</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Obuchi</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Masuda</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsunaga</surname>
                    <given-names>T.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A novel frameshift mutation in KCNQ4 in a family with autosomal recessive non-syndromic hearing loss.</article-title>
                <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>463</volume>
                <fpage>582</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26036578</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.watabe.2013.475">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Watabe</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsunaga</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Namba</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mutai</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Inoue</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ogawa</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2013</year>
                <article-title>Moderate hearing loss associated with a novel KCNQ4 non-truncating mutation located near the N-terminus of the pore helix.</article-title>
                <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>432</volume>
                <fpage>475</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23399560</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.wu.2013.e57369">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wu</surname>
                    <given-names>CC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lin</surname>
                    <given-names>YH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lu</surname>
                    <given-names>YC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>WS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hsu</surname>
                    <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2013</year>
                <article-title>Application of massively parallel sequencing to genetic diagnosis in multiplex families with idiopathic sensorineural hearing impairment.</article-title>
                <source>PLoS One</source>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>e57369</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23451214</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.xia.1998.370">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Xia</surname>
                    <given-names>JH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>CY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tang</surname>
                    <given-names>BS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pan</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dai</surname>
                    <given-names>HP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>BR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Xie</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hu</surname>
                    <given-names>DX</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zheng</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shi</surname>
                    <given-names>XL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>DA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Xia</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yu</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liao</surname>
                    <given-names>XD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feng</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>YF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Xiao</surname>
                    <given-names>JY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Xie</surname>
                    <given-names>DH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>JZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in the gene encoding gap junction protein beta-3 associated with autosomal dominant hearing impairment.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>370</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843210</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Suggested_Reading">
          <title>Suggested Reading</title>
          <ref-list id="dfna2.Suggested_Reading.reflist0">
            <ref id="dfna2.REF.petit">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Petit C, Levilliers J, Marlin S, Hardelin J. Hereditary hearing loss. In: Valle D, Beaudet AL, Vogelstein B, Kinzler KW, Antonarakis SE, Ballabio A, Gibson K, Mitchell G, eds. <italic toggle="yes">The Online Metabolic and Molecular Bases of Inherited Disease (OMMBID)</italic>. New York, NY: McGraw-Hill. Chap 254. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ommbid.mhmedical.com/">online</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfna2.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="dfna2.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medicine.uiowa.edu/morl/">Molecular Otolaryngology Research Laboratories home page</ext-link>
          </p>
          <p>
            <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hereditaryhearingloss.org/">Hereditary Hearing Loss home page</ext-link>
          </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfna2.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>20 August 2015 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>20 June 2013 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>17 February 2011 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>4 April 2008 (me) Review posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>19 December 2007 (rjhs) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="dfna2.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Audiogram from a 12-year-old with DFNA2 hearing loss Note that the loss is greater in the high frequencies. With time, hearing at all frequencies progressively deteriorates.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="dfna2-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
