<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="dld-def" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">dld-def</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Dihydrolipoamide Dehydrogenase Deficiency</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: DLD Deficiency, E3 Deficiency, Lipoamide Dehydrogenase Deficiency</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Quinonez</surname>
            <given-names>Shane C</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Clinical Lecturer <break/>University of Michigan<break/>Ann Arbor, Michigan</aff>
          <email>squinon@med.umich.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Thoene</surname>
            <given-names>Jess G</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Active Emeritus Professor of Pediatrics<break/>Director, Biochemical Genetics Laboratory<break/>University of Michigan<break/>Ann Arbor, Michigan</aff>
          <email>jthoene@med.umich.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2014-07-17" date-type="created">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="diastrophic-d" document-type="chapter">Diastrophic Dysplasia</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="dcm-ov" document-type="chapter">Dilated Cardiomyopathy Overview</related-object>
      <abstract id="dld-def.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>The phenotypes of dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency are an overlapping continuum that ranges from early-onset neurologic manifestations to adult-onset isolated liver involvement. Early-onset DLD deficiency typically manifests as a hypotonic infant with lactic acidosis. Affected infants frequently do not survive their initial metabolic decompensation, or die within the first few years of life during a recurrent metabolic decompensation. Children who live beyond the first two to three years frequently exhibit growth deficiencies and residual neurologic deficits (intellectual disability, spasticity, ataxia, and seizures). In contrast, isolated liver involvement can present as early as the neonatal period and as late as the third decade. Evidence of liver injury/failure is preceded by nausea and emesis and frequently associated with encephalopathy and/or coagulopathy. Acute metabolic episodes are frequently associated with lactate elevations, hyperammonemia, and hepatomegaly. With resolution of the acute episodes patients frequently return to baseline with no residual neurologic deficit or intellectual disability. Liver failure can result in death, even in those with late-onset disease.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of DLD deficiency is suspected in a proband with a characteristic clinical history and biochemical evidence of defective function of three mitochondrial enzyme complexes (branched chain alpha-ketoacid dehydrogenase [BCKDH] complex, &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase [&#x003b1;KGDH] complex, and pyruvate dehydrogenase [PDH] complex). These may manifest as lactic acidosis, elevated &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate in the urine, the presence of branched chain keto-acids in the urine, elevated plasma levels of branched chain amino acids (leucine, isoleucine, and valine), and the presence of allo-isoleucine in plasma. Of note, these biochemical changes may be absent or intermittent. The diagnosis is confirmed by the presence of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Management of DLD deficiency is difficult due to the various metabolic pathways involved. Management of the early-onset neurologic presentation relies on empiric treatment of the three isolated enzyme complex deficiencies (none of which appear to significantly alter the natural history of the disease):</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>BCKDH complex deficiency: dietary leucine restriction, BCAA-free medical foods, judicious supplementation with isoleucine and valine, and frequent clinical and biochemical monitoring;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>&#x003b1;KGDH complex: very rare, no recommendations available;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>PDH complex: ketogenic diet (due to defective carbohydrate oxidation), trial of dichloroacetate (DCA), and thiamine supplementation.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Management of the primarily hepatic presentation typically involves supportive therapy during times of acute liver injury or failure, including nutritional support, IV glucose for hypoglycemia, correction of metabolic acidosis, correction of coagulopathy, and avoidance of liver-toxic medications.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of primary manifestations:</italic> No compelling evidence exists for the prevention of acute episodes, despite multiple attempted dietary strategies and medications.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Routine monitoring of growth and development; plasma amino acid levels (to guide dietary management). For those receiving DCA, monitoring for the development of peripheral neuropathy.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Fasting, catabolic stressors, liver-toxic medications.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> If the <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> pathogenic variants in an affected proband are known, at-risk sibs should undergo molecular genetic testing prenatally or as soon as possible after birth so that those who have inherited both pathogenic variants can receive appropriate interventions and avoid risk factors that may precipitate an acute event.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>DLD deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Carrier testing for at-risk relatives and prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk are possible if the <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> pathogenic variants in the family are known.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="dld-def.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) functions as the E3 subunit of three mitochondrial enzyme complexes: branched chain alpha-ketoacid dehydrogenase (BCKDH) complex, &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase (&#x003b1;KGDH) complex, and pyruvate dehydrogenase (PDH) complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.chuang.2014">Chuang et al 2014</xref>]. Of note, although DLD also functions as the L protein of the glycine cleavage system, pathogenic variants of <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> do not appear to date to impair the function of this system in vivo.</p>
        <p>The phenotypic spectrum of DLD deficiency includes an early-onset neurologic presentation, a primarily hepatic presentation, and a mild myopathic presentation (seen in one patient).</p>
        <p>No formal diagnostic criteria have been established for dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency.</p>
        <p>
          <bold>The diagnosis of dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency is suspected in individuals with the following presentations:</bold>
        </p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Neurologic (early-onset hypotonia, lethargy, and emesis)</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>In untreated infants, manifestations progress to deepening encephalopathy (lethargy, tone abnormalities, feeding difficulties, decreased level of alertness, and occasionally seizures) and eventual death.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Those who survive the first years of life frequently display neurologic impairment.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Abnormal laboratory findings typically associated with the neurologic presentation include the following:</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Metabolic acidosis: Arterial pH &#x0003c;7.35 or venous pH &#x0003c;7.32 and serum bicarbonate &#x0003c;22 mmol/L in children and adults or &#x0003c;17 mmol/L in neonates</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Elevated plasma concentration of lactate: &#x0003e;2.2 mmol/L</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Hypoglycemia: &#x0003c;40 mg/dL (&#x0003c;2.2 mmol/L)</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Hepatic (recurrent liver injury/failure frequently preceded by nausea and emesis)</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Liver injury can range from isolated elevated transaminases to fulminant hepatic failure and death.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Age of onset ranges from the neonatal period to the third decade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.barak.1998.482">Barak et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">Brassier et al 2013</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Patients with the hepatic form typically have normal intellect with no residual neurologic deficit between acute metabolic episodes unless neurologic damage has occurred.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Myopathic. The one patient with this mild phenotype exhibited ptosis, weakness, and elevated plasma creatine kinase and lactate levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quintana.2010.s315">Quintana et al 2010</xref>].</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Elevated citrulline on newborn screening (NBS) dried blood spot. Two symptomatic infants with DLD deficiency had an elevated citrulline level on dried blood spot testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.haviv.2014.243">Haviv et al 2014</xref>]. Note that newborn screening has failed to identify asymptomatic individuals with DLD deficiency when either dried blood spot citrulline or leucine is used as a primary screening analyte.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>
          <bold>The diagnosis of dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency is established in a proband with:</bold>
        </p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>A clinical history consistent with DLD deficiency (see preceding section).</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Biochemical evidence of defective BCKDH, &#x003b1;KGDH, or PDH function:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Lactic acidosis (plasma lactate &#x0003e;2.2 mmol/L and arterial pH &#x0003c;7.35)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Elevated urine &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate levels (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld">Table 1</xref>)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Presence of branched chain keto-acids in urine</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Elevated branched chain amino acids (leucine, isoleucine, and valine) in plasma and the presence of allo-isoleucine in plasma (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld">Table 1</xref>). Note: Individuals with an early-onset or hepatic presentation only occasionally have biochemical evidence of dysfunctional branched chain amino acid (BCAA) metabolism (i.e., elevations of allo-isoleucine and branched chain ketoacids; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld">Table 1</xref>), making leucine an unreliable marker for screening.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>The presence of either biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t">Table 2</xref>) or decreased DLD enzymatic activity in fibroblasts, lymphocytes, or liver tissue if molecular genetic testing is not available or is not definitive.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <table-wrap id="dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Table 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Metabolic Abnormalities in DLD Deficiency by Presentation</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_1">Metabolite</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Presentation</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_3" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_3">Normal</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Neurologic</th>
                <th headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatic</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma lactate</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_1" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;2.2 &#x000b5;mol/L</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal to elevated</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typically normal</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neonates: 4-524 mmol/mol creatinine<break/>Children: 36-117 mmol/mol creatinine<break/>Adults: 4-74 mmol/mol creatinine</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine branched chain keto-acids&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent to elevated</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typically absent</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neonates&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup>: &#x0003c;7 mmol/mol creatinine<break/>All other ages: not detectable</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma leucine&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal to elevated</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typically normal</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infants: 46-147 &#x000b5;mol/L<break/>Children: 30-246 &#x000b5;mol/L<break/>Adolescents-adults: 86-206 &#x000b5;mol/L</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma isoleucine&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal to elevated</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typically normal</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infants: 12-77 &#x000b5;mol/L<break/>Children: 6-122 &#x000b5;mol/L<break/>Adolescents-adults: 34-106 &#x000b5;mol</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma valine&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal to elevated</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typically normal</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infants: 79-217 &#x000b5;mol/L<break/>Children: 132-480 &#x000b5;mol/L<break/>Adolescents-adults: 155-343 &#x000b5;mol</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma allo-isoleucine</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal to elevated</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_2 hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typically normal</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;5 &#x000b5;mol/L&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.1.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hoffmann.2002">Hoffmann &#x00026; Feyh [2002]</xref>
              </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.1.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>2-oxoisocaproate and 2-oxo-3-methylvalerate; 2-oxoisovalerate detectable only in premature infants</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.1.3">
              <label>3. </label>
              <p>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shih.2002">Shih [2002]</xref>
              </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.1.4">
              <label>4. </label>
              <p>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.schadewaldt.1999.1734">Schadewaldt et al [1999]</xref>
              </p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Table 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Dihydrolipoamide Dehydrogenase Deficiency</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with Pathogenic Variants Detectable by This Method</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39/40 (98%)&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Targeted analysis for pathogenic variants&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_t_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See footnote 7</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.2.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dld-def" object-id="dld-def.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dld-def.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.2.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.2.3">
              <label>3. </label>
              <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.liu.1993.5186">Liu et al [1993]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.1996.1925">Hong et al [1996]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.1997.160">Hong et al [1997]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al [1999]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shany.1999.163">Shany et al [1999]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cerna.2001.1319">Cerna et al [2001]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.grafakou.2003.714">Grafakou et al [2003]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.2003.816">Hong et al [2003]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.odi_vre.2005.323">Odi&#x000e8;vre et al [2005]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cameron.2006.1542">Cameron et al [2006]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.sansaricq.2006.203">Sansaricq et al [2006]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quintana.2010.s315">Quintana et al [2010]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">Brassier et al [2013]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quinonez.2013.67">Quinonez et al [2013]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.haviv.2014.243">Haviv et al [2014]</xref></p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.2.4">
              <label>4. </label>
              <p>Testing that identifies exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications not detectable by sequence analysis of the coding and flanking intronic regions of genomic DNA. Included in the variety of methods that may be used are: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and chromosomal microarray (CMA) that includes this gene/chromosome segment.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.2.5">
              <label>5. </label>
              <p>No deletions or duplications involving <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> have been reported to cause dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.2.6">
              <label>6. </label>
              <p>Variant panels may differ by laboratory.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="dld-def.TF.2.7">
              <label>7. </label>
              <p>The <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus">c.685G&#x0003e;T</xref> (p.Gly229Cys) pathogenic variant is common in Ashkenazi Jews (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dld-def.Prevalence">Prevalence</xref>).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dld-def.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="dld-def.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>As part of three mitochondrial enzyme complexes (branched chain alpha-ketoacid dehydrogenase complex, &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase complex, and pyruvate dehydrogenase complex), dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) functions as the E3 subunit responsible for the reoxidation of the reduced lipoyl moiety of the E2 subunit.</p>
          <p>Persons with dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency exhibit variable phenotypic and biochemical consequences based on the three affected enzyme complexes. Although the spectrum of disease ranges from early-onset neurologic manifestations to isolated adult-onset liver involvement, it is a continuum and differentiation between the two major presentations can occasionally be difficult.</p>
          <p><bold>Early-onset neurologic presentation.</bold> The most frequent clinical picture in early-onset DLD deficiency is that of a hypotonic infant with lactic acidosis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu">Table 3</xref>). Affected infants frequently do not survive their initial metabolic decompensation or die within the first one to two years of life during a recurrent metabolic decompensation. Children who live beyond the first two to three years frequently exhibit growth deficiencies and residual neurologic deficits including intellectual disability, spasticity (hypertonia and/or hyperreflexia), ataxia, and seizures. Of note, normal intellectual functioning has been reported in individuals with early-onset disease with compound heterozygosity for the <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus">c.685G&#x0003e;T</xref> (p.Gly229Cys) pathogenic variant and an additional pathogenic allele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>].</p>
          <p>Hepatomegaly and liver dysfunction/failure (elevated transaminases, synthetic failure) occur in individuals with an early-onset neurologic picture and can occasionally be a cause of death (<xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu">Table 3</xref>).</p>
          <p>Similar to other inborn errors of metabolism, DLD deficiency is associated with recurrent episodes of metabolic decompensation typically triggered by illness/fever, surgery, fasting, or diet (high in fats and/or protein). Owing to the variability in each individual&#x02019;s biochemical phenotype, some patients have experienced worsening of clinical status with high-fat diets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.robinson.1981.35">Robinson et al 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.1997.160">Hong et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">Brassier et al 2013</xref>], while others have achieved metabolic control with ketogenic diets (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dld-def.Management">Management</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cerna.2001.1319">Cerna et al 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.grafakou.2003.714">Grafakou et al 2003</xref>].</p>
          <p>Liver biopsies have shown increased glycogen content and mild fibrosis or fatty, acute necrosis with a Reye syndrome-like appearance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.grafakou.2003.714">Grafakou et al 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cameron.2006.1542">Cameron et al 2006</xref>]. Between acute episodes both liver size and transaminase levels can return to normal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.sansaricq.2006.203">Sansaricq et al 2006</xref>].</p>
          <p>Other findings of the early-onset neurologic presentation include the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Leigh syndrome phenotype</bold>, identified in at least six patients with DLD deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quinonez.2013.67">Quinonez et al 2013</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Cardiac dysfunction,</bold> reported with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy in two patients and &#x0201c;myocardial dysfunction&#x0201d; in one [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shany.1999.163">Shany et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.odi_vre.2005.323">Odi&#x000e8;vre et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cameron.2006.1542">Cameron et al 2006</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Hyperammonemia</bold> (&#x02264;250 &#x000b5;mol/L), observed at the time of initial presentation although typically associated with various degrees of hepatic injury/failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quinonez.2013.67">Quinonez et al 2013</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Vision impairment/optic atrophy</bold> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.robinson.1977.1198">Robinson et al 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.1997.160">Hong et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shany.1999.163">Shany et al 1999</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Features of the Early-onset Neurologic Phenotype</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Disease Features</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" rowspan="13" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Clinical presentation&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypotonia</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Developmental delay</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Emesis</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Hepatomegaly</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Lethargy</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Seizures</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Spasticity (hypertonia and/or hyperreflexia)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Leigh syndrome phenotype</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Failure to thrive</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Microcephaly</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Vision impairment</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Ataxia</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Cardiac involvement</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" rowspan="11" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Laboratory abnormalities</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic acidosis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Elevated plasma lactate&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Elevated urine &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Hypoglycemia&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Elevated plasma BCAA&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Elevated transaminases</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Elevated urine branched chain keto-acids&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Hepatic failure</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Elevated plasma allo-isoleucine&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Low free plasma carnitine&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Hyperammonemia&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/23</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Only patients biochemically confirmed to have DLD deficiency included</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>BCAA = branched chain amino acids</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.3.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.robinson.1977.1198">Robinson et al [1977]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.robinson.1981.35">Robinson et al [1981]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.munnich.1982.167">Munnich et al [1982]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.kuhara.1983.133">Kuhara et al [1983]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.matalon.1984.65">Matalon et al [1984]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.bonnefont.1992.255">Bonnefont et al [1992]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.liu.1993.5186">Liu et al [1993]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1995.72">Elpeleg et al [1995]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.craigen.1996.69">Craigen [1996]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.1996.1925">Hong et al [1996]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1997b.256">Elpeleg et al [1997b]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.1997.160">Hong et al [1997]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al [1999]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shany.1999.163">Shany et al [1999]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cerna.2001.1319">Cerna et al [2001]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.grafakou.2003.714">Grafakou et al [2003]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.2003.816">Hong et al [2003]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.odi_vre.2005.323">Odi&#x000e8;vre et al [2005]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cameron.2006.1542">Cameron et al [2006]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.sansaricq.2006.203">Sansaricq et al [2006]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quinonez.2013.67">Quinonez et al [2013]</xref></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.3.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>Later physical examination and neurologic findings are likely underrepresented as children with an early-onset presentation frequently die in their first year(s) of life.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.3.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Arterial pH &#x0003c;7.35 or venous pH &#x0003c;7.32; serum bicarbonate &#x0003c;22 mmol/L in infants, children, and adults; or &#x0003c;17 mmol/L in neonates</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.3.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld">Table 1</xref>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.3.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Glucose &#x0003c;40 mg/dL</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.3.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>Carnitine (free) &#x0003c;38&#x000b1;22 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.millington.2002">Millington 2002</xref>]</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.3.7">
                <label>7. </label>
                <p>Ammonia &#x0003e;100 &#x000b5;mol/L in neonates or &#x0003e;60 &#x000b5;mol/L in infants, children, and adults</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Hepatic presentation.</bold> Patients with a primarily hepatic presentation can develop signs and symptoms as early as the neonatal period and as late as the third decade of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.barak.1998.482">Barak et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">Brassier et al 2013</xref>]. Evidence of liver injury/failure (<xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat">Table 4</xref>) is preceded by nausea and emesis and frequently associated with encephalopathy and/or coagulopathy. Liver failure as a cause of death has been reported in multiple patients, including those who presented later in life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1997a.238">Elpeleg et al 1997a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>].</p>
          <p>Acute metabolic episodes are frequently associated with lactate elevations, hyperammonemia, and hepatomegaly. With resolution of the acute episodes (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dld-def.Management">Management</xref>) patients may return to baseline with normal transaminases, coagulation parameters, mental status, and no residual neurologic deficit or intellectual disability.</p>
          <p>Affected individuals frequently experience lifelong recurrent attacks of hepatopathy that decrease with age. Attacks are often precipitated by catabolism, intercurrent illness/fever, and dietary extremes. These patients additionally are more susceptible to hepatotropic viruses (e.g., Epstein-Barr virus) and medications (e.g., acetaminophen) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">Brassier et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quinonez.2013.67">Quinonez et al 2013</xref>].</p>
          <p>Liver biopsy electron microscopy has shown the presence of lipid droplets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">Brassier et al 2013</xref>].</p>
          <table-wrap id="dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 4. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Clinical Features of the Hepatic Phenotype</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Disease Features</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" rowspan="6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Clinical presentation</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nausea/emesis</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Hepatomegaly</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Hepatic encephalopathy</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Muscle cramps</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Behavioral disturbances</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Vision loss</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" rowspan="8" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <bold>Laboratory abnormalities</bold>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevated transaminases</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Coagulopathy</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Elevated lactate&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Hyperammonemia&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Hypoglycemia&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Elevated urine &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Low carnitine&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Elevated plasma BCAA&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/13</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Only patients biochemically confirmed to have DLD deficiency included</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>BCAA = branched chain amino acids</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.4.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1990.709">Elpeleg et al [1990]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.aptowitzer.1997.599">Aptowitzer et al [1997]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1997a.238">Elpeleg et al [1997a]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.barak.1998.482">Barak et al [1998]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al [1999]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">Brassier et al [2013]</xref></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.4.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.metabolic_abnormalities_in_dld">Table 1</xref>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.4.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Ammonia &#x0003e;100 &#x000b5;mol/L in neonates or &#x0003e;60 &#x000b5;mol/L in infants, children, and adults</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.4.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>Glucose &#x0003c;40 mg/dL</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.4.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Carnitine (free) &#x0003c;38&#x000b1;22 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.millington.2002">Millington 2002</xref>]</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p>Although <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.features_of_the_earlyonset_neu">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.clinical_features_of_the_hepat">Table 4</xref> reveal features common to both the early-onset neurologic presentation and the hepatic presentation (i.e., elevated transaminases, hepatomegaly, and lactate elevations), differentiation of the two types can be difficult especially in neonates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.2003.816">Hong et al 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cameron.2006.1542">Cameron et al 2006</xref>]. To date, the only patient with a hepatic phenotype who displayed hypotonia or residual neurologic deficiencies had experienced a severe episode associated with deep coma and residual vision loss and behavioral disturbances [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1990.709">Elpeleg et al 1990</xref>]. Therefore, the absence of hypotonia and neurologic deficit and the presence of hepatic signs are useful discriminating features.</p>
          <p><bold>Myopathic presentation.</bold> One patient has been described with a mild phenotype consisting primarily of myopathic symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quintana.2010.s315">Quintana et al 2010</xref>]. The patient exhibited ptosis, weakness, and an elevated creatine kinase and lactate.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>Phenotypic severity is difficult to predict based on genotype and residual enzyme function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shany.1999.163">Shany et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quinonez.2013.67">Quinonez et al 2013</xref>].</p>
          <p>Individuals homozygous for the <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus">c.685G&#x0003e;T</xref> (p.Gly229Cys) pathogenic variant, which is common in the Ashkenazi Jewish population, were initially thought to have a milder, primarily hepatic presentation. Subsequently, individuals homozygous for <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus">c.685G&#x0003e;T</xref> (p.Gly229Cys) were found to have the early-onset neonatal neurologic presentation as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.2003.816">Hong et al 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.sansaricq.2006.203">Sansaricq et al 2006</xref>]. Conversely, all individuals with an exclusively hepatic presentation have been homozygous for the <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus">c.685G&#x0003e;T</xref> (p.Gly229Cys) pathogenic variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">Brassier et al 2013</xref>].</p>
          <p>Newborn screening (NBS) has recently identified two symptomatic infants with DLD deficiency who had an elevated citrulline level on dried blood spot (DBS) testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.haviv.2014.243">Haviv et al 2014</xref>]. Both of these infants as well as all subsequently identified children in the initial report were homozygous for the <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus">c.685G&#x0003e;T</xref> (p.Gly229Cys) pathogenic variant or compound heterozygous for that allele and another pathogenic variant. An elevated citrulline level has also been seen in a patient without the <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus">c.685G&#x0003e;T</xref> (p.Gly229Cys) allele [Authors, personal observation]. Note: The exact mechanism of hypercitrullinemia in these infants has yet to be identified; aspartate depletion through decreased oxaloacetate production has been suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.haviv.2014.243">Haviv et al 2014</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>DLD deficiency is occasionally referred to as maple syrup urine disease (MSUD) type 3 as it functions as the E3 subunit of BCKDH. Note that MSUD type 1 is caused by biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">BCKDHA</italic> (E1&#x003b1;) or <italic toggle="yes">BCKDHB</italic> (E1&#x003b2;) and MSUD type 2 is caused by biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DBT</italic> (E2). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="msud" document-type="chapter">Maple Syrup Urine Disease</related-object>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>In the Ashkenazi Jewish population, the carrier frequency of the <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus">c.685G&#x0003e;T</xref> (p.Gly229Cys) pathogenic variant is estimated to be between 1:94 and 1:110 with an estimated disease frequency of 1:35,000 to 1:48,000 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.scott.2010.1240">Scott et al 2010</xref>]. This is likely an underestimate of disease, as additional pathogenic variants account for DLD deficiency in this population as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>].</p>
          <p>The incidence and carrier frequency in other populations is unknown and likely very rare.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dld-def.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Diso">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dld-def.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p><bold>Pyruvate dehydrogenase complex (PDHC) deficiency</bold> most commonly presents with neurologic impairment, hypotonia, structural brain abnormalities, and lactic acidosis with a normal lactate:pyruvate ratio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.patel.2012.385">Patel et al 2012</xref>]. While the clinical findings and preliminary laboratory values are similar, individuals with DLD deficiency frequently also display biochemical evidence of: (a) defective &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase with elevated urine &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate; and (b) branched chain alpha-ketoacid dehydrogenase complex dysfunction with elevated plasma branched chain amino acids and urine branched chain ketoacids.</p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="msud" document-type="chapter"><bold>Maple syrup urine disease (MSUD) types 1 and 2</bold></related-object><bold>.</bold> Signs in individuals with classic MSUD by age:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>12 to 24 hours: a maple syrup odor in cerumen, elevated plasma concentrations of branched-chain amino acids (BCAAs) (leucine, isoleucine, and valine) and allo-isoleucine, and a generalized disturbance of plasma amino acid concentration ratios</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Two to three days: ketonuria, irritability, and poor feeding</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Four to five days: deepening encephalopathy manifesting as lethargy, intermittent apnea, opisthotonus, and stereotyped movements such as "fencing" and "bicycling"</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Seven to ten days: possible coma and central respiratory failure</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Individuals with DLD deficiency (which may be referred to as MSUD type 3; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dld-def.Nomenclature">Nomenclature</xref>) can typically be differentiated from MSUD types 1 and 2 by the presence of severe lactic acidosis, &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate excretion in the urine, and liver involvement. The maple syrup odor frequently seen in patients with MSUD types 1 and 2 is not typically found in individuals with DLD deficiency.</p>
        <p><bold>Isolated &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase deficiency</bold> has been reported in two sets of consanguineous siblings with choreoathetoid movements, hypotonia, developmental delay, and lactic acidosis. All patients exhibited isolated elevations of &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate in the urine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.kohlsch_tter.1982.32">Kohlsch&#x000fc;tter et al 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.guffon.1993.821">Guffon et al 1993</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold>Elevated citrulline on newborn screening dried blood spot</bold> has been identified in two symptomatic patients with DLD deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.haviv.2014.243">Haviv et al 2014</xref>]. As recommended by the American College of Medical Genetics (see <named-content content-type="highlight-1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.acmg.net/StaticContent/ACT/Citrullinemia.pdf">ACMG ACT Sheet</ext-link></named-content> / <named-content content-type="highlight-1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.acmg.net/docs/ACT%20Sheets/Algorithms/Visio-Citrulline.pdf">ACMG Algorithm</ext-link></named-content>), other causes of an elevated citrulline on dried blood spot including <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="ctlm" document-type="chapter">citrullinemia type I</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="args-aciduria" document-type="chapter">argininosuccinic acidemia</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="citrin" document-type="chapter">citrullinemia type II</related-object> (citrin deficiency), and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pdc" document-type="chapter">pyruvate carboxylase deficiency</related-object> should be investigated.</p>
        <p><bold>Defects in lipoic acid metabolism</bold> have recently been identified as a cause of neonatal lactic acidosis and a biochemical phenotype similar to DLD deficiency. Lipoic acid is the essential cofactor attached to the E2 subunits of BCKDH, &#x003b1;KGDH, and PDH as well as to the H protein of the glycine cleavage system (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nkh" document-type="chapter">Glycine Encephalopathy</related-object>). Pathogenic variants have been identified in multiple genes encoding enzymes involved in lipoic acid metabolism: <italic toggle="yes">NUF1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BOLA3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">LIAS</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">IBA57</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">LIPT1</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cameron.2011.486">Cameron et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.mayr.2011.792">Mayr et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.navarrosastre.2011.656">Navarro-Sastre et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.ajit_bolar.2013.2590">Ajit Bolar et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.haack.2013.55">Haack et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.soreze.2013.192">Soreze et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.tort.2014.1907">Tort et al 2014</xref>]. Unlike children with DLD deficiency, children with defects in lipoic acid metabolism (except <italic toggle="yes">LIPT1</italic> deficiency) have elevated glycine in body fluids.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dld-def.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="dld-def.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Di">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>In the acute setting, measurement/evaluation of:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Blood acid-base status</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Plasma/serum concentration of lactate, glucose, and ammonia</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Plasma amino acids</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Plasma total and free carnitine</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Urine organic acids</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Liver function and transaminases (ALT/AST)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Liver size via physical examination and/or ultrasonography</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Cardiac size via echocardiography</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Clinical genetics consultation</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>After metabolic stability has been achieved:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Clinical assessment of physical growth and development status</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Formal ophthalmologic evaluation if concern for vision loss</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Brain MRI if clinical concern for Leigh-like syndrome or other structural brain damage</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Clinical genetics consultation</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Consensus recommendations for the management of DLD deficiency do not currently exist. Theoretical difficulties exist for the management of these patients based on the various metabolic pathways affected by the three affected enzyme complexes. In practice, these difficulties have been experienced and make empiric treatment recommendations challenging.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> pathogenic variants cause variable deficiency in three enzymatic pathways. The treatment for individual enzyme complex deficiencies warrants consideration:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Branched chain alpha-ketoacid dehydrogenase (BCKDH) complex.</bold> Management consists primarily of dietary leucine restriction, BCAA-free medical foods, judicious supplementation with isoleucine and valine, and frequent clinical and biochemical monitoring (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="msud" document-type="chapter">MSUD</related-object>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>&#x003b1;-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase (&#x003b1;KGDH) complex.</bold> Due to the rarity of this isolated deficiency, limited information is available for the management of these patients.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Pyruvate dehydrogenase (PDH) complex.</bold> Due to defective carbohydrate oxidation, ketogenic diets have become part of regular management in these patients. Additionally, dichloroacetate (DCA) and thiamine supplementation are frequently tried [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.patel.2012.385">Patel et al 2012</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <sec id="dld-def.EarlyOnset_Neurologic_Presentati">
            <title>Early-Onset Neurologic Presentation</title>
            <p><bold>Review of treatment strategies.</bold> The multiple strategies that have been attempted in children with an early-onset neurologic presentation do not appear to significantly alter the natural history of disease. Even with treatment, children often die in the neonatal/infantile period or experience various degrees of chronic neurologic impairment if they survive the initial episode. The individual treatment strategies typically address deficiency of one abnormal enzymatic complex.</p>
            <p><bold>Protein/BCAA-restriction.</bold> Based on decreased BCKDH activity, restriction of protein to recommended dietary allowances (RDA) has been attempted with questionable results. Three of the six reported patients experienced laboratory and/or clinical improvement with the use of protein restriction alone or in combination with medication therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.craigen.1996.69">Craigen 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1997b.256">Elpeleg et al 1997b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.grafakou.2003.714">Grafakou et al 2003</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Ketogenic/high-fat diet.</bold> Ketogenic/high-fat diets are frequently employed in PDH deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.patel.2012.385">Patel et al 2012</xref>] and as a result have been attempted in DLD deficiency. A total of seven patients reported to date have been tried on a ketogenic/high-fat diet:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Five had no clinical or biochemical benefit. Of note, two of the five experienced clinical worsening with an increase in acidosis and hypoglycemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.robinson.1981.35">Robinson et al 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.craigen.1996.69">Craigen 1996</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Two improved clinically. One was treated with lipid infusions (instead of high-dextrose infusions) during acute episodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.hong.1997.160">Hong et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cerna.2001.1319">Cerna et al 2001</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Carbohydrate tolerance.</bold> Patients with PDH deficiency classically present with lactate elevations due to defective carbohydrate oxidation. Although dextrose infusions may theoretically cause further lactate elevations during acute episodes, provision of dextrose-containing IV fluids is essential for the majority of acutely decompensated patients. Only one patient experienced worsening acidosis with increased dextrose concentrations in the TPN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cerna.2001.1319">Cerna et al 2001</xref>]. Not surprisingly, this patient is one of the two who benefitted from a ketogenic/high-fat diet.</p>
            <p><bold>Dichloroacetate (DCA).</bold> Through its ability to stimulate PDH activity by inhibiting PDH kinase, DCA has long been used to safely treat patients with congenital lactic acidosis, mitochondrial disorders, and PDH deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.stacpoole.2008.e1223">Stacpoole et al 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.patel.2012.385">Patel et al 2012</xref>]. A total of five patients have been tried on DCA with four experiencing at least transient decreases in lactic acid elevations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.craigen.1996.69">Craigen 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1997b.256">Elpeleg et al 1997b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.cerna.2001.1319">Cerna et al 2001</xref>].</p>
            <p>Additional therapies used with limited success include:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Thiamine</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Coenzyme Q<sub>10</sub></p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Lipoic acid</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Riboflavin</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Biotin</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Empiric recommendations</bold>
<bold>for acute management</bold> (based on the above review)</p>
            <p>Goals of therapy should be the correction of metabolic acidosis, promotion of an anabolic/metabolically stable state, maintenance of normoglycemia, and treatment of precipitating factors that may be present. This is typically achieved by the following:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Metabolic acidosis should be treated with sodium bicarbonate if bicarbonate is &#x02264;14 mEq/L and/or blood pH &#x0003c;7.2.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Promotion of an anabolic state:</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Maintain serum glucose concentration in the normal range. D<sub>10</sub> (half or full-normal saline) with age-appropriate electrolytes should be started at maintenance rate and adjusted based on the presence or absence of increased intracranial pressure or hypoglycemia.</p>
                    <list list-type="bullet">
                      <list-item>
                        <p>Elevation of plasma leucine and increased intracranial pressure are a potential complication of DLD deficiency. Similar to the management of classic MSUD link, overhydration and quickly infused boluses of fluids should be avoided if possible.</p>
                      </list-item>
                      <list-item>
                        <p>If provision of dextrose-containing fluids worsens metabolic acidosis, consider decreasing the infusion rate and providing the majority of calories in the form of intralipid.</p>
                      </list-item>
                    </list>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Intralipids can be added to provide additional calories with cautious monitoring for acidemia.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Protein should initially be withheld for a maximum of 24 hours to avoid worsening of catabolism. Protein should then be reintroduced gradually.</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Branched-chain amino acids should be introduced slowly and followed closely with frequent plasma amino acid evaluations.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Goal levels/ratios should be similar to those listed in <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="msud" document-type="chapter">MSUD</related-object>.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Levocarnitine (IV or PO) 50 - 100 mg/kg/d divided three times per day should be given during the acute period.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Dichloroacetate (DCA) can be considered and continued if lactate decreases with its introduction.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Any precipitating factors (infection, fasting, medications) should be treated/discontinued as soon as possible.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>If lactic acidosis/encephalopathy persists, dialysis can be considered as it has been successful in DLD deficiency and classic MSUD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.schaefer.1999.910">Schaefer et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quinonez.2013.67">Quinonez et al 2013</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="dld-def.Hepatic_Presentation">
            <title>Hepatic Presentation</title>
            <p>Management of patients with the primarily hepatic presentation typically involves supportive therapy during times of acute liver injury or failure, including the following:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Nutritional support in the form of dextrose-containing IV fluids (6-8 mg/kg/min) with age-appropriate electrolytes and/or frequent feedings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1990.709">Elpeleg et al 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">Brassier et al 2013</xref>]</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Correction of metabolic acidosis with sodium bicarbonate</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Correction of any coagulopathy with fresh frozen plasma</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Consideration of DCA treatment for lactic acidosis during acute episodes and for chronic management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.aptowitzer.1997.599">Aptowitzer et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>]</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Use of dialysis to treat persistent lactic acidosis and encephalopathy (successfully in one patient) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1990.709">Elpeleg et al 1990</xref>]</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Avoidance of liver-toxic medications</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Episodes of catabolic stress (e.g., intercurrent illness, surgical procedures, pregnancy) require the assistance/care of a biochemical geneticist.</p>
            <p>Limited data exist for chronic management of individuals with the primarily hepatic presentation. Between episodes, patients typically return to baseline and do not require treatment beyond the avoidance of fasting, catabolic stressors, and liver-toxic medications.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Prevention_of_Primary_Manifestat">
          <title>Prevention of Primary Manifestations</title>
          <p>No compelling evidence exists for the prevention of acute episodes, despite multiple attempted dietary strategies and medications. The frequency of acute episodes decreases with age in most patients with DLD deficiency.</p>
          <p>Although no specific therapy exists to prevent the neurologic dysfunction and/or the hepatic manifestations of DLD deficiency, avoidance of precipitating factors is recommended. As such, empiric recommendations include the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Provide protein intake at or around RDA and titrate based on growth and plasma amino acid values. See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="msud" document-type="chapter">MSUD</related-object> for the recommended intake and target levels of leucine, isoleucine, and valine.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Supplement with levocarnitine if deficient.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Avoid fasting, catabolic states, and extremes of dietary intake until dietary tolerance/stressors are identified.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Avoid liver-toxic medications.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complica">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Age-appropriate immunizations including the influenza vaccine should be provided.</p>
          <p>Dichloroacetate (DCA) has been associated with the development of peripheral neuropathy; thus, patients receiving this medication require close monitoring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.stacpoole.2008.e1223">Stacpoole et al 2008</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>A patient&#x02019;s primary care physician and biochemical geneticist should follow growth and development regularly. Developmental delays should be identified and treated as early as possible.</p>
          <p>Plasma amino acid levels should be regularly followed to guide dietary management by the biochemical geneticist in conjunction with a qualified metabolic nutritionist.</p>
          <p>Complications of DLD deficiency including hepatomegaly, cardiomyopathy, and CNS changes require regular surveillance if present.</p>
          <p>Patients receiving dichloroacetate (DCA) need to be monitored for the development of peripheral neuropathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.stacpoole.2008.e1223">Stacpoole et al 2008</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Avoid the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Fasting</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Catabolic stressors</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Liver-toxic medications</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> pathogenic variants in an affected relative are known, at-risk sibs should undergo molecular genetic testing as soon as possible after birth so that those who have inherited both pathogenic variants can receive appropriate treatment and avoid risk factors that may precipitate an acute event. In some instances, families choose to perform prenatal testing so that treatment can begin shortly after birth for those who have inherited both pathogenic variants.</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dld-def.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issue">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dld-def.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="dld-def.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected child are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one pathogenic variant).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Once an at-risk sib is known to be unaffected, the risk of his/her being a carrier is 2/3.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> The offspring of an individual with DLD deficiency are obligate heterozygotes (carriers) for a <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Carrier_Detection">
          <title>Carrier Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> pathogenic variants in the family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issue">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dld-def.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected, are carriers, or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dld-def.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplanta">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once both <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing and preimplantion genetic diagnosis for a pregnancy at increased risk for DLD deficiency are possible options.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dld-def.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dld-def.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="dld-def.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) functions as the E3 subunit in three mitochondrial enzyme complexes (BCKDH, &#x003b1;KGDH, PDH) and the L protein of the glycine cleavage system.</p>
          <p>As the E3 subunit, it catalyzes the oxidative regeneration of the lipoic acid covalently bound to the E2 subunit, generating NADH in the process. <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> loss-of-function pathogenic variants lead to variable dysfunction of BCKDH, &#x003b1;KGDH, and PDH. The decreased activity of these three enzyme complexes leads to the often severe and variable phenotype seen in DLD deficiency.</p>
          <p>To date no patient with DLD deficiency has presented with biochemical evidence of glycine cleavage system dysfunction (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nkh" document-type="chapter">Glycine Encephalopathy</related-object>).</p>
          <p>Additionally, multiple <italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> pathogenic variants have been associated with elevated reactive oxygen species (ROS) generation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.vaubel.2011.40232">Vaubel et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.ambrus.2013.145">Ambrus &#x00026; Adam-Vizi 2013</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> comprises 14 exons and is approximately 30 kb long. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dld-def" object-id="dld-def.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> Variant types include missense, nonsense, small deletions, small insertions, and splice site variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.quinonez.2013.67">Quinonez et al 2013</xref>].</p>
          <p>The <xref ref-type="table" rid="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus">c.685G&#x0003e;T</xref> (p.Gly229Cys) pathogenic variant is common in the Ashkenazi Jewish population. Carrier frequency is estimated at between 1:94 and 1:110 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">Shaag et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dld-def.REF.scott.2010.1240">Scott et al 2010</xref>].</p>
          <table-wrap id="dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 5. </label>
            <caption>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">DLD</italic> Pathogenic Variants Discussed in This <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic></p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.685G&#x0003e;T&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly229Cys</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dld-def.T.dld_pathogenic_variants_discus_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000108.4">NM_000108.4</ext-link>
                    <break/>
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_000099.2">NP_000099.2</ext-link>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dld-def.TF.5.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dld-def.Prevalence">Prevalence</xref>.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The normal gene product is dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase, a 50-kd protein composed of 509 amino acids.</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Pathogenic variants cause the dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase enzyme to be inactive or absent.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dld-def.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="dld-def.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="dld-def.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.ajit_bolar.2013.2590">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ajit Bolar</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vanlander</surname>
                    <given-names>AV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wilbrecht</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van der Aa</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smet</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vandeweyer</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kooy</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eyskens</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Latter</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Delanghe</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Govaert</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leroy</surname>
                    <given-names>JG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Loeys</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lill</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Laer</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Coster</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutation of the iron-sulfur cluster assembly gene IBA57 causes severe myopathy and encephalopathy.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>22</volume>
                <fpage>2590</fpage>
                <lpage>602</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23462291</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.ambrus.2013.145">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ambrus</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adam-Vizi</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Molecular dynamics study of the structural basis of dysfunction and the modulation of reactive oxygen species generation by pathogenic mutants of human dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Biochem Biophys.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>538</volume>
                <fpage>145</fpage>
                <lpage>55</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24012808</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.aptowitzer.1997.599">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aptowitzer</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saada</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Faber</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kleid</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>ON</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Liver disease in the Ashkenazi-Jewish lipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr.</source>
                <year>1997</year>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>599</fpage>
                <lpage>601</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9161958</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.barak.1998.482">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barak</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huminer</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Segal</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ben Ari</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Halevy</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tur-Kaspa</surname>
                    <given-names>R.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency: a newly discovered cause of acute hepatitis in adults.</article-title>
                <source>J Hepatol.</source>
                <year>1998</year>
                <volume>29</volume>
                <fpage>482</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9764998</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.bonnefont.1992.255">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonnefont</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chretien</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rustin</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vassault</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aupetit</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Charpentier</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rabier</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saudubray</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munnich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Alpha-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase deficiency presenting as congenital lactic acidosis.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>1992</year>
                <volume>121</volume>
                <fpage>255</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1640293</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.brassier.2013.28">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brassier</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ottolenghi</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boutron</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bertrand</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valmary-Degano</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cervoni</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chretien</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arnoux</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rabier</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lacaille</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Keyzer</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Di Martino</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Lonlay</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency: a still overlooked cause of recurrent acute liver failure and Reye-like syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>109</volume>
                <fpage>28</fpage>
                <lpage>32</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23478190</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.cameron.2011.486">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cameron</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Janer</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Levandovskiy</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mackay</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rouault</surname>
                    <given-names>TA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tong</surname>
                    <given-names>WH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oglivie</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shoubridge</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>BH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in iron-sulfur cluster scaffold genes NFU1 and BOLA3 cause a fatal deficiency of multiple respiratory chain and 2-oxoacid dehydrogenase enzymes.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>89</volume>
                <fpage>486</fpage>
                <lpage>95</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21944046</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.cameron.2006.1542">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cameron</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Levandovskiy</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mackay</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raiman</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Renaud</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clarke</surname>
                    <given-names>JT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feigenbaum</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>BH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Novel mutations in dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency in two cousins with borderline-normal PDH complex activity.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>140</volume>
                <fpage>1542</fpage>
                <lpage>52</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16770810</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.cerna.2001.1319">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cerna</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wenchich</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hansikov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kmoch</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peskova</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chrastina</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brynda</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeman</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Novel mutations in a boy with dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Med Sci Monit.</source>
                <year>2001</year>
                <volume>7</volume>
                <fpage>1319</fpage>
                <lpage>25</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11687750</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.chuang.2014">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Chuang DT, Shih VE, Max Wynn RR. Maple syrup urine disease (branched-chain ketoaciduria). In: Valle D, Beaudet AL, Vogelstein B, Kinzler KW, Antonarakis SE, Ballabio A, Gibson K, Mitchell G, eds. <italic toggle="yes">The Online Metabolic and Molecular Bases of Inherited Disease (OMMBID).</italic> Chap 87. New York, NY: McGraw-Hill. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ommbid.mhmedical.com/">online</ext-link>. 2014. Accessed 5-2-16.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.craigen.1996.69">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Craigen</surname>
                    <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Leigh disease with deficiency of lipoamide dehydrogenase: treatment failure with dichloroacetate.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Neurol.</source>
                <year>1996</year>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>69</fpage>
                <lpage>71</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8652022</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1990.709">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>ON</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Christensen</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hurvitz</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Branski</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Recurrent, familial Reye-like syndrome with a new complex amino and organic aciduria.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>1990</year>
                <volume>149</volume>
                <fpage>709</fpage>
                <lpage>12</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2120061</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1995.72">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>ON</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ruitenbeek</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jakobs</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barash</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Vivo</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Amir</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Congenital lacticacidemia caused by lipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency with favorable outcome.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>1995</year>
                <volume>126</volume>
                <fpage>72</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7815230</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1997a.238">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>ON</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saada</surname>
                    <given-names>AB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shaag</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glustein</surname>
                    <given-names>JZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ruitenbeek</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tein</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Halevy</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency: a new cause for recurrent myoglobinuria.</article-title>
                <source>Muscle Nerve.</source>
                <year>1997a</year>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>238</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9040667</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.elpeleg.1997b.256">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>ON</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shaag</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glustein</surname>
                    <given-names>JZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Anikster</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Joseph</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saada</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency in Ashkenazi Jews: an insertion mutation in the mitochondrial leader sequence.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>1997b</year>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>256</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9298831</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.grafakou.2003.714">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grafakou</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oexle</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van den Heuvel</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smeets</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Trijbels</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goebel</surname>
                    <given-names>HH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bosshard</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Superti-Furga</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steinmann</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smeitink</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Leigh syndrome due to compound heterozygosity of dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase gene mutations. Description of the first E3 splice site mutation.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>162</volume>
                <fpage>714</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12925875</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.guffon.1993.821">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Guffon</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lopez-Mediavilla</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dumoulin</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mousson</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Godinot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrier</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Collombet</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Divry</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mathieu</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Guibaud</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>2-Ketoglutarate dehydrogenase deficiency, a rare cause of primary hyperlactataemia: report of a new case.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <year>1993</year>
                <volume>16</volume>
                <fpage>821</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8295396</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.haack.2013.55">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haack</surname>
                    <given-names>TB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rolinski</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haberberger</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schum</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Strecker</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Graf</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Athing</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoppen</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wittig</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sperl</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Freisinger</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayr</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Strom</surname>
                    <given-names>TM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meitinger</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prokisch</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Homozygous missense mutation in BOLA3 causes multiple mitochondrial dysfunctions syndrome in two siblings.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>36</volume>
                <fpage>55</fpage>
                <lpage>62</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22562699</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.haviv.2014.243">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haviv</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeharia</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Belaiche</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haimi Cohen</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saada</surname>
                    <given-names>A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Elevated plasma citrulline: look for dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>173</volume>
                <fpage>243</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23995961</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.hoffmann.2002">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Hoffmann GF, Feyh P. Organic acid analysis. In: Blau N, Duran M, Blaskovics ME, Gibson KM, eds. <italic toggle="yes">Physician&#x02019;s Guide to the Laboratory Diagnosis of Metabolic Diseases</italic>. 2 ed. Berlin, Germany: Springer; 2002:27-44.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.hong.1996.1925">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hong</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kerr</surname>
                    <given-names>DS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Craigen</surname>
                    <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tan</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pan</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lusk</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patel</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Identification of two mutations in a compound heterozygous child with dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
                <year>1996</year>
                <volume>5</volume>
                <fpage>1925</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8968745</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.hong.1997.160">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hong</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kerr</surname>
                    <given-names>DS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>TC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lusk</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Powell</surname>
                    <given-names>BR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patel</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Deficiency of dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase due to two mutant alleles (E340K and G101del). Analysis of a family and prenatal testing.</article-title>
                <source>Biochim Biophys Acta.</source>
                <year>1997</year>
                <volume>1362</volume>
                <fpage>160</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9540846</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.hong.2003.816">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hong</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Korman</surname>
                    <given-names>SH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ghoshal</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wu</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barash</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kang</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oh</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kwon</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gutman</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rachmel</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patel</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Identification of a common mutation (Gly194Cys) in both Arab Moslem and Ashkenazi Jewish patients with dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (E3) deficiency: possible beneficial effect of vitamin therapy.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>26</volume>
                <fpage>816</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14765544</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.kohlsch_tter.1982.32">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kohlsch&#x000fc;tter</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Behbehani</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Langenbeck</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Albani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heidemann</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoffmann</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kleineke</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lehnert</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wendel</surname>
                    <given-names>U.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A familial progressive neurodegenerative disease with 2-oxoglutaric aciduria.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>1982</year>
                <volume>138</volume>
                <fpage>32</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7075624</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.kuhara.1983.133">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kuhara</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shinka</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Inoue</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoshino</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sakaguchi</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Studies of urinary organic acid profiles of a patient with dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Chim Acta.</source>
                <year>1983</year>
                <volume>133</volume>
                <fpage>133</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6688766</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.liu.1993.5186">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>TC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kim</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arizmendi</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kitano</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patel</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Identification of two missense mutations in a dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase-deficient patient.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA.</source>
                <year>1993</year>
                <volume>90</volume>
                <fpage>5186</fpage>
                <lpage>90</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8506365</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.matalon.1984.65">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matalon</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stumpf</surname>
                    <given-names>DA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Michals</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hart</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Parks</surname>
                    <given-names>JK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goodman</surname>
                    <given-names>SI</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency with primary lactic acidosis: favorable response to treatment with oral lipoic acid.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>1984</year>
                <volume>104</volume>
                <fpage>65</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6418873</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.mayr.2011.792">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayr</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
                    <given-names>FA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fauth</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bergheim</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meierhofer</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Radmayr</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zschocke</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koch</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sperl</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lipoic acid synthetase deficiency causes neonatal-onset epilepsy, defective mitochondrial energy metabolism, and glycine elevation.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>89</volume>
                <fpage>792</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22152680</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.millington.2002">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Millington DS. Tandem mass spectrometry in clinical diagnosis. In: Blau N, Duran M, Blaskovics ME, Gibson KM, eds. <italic toggle="yes">Physician&#x02019;s Guide to the Laboratory Diagnosis of Metabolic Diseases</italic>. 2 ed. Berlin: Springer; 2002:57-75.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.munnich.1982.167">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munnich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saudubray</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Charpentier</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marsac</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rocchiccioli</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Amedee-Manesme</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coude</surname>
                    <given-names>FX</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frezal</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>BH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Congenital lactic acidosis, alpha-ketoglutaric aciduria and variant form of maple syrup urine disease due to a single enzyme defect: dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Acta Paediatr Scand.</source>
                <year>1982</year>
                <volume>71</volume>
                <fpage>167</fpage>
                <lpage>71</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6897145</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.navarrosastre.2011.656">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Navarro-Sastre</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tort</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stehling</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Uzarska</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arranz</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Del Toro</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Labayru</surname>
                    <given-names>MT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Landa</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Font</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garcia-Villoria</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Merinero</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ugarte</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gutierrez-Solana</surname>
                    <given-names>LG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Campistol</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garcia-Cazorla</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vaquerizo</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Riudor</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Briones</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ribes</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lill</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A fatal mitochondrial disease is associated with defective NFU1 function in the maturation of a subset of mitochondrial Fe-S proteins.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>89</volume>
                <fpage>656</fpage>
                <lpage>67</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22077971</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.odi_vre.2005.323">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Odi&#x000e8;vre</surname>
                    <given-names>MH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chretien</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munnich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>BH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dumoulin</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Masmoudi</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kadhom</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>R&#x000f6;tig</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rustin</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonnefont</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A novel mutation in the dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase E3 subunit gene (DLD) resulting in an atypical form of alpha-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>25</volume>
                <fpage>323</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15712224</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.patel.2012.385">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patel</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                    <given-names>TW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Subramony</surname>
                    <given-names>SH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shuster</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stacpoole</surname>
                    <given-names>PW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The spectrum of pyruvate dehydrogenase complex deficiency: clinical, biochemical and genetic features in 371 patients.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>106</volume>
                <fpage>385</fpage>
                <lpage>94</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22896851</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.quinonez.2013.67">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Quinonez</surname>
                    <given-names>SC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leber</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martin</surname>
                    <given-names>DM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thoene</surname>
                    <given-names>JG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bedoyan</surname>
                    <given-names>JK</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Leigh syndrome in a girl with a novel DLD mutation causing E3 deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Neurol.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>48</volume>
                <fpage>67</fpage>
                <lpage>72</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23290025</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.quintana.2010.s315">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Quintana</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pineda</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Font</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vilaseca</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tort</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ribes</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Briones</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency in a Spanish patient with myopathic presentation due to a new mutation in the interface domain.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>33</volume>
                <supplement>Suppl 3</supplement>
                <fpage>S315</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20652410</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.robinson.1981.35">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>BH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kahler</surname>
                    <given-names>SG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kirkman</surname>
                    <given-names>HN</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lactic acidemia, neurologic deterioration and carbohydrate dependence in a girl with dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>1981</year>
                <volume>136</volume>
                <fpage>35</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6894281</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.robinson.1977.1198">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>BH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sherwood</surname>
                    <given-names>WG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fraser</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Deficiency of dihydrolipoyl dehydrogenase (a component of the pyruvate and alpha-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase complexes): a cause of congenital chronic lactic acidosis in infancy.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Res.</source>
                <year>1977</year>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>1198</fpage>
                <lpage>202</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">413089</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.sansaricq.2006.203">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sansaricq</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pardo</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Balwani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grace</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raymond</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Biochemical and molecular diagnosis of lipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency in a North American Ashkenazi Jewish family.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis.</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>29</volume>
                <fpage>203</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16601893</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.schadewaldt.1999.1734">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schadewaldt</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bodner-Leidecker</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hammen</surname>
                    <given-names>HW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wendel</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Significance of L-alloisoleucine in plasma for diagnosis of maple syrup urine disease.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Chem.</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>45</volume>
                <fpage>1734</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508118</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.schaefer.1999.910">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Straube</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oh</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mehls</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayatepek</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Dialysis in neonates with inborn errors of metabolism.</article-title>
                <source>Nephrol Dial Transplant.</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>910</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10328469</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.scott.2010.1240">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scott</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Edelmann</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Luo</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Desnick</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Kornreich. Experience with carrier screening and prenatal diagnosis for 16 Ashkenazi Jewish genetic diseases.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>31</volume>
                <fpage>1240</fpage>
                <lpage>50</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20672374</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.shaag.1999.177">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shaag</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saada</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berger</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mandel</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Joseph</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feigenbaum</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>ON</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Molecular basis of lipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency in Ashkenazi Jews.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>82</volume>
                <fpage>177</fpage>
                <lpage>82</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9934985</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.shany.1999.163">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shany</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saada</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Landau</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shaag</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hershkovitz</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elpeleg</surname>
                    <given-names>ON</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency due to a novel mutation in the interface domain.</article-title>
                <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>262</volume>
                <fpage>163</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10448086</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.shih.2002">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Shih VE. Amino acid analysis. In: Blau N, Duran M, Blaskovics ME, Gibson KM, eds. <italic toggle="yes">Physician&#x02019;s Guide to the Laboratory Diagnosis of Metabolic Diseases</italic>. 2 ed. Berlin, Germany: Springer; 2002:11-26.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.soreze.2013.192">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Soreze</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boutron</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Habarou</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barnerias</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nonnenmacher</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Delpech</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mamoune</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chr&#x000e9;tien</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hubert</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bole-Feysot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nitschke</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Correia</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sardet</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boddaert</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamel</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Delahodde</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ottolenghi</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Lonlay</surname>
                    <given-names>P.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in human lipoyltransferase gene LIPT1 cause a Leigh disease with secondary deficiency for pyruvate and alpha-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase.</article-title>
                <source>Orphanet J Rare Dis.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>192</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24341803</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.stacpoole.2008.e1223">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stacpoole</surname>
                    <given-names>PW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gilbert</surname>
                    <given-names>LR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Neiberger</surname>
                    <given-names>RE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carney</surname>
                    <given-names>PR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valenstein</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Theriaque</surname>
                    <given-names>DW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shuster</surname>
                    <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Evaluation of long-term treatment of children with congenital lactic acidosis with dichloroacetate.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatrics.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>121</volume>
                <fpage>e1223</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18411236</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.tort.2014.1907">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tort</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ferrer-Cort&#x000e8;s</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thi&#x000f3;</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Navarro-Sastre</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matalonga</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Quintana</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bujan</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arias</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Villoria</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Acquaviva</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vianey-Saban</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Artuch</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Cazorla</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Briones</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ribes</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in the lipoyltransferase LIPT1 gene cause a fatal disease associated with a specific lipoylation defect of the 2-ketoacid dehydrogenase complexes.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>23</volume>
                <fpage>1907</fpage>
                <lpage>15</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24256811</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dld-def.REF.vaubel.2011.40232">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vaubel</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rustin</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Isaya</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in the dimer interface of dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase promote site-specific oxidative damages in yeast and human cells.</article-title>
                <source>J Biol Chem.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>286</volume>
                <fpage>40232</fpage>
                <lpage>45</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21930696</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dld-def.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="dld-def.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>17 July 2014 (me) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>21 February 2014 (sq) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
