<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="dnmt1-ddsn" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">dnmt1-ddsn</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>
<italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-Related Dementia, Deafness, and Sensory Neuropathy</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: Hereditary Sensory and Autonomic Neuropathy Type 1 with Dementia and Hearing Loss, Hereditary Sensory Neuropathy Type IE, HSNIE</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Klein</surname>
            <given-names>Christopher J</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <email>klein.christopher@mayo.edu</email>
          <aff>Mayo Clinic<break/>Rochester, Minnesota</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2012-02-16" date-type="created">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2012-05-17" date-type="revised">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="cmt-dib" document-type="chapter">
<italic toggle="yes">DNM2</italic>-Related Intermediate Charcot-Marie-Tooth Neuropathy</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="drpla" document-type="chapter">DRPLA</related-object>
      <abstract id="dnmt1-ddsn.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-related dementia, deafness, and sensory neuropathy (HSAN IE) is a degenerative disorder of the central and peripheral nervous systems characterized by sensory impairment of the distal lower extremities, loss of sweating (sudomotor function) on the distal aspects of the upper and lower limbs, sensorineural hearing loss, and dementia. Affected persons are normal in their youth but begin to manifest progressive sensory neuropathy and moderate to severe progressive sensorineural deafness by age 20 to 35 years. The sensory alterations result in gait unsteadiness from sensory ataxia and mutilating ulcers and/or amputations of distal extremities in approximately 50% of affected persons. Dementia usually manifests by the fourth decade.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis is based on clinical findings and molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>, the only gene in which pathogenc variants are known to cause HSAN IE.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Injury prevention when sensory impairment is significant; use of hearing aids and/or assistive communication methods as needed. Sedative or antipsychotic drugs help to reduce the extreme restlessness, roaming behavior, delusions, and hallucinations associated with dementia. Behavioral changes and the loss of insight and judgment are often a considerable burden for partners / caregivers, who need information about the disease and psychological support.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> To prevent injury to extremities with decreased sensation protect the skin with appropriate socks and shoes and avoid exposure of feet to hot water.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Daily: examine feet for evidence of skin injury. Annually: (1) audiogram and (2) clinical testing for dementia by observation of behavior and use of tools such as Mini Mental State Exam (MMSE)</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Sharp objects and hot water, which may damage skin.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>HSAN IE is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. The proportion of HSAN IE caused by <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variants is unknown. Each child of an individual with HSAN IE has a 50% chance of inheriting the pathogenc variant. If the pathogenc variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for at-risk pregnancies is possible through laboratories offering either prenatal testing for the gene of interest or custom testing.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Clinical_Diagnosis">
          <title>Clinical Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-related dementia, deafness, and sensory neuropathy (HSAN IE) is established in individuals with the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Sensory impairment,</bold> which is predominantly loss of feeling to touch, pain, temperature, and proprioception of the feet and legs, with less severe loss in the hands. Pain tends to be minimal but can be lancinating or burning; some have described parathesias. The face and trunk are characteristically spared.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Autonomic dysfunction,</bold> manifest as loss of sweating (sudomotor abnormalities). Laboratory-based tests such as tilt table testing for postural hypotension, quantitative sudomotor axon reflex testing (QSART), and thermoregulatory sweat testing (TST) can help to identify postganglionic sudomotor abnormalities that spare cardiovagal and adrenergic autonomic functions.Special quantitative sensory testing and histopathologic preparations can assist in studying the sensory fibers implicated in autonomic involvement. The HSAN IE pan sensory neuropathy affects large proprioceptive and vibratory sensing fibers as well as small heat-, pain-, and temperature-sensing fibers.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Dementia.</bold> Progressive decline in cognition and behavior is usually the first manifestations of dementia. Wechsler Adult Intelligence and Memory Scales as well as Boston naming test and the Mini Mental State Exam (MMSE) can be used to identify diffuse cortical dementia. Brain imaging of affected persons can also help to determine the existence of global atrophy without intraparenchymal signal change.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Moderate to severe sensorineural</bold>
<bold>hearing</bold>
<bold>loss</bold> (i.e., 70- to 80-db loss at 4000 Hz) beginning in the teens or early 20s</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Molecular_Genetic_Testing">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Testing</title>
          <p><bold>Gene.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> is the only gene in which pathogenc variants are known to cause <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-related dementia, deafness, and sensory neuropathy.</p>
          <table-wrap id="dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-Related Dementia, Deafness, and Sensory Neuropathy</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allelic Variants Detected&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variant Detection Frequency by Test Method&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Targeted analysis for pathogenic variants</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <xref ref-type="table" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v">c.1484A&#x0003e;G</xref>
                    <break/>
                    <xref ref-type="table" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v">c.1470_1472delTCCinsATA</xref>
                    <break/>
                    <xref ref-type="table" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v">c.1483T&#x0003e;C</xref>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% for the targeted variant&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence variants including the 3 known pathogenic variants above</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="dnmt1-ddsn.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dnmt1-ddsn" object-id="dnmt1-ddsn.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dnmt1-ddsn.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dnmt1-ddsn.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>The ability of the test method used to detect a variant that is present in the indicated gene</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dnmt1-ddsn.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>In 6/6 families identified to date, all affected family members had a heterozygous pathogenic variant in the targeting sequence domain of <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dnmt1-ddsn.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Examples of pathogenic variants detected by sequence analysis may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Testing_Strategy">
          <title>Testing Strategy</title>
          <p>
            <bold>To confirm/establish the diagnosis in a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Perform targeted analysis for pathogenic variants if clinical examination reveals:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Young adult-onset hearing loss</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Foot ulcers</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Loss of sensation in the feet</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Depressed tendon reflexes in the lower limbs</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Signs of memory loss or abnormal behavior</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If no pathogenc variant is detected, sequence analysis of the coding region and related intron junctions of <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> may be performed.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Predictive testing</bold> for at-risk asymptomatic adult family members requires prior identification of the pathogenc variant in the family.</p>
          <p><bold>Prenatal diagnosis and preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)</bold> for at-risk pregnancies require prior identification of the pathogenc variant in the family.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-related dementia, deafness, and sensory neuropathy (HSAN IE) is a degenerative disorder of the central and peripheral nervous systems characterized by sensory impairment, sudomotor dysfunction (loss of sweating), dementia, and sensorineural hearing loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.klein.2011.595">Klein et al 2011</xref>]. Affected persons are normal in their youth but begin to manifest progressive sensorineural deafness and sensory neuropathy by age 20 to 35 years.</p>
          <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.winkelmann.2012.2205">Winkelmann et al [2012]</xref> have reported four families with pathogenc variants in <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> associated with early onset (18-44 years) of a narcolepsy/cataplexy syndrome followed by ataxia, deafness, sensory neuropathy and memory loss. The ataxia appeared to be cerebellar in nature.</p>
          <p><bold>Sensory impairment</bold> can manifest as early as the second decade of life, starting with loss of sensation leading to painless extremity injuries, and is associated with hyporeflexia. The disease predominantly affects the distal lower extremities with minimal to no motor involvement. The sensory alterations are associated with gait unsteadiness from sensory ataxia and mutilating acropathy with ulcers and/or amputations of distal extremities in approximately 50% of affected persons.</p>
          <p><bold>Autonomic dysfunction</bold> that is limited to loss of sweating (sudomotor) on the distal aspects of the upper and lower limbs.</p>
          <p><bold>Dementia</bold> manifests as progressive cognitive, executive function and behavioral decline usually by the fourth decade. Behavior changes including anger and change in personality may precede decline in memory. Memory loss, apathy, indifference, inattention, and somnolence have all been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.wright.1995.560">Wright &#x00026; Dyck 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.hojo.1999.357">Hojo et al 1999</xref>]. Irritability, delusions, and delirium are also reported.</p>
          <p><bold>Moderate to severe sensorineural</bold>
<bold>hearing</bold>
<bold>loss</bold> (i.e., 70- to 80-db loss at 4000 Hz) typically begins in the teens or early 20s.</p>
          <p><bold>Gait ataxia</bold> is common and is usually the result of sensory loss in the feet, but rarely may be cerebellar ataxia.</p>
          <p><bold>Electrophysiologic testing</bold> shows:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Length-dependent sensory axonal loss including both small fiber loss (drC and A&#x003c3;) and large fiber proprioceptive A&#x003b2; loss;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Absent or reduced sensory nerve action potentials with normal motor nerve conduction velocities.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>PET and SPECT</bold> imaging have been used to show medial frontal and thalamic hypometabolism.</p>
          <p><bold>Sural nerve biopsy</bold> shows marked loss of myelinated fibers without onion bulb change.</p>
          <p><bold>Brain neuropathology</bold> at autopsy has shown diffuse neuronal loss without distinctive histologic features and no amyloid, tau, or &#x003b1;-synuclein inclusions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.klein.2011.595">Klein et al 2011</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.GenotypePhenotype_Correlation">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>Three pathogenc variants in exon 21 of <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> have been associated with narcolepsy / cataplexy (p.Ala570Val, p.Gly605Ala, and p.Val606Phe).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>Penetrance is high in the few reported families.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-related dementia, deafness, and sensory neuropathy, also known as hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type IE (HSAN IE), is considered a sensory-predominant neuropathy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>To date, only six families have been identified with HSAN IE.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Genetically_Related_Allelic_D">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No other phenotypes are known to be associated with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1.</italic></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Autosomal dominant hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies are genetically heterogeneous, but hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type IE (HSAN IE) that includes dementia and hearing loss represents a unique phenotype.</p>
        <p>The combination of neuropathy with hearing loss can be confused with some forms of <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="cmt" document-type="chapter">Charcot-Marie-Tooth</related-object> (CMT) and the dementia is similar to that found in frontotemporal dementia (FTD) or, more commonly, global cognitive disorder. However, if it is recognized that the neuropathy, hearing loss, and dementia represent a single syndrome, the diagnosis should be clear when it occurs in persons younger than age 50 years.</p>
        <p>See <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omim.org/phenotypicSeries/PS162400">Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy: OMIM Phenotypic Series</ext-link> to view genes associated with HSAN in OMIM.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Evaluations_Following_Initial">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs of an individual diagnosed with <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-related dementia, deafness, and sensory neuropathy (HSAN IE), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Neurologic examination to determine the extent of sensory involvement, including sensory testing and observation for skin ulceration</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Past medical history to determine extent of autonomic involvement</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation of central nervous system involvement, using tests of cognitive function and brain imaging</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Audiologic examination to determine if hearing loss is present and, if present, its type and severity</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Medical genetics consultation</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Currently no effective treatment exists for any type of HSAN.</p>
          <p>The emphasis of management is to help parents and affected individuals understand the sudomotor defect and injury prevention when sensory impairment is significant.</p>
          <p>Because hearing loss may be severe, initial use of hearing aids and/or assistive communication methods may be needed.</p>
          <p>Sedative or antipsychotic drugs help to reduce extreme restlessness, roaming behavior, delusions, and hallucinations associated with dementia.</p>
          <p>Because behavioral changes and the loss of insight and judgment in individuals often present a considerable burden for partners or other caregivers, information about the disease and psychological support for partners or other caregivers are essential.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Prevention_of_Secondary_Compl">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>To prevent injury to extremities with decreased sensation, protect the skin with appropriate socks and shoes and avoid exposure of feet to hot water.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p><bold>Sensory impairment.</bold> Examine feet on a daily basis to screen for skin injury.</p>
          <p><bold>Dementia.</bold> Perform annual routine clinical testing for dementia:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Observation of behavior</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Use of tools such as the Mini Mental State Exam (MMSE)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Hearing loss.</bold> Perform annual audiogram.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Avoid sharp objects and hot water, which may damage skin.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Ri">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Is">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">ClinicalTrials,gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-related dementia, deafness, and sensory neuropathy (HSAN IE) is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>To date, all individuals diagnosed with HSAN IE have had an affected parent.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A proband with HSAN IE may have the disorder as the result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenc variant. Because simplex cases (i.e., a single occurrence in a family) have not been evaluated sufficiently to determine if the variant was <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>, the proportion of HSAN IE caused by <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> variants is unknown.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the pathogenc variant found in the proband cannot be detected in leukocyte DNA of either parent, two possible explanations are germline mosaicism in a parent or a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenc variant in the proband. Although no instances of germline mosaicism have been reported, it remains a possibility.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recommendations for the evaluation of parents of a proband with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenc variant include clinical evaluation of parents and molecular genetic testing if the variant has been identified in the proband. Such evaluations may determine that one is affected but has escaped previous diagnosis because of failure to recognize the syndrome and/or a milder phenotypic presentation. Therefore, an apparently negative family history cannot be confirmed until appropriate evaluations have been performed.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: Although all affected individuals in six of six families reported with HSAN IE have an affected parent, the family history, in other families, may appear to be negative because of failure to recognize the disorder in family members, early death of the parent before the onset of symptoms, or late onset of the disease in the affected parent.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to the sibs of the proband depends on the genetic status of the proband&#x02019;s parents.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband is affected, the risk to the sibs is 50%.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When the parents are clinically unaffected, the risk to the sibs of a proband appears to be low.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The sibs of a proband with clinically unaffected parents are still at increased risk for HSAN IE because of the possibility of reduced penetrance in a parent.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the pathogenc variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, the risk to sibs is low but greater than that of the general population because of the possibility of germline mosaicism.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Each child of an individual with HSAN IE has a 50% chance of inheriting the pathogenc variant.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> The risk to other family members depends on the status of the proband's parents. If a parent is affected, his or her family members may be at risk.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Is">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p><bold>Considerations in families with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenc variant.</bold> When neither parent of a proband with an autosomal dominant condition has clinical evidence of the disorder it is likely that the proband has a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenc variant. However, possible non-medical explanations including alternate paternity or maternity (e.g., with assisted reproduction) or undisclosed adoption could also be explored.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Prenatal_Testing">
          <title>Prenatal Testing</title>
          <p>If the pathogenc variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for at-risk pregnancies may be available from a clinical laboratory offering either testing for the gene of interest or custom testing.</p>
          <p><bold>Preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)</bold> may be an option for some families in which the pathogenc variant has been identified.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesi">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> maintains patterns of methylated cytosine residues in the mammalian genome. Studies of individuals with <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>-related dementia, deafness, and sensory neuropathy (HSAN IE) have provided a direct link between <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> defects and a neurodegenerative disorder affecting both the central and peripheral nervous systems, and suggest that <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> participates in a precise mechanism of dynamic regulation of neuronal survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.klein.2011.595">Klein et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> Two transcript variants encoding different isoforms have been found for this gene [provided by RefSeq, Aug 2008]. The transcript variant <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001379.2">NM_001379.2</ext-link> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v">Table 2</xref>) comprises 40 coding exons, numbered 1-41 but without exon 5. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dnmt1-ddsn" object-id="dnmt1-ddsn.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> In 6/6 families identified to date, all affected family members had a heterozygous pathogenc variant in the targeting sequence domain of <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic>. The variants identified are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v">Table 2</xref>.</p>
          <table-wrap id="dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 2. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Selected <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> Pathogenic Variants</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change<break/>(Alias&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup>)</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein Amino Acid Change<break/>(Alias&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup>)</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1484A&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Tyr495Cys</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_3" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001379.2">NM_001379.2</ext-link>
                    <break/>
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_001370.1">NP_001370.1</ext-link>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1470_1472delTCCinsATA<break/>(1470TCC-1472ATA)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Asp490_Pro491delinsGluTyr<break/>(D490E-P491Y)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1483T&#x0003e;C</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dnmt1-ddsn.T.selected_dnmt1_pathogenic_v_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Tyr495His</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the author. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dnmt1-ddsn.TF.2.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>Variant designation that does not conform to current naming conventions</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_001370.1">NP_001370.1</ext-link> encodes a DNA (cytosine-5)-methyltransferase 1 with 1616 amino acids. This isoform has the same N- and C-termini but is shorter than the isoform <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_001124295.1">NP_001124295.1</ext-link>, which has 1632 amino acids. The pathogenc variants occurred in the targeting-sequence domain of the protein, the N-terminal regulatory region shown to be an important factor for the structure, function, and localization of DNA (cytosine-5)-methyltransferase 1 required for enzymatic function; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.klein.2011.595">Klein et al [2011]</xref> for domain structure.</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Expression of either mutated <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> expressing p.Tyr495Cys or p.Asp490_Pro491delinsGluTyr showed misfolded DNA (cytosine-5)-methyltransferase 1 and resulted in premature protein degradation, reduced methyltransferase activity, and impaired heterochromatin binding during the G<sub>2</sub> cell cycle phase. The pathogenic mechanism of mutant <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> is potentially complex and provides a new direction for the study of neurodegeneration. <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> is highly expressed in postmitotic neurons and the adult central nervous system. It interacts with a series of important cell cycle-regulating proteins and is likely involved in neuronal differentiation and migration and neural connection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.spada.2006.224">Spada et al 2006</xref>]. It remains to be determined how DNMT1 participates in a precise mechanism of dynamic regulation of the nervous system.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="dnmt1-ddsn.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.hojo.1999.357">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hojo</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Imamura</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takanashi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ishii</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sasaki</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Imura</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ozono</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takatsuki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takauchi</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mori</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Hereditary sensory neuropathy with deafness and dementia: a clinical and neuroimaging study.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Neurol.</source>
                <volume>6</volume>
                <fpage>357</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10210919</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.klein.2011.595">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botuyan</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammans</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hojo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karpf</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boardman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Litchy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Middha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>B Dyck PJ, Parisi JE, Mer G, Smith DI, Dyck PJ<year>2011</year><article-title>Mutations in DNMT1 cause hereditary sensory neuropathy with dementia and hearing loss.</article-title><source>Nat Genet.</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21532572</pub-id></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.spada.2006.224">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spada</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rothbauer</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zolghadr</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schermelleh</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leonhardt</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Regulation of DNA methyltransferase 1.</article-title>
                <source>Adv Enzyme Regul.</source>
                <volume>46</volume>
                <fpage>224</fpage>
                <lpage>34</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16859735</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.winkelmann.2012.2205">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Winkelmann</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lin</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schormair</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kornum</surname>
                    <given-names>BR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Faraco</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Plazzi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Melberg</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cornelio</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Urban</surname>
                    <given-names>AE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pizza</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Poli</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grubert</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wieland</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Graf</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hallmayer</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Strom</surname>
                    <given-names>TM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mignot</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in DNMT1 cause autosomal dominant cerebellar ataxia, deafness and narcolepsy.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
                <volume>21</volume>
                <fpage>2205</fpage>
                <lpage>10</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22328086</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.wright.1995.560">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wright</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dyck</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1995</year>
                <article-title>Hereditary sensory neuropathy with sensorineural deafness and early-onset dementia.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology.</source>
                <volume>45</volume>
                <fpage>560</fpage>
                <lpage>2</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7898717</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="dnmt1-ddsn.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>17 May 2012 (cd) Revision: sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> available clinically</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>8 March 2012 (cd) Revision: four families with mutations in <italic toggle="yes">DNMT1</italic> associated with early onset of a narcolepsy / cataplexy syndrome followed by ataxia, deafness, sensory neuropathy, and memory loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dnmt1-ddsn.REF.winkelmann.2012.2205">Winkelmann et al 2012</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>16 February 2012 (me) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>24 October 2011 (cjk) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
