<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="image" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">image</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>IMAGe Syndrome</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: Intrauterine Growth Restriction, Metaphyseal Dysplasia, Adrenal Hypoplasia Congenita, and Genital Anomalies</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bennett</surname>
            <given-names>James</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Division of Genetic Medicine<break/>Department of Pediatrics<break/>Seattle Children&#x02019;s Hospital<break/>University of Washington<break/>Seattle, Washington</aff>
          <email>jtbenn@u.washington.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Schrier Vergano</surname>
            <given-names>Samantha A</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Division of Medical Genetics and Metabolism<break/>Department of Pediatrics<break/>Children&#x02019;s Hospital of the King&#x02019;s Daughters<break/>Eastern Virginia Medical School<break/>Norfolk, Virginia</aff>
          <email>samantha.vergano@chkd.org</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Deardorff</surname>
            <given-names>Matthew A</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Division of Human Genetics <break/>Children&#x02019;s Hospital of Philadelphia<break/>Department of Pediatrics<break/>Perelman School of Medicine<break/>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</aff>
          <email>deardorff@email.chop.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2014-03-13" date-type="created">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2016-09-08" date-type="updated">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="vws" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">IRF6</italic>-Related Disorders</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="ibmpfd" document-type="chapter">Inclusion Body Myopathy with Paget Disease of Bone and/or Frontotemporal Dementia</related-object>
      <abstract id="image.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>IMAGe syndrome is an acronym for the major findings of <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>ntrauterine growth restriction (IUGR), <italic toggle="yes">m</italic>etaphyseal dysplasia, <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>drenal hypoplasia congenita, and <italic toggle="yes">ge</italic>nitourinary abnormalities (in males). Findings reported in individuals with a clinical and/or molecular diagnosis include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>IUGR;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Some type of skeletal abnormality (most commonly delayed bone age and short stature and, occasionally, metaphyseal and epiphyseal dysplasia of varying severity);</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Adrenal insufficiency often presenting in the first month of life as an adrenal crisis or rarely later in childhood with failure to thrive and recurrent vomiting;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Genital abnormalities in males (cryptorchidism, micropenis, and hypospadias) but not in females.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Hypotonia and developmental delay are reported in some; cognitive outcome appears to be normal in the majority.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of IMAGe syndrome is established in a proband with suggestive findings and/or by the identification of a heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant in the PCNA (proliferating cell nuclear antigen)-binding domain of the maternally expressed allele.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Management of adrenal insufficiency in IMAGe syndrome is similar to management of adrenal insufficiency from other causes and should be under the supervision of an endocrinologist. Chronic treatment includes replacement doses of glucocorticoids and mineralocorticoids and oral supplements of sodium chloride. Steroid doses should be optimized to allow for linear growth without risking an adrenal crisis. Assessment for growth hormone deficiency should be considered. Routine management of cryptorchidism and hypospadias by a urologist, and routine hormone replacement by an endocrinologist for hypogonadotropic hypogonadism. Management by an orthopedist as needed for skeletal complications such as scoliosis and hip dysplasia. Occupational, speech, or physical therapy as needed, particularly in those with hypotonia.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> Vigilance during illnesses and surgeries to prevent adrenal crisis.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Routine evaluations by an endocrinologist to monitor adrenal function. Evaluation as needed by an orthopedist to monitor for skeletal complications and/or a neurologist to monitor for developmental delay and/or hypotonia.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> To allow early diagnosis and management of adrenal insufficiency in at-risk newborns, molecular genetic testing should be pursued if the familial <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant in the family is known; if the familial pathogenic variant is not known, screening for serum electrolyte abnormalities, elevated serum ACTH level, and skeletal features of IMAGe syndrome can be performed.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Pregnancy management:</italic> Risks to a mother with IMAGe syndrome during pregnancy include possible adrenal insufficiency; risks during delivery include cephalopelvic disproportion.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>Typically a <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant causing IMAGe syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner; however, only maternal transmission of the pathogenic variant results in IMAGe syndrome. Each child of a woman with a heterozygous pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> variant has a 50% chance of inheriting the variant and being affected. Each child of a man with a heterozygous pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> variant has a 50% chance of inheriting the variant but is expected to be unaffected. If the pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing is possible for pregnancies at increased risk (i.e., when the mother has the pathogenic variant).</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="image.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>IMAGe syndrome is an acronym for the major findings in this disorder: <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>ntrauterine growth restriction, <italic toggle="yes">m</italic>etaphyseal dysplasia, <italic toggle="yes">a</italic>drenal hypoplasia congenita, and <italic toggle="yes">ge</italic>nitourinary abnormalities (in males) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.vilain.1999.4335">Vilain et al 1999</xref>].</p>
        <p>No formal clinical diagnostic criteria for IMAGe syndrome have been defined.</p>
        <sec id="image.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>IMAGe syndrome <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following clinical, imaging, and suggestive laboratory findings.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Clinical findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR)*</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Postnatal growth deficiency, with variable growth hormone deficiency</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Adrenal hypoplasia congenita (AHC)*, often presenting as spontaneous adrenal crisis in the first week to month of life, with hypotension, hyponatremia, and hyperkalemia, which can be life-threatening.</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Some individuals with AHC may present with adrenal insufficiency during childhood or early adulthood.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Later-onset adrenal insufficiency can be precipitated by stress, such as illness or surgery.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Genital abnormalities in males, including unilateral or bilateral cryptorchidism, hypospadias, micropenis, and chordee.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>*Note: The clinical features of IUGR and AHC, with or without a family history of IMAGe syndrome, are highly suggestive of the diagnosis.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Imaging findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Metaphyseal and/or epiphyseal dysplasia, mesomelia, osteopenia, gracile long bones, and delayed bone age on radiographs</p>
              <p>Note: Skeletal abnormalities, which are age dependent, can be absent or subtle.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Adrenal imaging that suggests small or normal-sized adrenal glands, in contrast to enlarged adrenal glands seen in individuals with congenital adrenal hyperplasia (CAH)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Suggestive laboratory findings</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Evidence of adrenal insufficiency during a crisis including hyponatremia, hyperkalemia, and elevated ACTH levels, frequently greater than 1000 pg/mL (normal 10-60)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Lack of findings consistent with other causes of adrenal insufficiency</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of IMAGe syndrome <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with suggestive findings and/or by the identification of a heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant in the PCNA (proliferating cell nuclear antigen)-binding domain of the maternally expressed allele (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i">Table 1</xref>)<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></p>
          <p>Molecular testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold>, use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>, and <bold>more comprehensive</bold>
<bold>genomic testing</bold>.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> For a suspected diagnosis of IMAGe syndrome, sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> should be performed first. Deletions and duplications in <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> have not been reported to cause IMAGe syndrome.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="image.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of condition at the most reasonable cost. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing based tests.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>More comprehensive genomic testing</bold> (when available) including whole-exome sequencing (WES) and whole-genome sequencing (WGS) may be considered if single-gene testing (and/or use of a multi-gene panel that includes <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic>) fails to confirm a diagnosis in an individual with features of IMAGe syndrome. Such testing may provide or suggest a diagnosis not previously considered (e.g., mutation of a different gene or genes that results in a similar clinical presentation). For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in IMAGe Syndrome</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Pathogenic Variant&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/9 families&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No abnormalities anticipated&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_i_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="image.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="image" object-id="image.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="image.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="image.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="image.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="image.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>At present all six reported pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> in persons with IMAGe syndrome have been located within an eight-amino-acid region of the PCNA-binding domain (nucleotides c.814 to c. 836, based on <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000076.2">NM_000076.2</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.hamajima.2013.e75137">Hamajima et al 2013</xref>].</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="image.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="image.TF.1.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>No deletions or duplications of <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> have been reported or are anticipated in persons with IMAGe syndrome due to the gain-of-function disease mechanism.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="image.TF.1.7">
                <label>7. </label>
                <p>Although all individuals with typical clinical features of IMAGe syndrome tested to date have had an identifiable <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant, it is possible that other loci may play a role in its etiology.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="image.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="image.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Twenty-eight individuals reported from 16 families have features consistent with the clinical diagnosis of IMAGe syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.vilain.1999.4335">Vilain et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.lienhardt.2002.71">Lienhardt et al 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.pedreira.2004.274">Pedreira et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.bergad_.2005.3186">Bergad&#x000e1; et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.hutz.2006.66">Hutz et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.tan.2006.1778">Tan et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.ko.2007.879">Ko et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.amano.2008.2130">Amano et al 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.balasubramanian.2010.3138">Balasubramanian et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.hamajima.2013.e75137">Hamajima et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.bodian.2014.530">Bodian et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.kato.2014.706">Kato et al 2014</xref>]. Of these 28 individuals, 17 from nine unrelated families have had the diagnosis confirmed molecularly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.hamajima.2013.e75137">Hamajima et al 2013</xref>]. Of the 11 who have not had confirmatory genetic testing, nearly all have clinical findings that significantly overlap those of the individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis.</p>
          <p>A diagnosis of IMAGe syndrome has been considered in other published cases; however, the clinical information was either significantly different from the 28 typical cases or insufficient to determine the diagnosis with certainty, and pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> variants were not reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.blethen.1990.110">Blethen et al 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.hall.1991.63a">Hall &#x00026; Stelling 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.le.1996.854">Le &#x00026; Kutteh 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.coman.2007.2085">Coman et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.mcdonald.2010.154">McDonald et al 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.lindemeyer.2014.165">Lindemeyer et al 2014</xref>]. Several of these cases are further discussed in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="image.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>.</p>
          <p>Because the genetic etiology of IMAGe syndrome has only recently been elucidated, it is likely that the spectrum and natural history of IMAGe syndrome will be refined as more affected individuals are identified.</p>
          <p>Although intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR) may be detected prenatally, IMAGe syndrome is typically evident at birth with IUGR, mild dysmorphic features, adrenal insufficiency, and, in males, genitourinary abnormalities. Of 23 individuals with information about age and findings at presentation, one was identified prenatally, 13 at birth, four in the first month of life, three from age one month to one year, one at age five years, and one at age 15 years.</p>
          <p><bold>Growth.</bold> All neonates have had IUGR with birth weights from -2 to -4 SD and birth lengths from -1.8 to -4.5 SD. Of the nine for whom information was available at birth, five had a normal OFC and four had an OFC from -2 to -3 SD.</p>
          <p>Individuals with IMAGe syndrome consistently demonstrate continued short stature (height -2.7 to -6.5 SD) and postnatal failure to thrive (weight -2 to -7 SD). Of the nine on whom longitudinal information was available, postnatal OFC was normal in seven and below -2 SD in two.</p>
          <p><bold>Skeletal.</bold> All affected individuals have had some skeletal abnormality, most commonly delayed bone age and short stature. Metaphyseal and epiphyseal dysplasia of the long bones are common. The metaphyses are frequently described as striated and the diaphyses as gracile.</p>
          <p>A significant degree of age-dependent variation is observed: in some, the metaphyseal dysplasia may be late, mild, and/or easily missed. Most children have radiologic evidence of skeletal abnormality by age five years.</p>
          <p>Less common skeletal features include progressive and severe scoliosis with onset before age five years, ovoid-shaped vertebral bodies, short first metatarsals, hallux valgus, and hip dysplasia.</p>
          <p>In one individual, fractures of the humerus and tibia were present at birth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.lienhardt.2002.71">Lienhardt et al 2002</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Adrenal insufficiency</bold> appears to be universal. Although this may be due to an ascertainment bias for probands, in one family it appeared fully penetrant, with adrenal insufficiency present in 7/7 individuals who possessed a maternally inherited <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>].</p>
          <p>Adrenal crisis, presenting with hyponatremia, hyperkalemia, and life-threatening hypotension, can occur within the first month of life, typically within the first week; extremely elevated ACTH levels, frequently above 1000 pg/mL (normal 10-60), can cause severe hyperpigmentation in these infants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.vilain.1999.4335">Vilain et al 1999</xref>].</p>
          <p>A few individuals do not have adrenal crisis, but rather milder adrenal insufficiency, presenting with failure to thrive and recurrent vomiting. One child, who experienced recurrent vomiting associated with mild infections from birth, was diagnosed with adrenal insufficiency at age five years following diagnosis of IMAGe syndrome in her younger brother [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.lienhardt.2002.71">Lienhardt et al 2002</xref>]. Another affected individual was diagnosed with hypoaldosteronism without glucocorticoid deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.bodian.2014.530">Bodian et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Genitourinary abnormalities.</bold> Genital abnormalities, which are nearly universal in males with IMAGe syndrome, have not been reported in females. Reported abnormalities include cryptorchidism (usually bilateral), micropenis, and hypospadias.</p>
          <p>Of the 28 individuals reported with IMAGe syndrome 20 are male, which may represent ascertainment bias due to the presence of genital abnormalities in males only. Two females with IMAGe syndrome have had children [Authors, unpublished observations]. No males with IMAGe syndrome are known to have reproduced.</p>
          <p>Hydronephrosis has been reported; however, the majority of affected individuals are reported to have normal renal ultrasound examinations.</p>
          <p><bold>Neurologic.</bold> Developmental outcome is believed to be normal, as 15 of the 16 individuals in whom cognitive outcome was mentioned were reported as normal; the oldest reported was 26 years old.</p>
          <p>Hypotonia was reported in six individuals and noted to be absent in four others; some of those reported with developmental delay likely had motor delays secondary to hypotonia.</p>
          <p>In one affected individual who had wasting of facial and distal muscles, muscle biopsy showed nonspecific myopathic changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.lienhardt.2002.71">Lienhardt et al 2002</xref>].</p>
          <p>Of seven affected individuals with classic IMAGe syndrome for whom head imaging was reported (3 via cranial ultrasound examination, 1 via head CT, and 3 via brain MRI), all were normal.</p>
          <p><bold>Other.</bold> Characteristic facial features that have been reported in the vast majority of individuals include frontal bossing, depressed or wide nasal bridge, and small/low-set ears; features are typically appreciated by toddler age. The facial profile can be similar to the &#x0201c;triangular&#x0201d; facies seen in <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rss" document-type="chapter">Russell-Silver syndrome</related-object>. The facial profile may change with time. Micrognathia or retrognathia are also frequently reported. Less commonly reported are cleft palate or cleft uvula, craniosynostosis, short palpebral fissures, smooth philtrum, and microglossia.</p>
          <p>Variable hypercalcemia of unclear etiology, occasionally with evidence of soft tissue calcifications, was reported in eight of 16 affected individuals on whom information was available. Several individuals have had nephrocalcinosis-associated hypercalcuria. While this hypercalcemia may be a part of IMAGe syndrome itself, it may be secondary to sodium chloride supplementation, which is part of the treatment of the mineralocorticoid deficiency associated with adrenal insufficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.bergad_.2005.3186">Bergad&#x000e1; et al 2005</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>Currently, no genotype-phenotype correlations are known.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>Although few large pedigrees with IMAGe syndrome have been reported to date, it is clear that the mode of inheritance is autosomal dominant in which only maternal transmission of the imprinted pathogenic variant results in IMAGe syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>].</p>
          <p>In one large family of 24 individuals, all seven individuals with IMAGe syndrome inherited the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant from their mother. Consistent with the imprinted expression of <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic>, unaffected individuals either inherited the pathogenic variant from their father (n=9) or did not have the pathogenic variant (n=8) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.bergad_.2005.3186">Bergad&#x000e1; et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>Prior to the identification of its molecular basis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>], IMAGe syndrome was referred to as IMAGe association [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.vilain.1999.4335">Vilain et al 1999</xref>].</p>
          <p>Historically the term &#x0201c;intrauterine growth retardation&#x0201d; was used. More recently, the term &#x0201c;intrauterine growth restriction&#x0201d; has come into favor.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>The prevalence of IMAGe syndrome is currently unknown. A total of 28 affected individuals from 16 families have been reported to date.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="image.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disord">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> is located in the chromosome 11p15 imprinting clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="image.F1">Figure 1</xref>) where abnormal methylation and complex rearrangements can result in other genetically related disorders (see also <xref ref-type="sec" rid="image.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>).</p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="bws" document-type="chapter">Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome</related-object> (BWS), an overgrowth disorder, is associated with loss-of-function pathogenic variants including nonsense and truncating variants as well as missense variants outside the proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA)-binding domain of <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic>. Dysregulation of the imprinting domain(s) and chromosomal rearrangements of this region are also a cause of BWS and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rss" document-type="chapter">Russell-Silver syndrome</related-object>. For details see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="image.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.soejima.2013.402">Soejima &#x00026; Higashimoto [2013]</xref>.</p>
        <p>One family with three generations of nine individuals with Russell-Silver syndrome without detectable adrenal insufficiency has been reported. In this family a <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> p.Arg279Leu variant segregates with the RSS phenotype. Although the variant occurs in the same residue as the IMAGe-causing p.Arg279Pro variant and mildly stabilizes the protein, the p.Arg279Leu variant has no significant effect on cell cycle progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.brioude.2013.823">Brioude et al 2013</xref>]. This family reflects the overlap of RSS and IMAGe syndrome phenotypes.</p>
        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.kerns.2014.e2117">Kerns et al [2014]</xref> reported a family in which intrauterine growth restriction, short stature, and/or early-adulthood-onset diabetes was found in 20 members, none of whom demonstrated adrenal insufficiency. They identified a <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> variant (c.842G&#x0003e;T, p.Arg281Ile) that cosegregated with the phenotype.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="image.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="image.Adrenal_Insufficiency">
          <title>Adrenal Insufficiency</title>
          <p><bold>Congenital adrenal hyperplasia (CAH)</bold> resulting from <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="cah" document-type="chapter">21-hydroxylase deficiency</related-object>, 11-beta hydroxylase deficiency (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/202010">OMIM</ext-link>), 3-beta hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase deficiency (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/201810">OMIM</ext-link>), or 17-alpha hydroxylase deficiency (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/202110">OMIM</ext-link>) can present with ambiguous genitalia at birth and adrenal crisis in infancy or childhood. CAH is far more common than IMAGe syndrome. In addition to distinct biochemical profiles, CAH and IMAGe syndrome differ in the following ways:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Infants with CAH rarely have IUGR.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The genital abnormalities of CAH are typically virilization of females, whereas the genital abnormalities of IMAGe syndrome are undervirilization of males, including cryptorchidism and hypospadias.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The adrenal glands are hypertrophic in CAH and hypoplastic in IMAGe syndrome.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="ahc" document-type="chapter"><bold>X-linked adrenal hypoplasia congenita</bold></related-object>
<bold>(X-linked AHC)</bold> is caused by mutation of the X-linked gene <italic toggle="yes">NROB1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">DAX1</italic>). Males with X-linked AHC can present with adrenal crisis, Addison disease, and/or hypogonadotropic hypogonadism. Onset of adrenal insufficiency in affected males is in infancy (average age 3 weeks) in approximately 60% and in childhood in approximately 40%. A few affected males present in adulthood with infertility.</p>
          <p>Affected males may have cryptorchidism and typically have delayed puberty (onset age &#x0003e;14 years) caused by hypogonadotropic hypogonadism. Males are infertile despite treatment with exogenous gonadotropin therapy or pulsatile gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH). Heterozygous females may occasionally have symptoms of adrenal insufficiency or hypogonadotropic hypogonadism.</p>
          <p>Although males with X-linked AHC typically do not have growth restriction, metaphyseal dysplasia, or the facial features of IMAGe syndrome, in the newborn period their phenotypic features can overlap with males who have IMAGe syndrome, as both conditions include adrenal insufficiency, adrenal hypoplasia, and cryptorchidism.</p>
          <p>The disorders are typically distinguished clinically by the presence of growth restriction in IMAGe syndrome and molecularly by the following findings in males with X-linked AHC:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>A contiguous gene deletion including the gene encoding glycerol kinase (<italic toggle="yes">GK</italic>) with or without deletion of <italic toggle="yes">DMD</italic>, the gene encoding dystrophin (~1/3 of all affected individuals). A contiguous gene deletion can be identified by fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) using a <italic toggle="yes">NR0B1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">DAX1</italic>) cosmid probe or by other deletion/duplication testing methods.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">NR0B1</italic> pathogenic variant identifiable by sequence analysis in nearly 100% of males with isolated AHC and a positive family history consistent with X-linked inheritance (~1/3 of affected individuals)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">NR0B1</italic> pathogenic variant identifiable by sequence analysis in 50% to 70% of males with isolated AHC and a negative family history (~1/3 of affected individuals)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Antley-Bixler syndrome with genital anomalies and disordered steroidogenesis</bold> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="abs" document-type="chapter">Cytochrome P450 Oxidoreductase Deficiency</related-object>) is characterized by growth deficiency, skeletal anomalies, genital abnormalities, and adrenal crises. However, affected individuals typically present with craniosynostosis and often have radiohumeral synostosis, midface retrusion, choanal stenosis or atresia, and multiple joint contractures. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">POR</italic>, the gene encoding NADPH-cytochrome P450 oxidase, have been implicated; inheritance is autosomal recessive.</p>
          <p><bold>Mosaic monosomy 7.</bold> Several males with features of IMAGe syndrome (IUGR [~-2 SD], adrenal hypoplasia or insufficiency, micropenis with severe hypospadias), and mosaic monosomy 7 have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.le.1996.854">Le &#x00026; Kutteh 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.mcdonald.2010.154">McDonald et al 2010</xref>]. As in <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mono7-mds" document-type="chapter">familial monosomy 7 syndrome</related-object>, these individuals may also manifest persistent thrombocytopenia, myelodysplasia, anemia, or neutropenia.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Disorders_of_Growth">
          <title>Disorders of Growth</title>
          <p>Frequently children with IMAGe syndrome have short stature with a normal head size and normal cognitive development. Other disorders of growth with these features should be considered:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rss" document-type="chapter"><bold>Russell-Silver syndrome</bold></related-object>
<bold>(RSS)</bold> is characterized by intrauterine growth restriction and postnatal growth deficiency. Affected individuals typically display proportionate short stature, normal head circumference, fifth digit clinodactyly, genital abnormalities, hemihypotrophy or limb-length asymmetry, and caf&#x000e9;-au-lait spots. Growth velocity is normal in children with RSS.</p>
              <p>Hypomethylation of the paternal imprinting region of 11p15 and maternal uniparental disomy of chromosome 7 have been shown to be causative in a subset of affected individuals. (Abnormalities of 11p15 region resulting in RSS are summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="image.F1">Figure 1</xref>.) Hence, RSS is genetically heterogeneous, and the diagnosis is therefore primarily based on identification of consistent facial and clinical features that include prenatal and postnatal growth retardation with normal head circumference.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="gr_3ms" document-type="chapter"><bold>3-M syndrome</bold></related-object> is characterized by severe pre- and postnatal growth retardation (final height 5-6 SD below the mean), distinctive facial features (including a triangular face, fleshy earlobes, bulbous nose) and normal intelligence. Additional features include short broad neck, prominent trapezii, deformed sternum, short thorax, square shoulders, winged scapulae, hyperlordosis, short fifth fingers, prominent heels, and loose joints. Males with 3-M syndrome have hypogonadism and, occasionally, hypospadias. 3-M syndrome is caused by biallelic pathogenic variants in one of three genes (<italic toggle="yes">CUL7</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">OBSL1</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">CCDC8</italic>); inheritance is autosomal recessive.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="image.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="image.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diag">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with IMAGe syndrome, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Endocrinologic evaluation* to manage adrenal insufficiency, typically including:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Serum and urine concentration of electrolytes</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Serum concentration of glucose and ACTH</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Assessment of arterial blood gases</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Consultation with an endocrinologist</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
              <p>*Of note, individuals who are in shock often have hyponatremia, hyperkalemia, hypoglycemia, acidosis, markedly elevated serum ACTH, and increased urinary excretion of sodium.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Urogenital evaluation and consultation with a urologist to consider management of undescended testicles and/or genital surgery</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p><bold>Adrenal insufficiency.</bold> Management of adrenal insufficiency in IMAGe syndrome is similar to management of adrenal insufficiency from other causes and should be under the supervision of an endocrinologist.</p>
          <p>Episodes of acute adrenal insufficiency require close monitoring of blood pressure, hydration, clinical status, and serum concentration of glucose and electrolytes. Treatment with IV saline, glucose, and cortisol are utilized. If the serum electrolytes do not improve, a mineralocorticoid (fludrocortisone) is added or the dose of cortisol is increased.</p>
          <p>Once the acute episode has been managed, replacement doses of glucocorticoids and mineralocorticoids and oral supplements of sodium chloride are given. Dosages must be increased with stress, such as intercurrent illness, surgery, or trauma. Steroid doses need to be managed to enable optimal linear growth without risking an adrenal crisis.</p>
          <p>The wearing of a Medic Alert<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> bracelet is strongly recommended.</p>
          <p><bold>Growth hormone (GH) therapy.</bold> Although information regarding anticipated adult height in IMAGe syndrome is limited, assessment for GH deficiency should be considered, as one child showed poor GH response to glucagon stimulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.pedreira.2004.274">Pedreira et al 2004</xref>] and other children with normal GH secretion have demonstrated a response in growth with growth hormone therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.lienhardt.2002.71">Lienhardt et al 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.kato.2014.706">Kato et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Genitourinary abnormalities.</bold> Routine surgical management of cryptorchidism and hypospadias by a urologist is indicated.</p>
          <p>Males with hypogonadotropic hypogonadism are likely to need increasing doses of testosterone to induce puberty. Long-term adrenal steroid replacement and testosterone replacement should be managed by an experienced endocrinologist.</p>
          <p><bold>Orthopedic intervention</bold> as necessary for skeletal complications, including scoliosis and hip dysplasia, is appropriate.</p>
          <p><bold>Occupational, speech, or physical therapy</bold> as needed is appropriate, particularly with the hypotonia that often accompanies the syndrome.</p>
          <p><bold>Neurologic</bold> evaluation is indicated if developmental delay and/or hypotonia are present.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complicati">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Vigilance is required during illnesses and surgeries to prevent adrenal crisis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Surveillance includes:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Frequent evaluations by an endocrinologist for management of adrenal insufficiency and growth hormone therapy;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation by an orthopedist as needed to monitor skeletal complications such as scoliosis, tibial/femoral bowing, or pain associated with the skeletal dysplasia;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Neurologic follow up as needed for evaluation of developmental delay and/or hypotonia.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>If prenatal testing for IMAGe syndrome has not been performed, it is appropriate to evaluate newborn sibs of a proband to enable prompt diagnosis and management of adrenal insufficiency.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic testing is indicated if the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant in the family is known;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant in the family is not known, family members can be screened for serum electrolyte abnormalities, elevated serum ACTH level, and skeletal features of IMAGe syndrome, including short stature and delayed bone age.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="image.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>Risks to a mother with IMAGe syndrome during pregnancy include potential adrenal insufficiency; risks during delivery include cephalopelvic disproportion.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="image.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="image.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>The <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant is inherited in an autosomal dominant maternally imprinted manner. In any given affected individual, a pathogenic variant that causes IMAGe syndrome can either be inherited from the mother or arise <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> on the maternally derived <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> allele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>]. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="image.F2">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>In many families with molecularly confirmed IMAGe syndrome, the mother was heterozygous for the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant identified in the proband.</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>In most families, the pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> variant was inherited from an unaffected mother [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.hamajima.2013.e75137">Hamajima et al 2013</xref>].</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>In at least two other families, two women with IMAGe syndrome and a known <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant have had children (one of these children also had IMAGe syndrome) [Authors, unpublished observation].</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recommendations for the evaluation of the mother of a proband include <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> molecular genetic testing.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in maternal leukocyte DNA, possible explanations include a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant in the proband or maternal germline mosaicism.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The father of an affected child with IMAGe syndrome caused by a pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> variant will not have the disorder nor will he be heterozygous for the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant; therefore, he does not require further evaluation/testing.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> The risk to the sibs of the proband depends on the genetic status of the proband&#x02019;s mother:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>When the mother of the proband has the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant, the risk to the sibs is 50%.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in maternal leukocyte DNA, the risk to sibs is slightly greater than that of the general population (though still &#x0003c;1%) because of the possibility of maternal germline mosaicism.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Offspring of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Each child of a woman with IMAGe syndrome has a 50% chance of inheriting the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant and being affected.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Each child of a man with IMAGe syndrome has a 50% chance of inheriting the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant but is expected to be unaffected.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> The risk to other family members depends on the status of the proband's mother: if the proband&#x02019;s mother has the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variant, her family members may be at risk.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="image.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk of having a child with IMAGe syndrome.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="image.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantati">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk (i.e., when the mother has the pathogenic variant) and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible options.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="image.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="image.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="image.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> is located within an imprinted locus at 11p15 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="image.F1">Figure 1</xref>). Imprinting is the epigenetic modification of one of the two alleles of a gene which leads to differential expression depending on the parental origin of the allele. In the case of <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic>, the maternal allele is preferentially expressed.</p>
          <p>See OMIM (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/130650">130650</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/180860">180860</ext-link>) for other phenotypes resulting from dysregulation of the genes shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="image.F1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> comprises three exons, two of which are coding. The longest transcript variant (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000076.2">NM_000076.2</ext-link>) has 1943 nucleotides, 948 of which are coding. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="image" object-id="image.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic variants</bold>. All reported <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variants in individuals with IMAGe syndrome are missense variants on the maternally inherited allele that fall within an eight amino-acid region of the PCNA (proliferating cell nuclear antigen)-binding domain (residues 274-279) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>]. To date, 17 individuals from nine unrelated families with molecularly confirmed IMAGe syndrome have been reported: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al [2012]</xref> reported 11 patients from five families, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.hamajima.2013.e75137">Hamajima et al [2013]</xref> three individuals from one family, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.kato.2014.706">Kato et al [2014]</xref> two individuals from two families, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.bodian.2014.530">Bodian et al [2014]</xref> one individual.</p>
          <table-wrap id="image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 2. </label>
            <caption>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> Pathogenic Variants Discussed in This <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic></p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.815T&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ile272Ser</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_3" rowspan="8" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000076.2">NM_000076.2</ext-link>
                    <break/>
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_000067.1">NP_000067.1</ext-link>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.820G&#x0003e;A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Asp274Asn</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.826T&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Phe276Val</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.827T&#x0003e;C</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Phe276Ser</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.832A&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Lys278Glu</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.836G&#x0003e;C</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg279Pro</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.836G&#x0003e;T</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg279Leu</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.842G&#x0003e;T</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_image.T.cdkn1c_pathogenic_variants_discu_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg281Ile</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The longest isoform of <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C,</italic>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_000067.1">NP_000067.1</ext-link>, is cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1C, also known as p57KIP2, a 316-residue protein that binds to and inhibits G1 phase cyclin-dependent kinases. It functions as a tumor suppressor and negative regulator of cellular proliferation. CDKN1C possesses an amino-terminal cyclin-dependent kinase-binding domain, a central PAPA domain consisting of highly polymorphic proline-alanine repeats, and a carboxy-terminal PCNA domain.</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Coimmunoprecipitation studies in HEK293T cells suggest that pathogenic variants associated with IMAGe syndrome disrupt binding to PCNA, which likely is required for ubiquitin-mediated degradation of p57KIP2/CDKN1C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al 2012</xref>]. Transient transfection experiments in HEK293T cells showed that IMAGe syndrome-associated <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variants were more stable than wild-type CDKN1C protein, likely because the mutated CDKN1C protein is more resistant to proteasome-mediated degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.hamajima.2013.e75137">Hamajima et al 2013</xref>].</p>
          <p>Pathogenic variants in the PCNA-binding site of CDKN1C significantly increase CDKN1C protein stability and prevent cell-cycle progression into the S phase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.borges.2015.2">Borges et al 2015</xref>]. Interestingly, p.Arg281Ile, which was associated with IUGR, short stature, and/or early-adulthood-onset diabetes but not adrenal insufficiency, did not abrogate PCNA binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.kerns.2014.e2117">Kerns et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p>This gain-of-function pathogenic mechanism causing IMAGe syndrome and related conditions is in contrast to loss-of-function pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> that cause <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="bws" document-type="chapter">Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome</related-object> (BWS).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="image.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="image.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="image.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="image.REF.amano.2008.2130">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Amano</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Naoaki</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ishii</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Narumi</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hachiya</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishimura</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hasegawa</surname>
                    <given-names>T.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Radiological evolution in IMAGe association: a case report.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>146A</volume>
                <fpage>2130</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18627061</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arboleda</surname>
                    <given-names>VA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Parnaik</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fleming</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Banerjee</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ferraz-de-Souza</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>D&#x000e9;lot</surname>
                    <given-names>EC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rodriguez-Fernandez</surname>
                    <given-names>IA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Braslavsky</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bergad&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dell'Angelica</surname>
                    <given-names>EC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nelson</surname>
                    <given-names>SF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martinez-Agosto</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Achermann</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vilain</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in the PCNA-binding domain of CDKN1C cause IMAGe syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>44</volume>
                <fpage>788</fpage>
                <lpage>92</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22634751</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.balasubramanian.2010.3138">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Balasubramanian</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sprigg</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                    <given-names>DS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>IMAGe syndrome: Case report with a previously unreported feature and review of published literature.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>152A</volume>
                <fpage>3138</fpage>
                <lpage>42</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21108398</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.bergad_.2005.3186">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bergad&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Del Rey</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lapunzina</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bergad&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fellous</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Copelli</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Familial occurrence of the IMAGe association: additional clinical variants and a proposed mode of inheritance.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>90</volume>
                <fpage>3186</fpage>
                <lpage>90</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15769992</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.blethen.1990.110">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blethen</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wenick</surname>
                    <given-names>GB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hawkins</surname>
                    <given-names>LA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1990</year>
                <article-title>Congenital adrenal hypoplasia in association with growth hormone deficiency, developmental delay, partial androgen resistance, unusual facies, and skeletal abnormalities.</article-title>
                <source>Dysmorph Clin Genet</source>
                <volume>4</volume>
                <fpage>110</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.bodian.2014.530">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bodian</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Solomon</surname>
                    <given-names>BD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khromykh</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thach</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iyer</surname>
                    <given-names>RK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Link</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                    <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baveja</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vockley</surname>
                    <given-names>JG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Niederhuber</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>Diagnosis of an imprinted-gene syndrome by a novel bioinformatics analysis of whole-genome sequences from a family trio.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Genomic Med.</source>
                <volume>2</volume>
                <fpage>530</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25614875</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.borges.2015.2">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Borges</surname>
                    <given-names>KS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arboleda</surname>
                    <given-names>VA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vilain</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2015</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in the PCNA-binding site of CDKN1C inhibit cell proliferation by impairing the entry into S phase.</article-title>
                <source>Cell Div.</source>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>2</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25861374</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.brioude.2013.823">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brioude</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oliver-Petit</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blaise</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Praz</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rossignol</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Jule</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thibaud</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Faussat</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tauber</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Bouc</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Netchine</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2013</year>
                <article-title>CDKN1C mutation affecting the PCNA-binding domain as a cause of familial Russell Silver syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet.</source>
                <volume>50</volume>
                <fpage>823</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24065356</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.coman.2007.2085">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coman</surname>
                    <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>White</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Amor</surname>
                    <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Two siblings with 46,XY DSD, congenital adrenal hypoplasia, aniridia, craniofacial, and skeletal abnormalities and intrauterine growth retardation: a new syndrome?</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>143A</volume>
                <fpage>2085</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17702017</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.hall.1991.63a">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hall</surname>
                    <given-names>BD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stelling</surname>
                    <given-names>MW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1991</year>
                <article-title>Adrenal hypoplasia associated with severe growth deficiency, specific pattern of malformations and psychomotor retardation.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Res.</source>
                <volume>39</volume>
                <fpage>63A</fpage>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.hamajima.2013.e75137">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamajima</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Johmura</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Suzuki</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakanishi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saitoh</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Increased protein stability of CDKN1C causes a gain-of-function phenotype in patients with IMAGe syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>PLoS One.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>e75137</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24098681</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.hutz.2006.66">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hutz</surname>
                    <given-names>JE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Krause</surname>
                    <given-names>AS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Achermann</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vilain</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tauber</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lecointre</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McCabe</surname>
                    <given-names>ER</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hammer</surname>
                    <given-names>GD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Keegan</surname>
                    <given-names>CE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>IMAGe association and congenital adrenal hypoplasia: no disease-causing mutations found in the ACD gene.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Genet Metab.</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>88</volume>
                <fpage>66</fpage>
                <lpage>70</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16504561</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.kato.2014.706">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kato</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamajima</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hasegawa</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Amano</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horikawa</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishimura</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakashima</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fuke</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sano</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fukami</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ogata</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>IMAGe syndrome: clinical and genetic implications based on investigations in three Japanese patients.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</source>
                <volume>80</volume>
                <fpage>706</fpage>
                <lpage>13</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24313804</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.kerns.2014.e2117">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kerns</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Guevara-Aguirre</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Andrew</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Geng</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Guevara</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Guevara-Aguirre</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Guo</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oddoux</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shen</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zurita</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
                    <given-names>RG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ostrer</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hwa</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dauber</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>A novel variant in CDKN1C is associated with intrauterine growth restriction, short stature, and early-adulthood-onset diabetes.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab.</source>
                <volume>99</volume>
                <fpage>E2117</fpage>
                <lpage>22</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25057881</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.ko.2007.879">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ko</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>JH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kim</surname>
                    <given-names>GH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kim</surname>
                    <given-names>AR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoo</surname>
                    <given-names>HW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A case of a Korean newborn with IMAGe association presenting with hyperpigmented skin at birth.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>166</volume>
                <fpage>879</fpage>
                <lpage>80</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17120039</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.le.1996.854">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le</surname>
                    <given-names>SQ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kutteh</surname>
                    <given-names>WH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Monosomy 7 syndrome associated with congenital adrenal hypoplasia and male pseudohermaphroditism.</article-title>
                <source>Obstet Gynecol.</source>
                <year>1996</year>
                <volume>87</volume>
                <fpage>854</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8677114</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.lienhardt.2002.71">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lienhardt</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mas</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kalifa</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chaussain</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tauber</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>IMAGe association: additional clinical features and evidence for recessive autosomal inheritance.</article-title>
                <source>Horm Res.</source>
                <year>2002</year>
                <volume>57</volume>
                <supplement>Suppl 2</supplement>
                <fpage>71</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12065932</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.lindemeyer.2014.165">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindemeyer</surname>
                    <given-names>RG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rashewsky</surname>
                    <given-names>SE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Louie</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schleelein</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Anesthetic and dental management of a child with IMAGe syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Anesth Prog.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>61</volume>
                <fpage>165</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25517553</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.mcdonald.2010.154">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McDonald</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wilson</surname>
                    <given-names>DB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pumbo</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kulkarni</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mason</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Else</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bessler</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ferkol</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shenoy</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Acquired monosomy 7 myelodysplastic syndrome in a child with clinical features suggestive of dyskeratosis congenita and IMAGe association.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>54</volume>
                <fpage>154</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19760774</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.pedreira.2004.274">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pedreira</surname>
                    <given-names>CC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Savarirayan</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zacharin</surname>
                    <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>IMAGe syndrome: a complex disorder affecting growth, adrenal and gonadal function, and skeletal development.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>144</volume>
                <fpage>274</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14760276</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.soejima.2013.402">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Soejima</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Higashimoto</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Epigenetic and genetic alterations of the imprinting disorder Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome and related disorders.</article-title>
                <source>J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>58</volume>
                <fpage>402</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23719190</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.tan.2006.1778">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tan</surname>
                    <given-names>TY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jameson</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Campbell</surname>
                    <given-names>PE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ekert</surname>
                    <given-names>PG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zacharin</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Savarirayan</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Two sisters with IMAGe syndrome: cytomegalic adrenal histopathology, support for autosomal recessive inheritance and literature review.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>140</volume>
                <fpage>1778</fpage>
                <lpage>84</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16835919</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="image.REF.vilain.1999.4335">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vilain</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Merrer</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lecointre</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Desangles</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kay</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maroteaux</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McCabe</surname>
                    <given-names>ER</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>IMAGe, a new clinical association of intrauterine growth retardation, metaphyseal dysplasia, adrenal hypoplasia congenita, and genital anomalies.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab.</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>84</volume>
                <fpage>4335</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10599684</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="image.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="image.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>8 September 2016 (ma) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>13 March 2014 (me) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>11 September 2013 (md) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="image.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>The chromosome 11p15.5 imprinted region and pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> gain-of-function variants that cause IMAGe syndromeThe chromosome 11p15.5 imprinting cluster is functionally divided into Domain 1 and Domain 2. Domain 2 includes the imprinted gene <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> and is regulated by methylation status of the imprinting center 2 (IC2). IC2 is normally methylated on the maternal chromosome and unmethylated on the paternal chromosome, resulting in expression of <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> from the maternal allele only [reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.soejima.2013.402">Soejima &#x00026; Higashimoto 2013</xref>]. The CDKN1C protein schematic shows three key domains: the CDK inhibitory domain which is essential for its role in cell cycle inhibition; the PAPA domain with proline-alanine repeats; and the proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA)-binding domain which binds to PCNA to down-regulate the function of CDKN1C. Symbols above and below the protein schematic indicate the domain locations of <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> pathogenic variants causing IMAGe syndrome and Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome (BWS). IMAGe syndrome is caused by gain-of-function pathogenic missense variants in the <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> region encoding the PCNA-binding domain (amino acids 271-279) of the maternal allele, which cause loss of PCNA binding and pathogenic CDKN1C gain of function.BWS, in contrast, is caused by one of the five following mechanisms: (1) pathogenic loss-of-function variants in the maternal <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> allele, including nonsense and truncating variants as well as missense variants outside the region encoding the PCNA-binding domain; (2) genomic variants involving chromosome 11p15.5 (e.g., duplications, inversions, or translocations) or copy number variants including microduplications or microdeletions of 11p15.5 that reduce the relative dosage of the maternal allele; (3) paternal uniparental disomy of 11p15.5; (4) IC2 loss of methylation on the maternal chromosome; or (5) IC1 gain of methylation on the maternal chromosome. See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="bws" document-type="chapter">Beckwith-Wiedemann Syndrome</related-object> for details.Although 11p15.5-related Russell-Silver syndrome (like IMAGe syndrome) is a disorder of reduced growth, it is caused by (1) hypomethylation of IC1 on the paternal chromosome or (2) chromosomal abnormalities that reduce relative expression of this region from the paternal chromosome (e.g., maternal uniparental disomy, maternally inherited duplications, and other rare chromosomal abnormalities). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rss" document-type="chapter">Russell-Silver Syndrome</related-object> for details.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="image-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="image.F2" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Pedigree of a family demonstrating autosomal dominant maternally imprinted inheritance of IMAGe syndrome. Individuals labeled T/G are heterozygous for the normal &#x0201c;T&#x0201d; allele and the &#x0201c;G&#x0201d; pathogenic variant (<italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic> c.825T&#x0003e;G); individuals labeled T/T are homozygous for the normal T allele. Autosomal dominant transmission is evident; however, only maternal inheritance of the pathogenic variant (G) results in IMAGe syndrome. Of the family members tested for pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1C</italic>, all seven affected individuals had the G variant on the maternally inherited allele and all nine unaffected individuals who had the G variant had inherited it on the paternal allele. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="image.REF.arboleda.2012.788">Arboleda et al [2012]</xref>; reprinted by permission from Macmillan Publishers Ltd.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="image-Image002" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
