<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="oi" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">oi</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title><italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-Related Osteogenesis Imperfecta</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: Brittle Bone Disease, OI</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Steiner</surname>
            <given-names>Robert D</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Executive Director, Marshfield Clinic Research Foundation<break/>Marshfield, Wisconsin</aff>
          <email>steiner.robert@mcrf.mfldclin.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Adsit</surname>
            <given-names>Jessica</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS, CGC</degrees>
          <aff>Legacy Center for Maternal Fetal Medicine<break/>Portland, Oregon</aff>
          <email>jadsit@lhs.org</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Basel</surname>
            <given-names>Donald</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Medical College of Wisconsin<break/>Milwaukee, Wisconsin</aff>
          <email>dbasel@mcw.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="clpb-def" document-type="chapter">CLPB Deficiency</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="col4a1-dis" document-type="chapter">
<italic toggle="yes">COL4A1</italic>-Related Disorders</related-object>
      <abstract id="oi.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related osteogenesis imperfecta (OI) is characterized by fractures with minimal or absent trauma, variable dentinogenesis imperfecta (DI), and, in adult years, hearing loss. The clinical features of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI represent a continuum ranging from perinatal lethality to individuals with severe skeletal deformities, mobility impairments, and very short stature to nearly asymptomatic individuals with a mild predisposition to fractures, normal dentition, normal stature, and normal life span. Fractures can occur in any bone, but are most common in the extremities. DI is characterized by grey or brown teeth that may appear translucent and wear down and break easily. <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI has been classified into four types (I, II, III, and IV) based on clinical presentation and radiographic findings. This classification system can be helpful in providing information about prognosis and management for a given individual. The four OI types are now referred to as follows:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>OI type I: classic non-deforming OI with blue sclerae</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>OI type II: perinatally lethal OI</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>OI type III: progressively deforming OI</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>OI type IV: common variable OI with normal sclerae</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI is based on:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Family history, a history of fractures, and characteristic physical findings;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Radiographic findings (fractures of varying ages and stages of healing, wormian bones, "codfish" vertebrae, and osteopenia); and</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> and/or biochemical analysis of type 1 collagen.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Biochemical testing (i.e., analysis of the structure and quantity of type I collagen synthesized in vitro by cultured dermal fibroblasts) detects abnormalities in 98% of individuals with historically classified OI type II, about 90% with OI type I, about 84% with OI type III, and about 84% with OI type IV. Molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> detects abnormalities in more than 90% of individuals with historically classified OI types I, II, III, or IV.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Ideally, management is by a multidisciplinary team including specialists in the medical management of OI, orthopedics, rehabilitation medicine, pediatric dentistry, and otology/otolaryngology. Parents/other caregivers must practice safe handling techniques. Mainstays of treatment include: bracing of limbs; orthotics to stabilize lax joints; promotion of appropriate physical activity; muscle strengthening; pain management; and physical and occupational therapy to maximize bone stability, improve mobility, prevent contractures, and prevent head and spinal deformity. Mobility devices are used as needed. Fractures are treated with: intramedullary rodding when indicated to provide anatomic positioning of limbs; as short a period of immobility as is practical; small and lightweight casts; and physical therapy as soon as casts are removed. Progressive scoliosis in severe OI does not respond well to conservative or surgical management. Dental care strives to maintain both primary and permanent dentition, a functional bite or occlusion, optimal gingival health, and overall appearance. Conductive hearing loss may be improved with middle ear surgery; later-onset sensorineural hearing loss is treated in the same manner as it is when caused by other conditions.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> During general anesthesia proper positioning on the operating room table and use of cushioning such as egg crate foam can help avoid fractures.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Twice-yearly dental visits beginning in early childhood or even infancy for those with DI or at risk for DI. Hearing evaluation at three- to five-year intervals perhaps beginning as early as age five years until hearing loss is identified, then as indicated based on the nature and degree of hearing loss and associated interventions.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Therapies under investigation:</italic> The role of treatment with bisphosphonates in changing the natural history of OI is incompletely understood. The Cochrane database contains a detailed meta-analysis of available data and as of the most recent update, bisphosphonate therapy did not appear to reduce fracture incidence but it did impact bone density and adult height. Oral alendronate treatment for two years in children with OI significantly decreased bone turnover and increased spine areal bone mineral density (BMD) but was not associated with improved fracture outcomes. Similarly, risedronate increased BMD and reduced first and recurrent clinical fractures in children with OI. Furthermore, human growth hormone therapy as an adjunct to bisphosphonate therapy correlated with improved linear growth and increased BMD.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. The proportion of cases caused by a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> mutation varies by the severity of disease: approximately 60% of cases of classic non-deforming OI with blue sclerae or common variable OI with normal sclerae, virtually 100% of perinatally lethal OI, and close to 100% of progressively deforming OI are <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>. Gonadal mosaicism may be present in 3%-5% of cases. Each child of an individual with a dominantly inherited form of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI has a 50% chance of inheriting the mutation and of developing some manifestations of OI. Prenatal testing in at-risk pregnancies can be performed by molecular genetic testing if the <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> mutation has been identified in an affected relative. Ultrasound examination performed in a center with experience in diagnosing OI can be valuable in the prenatal diagnosis of the lethal form and most severe forms prior to 20 weeks' gestation; milder forms may be detected later in pregnancy if fractures or deformities occur.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="oi.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related osteogenesis imperfecta (OI) is a group of disorders characterized by fractures with minimal or absent trauma, variable dentinogenesis imperfecta (DI), and late-onset hearing loss; however, it is now apparent that the clinical features of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI represent a continuum ranging from perinatal lethality to near-absence of symptoms. The pathogenetic approach to osteogenesis imperfecta has changed with the recent identification of several genes which, when mutated, cause OI. Mutations in all of the recently identified genes (except for the gene which causes OI type V) cause recessively inherited OI. The clinical classification is distinct from the genetic diagnosis, as the recessively inherited forms typically present similarly to the more severe <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related perinatally lethal OI and progressively deforming OI. In time, this clinical classification will be revised; however, there is currently no clear consensus as to the clinical distinctions between the overlapping dominantly and recessively inherited phenotypes. The milder classic non-deforming OI and common variable OI with normal sclerae are caused by mutations in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic></p>
        <p><bold>The clinical diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related osteogenesis imperfecta (OI)</bold> depends on the presence of a number of features (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related">Table 1</xref>). No "diagnostic criteria" exist for types of OI. Features of OI include the following:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Fractures</bold> with minimal or no trauma in the absence of other factors, such as abuse or other known disorders of bone</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Short stature</bold> or stature shorter than predicted based on stature of unaffected family members, often with <bold>bone deformity</bold></p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <bold>Blue / grey sclera hue</bold>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <bold>Dentinogenesis imperfecta (DI)</bold>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>
              <bold>Progressive, post-pubertal hearing loss</bold>
            </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Ligamentous laxity</bold> and other signs of connective tissue abnormality</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Family history</bold> of OI, usually consistent with autosomal dominant inheritance</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <table-wrap id="oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Clinical Features of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-Related Osteogenesis Imperfecta by Type</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inheritance</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fractures</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bone Deformity</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stature</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DI</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sclerae</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_9" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hearing Loss</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Classic non-deforming OI with blue sclerae</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Few to 100</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncommon</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal or slightly short for family</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rare</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blue</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_9" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present in about 50%</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Perinatally lethal OI</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perinatal lethal</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple fracture of ribs, minimal calvarial mineralization, platyspondyly, marked compression of long bones</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severely short stature</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dark blue</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_9" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Progressively deforming OI</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thin ribs, platyspondyly, thin gracile bones with many fractures, "popcorn" epiphyses common</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate to severe</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very short</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blue</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_9" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequent</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Common variable OI with normal sclerae</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate to mild</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild to moderate</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variably short stature</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/-</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal to grey</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_col1a12related_1_1_1_9" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Some</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p><bold>Radiographic features of OI</bold> change with age. The major findings include the following (<xref ref-type="table" rid="oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel">Table 2</xref>):</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Fractures</bold> of varying ages and stages of healing, often of the long bones but may also involve ribs and skull. Metaphyseal fractures characteristic of child abuse can be seen in a small number of children with OI.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>"Codfish" vertebrae,</bold> which are the consequence of spinal compression fractures, seen more commonly in the adult</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Wormian bones,</bold> defined as "sutural bones which are 6 mm by 4 mm (in diameter) or larger, in excess of ten in number, with a tendency to arrangement in a mosaic pattern" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.cremin.1982.35">Cremin et al 1982</xref>]. Wormian bones are suggestive of but not pathognomic for OI.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Protrusio acetabuli</bold> in which the socket of the hip joint is too deep and the acetabulum bulges into the cavity of the pelvis causing intrapelvic protrusion of the acetabulum.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Osteopenia</bold> or osteoporosis detected by dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DEXA). Bone density can be normal, especially in OI type I, as DEXA measures mineral content rather than collagen content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.deodhar.1994.463">Deodhar &#x00026; Woolf 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.paterson.1994.104">Paterson &#x00026; Mole 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.cepollaro.1999.129">Cepollaro et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.lund.1999.1083">Lund et al 1999</xref>].</p>
            <p>Note: (1) A major determinant of bone density may be the individual&#x02019;s ability to ambulate. (2) Bone density standards for children under age two years have been determined after sampling very small populations (often &#x0003c;10 persons), thus reliability is an issue (3) Bone density standards for children are based on height; corrections for short stature of severely affected individuals may need to be made. Bone density is not typically measured in children before age two years because of their inability to lie still, though this may be accomplished with patience in sleeping infants. It is not useful to compare bone density in individuals with OI to standards of individuals without OI, but it is useful to follow the bone density of an individual with OI over time.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <table-wrap id="oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Radiographic Findings of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-Related Osteogenesis Imperfecta by Type</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skull</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Back</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extremities</th>
                <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Classic non-deforming OI with blue sclerae</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wormian bones</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Codfish vertebrae (adults)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thin cortices</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteopenia</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Perinatally lethal OI</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perinatal lethal</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Undermineralization; plaques of calcification</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platyspondyly</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severely deformed; broad, crumpled, bent femurs</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small beaded ribs; findings are pathognomonic</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Progressively deforming OI</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wormian bones</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Codfish vertebrae; kyphoscoliosis</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flared metaphyses ("popcorn"-like appearance [childhood]), bowing, thin cortices</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thin ribs, severe osteoporosis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Common variable OI with normal sclerae</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b1; Wormian bones</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Codfish vertebrae</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thin cortices</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_col1a12rel_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protrusio acetabuli in a subset</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>An algorithm for the diagnosis of OI has been published; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.basel.2009.375">Basel &#x00026; Steiner [2009]</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="oi.F1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
        <sec id="oi.Testing">
          <title>Testing</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Biochemical</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Serum concentrations</bold> of vitamin D, calcium, phosphorous, and alkaline phosphatase are typically normal; however, the latter may be elevated acutely in response to fracture.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Analysis of type 1 collagen</bold> synthesized in vitro by culturing dermal fibroblasts obtained from a small skin biopsy shows the structure and quantity of the collagen. The sensitivity of biochemical testing is approximately 90% in individuals with clinically confirmed OI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.wenstrup.1990.975">Wenstrup et al 1990</xref>; Byers PH, personal communication]. Biochemical analysis is helpful in separating individuals with quantitative defects (classic non-deforming OI) from those with qualitative defects (perinatally lethal OI, progressively deforming OI, and common variable OI with normal sclerae).</p>
              <p>The limitation of biochemical analysis is that it will not identify some quantitative defects of type 1 procollagen, variants that alter sequences in some coding regions of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.van_dijk.2011.1">van Dijk et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <sec id="oi.Molecular_Genetic_Testing">
            <title>Molecular Genetic Testing</title>
            <p><bold>Genes.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> are the genes in which pathogenic variants are known to cause <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1-</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>-related OI. They encode the two chains pro &#x003b1;1(I) and pro &#x003b1;2(I), respectively, of type I procollagen.</p>
            <table-wrap id="oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 3. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-Related Osteogenesis Imperfecta</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                    <th id="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/COL1A2</italic>-Related OI Attributed to Pathogenic Variants in This Gene</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variants Detected&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">~5%-70%&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence variants (&#x0003e;95%)&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon or whole-gene deletions (1%-2%)&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                      <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">~5%-30&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence variants (&#x0003e;95%)&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon or whole-gene deletions (1%-2%)&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
              <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn id="oi.TF.3.1">
                  <label>1. </label>
                  <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="oi" object-id="oi.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="oi.TF.3.2">
                  <label>2. </label>
                  <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="oi.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="oi.TF.3.3">
                  <label>3. </label>
                  <p>Byers P, personal communication</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="oi.TF.3.4">
                  <label>4. </label>
                  <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="oi.TF.3.5">
                  <label>5. </label>
                  <p>Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> cDNA to detect pathogenic variants in the coding sequence and sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> genomic DNA to detect pathogenic variants that alter either sequence or stability of mRNA identify close to 100% of pathogenic variants in these two genes.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="oi.TF.3.6">
                  <label>6. </label>
                  <p>Testing that identifies exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications not readily detectable by sequence analysis of the coding and flanking intronic regions of genomic DNA; included in the variety of methods that may be used are: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and chromosomal microarray (CMA) that includes this gene/chromosome segment.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="oi.TF.3.7">
                  <label>7. </label>
                  <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.van_dijk.2010.736">van Dijk et al [2010]</xref> and <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="oi" object-id="oi.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object>, HGMD</p>
                </fn>
              </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Testing_Strategy_for_a_Proband">
          <title>Testing Strategy for a Proband</title>
          <p><bold>To confirm/establish the diagnosis in a proband.</bold> An approach to the molecular diagnosis of OI has been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.van_dijk.2012.11">van Dijk et al 2012</xref>] See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="oi.F2">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
          <p>The sensitivity for identifying <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2-</italic> related OI by molecular genetic testing is similar to the sensitivity of analysis of the structure and quantity of type 1 collagen in cultured fibroblasts from a skin biopsy, but current diagnostic algorithms favor molecular genetic testing as the first-line test for laboratory confirmation of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2-</italic> related OI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.van_dijk.2011.1">van Dijk et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p>In an individual with suspected OI, the suggested diagnostic work flow is as follows:</p>
          <list list-type="order">
            <list-item>
              <label>1</label>
              <p>Perform sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic> (may require follow-up studies to determine whether a variant is causative).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <label>2</label>
              <p>If no pathogenic variant is found by sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>, deletion/duplication analysis (which detects an additional 1%-2% of pathogenic variants) can be pursued.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <label>3</label>
              <p>If no causative <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic> variant is found, re-review clinical data. With clear evidence of moderate to severe OI, further analysis should proceed to screening for the non-<italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related genetic disorders (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="oi.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Prenatal diagnosis and preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)</bold> for at-risk pregnancies require prior identification of the pathogenic variant(s) in the family.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="oi.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="oi.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>The severity of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related osteogenesis imperfecta (OI) ranges from perinatal lethality to individuals with severe skeletal deformities, mobility impairments, and very short stature to nearly asymptomatic individuals with a mild predisposition to fractures, normal stature, and normal life span. Although <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI comprises the largest proportion of OI, recent classifications based on molecular genetic findings have identified additional types of OI (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="oi.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>)</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic> related OI is classified into four types based on clinical presentation, radiographic features, family history, and natural history [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.sillence.1979.101">Sillence et al 1979</xref>]. An update of the Sillence classification was recently proposed and has gained some acceptance (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.emery.2012">Emery &#x00026; Rimoin [2012]</xref>). Although this classification of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI into types is helpful in providing information about prognosis and management of a given individual, the features of different types of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI overlap and it is not always easy to categorize the extent of the clinical disorder. It is helpful to remember that the severity of clinical and radiographic features lies on a continuum and that the "types" are defined using characteristics that appear to form clinical "nodes." Interfamilial variability is apparent among individuals with the same OI type and intrafamilial variability is apparent among individuals with the same pathogenic variant. Nonetheless, it is reasonable to continue to think of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI in terms of these types in order to provide information about the expected natural history of the disorder.</p>
          <p><bold>Classic non-deforming OI with blue sclerae (previously OI type I)</bold> is characterized by blue sclerae and normal stature. A small proportion of infants with OI type I have femoral bowing at birth. The first fractures may occur at birth or with diapering. More often, the first fractures occur when the infant begins to walk and, more importantly, to fall. Fractures generally occur at a rate of a few to several per year and then decrease in frequency after puberty. Fracture frequency often increases again in adulthood, especially in postmenopausal women and men beyond the fifth decade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.paterson.1984.1694">Paterson et al 1984</xref>]. Affected individuals may have anywhere from a few fractures to more than 100, but the fractures usually heal normally with no resulting deformity.</p>
          <p>Most affected individuals have normal or near normal stature, but may be shorter than other members of their families.</p>
          <p>Joint hypermobility predisposes to a number of minor co-morbidities. The primary clinical concern is early-onset degenerative joint disease due to poor alignment of articular surfaces.</p>
          <p>In their classification of OI, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.sillence.1979.101">Sillence et al [1979]</xref> designated a subset of classic non-deforming OI with dentinogenesis imperfecta (DI) (OI type IB). In DI, morbidity results not from dental decay but rather from premature wearing down of the teeth, which interferes with chewing. DI can be a significant cosmetic concern. Dental eruption in classic non-deforming OI can sometimes occur early.</p>
          <p>Progressive hearing loss occurs in about 50% of adults with classic non-deforming OI, beginning as a conductive hearing loss but with an additional sensorineural hearing loss component in time.</p>
          <p><bold>Perinatally lethal OI (previously OI type II).</bold> Abnormalities characteristic of perinatally lethal OI are evident at birth. Weight and length are small for gestational age. The sclerae are dark blue and connective tissue is extremely fragile. The skull is large for the body size and soft to palpation. Callus formation on the ribs may be palpable. Extremities are short and bowed. Hips are usually flexed and abducted in a "frog-leg" position. Although some fetuses with perinatally lethal die in utero or are spontaneously aborted, more typically infants die in the immediate perinatal period. More than 60% of affected infants die on the first day; 80% die within the first week; survival beyond one year is exceedingly rare and usually involves intensive support such as continuous assisted ventilation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.byers.1988.237">Byers et al 1988</xref>]. Death usually results from pulmonary insufficiency related to the small thorax, rib fractures, or flail chest because of lack of stable ribs. Those who survive the first few days of life may not be able to take in sufficient calories because of respiratory distress.</p>
          <p>Histologic evaluation of bone from infants with perinatally lethal OI shows marked reduction in collagen in secondary trabeculae and cortical bone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.horton.1980.19">Horton et al 1980</xref>]. Cortical bone is hypercellular with large osteocytes. Trabeculae contain woven bone with large immature osteoblasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.cole.1992.112">Cole et al 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.cole.1995.284">Cole &#x00026; Dalgleish 1995</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Progressively deforming OI (previously OI type III).</bold> The diagnosis of progressively deforming OI is readily apparent at birth. Fractures in the newborn period, simply with handling of the infant, are common. In some affected infants, the number and severity of rib fractures lead to death from pulmonary failure in the first few weeks or months of life.</p>
          <p>Infants who survive this period generally fare well, although most do not walk without assistance and usually use a wheel chair or other assistance for mobility because of severe bone fragility and marked bone deformity. Affected individuals have as many as 200 fractures and progressive deformity even in the absence of fracture. Progressively deforming OI is often difficult to manage orthopedically, even with intramedullary rod placement.</p>
          <p>Growth is extremely slow and adults with progressively deforming OI are among the shortest individuals known, with some having adult stature of less than one meter (3 feet).</p>
          <p>Intellect is normal unless there have been intracerebral hemorrhages (extremely rare and apparently limited to a particular genotype). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.faqeih.2009.461">Faqeih et al [2009]</xref> published a report identifying increased risk for intracranial hemorrhage in a &#x0201c;small number&#x0201d; of individuals who were identified to have pathogenic variants affecting exon 49 of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>, which codes for the most carboxy-terminal part of the triple-helical domain of the collagen alpha-2(I) chain. They concluded that this pathogenic variant appeared to increase the risk for abnormal limb development and intracranial bleeding.</p>
          <p>Even within progressively deforming OI, considerable heterogeneity is observed at the clinical level. Some individuals have normal-appearing teeth and facial appearance while others have DI and a large head and enlarged ventricles that reflect the soft calvarium. Relative macrocephaly and barrel chest deformity are observed. Usually sclerae are blue in infancy but lighten with age. Hearing loss generally begins in the teenage years. As molecular testing of this subgroup further differentiates those with <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI from the recessive forms, the clinical profile of this heterogeneous group will become more refined.</p>
          <p>Basilar impression, an abnormality of the craniovertebral junction caused by descent of the skull on the cervical spine, is common. Basilar impression is characterized by invagination of the margins of the foramen magnum upward into the skull, resulting in protrusion of the odontoid process into the foramen magnum. Basilar impression may progress to brain stem compression, obstructive hydrocephalus, or syringomyelia because of direct mechanical blockage of normal CSF flow [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.charnas.1993.2603">Charnas &#x00026; Marini 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.sillence.1994.427">Sillence 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.hayes.1999.357">Hayes et al 1999</xref>]. Symptoms of basilar impression become apparent with neck flexion. Findings include posterior skull pain, C2 sensory deficit, tingling in the fourth and fifth digits, and numbness in the medial forearm. When swimming, affected individuals may perceive that water temperature differs below and above the umbilicus. Lhermitte's sign (tingling on neck flexion) can be demonstrated at any stage. Basilar impression can cause headache with coughing, trigeminal neuralgia, loss of function of the extremities, or parasthesias. At its most severe levels of involvement, sleep apnea and death can occur.</p>
          <p><bold>Common variable OI with normal sclerae (previously OI type IV)</bold> is characterized by mild short stature, DI, adult-onset hearing loss, and normal-to-grey sclerae. This is the most variable form of OI, ranging in severity from moderately severe to so mild that it may be difficult to make the diagnosis.</p>
          <p>Stature is variable and may vary markedly within the family. DI is common but may be mild. Sclerae are typically light blue or gray at birth but quickly lighten to near normal. Hearing loss occurs in some. Basilar impression can occur.</p>
          <sec id="oi.Other_Considerations">
            <title>Other Considerations</title>
            <p><bold>Facial features.</bold> Infants and children with OI are often described as having a triangular-shaped face. The skull is relatively large compared to body size.</p>
            <p><bold>Other skeletal problems.</bold> Individuals with OI may also have scoliosis, early onset arthritis, non- inflammatory arthralgias and myofascial pain.</p>
            <p><bold>Skin.</bold> Easy bruising is a frequent observation in OI. This is believed to be caused by microvascular fragility and poor microstructural support of the connective tissues.</p>
            <p><bold>Hearing loss.</bold> Mixed conductive and sensorineural hearing loss afflicts the majority of adults with OI. Childhood onset hearing loss affects approximately 7% of affected children between ages five and nine years; progressive postpubertal hearing loss is more typical. The initial conductive hearing loss results from fractures of the bones of the middle ear with contracture and scarring of the incus. With age, sensorineural hearing loss compounds the preexisting conductive element. Fixation of the stapes is not unlike otosclerosis and surgical techniques such as stapedotomy used to treat otosclerosis have shown similar success in treating hearing loss in OI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.van_der_rijt.2003.717">van der Rijt &#x00026; Cremers 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.kuurila.2004.187">Kuurila et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.doi.2007.226">Doi et al 2007</xref>]. Bisphosphonate therapy has not been shown to influence hearing loss.</p>
            <p><bold>Gastrointestinal.</bold> Although complaints of constipation are common in adults with OI who are mobile in wheelchairs, it is not clear if this is a complication of OI itself or of the mode of transport. Bowel obstruction can occur as a result of protrusio acetabuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.lee.1995.1352">Lee et al 1995</xref>], but appears to be uncommon.</p>
            <p><bold>Cardiovascular.</bold> Mitral valve prolapse and aortic dilatation have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.mckusick.1972">McKusick 1972</xref>]. Aortic and mitral regurgitation have also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.stein.1977.637">Stein &#x00026; Kloster 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.hortop.1986.54">Hortop et al 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.vetter.1989.184">Vetter et al 1989</xref>]. A minority of individuals with OI have a slightly larger than normal aortic root diameter, but the risk of progression or dissection is not increased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.hortop.1986.54">Hortop et al 1986</xref>]. A recent case report and literature review presented six documented cases to date of individuals who have OI and developed an aortic dissection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.mcneeley.2012.553">McNeeley et al 2012</xref>]. Both arterial and/or aortic dissection have been reported in OI; it remains unclear if they occur more commonly in individuals with OI than in the general population.</p>
            <p><bold>Development.</bold> Cognition is expected to be normal but gross motor development may be hindered by joint hypermobility and progressive deformity due to recurrent fractures.</p>
            <p><bold>Functional limitations.</bold> Individuals with OI may experience other functional limitations, although these will be highly dependent on the specific physical manifestations of OI.</p>
            <p><bold>Life expectancy.</bold> The severely affected neonates with perinatally lethal OI typically do not survive, with a significant proportion of infants dying within the first 48 hours. Aggressive life support can prolong survival but ultimately the most severe forms remain perinatally lethal. Life expectancy for classic non-deforming OI and common variable OI is normal. Progressively deforming OI is highly variable and life expectancy may be shortened by the presence of severe kyphoscoliosis with attendant restrictive pulmonary disease resulting in cardiac insufficiency.</p>
            <p><bold>Pregnancy.</bold> Fertility is normal in OI. Pregnancy in women with OI, especially those with progressively deforming OI, can be complicated because of a small pelvis, which may necessitate delivery by cesarean section. The mode of delivery of infants with OI has been examined to determine if the frequency of complications is higher with vaginal or cesarean section delivery. No difference in the frequency of complications was found. A higher than expected frequency of non-vertex presentations has been noted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.cubert.2001.66">Cubert et al 2001</xref>]. The role of pregnancy in later fractures, loss of bone mineralization, progression of hearing loss, or any other physical consideration has not been examined in detail.</p>
            <p>For most women who have OI, pregnancy is uncomplicated. Joint laxity may increase, as it does with unaffected women, and reduce mobility in small, moderately affected women. Bleeding is probably not more common than usual and complications of vaginal tearing during delivery are not common. Women with OI who are very small require pre-term cesarean section because of respiratory compromise. It is uncertain whether post-partum pelvic relaxation is more common than usual.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>In general a clear genotype-phenotype correlation does not exist. General rules for genotype phenotype correlations in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI have been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.ben_amor.2011">Ben Amor et al 2011</xref>], but there are exceptions to these rules. It is important to keep these exceptions in mind in providing genetic counseling, particularly in the prenatal setting. Genotyping can be helpful in distinguishing classic non-deforming OI from all other types of OI.</p>
          <p>The most common type of <italic toggle="yes">COL1</italic> pathogenic variant in OI affects the triple helix domain of the COL1A1/2 chains. Glycine to serine substitutions may lead to a more severe phenotype in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> than a similar change in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>. Substitutions by arginine, aspartate, glutamate, and valine beyond the first 200 amino acid residues of COL1A1 are usually lethal but may have a variable outcome in COL1A2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.ben_amor.2011">Ben Amor et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Classic non-deforming OI</bold> almost always results from a pathogenic variant in one <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> allele that introduces premature termination codons and decreases the stability of mRNA. These pathogenic variants may occur by codon changes, by frame shifts, and by splicing that results in use of cryptic splice sites and frame shifts. The type I collagen molecule contains two pro &#x003b1;1(I) chains and a single &#x003b1;2(I) chain. If the number of available pro &#x003b1;1(I) chains decreases, the amount of the trimer manufactured is diminished because no more than one pro &#x003b1;2(I) chain can be accommodated per molecule.</p>
          <p><bold>Perinatally lethal OI, progressively deforming OI, and common variable OI</bold> all result from pathogenic variants that alter the structure of either pro &#x003b1;1(I) or pro &#x003b1;2(I) chains. This causes a dominant-negative effect whereby the abnormal protein is integrated into the triple helix and collagen fibril, which in turn undergoes continual remodeling, thus resulting in significantly compromised structural integrity of the bone matrix.</p>
          <p>The most common pathogenic variants result in substitution of another amino acid for glycine in the triple helical domain of either chain; serine, arginine, cysteine, and tryptophan result from substitutions in the first position of the glycine codon and alanine, valine, glutamic acid, and aspartic acid result from substitutions in the second position of the glycine codon.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Substitutions in the pro &#x003b1;1(I) chain by arginine, valine, glutamic acid, aspartic acid, and tryptophan are almost always lethal if they occur in the carboxyl-terminal 70% of the triple helix, and have a non-lethal but still moderately severe phenotype if they occur in the remainder of the chain.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>For the smaller side-chain residues (serine, alanine, and cysteine), the phenotypes are more variable and appear to reflect some characteristics of the stability profile of the triple helix that are not yet fully recognized.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Much more variability occurs with pathogenic variants that affect glycine residues in the pro &#x003b1; 2(I) chain, even with the large side-chain residues; therefore, it is more difficult to determine the genotype-phenotype relationship.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>The other common pathogenic variants affect splice sites. Pathogenic variants that lead to exon skipping in the pro &#x003b1;1(I) chain beyond exon 14 and in the pro &#x003b1;2(I) chain beyond exon 25 are generally lethal. The phenotypes resulting from pathogenic variants in the upstream region are more variable and may lead to significant joint hypermobility.</p>
          <p>A relatively small number of pathogenic variants that alter amino acid sequences in the carboxyl-terminal regions of both chains have been identified. These domains are used for chain association and pathogenic variants have the capacity to destroy this property or lead to abnormalities in chain association. The phenotypic effects of pathogenic variants that affect this domain appear to be milder when they result in exclusion rather than inclusion of the chain.</p>
          <p><bold>Somatic mosaicism</bold> for dominant pathogenic variants has been recognized in perinatally lethal OI, progressively deforming OI, and common variable OI. The phenotype of the individual with somatic mosaicism can range from no identifiable characteristics of OI to one of the mild forms.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Individuals with somatic mosaicism for variants that result in non-lethal forms of OI generally have no phenotypic features of OI, even when the variant is present in a majority of somatic cells.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Somatic mosaicism for variants that result in lethal OI can produce a mild OI phenotype if the variant is present in the majority of somatic cells; otherwise, the mosaicism is generally asymptomatic.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>The penetrance in individuals heterozygous for a <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> pathogenic variant is 100%, although expression may vary considerably, even in the same family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>Previously used nomenclature:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Classic non-deforming OI with blue sclerae: osteogenesis imperfecta type I</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Perinatally lethal OI: osteogenesis imperfecta type II</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Progressively deforming OI: osteogenesisi type III</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Common variable OI with normal sclerae: osteogenesis imperfecta type IV</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>The classification scheme of "OI congenita" and "OI tarda" was discarded because fractures at birth can be noted in mild OI and infants with severe OI may not have fractures at birth.</p>
          <p>In classifications of genetic conditions, OI may be considered a skeletal dysplasia, a connective tissue disorder, a disorder of collagen or extracellular matrix, or a disorder of bone fragility.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>Considering all types, OI has a prevalence of approximately 6-7:100,000. The two mildest forms, classic non-deforming OI and common variable OI, account for considerably more than half of all OI. OI is found in all racial and ethnic groups. The most recent estimates of prevalence come from Finland, where OI is thought to affect about 1:15,000 individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.kuurila.2002.939">Kuurila et al 2002</xref>]. If the same prevalence is assumed for the US, an estimated 18,000 people in the US would be affected. The incidence of the various subtypes includes all causes of OI, both-collagen related and the autosomal recessive subtypes.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Classic non-deforming OI has a prevalence of approximately 3-4:100,000. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.sillence.1979.101">Sillence et al [1979]</xref> reported an incidence in Australia of 3.5 in 100,000.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Perinatally lethal OI has an incidence of about 1-2:100,000. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.sillence.1979.101">Sillence et al [1979]</xref> reported an incidence in Australia of 1.6 per 100,000, translating to an approximate prevalence of 1:20,000 in those who survive early-childhood mortality. Perinatally lethal OI is often not considered in prevalence data because of early lethality. Increasingly, perinatally lethal OI is recognized in utero as a consequence of early screening by ultrasound examination with resultant elective termination of pregnancy. This has resulted in a reduced incidence in affected live births in developed countries.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Progressively deforming OI has a prevalence of 1-2:100,000. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.sillence.1979.101">Sillence et al [1979]</xref> reported an incidence in Australia of 1.6 per 100,000 for progressively deforming OI.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.sillence.1979.101">Sillence et al [1979]</xref> believed common variable OI to be uncommon. Since then it has been recognized to be a relatively common form of OI, probably about as common as classic non-deforming OI.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="oi.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disorders">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="caffey" document-type="chapter"><bold>Caffey disease</bold></related-object>
<bold>(infantile cortical hyperostosis)</bold> is an unusual bone disorder typically associated with some of the following clinical features: mild congenital leg curvature, cortical hyperostosis, curved tibia, irregularity of bone cortex, episodic fever with hot, tender swelling of involved bones (e.g., mandible, ribs), and autosomal dominant inheritance in familial cases. Recently, pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> have been identified in familial cases. Caffey disease is clinically distinct from OI and not usually mistaken for it.</p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="eds" document-type="chapter"><bold>Classic Ehlers-Danlos syndrome</bold></related-object>
<bold>(EDS),</bold> which includes EDS type I and EDS type II, is characterized by skin hyperextensibility, abnormal wound healing, and joint hypermobility. Bones are not unusually fragile and fractures are not increased. Classic EDS is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. More than 50% of individuals with classic EDS have an identifiable pathogenic variant in either <italic toggle="yes">COL5A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL5A2</italic>.</p>
        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.nuytinck.2000.1398">Nuytinck et al [2000]</xref> described two unrelated individuals with classic EDS who were identified to have a substitution of arginine with cysteine in the highly conserved triple helical domain of the pro &#x003b1;1(I) chains in fibrillar collagens. Two arginine-to-cysteine substitutions in the collagen alpha-1(I) chain are associated with classic EDS. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.symoens.2004.e96">Symoens et al [2004]</xref> reported a child with a classic EDS phenotype who was found to harbor a pathogenic variant in the untranslated C-propeptide domain of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic>, which historically has been associated with severe lethal OI.</p>
        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.malfait.2007.387">Malfait et al [2007]</xref> described three unrelated individuals with arginine-to-cysteine substitutions in the collagen alpha-1(I) chain who developed iliac or femoral dissection in early adulthood and also had symptoms of classic EDS and osteopenia. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.cabral.2007.396">Cabral et al [2007]</xref> also report a small family with individuals with a substitution of arginine to cysteine in the collagen alpha-1(I) chain and a combined OI/classic EDS phenotype.</p>
        <p><bold>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome (EDS) arthrochalasia type (formerly EDS VIIA and VIIB).</bold> Affected individuals have congenital bilateral hip dislocation, short stature, joint hypermobility, osteopenia, kyphoscoliosis, velvety hyperextensible skin, and mild bone fragility. The <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> pathogenic variants that cause the arthrochalasia type of EDS affect the splicing of exon 6. This encodes the site at which the amino-terminal procollagen protease cleaves the amino-terminal propeptide from procollagen in the course of extracellular processing. Because all or part of the exon is missing from the final product, the pro &#x003b1; chains retain the extended propeptide, which interferes with normal fibrillogenesis.</p>
        <p><bold>Osteoporosis.</bold> The common variant Sp1 in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> has been shown to affect bone mineral density and quality, predisposing to osteoporotic fractures, particularly of the vertebrae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.grant.1996.203">Grant et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.uitterlinden.1998.1016">Uitterlinden et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.mann.2001.899">Mann et al 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.mann.2003.711">Mann &#x00026; Ralston 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.jin.2011.911">Jin et al 2011</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold>Arterial dissection.</bold> At this time it is unclear whether there is a clear association between spontaneous arterial rupture and <italic toggle="yes">COL1A</italic> variants. A study investigating the histopathologic changes in spontaneous carotid artery dissection (sCAD) concluded that no unique connective tissue or vascular phenotype existed in individuals with a known connective tissue disorder when compared to control subjects with ischemic stroke of other etiologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.dittrich.2007.2120">Dittrich et al 2007</xref>].</p>
        <p>There have been several isolated case reports of individuals with an identified <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> variant who have suffered spontaneous arterial rupture. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.mayer.1996.552">Mayer et al [1996]</xref> described a G-to-C transversion in one <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> allele resulting in a Gly13Ala substitution in the triple helical domain of the &#x003b1;1(I) chain of type I collagen in a 35-year-old woman with dissection of the right internal carotid artery and the right vertebral artery after scuba diving. Other than a history of easy bruising and bluish sclerae, she had no evidence of a connective tissue disorder or of OI. Her family history was negative for other individuals with vasculopathy<bold>.</bold>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.malfait.2007.387">Malfait et al [2007]</xref> describe three unrelated individuals with arginine-to-cysteine substitutions in the collagen alpha-1(I) chain who developed iliac or femoral dissection in early adulthood and also had symptoms of classic EDS and osteopenia.</p>
        <p>See also Clinical Description, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="oi.Other_Considerations">Other Considerations</xref>, <bold>Cardiovascular</bold> for details relating to aortic root dilatation and dissection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="oi.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="oi.COL1A12Related_Osteogenesis_Imperfect">
          <title><italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-Related Osteogenesis Imperfecta (OI)</title>
          <p>The primary differential diagnosis for individuals with features of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI are autosomal recessive subtypes of OI and those subtypes of OI in which specific pathogenic variants have not yet been identified. <xref ref-type="table" rid="oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes">Table 5</xref> summarize the clinical and radiographic features of these subtypes of OI.</p>
          <table-wrap id="oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 4. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Clinical Features of OI by Type</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inheritance</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fractures</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bone Deformity</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stature</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DI</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sclerae</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_9" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hearing Loss</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OI with calcification in interosseous membranes</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple with hypertrophic callus</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_9" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OI type VI</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncertain</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhizomelic shortening</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild short stature</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_9" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OI types VII-XI</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe to moderate</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">variable</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_7" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_8" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.clinical_features_of_oi_by_type_1_1_1_9" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="oi.TF.4.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>Previous nomenclature for type is used.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <table-wrap id="oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 5. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Radiographic Findings of Osteogenesis Imperfecta by Type</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skull</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Back</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extremities</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OI with calcification in interosseous membranes</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?Wormian bones</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertrophic callus, usually of the femurs; mineralization of the interosseus membrane in the forearm</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OI type VI</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?Wormian bones</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similar to common variable OI</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OI types VII-XI</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe to intermediate</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?Wormian bones</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similar to perinatally lethal OI and progressively deforming OI</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_oi.T.radiographic_findings_of_osteogenes_1_1_1_6" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhizomelic shortening</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="oi.TF.5.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>Previous nomenclature for type is used.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Histomorphometric evaluation</bold> of iliac crest bone from individuals with OI with calcification in interosseous membranes, type VI, and type VII OI shows maintained lamellar structure, reduced cortical width and cancellous bone volume, and increased bone remodeling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.rauch.2000.581">Rauch et al 2000</xref>]. The distinction of OI type VI from common variable OI and OI with calcification in interosseous membranes rests in part on a characteristic "fish scale" appearance under polarized light.</p>
          <p><bold>OI with calcification in interosseous membranes (previously OI type V).</bold> This group was initially thought to have either progressively severe OI or common variable OI because of short stature and fractures. Sclerae were generally white. Two features distinguish OI with calcification in interosseous membranes:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Striking hypertrophic callus formation, usually at the site of fractures and often in the femoral shaft; and</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Calcification of the interosseous membrane between the ulna and the radius that leads to the inability to fully supinate and pronate the forearm</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>OI with calcification in interosseous membranes accounts for about 5% of OI. OI with calcification in interosseous membranes has recently been found to be caused by pathogenic variants in the 5&#x02019; UTR of <italic toggle="yes">IFITM5</italic>.</p>
          <p><bold>OI type VI.</bold> The clinical features of OI type VI are similar to those of common variable OI. The defining features of OI with calcification in interosseous membranes are absent. OI type VI accounts for about 5% of OI. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SERPINF1</italic> are believed to be causative.</p>
          <p><bold>OI type VII</bold> is distinguished by rhizomelic shortening of all limbs. OI type VII has been found to date only in a Native Canadian population. It is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. OI type VII maps to a 4.5-Mb region on the short arm of chromosome 3. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">CRTAP</italic> are causative</p>
          <p><bold>OI type VIII</bold> is a lethal/severe OI with a phenotype that overlaps that of perinatally lethal OI or progressively deforming OI with severe osteoporosis, shortened long bones, and a soft skull with wide open fontanel. However, individuals with OI type VIII typically have white sclerae, a round face, and a short barrel-shaped chest. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">LEPRE1</italic> are causative.</p>
          <p><bold>OI type IX</bold> is an autosomal recessive, severe form of OI. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">PPIB</italic> are causative.</p>
          <p><bold>OI type X</bold> is an autosomal recessive form of OI characterized by multiple bone deformities and fractures, generalized osteopenia, dentinogenesis imperfecta, and blue sclerae. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SERPINH1</italic> are causative.</p>
          <p><bold>OI type XI</bold> is an autosomal recessive form of OI. Affected individuals may have joint contractures. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">FKBP10</italic> can cause OI type XI.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.All_Forms_of_OI">
          <title>All Forms of OI</title>
          <p>The differential diagnosis of OI depends largely on the age at which the individual is assessed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.plotkin.2004.16">Plotkin 2004</xref>]. Clinical features that help to differentiate OI from other conditions include characteristic triangular facies, blue sclerae, joint hypermobility, dental abnormalities, and, in adults, hearing loss.</p>
          <sec id="oi.In_Utero">
            <title>In Utero</title>
            <p>Early prenatal ultrasound examination or radiographic findings may lead to a consideration of <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hops" document-type="chapter">hypophosphatasia</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="td" document-type="chapter">thanatophoric dysplasia</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="campo-dysp" document-type="chapter">campomelic dysplasia</related-object>, and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="achon1b" document-type="chapter">achondrogenesis</related-object> as well as perinatally lethal OI. In some cases, either biochemical or molecular testing can be a useful adjunct.</p>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hops" document-type="chapter"><bold>Hypophosphatasia</bold></related-object> is characterized by defective mineralization of bone and/or teeth in the presence of low activity of serum and bone alkaline phosphatase. Clinical features range from stillbirth without mineralized bone at the severe end to pathologic fractures of the lower extremities in later adulthood at the mild end. At least six clinical forms are currently recognized based on age at diagnosis and severity of features, including:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Perinatal (lethal) hypophosphatasia characterized by respiratory insufficiency and hypercalcemia;</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Perinatal (benign) hypophosphatasia with prenatal skeletal manifestations that slowly resolve into the milder childhood or adult form;</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Infantile hypophosphatasia with onset between birth and age six months of rickets without elevated serum alkaline phosphatase activity;</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Childhood hypophosphatasia that ranges from low bone mineral density for age with unexplained fractures to rickets;</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Adult hypophosphatasia characterized by early loss of adult dentition and stress fractures and pseudofractures of the lower extremities in middle age; and</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Odontohypophosphatasia characterized by premature exfoliation of primary teeth and/or severe dental caries as an isolated finding or as part of the above forms of hypophosphatasia.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Recurrence of perinatal and infantile hypophosphatasia may reliably be identified by prenatal ultrasound examination. Undermineralization, small thoracic cavity, shortened long bones, and bowing are typical features of autosomal recessive and severe hypophosphatasia. Long bone bowing has been reported prenatally in affected sibs and in children of individuals with childhood or adult hypophosphatasia, but the finding is not diagnostic of hypophosphatasia.</p>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="td" document-type="chapter"><bold>Thanatophoric dysplasia</bold></related-object> is a neonatal lethal short-limbed dwarfing condition. Ultrasound findings in the first trimester include shortening of the long bones, possibly visible as early as 12-14 weeks' gestation; in a few case reports, increased nuchal translucency and/or reverse flow in the ductus venosus have been observed. In the second and third trimester, ultrasound shows growth deficiency with limb length below the fifth centile recognizable by 20 weeks' gestation, well-ossified spine and skull, platyspondyly, ventriculomegaly, narrow chest cavity with short ribs, polyhydramnios, and bowed femurs (TD type I), cloverleaf skull (kleeblattschaedel) (often in TD type II; occasionally in TD type I) and/or relative macrocephaly. Up to 99% of pathogenic variants causing thanatophoric dysplasia type I and more than 99% of pathogenic variants causing thanatophoric dysplasia type II can be identified through molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">FGFR3</italic>.</p>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="campo-dysp" document-type="chapter"><bold>Campomelic dysplasia</bold></related-object>
<bold>(CD)</bold> is a skeletal dysplasia characterized by distinctive facies, Pierre Robin sequence with cleft palate, shortening and bowing of long bones, and club feet. Other findings include laryngotracheomalacia with respiratory compromise and ambiguous genitalia or normal female external genitalia in most individuals with a 46,XY karyotype. Many affected infants die in the neonatal period; additional problems identified in long-term survivors include short stature, cervical spine instability with cord compression, progressive scoliosis, and hearing impairment.</p>
            <p>Prenatal ultrasound examination may identify skeletal findings such as increased nuchal translucency, micrognathia, short bowed limbs, and hypoplastic scapulae that raise the possibility of CD in a fetus not known to be at increased risk.</p>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="achon1b" document-type="chapter"><bold>Achondrogenesis type 1B</bold></related-object> includes extremely short limbs with short fingers and toes, hypoplasia of the thorax, protuberant abdomen, and hydropic fetal appearance caused by the abundance of soft tissue relative to the short skeleton. The face is flat, the neck is short, and the soft tissue of the neck may be thickened. <italic toggle="yes">SLC26A2</italic> is the only gene known to be associated with this disorder.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="oi.Infancy_and_Childhood">
            <title>Infancy and Childhood</title>
            <p><bold>Non-accidental trauma (child abuse).</bold> OI needs to be distinguished from child physical abuse/non-accidental trauma. The prevalence of physical abuse is much greater than the prevalence of OI, and on rare occasion it can occur in a child with OI. Patient history, family history, physical examination, radiographic imaging, and the clinical course all contribute to the distinction of OI from child abuse. The overlap in clinical features includes multiple or recurrent fractures, fractures that do not match the history of trauma, and the finding of fractures of varying ages and at different stages of healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.carty.1988.350">Carty 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.ablin.1990.1035">Ablin et al 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.steiner.1996.542">Steiner et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.ablin.1997.111">Ablin &#x00026; Sane 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.marlowe.2002.382">Marlowe et al 2002</xref>].</p>
            <p>The continued occurrence of fractures in a child who has been removed from a possibly abusive situation lends support to the possibility of OI. Metaphyseal and rib fractures, thought to be virtually pathognomonic for child abuse, can occur in OI. The presence or absence of blue sclerae is unreliable in distinguishing OI from child abuse because blue sclerae are often found in unaffected normal infants until about age 18 months; children with OI type IV may not have blue sclerae.</p>
            <p>Family history is often unrevealing; families suspected of possible child abuse often provide an unverified family history of frequent fractures; conversely, the family history of individuals with OI often does not reveal any other affected individuals because of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant in the proband or the presence of a mild phenotype in relatives.</p>
            <p>Laboratory testing (biochemical studies or molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>) often is not needed, and in some cases the time required to perform such testing can delay proper disposition of child abuse cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.steiner.1996.542">Steiner et al 1996</xref>]. Marlowe and colleagues suggest: &#x0201c;Given the inability to identify all children with OI by clinical examination in situations of suspected NAI, laboratory testing for OI (and other genetic predispositions for fractures) is a valuable adjunct in discerning the basis for fractures and may identify a small group of children with previously undiagnosed OI&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.marlowe.2002.382">Marlowe et al 2002</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Bruck syndrome</bold> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/259450">OMIM</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.viljoen.1989.122">Viljoen et al 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.mcpherson.1997.28">McPherson &#x00026; Clemens 1997</xref>] is an autosomal recessive condition characterized by bone fragility, congenital joint contractures, clubfeet, normal or blue sclerae, and wormian bones. Some cases result from defects in the lysyl hydroxylase that hydroxylates the amino-terminal lysyl residues involved in crosslink formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.bank.1999.1054">Bank et al 1999</xref>]. More recently, investigators have identified pathogenic variants in additional genes as causative of Bruck syndrome, and there is significant overlap in both the clinical features and the genetic causes of Bruck syndrome and OI.</p>
            <p><bold>Osteoporosis pseudoglioma syndrome</bold> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/259770">OMIM</ext-link>) includes bone fragility and fractures, other skeletal deformities, pseudoglioma with blindness in infancy, and other anomalies. It is caused by pathogenic variants in the gene encoding the lipoprotein receptor-related protein 5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.gong.1996.146">Gong et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.gong.2001.513">Gong et al 2001</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Cole-Carpenter syndrome</bold> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/112240">OMIM</ext-link>) is characterized by bone deformities, multiple fractures, ocular proptosis, shallow orbits, orbital craniosynostosis, frontal bossing, and hydrocephalus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.cole.1987.76">Cole &#x00026; Carpenter 1987</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Hadju-Cheney syndrome</bold> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/102500">OMIM</ext-link>) is characterized by short stature, failure to thrive, conductive hearing loss, dysmorphic features, early tooth loss, genitourinary anomalies, osteopenia, pathologic fractures, wormian bones, failure of suture ossification, basilar impression, vertebral abnormalities, kyphoscoliosis, cervical instability, joint laxity, dislocation of the radial head, long bowed fibulae, pseudoclubbing, short distal digits, acroosteolysis, and hirsutism.</p>
            <p><bold>Gerodermia osteodysplastica</bold> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/231070">OMIM</ext-link>) is characterized by dwarfism, lax skin, osteoporosis, wormian bones, fractures, vertebral compression, dysmorphic facies.</p>
            <p><bold>Idiopathic juvenile osteoporosis (IJO)</bold> typically presents in pre-adolescents with fractures and osteoporosis. The fracture susceptibility and osteoporosis usually resolve spontaneously with puberty. The etiology of IJO is unknown.</p>
            <p><bold>Dentiogenesis imperfecta.</bold> DI can occur separately from OI as an isolated familial condition as a result of pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DSPP</italic> on chromosome 4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.rajpar.2002.2559">Rajpar et al 2002</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Other.</bold>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.levin.1985.257">Levin et al [1985]</xref> reported three families with apparent OI who had unusual skeletal lesions including multilocular radiolucent and radiopaque lesions of the maxilla and mandible (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/166260">OMIM</ext-link>). Coarse trabeculae and diffuse osteopenia were also noted. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.jones.1993.333">Jones &#x00026; Baughman [1993]</xref> reported multiple idiopathic mandibular bone cysts in an individual with OI. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.nishimura.1996.717">Nishimura et al [1996]</xref> reported a fragile bone syndrome in two individuals with craniognathic fibroosseous lesions and abnormal remodeling of the tubular bones.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="oi.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="oi.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diagnos">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs of an individual diagnosed with <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related osteogenesis imperfecta (OI), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical examination to assess deformities and presence of joint laxity</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hearing assessed through formal audiology</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Screening for basilar impression, best performed by CT and/or MRI scanning with views across the base of the skull. There is no universal agreement on when screening for basilar impression should be done; currently, it is recommended on the basis of concerning signs or symptoms on annual physical examination or on reported symptoms by the affected individual.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Cervical spine flexion and extension radiographs, obtained when children are able to cooperate with the examination or prior to participating in sporting activities in more mildly affected individuals</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Dental evaluation by age two to three years for all children with OI and at the time that teeth erupt in those with DI or at risk for DI</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Clinical genetics consultation</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Management focuses on supportive therapy to minimize fractures and maximize function, minimize disability, foster independence, and maintain overall health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.marini.1997.746">Marini &#x00026; Gerber 1997</xref>]. Ideally, OI is managed by a multidisciplinary team including specialists in the medical management of OI, orthopedics, rehabilitation medicine, pediatric dentistry, and otology/otolaryngology.</p>
          <p>Supportive therapy is individualized depending on the severity, the degree of impairment, and the age of the affected individual. Considerable support from medical personnel is generally required by parents caring for infants with perinatally lethal OI.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Physical medicine treatment</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Parents and other caregivers should be instructed in safe handling techniques. These are mostly common sense practices in order to relieve stress on a single point. For example: lift an affected infant by bracing the torso, neck and lower body; avoid any situation where increased pressure is placed on a single point on any long bone; when assisting an affected child in standing up, do not pull excessively on an extended arm but bend down and brace a greater surface area (such as placing a hand behind the back and pulling gently from the front (using the arm) while applying pressure from the rear); avoid sudden acceleration/deceleration movements; and avoid throwing a child in the air. Older children should not ride on amusement park rides. Caregivers should avoid recreating the circumstances of a fracture, as it is likely to happen again.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The use of bracing to try to stabilize progressively deforming limbs depends in part on the subtype of OI. Progressively deforming OI has proven to be progressive despite external or internal bracing. The use of internal rods or braces to support and stabilize deforming limbs is more successful in the milder subtypes of OI and is guided by the expertise of the managing orthopedist.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Orthotics to support ankle instability are used in toddlers with delayed walking secondary to joint hypermobility and in other affected individuals who suffer recurrent subluxations of their ankle joints.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical activity serves a number of purposes. It provides gravitational stressors required for bone growth and remodeling. The muscles supporting joints are strengthened by activity and as an overall benefit, improved joint stability aides in overall well-being as pain levels are reduced and mobility is increased. Physical activity can be self-directed or coordinated through the services of a physical therapist. Each affected individual&#x02019;s needs are unique and thus both physical and occupational therapy should be initiated for increased stability of bone, improved mobility, prevention of contractures, prevention of head and spinal deformity, aerobic fitness, and muscle strengthening</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Mobility devices, such as scooters and chairs for children, and modified automobiles for adults should be considered.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Some individuals with OI experience chronic daily pain associated with both fractures and non-specific myofascial pain associated with the generalized connective tissue disorder. Pain management plays an important role in the management of OI. Some affected individuals do well with minimal analgesics, but many benefit from a multidisciplinary pain management service. Analgesics can be used to control pain from fractures.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Orthopedic treatment.</bold> Fractures are treated as they would be in unaffected children and adults with attention to the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The period of immobility in children with OI should be shortened as much as is practical.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Casts should be small and lightweight.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical therapy should begin as soon as the cast is removed to promote mobility and enhance muscle strength and bone mass.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>At this time, intramedullary rodding remains a mainstay of orthopedic care to provide anatomic positioning of limbs that permits more normal function.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Progressive spinal deformities are particularly difficult to treat because of the poor quality of bone in severely affected children. Progressive scoliosis in severe OI does not respond to conservative management and response to surgical intervention may be limited.</p>
          <p><bold>Pharmacologic treatment.</bold> Bisphosphonates, analogs of pyrophosphate that decrease bone resorption, are being evaluated in both uncontrolled and controlled trials to assess the extent to which they can increase bone mass and bone strength and improve function in children with OI. These studies are still ongoing. Bisphosphonates have been used most extensively in severely affected children with OI; they may be useful in adults with OI as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.adami.2003.126">Adami et al 2003</xref>].</p>
          <p>The role of treatment with bisphosphonates in changing the natural history of OI is incompletely understood. The Cochrane Collaboration is an international network which assembles reviews on various management strategies based on randomized controlled clinical trials within its database in order to improve the practice of evidence-based medicine. As of the Cochrane Collaboration&#x02019;s most recent update of the OI review, bisphosphonate therapy did not appear to reduce fracture incidence but it did impact bone density and adult height [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.dwan.2014.cd005088">Dwan et al 2014</xref>] (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/14651858.CD005088.pub3/abstract;jsessionid=7EE4AB309EAD68F22BE8C7C5554CDE12.f02t02">full text</ext-link>).</p>
          <p>An open-label trial of cyclical intravenous pamidronate (bisphosphonate) was reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.glorieux.1998.947">Glorieux et al [1998]</xref>, and the effects of relatively long-term use in adults by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.astr_m.2002.356">Astr&#x000f6;m &#x00026; Soderhall [2002]</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.zeitlin.2003.1030">Zeitlin et al [2003]</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.falk.2003.573">Falk et al [2003]</xref> replicated the study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.glorieux.1998.947">Glorieux et al [1998]</xref> in children older than age 22 months, but did report one child with fracture non-union following treatment with pamidronate. No randomized placebo-controlled clinical trial of pamidronate has been published. Bisphosphonate treatment has produced improvements in bone histomorphometry, increased bone mineral density (BMD), decreased some biochemical markers of bone resorption, and possibly reduced fracture risk. In addition, some investigators have reported decreased bone pain in young, but not older, children following treatment.</p>
          <p>Pamidronate use is invasive and inconvenient, typically requiring intravenous infusions every three months four hours a day for three days and has real and potential complications. Recently, pamidronate has been offered even to very young children with OI, but complications including transient asymptomatic hypocalcemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.plotkin.2000.1846">Plotkin et al 2000</xref>] and symptomatic hypocalcemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.chien.2002.593">Chien et al 2002</xref>] have been noted. The long-term consequences of lowering bone turnover in children with OI are unknown, but may include delayed bone union after fracture or osteotomy.</p>
          <p>A randomized controlled clinical trial using the oral bisphosphonate alendronate was recently completed and the results published. Ward and colleagues found that treatment with oral alendronate for two years in children with OI significantly decreased bone turnover and increased spine areal BMD but was not associated with improved fracture outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.ward.2011.355">Ward et al 2011</xref>]. In a second study with a different oral bisphosphonate, Bishop and colleagues found that oral risedronate increased areal BMD and reduced first and recurrent clinical fractures in children with OI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.bishop.2010.32">Bishop et al 2010</xref>]. There have not been additional large placebo-controlled trials of IV bisphosphonates, and it is unlikely that additional large randomized placebo controlled studies comparing bisphosphonates with placebo to determine the impact of these agents in altering the natural history of OI will be conducted.</p>
          <p>Zoledronic acid, a newer bisphosphonate with a longer half life, greater potency, and more convenient dosing, is being studied in children with OI. A study comparing pamidronate to zoledronic acid was completed; to date, the results have not been published.</p>
          <p><bold>Basilar impression.</bold> Criteria for surgical intervention are not well defined. If surgery is undertaken, it should be done in a center experienced in the procedures used.</p>
          <p><bold>Dental treatment.</bold> The goals are the maintenance of both primary and permanent dentition, functional bite or occlusion, optimal gingival health, and overall appearance. Pediatric dentists are the most knowledgeable about DI in children. Some consensus exists that early dental restorative coverage of the primary molars and (if possible) aesthetic coverage of the upper anterior teeth is optimal. Plastic polymers are sometimes used to coat teeth. As anxiety can be an issue with children, pre-medication for anxiolysis (e.g., nitrous oxide analgesia or midazolam) can be used for treatment in a clinic setting.</p>
          <p>If warranted, orthodontic treatment can be initiated, but care must be taken in the use of orthodontic appliances because of the brittleness of the teeth.</p>
          <p>Dental restorations in adults may best be done by a general dentist knowledgeable about OI or a specialist in prosthetic dentistry.</p>
          <p><bold>Hearing loss.</bold> Surgical repair of the middle-ear bones and creation of a prosthetic incus can improve unaided hearing.</p>
          <p>Later hearing loss appears to have a significant sensorineural component that does not respond to middle ear surgery. Cochlear implantation has been used in a small number of individuals; outcome data are limited.</p>
          <p><bold>Management of lethal OI.</bold> It is appropriate to offer parents the option of allowing the infant to expire without attempting interventions such as assisted ventilation.</p>
          <p><bold>Other therapies.</bold> Early trials of anabolic steroids, sodium fluoride, testosterone, vitamins C and D, flavinoids, and calcitonin showed minimal or no improvement in bone formation, or too small a sample size was utilized for meaningful conclusions [reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.byers.1992.269">Byers &#x00026; Steiner 1992</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complications">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Special attention should be paid to anesthesia concerns including proper positioning on the operating room table, for which egg crate foam is recommended.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>The following are appropriate:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Dental examinations twice a year for those with DI or at risk for DI</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hearing evaluation at three- to five-year intervals perhaps beginning as early as age five years until hearing loss is identified, then as indicated based on the nature and degree of hearing loss and associated interventions</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Contact sports should be avoided.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="oi.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>Women with OI who have significant skeletal deformity and short stature should be followed during pregnancy by a high-risk prenatal care center.</p>
          <p>Delivery of an infant with OI by cesarean section or by vagina has about the same rate of complications for each type of OI. Delivery of an infant with OI by cesarean section is more frequent than in the general population because a non-vertex presentation cannot be corrected by external manipulation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p><bold>Human growth hormone</bold> has been evaluated as an adjunctive therapy in conjunction with bisphosphonates in a randomized controlled study. In this study, growth hormone therapy was reported to correlate with improved linear growth and increased BMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.antoniazzi.2010.479">Antoniazzi et al 2010</xref>]. An additional study presented similar results in 26 children with moderate to severe OI when growth hormone was used in isolation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.marini.2003.237">Marini et al 2003</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Bone marrow transplantation (BMT)</bold> to introduce normal mesenchymal stem cells that have the capacity to differentiate into normal osteoblasts as well as transplanted mesenchymal stromal cells which produce factors that stimulate endogenous bone growth in individuals with OI has been evaluated in a pilot clinical trial. Preliminary data was promising and a clinical to evaluate this treatment further has recently concluded [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.otsuru.2012.1933">Otsuru et al 2012</xref>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00187018?term=osteogenesis+imperfecta&#x00026;rank=7">www.clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>].</p>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="oi.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="oi.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Classic non-deforming osteogenesis imperfecta (OI), perinatally lethal OI, progressively deforming OI, and common variable OI caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Many individuals diagnosed with the milder forms of OI (classic non-deforming and some probands with common variable OI) have an affected parent.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The proportion of cases caused by <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variants varies by the severity of disease. Approximately 60% of individuals with mild OI have <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> variants; virtually 100% of individuals with progressively deforming or perinatally lethal OI have <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> variants.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recommendations for the evaluation of parents of a proband with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant include clinical examination of the parents and molecular genetic testing if the variant in the proband has been identified.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband is affected, the risk to the sibs is 50%.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When the parents are clinically unaffected, the risk to the sibs of a proband is about 5% because somatic and/or germline mosaicism in a parent is possible.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Each child of an individual with a dominantly inherited form of OI has a 50% chance of inheriting the pathogenic variant.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> The risk to other family members depends on the status of the proband's parents. If a parent is affected, his or her family members are at risk.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p><bold>Considerations in families with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant.</bold> When neither parent of a proband with an autosomal dominant condition has clinical evidence of the disorder, it is likely that the proband has a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant or that one parent has germline mosaicism with or without somatic mosaicism. Other explanations including alternate paternity or maternity (e.g., with assisted reproduction) or undisclosed adoption could also be explored.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Prenatal_Testing">
          <title>Prenatal Testing</title>
          <p>
            <bold>High-risk pregnancies</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Molecular genetic testing.</bold> Analysis of DNA extracted from fetal cells obtained by amniocentesis usually performed at about 15 to 18 weeks' gestation or chorionic villus sampling (CVS) at about ten to 12 weeks' gestation is possible if the disease-causing allele of an affected family member has been identified.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Biochemical analysis</bold> of collagen from fetal cells obtained by CVS at about ten to 12 weeks' gestation has been reported. An abnormality of collagen from cultured cells of an affected family member must be identified before this technique can be used for prenatal testing. Note: Biochemical analysis of collagen from amniocytes is not useful because amniocytes do not produce type I collagen.</p>
              <p>Note: Classic non-deforming cannot be identified prenatally even with CVS cells because the proportion of type I procollagen produced by normal cells is reduced compared to control cells and resembles type I procollagen production from individuals with OI; thus, false positive test results can be an issue.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Prenatal ultrasound examination</bold> performed in a center with experience in diagnosing OI, done at the appropriate gestational age, can be a valuable tool in the prenatal diagnosis of OI. Normally, ultrasound examination detects only the lethal and most severe forms of OI prior to 20 weeks' gestation; milder forms may be detected later in pregnancy when fractures or deformity occur:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>Perinatally lethal OI.</bold> The bony abnormalities can first be seen by ultrasound examination by about 13 to 14 weeks' gestation. By 16 weeks, femoral length is typically two or more weeks delayed, calvarial mineralization is essentially absent, and ribs generally have identified fractures.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>Progressively deforming OI.</bold> Limb length generally begins to fall below the growth curve at about 17 to 18 weeks' gestation; serial ultrasound examinations are required to confirm the trend.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: Gestational age is expressed as menstrual weeks calculated either from the first day of the last normal menstrual period or by ultrasound measurements.</p>
          <p><bold>Low-risk pregnancies.</bold> Routine prenatal ultrasound examination may identify a fetus not known to be at risk for <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/2</italic>-related OI with findings suggestive of OI (perinatally lethal OI or progressively deforming OI) including reduced echogenicity of fetal bones, bowed, crumpled femurs, beaded ribs, evidence of fractures, and markedly diminished calvarial mineralization. As a part of the evaluation of such findings, molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> may be considered; however, inability to identify a pathogenic variant does not eliminate the diagnosis of OI in the fetus.</p>
          <p><bold>Preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)</bold> may be an option for some families in which the pathogenic variant has been identified.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="oi.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="oi.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="oi.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>This review focuses on OI caused by pathogenic variants in either <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>. These two genes encode the &#x003b1; 1 and &#x003b1; 2 chains of collagen type I. Collagen type I is a heterotrimer consisting of two &#x003b1; 1 chains and one &#x003b1; 2 chain. It is initially synthesized as a pro &#x003b1; chain with a propeptide at each end (N-propeptide and C-propeptide). The propeptides are necessary for pro &#x003b1; chain association and triple helix formation that starts at the carboxy-terminal propeptide and extends to the aminoterminal propeptide.</p>
          <sec id="oi.COL1A1">
            <title>
              <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic>
            </title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> is 18 kilobases in size and is composed of 52 exons (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000088.3">NM_000088.3</ext-link>). For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="oi" object-id="oi.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> In the vast majority of instances, classic non-deforming OI results from pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> that result in premature termination codons. The majority of these variants are deletions or insertions of a small number of nucleotides, a number not divisible by three, in the coding sequences of exons throughout the gene. These variants (single-codon changes that introduce premature termination codons) and some splice site variants that lead to exclusive use of cryptic sites and generation of out-of-frame transcripts all lead to premature termination codons. The presence of a premature termination codon that is separated by one or more introns in the gene leads to marked instability of the mRNA derived from the mutated allele. As a consequence, the amount of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> mRNA is reduced to half the normal amount, with no compensation by the other allele.</p>
            <p>The majority of variants in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> that result in perinatally lethal OI, progressively deforming OI, and common variable OI result in substitutions for glycine within the triple helical domain of the pro &#x003b1; chain. The pro &#x003b1; chains consist of an amino-terminal propeptide, a triple helical segment of 1014 amino acids in which glycine is in every third position and prolines preceding glycine residues are generally hydroxylated, as are some lysyl residues in the Y-position of the Gly-X-Y triplet. Glycine, the smallest amino acid, must be in the third position to allow proper chain folding to occur. When substituted, the propagation of the triple helix is delayed, additional post-translation modification occurs, and some of the assembled trimers are never secreted. The consequence of these pathogenic variants is that a diminished amount of type I procollagen is secreted and some of the protein in the matrix has an abnormal structure. The clinical consequence appears to result from the position of the substituted glycine, the chain in which the substitution occurs, and the nature of the substituting amino acid.</p>
            <p>Perinatally lethal OI, progressively deforming OI, and common variable OI can also result from short deletions or duplications of single amino acids or Gly-X-Y triplets and from exon-skipping events within COL1A1. The relationship between genotype and phenotype is complex, although it appears that pathogenic variants closer to the 5' end of the coding sequence that affects the amino-terminal ends of the triple helical domains are likely to have milder clinical phenotypes. This is probably the reflection of chain association occurring at the carboxyl-terminal end of the chain so that a small part of the molecule is affected. Much is still to be learned about the final pathways of molecular pathogenesis.</p>
            <p>The pathogenic variants in most families are unique; only a few recurrent variants (mostly CpG dinucleotides) are seen in more than one family.</p>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> encodes the1464-amino acid pro &#x003b1; 1 chains of type I collagen whose triple helix comprises two &#x003b1; 1 chains and one &#x003b1; 2 chain. Type I is a fibril-forming collagen found in most connective tissues and is abundant in bone, cornea, dermis, and tendon.</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Classic non-deforming OI is generally characterized by decreased production of type I procollagen. With a reduction in the <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> mRNA, an obligatory decrease in the production of type I procollagen occurs, although the protein produced is structurally normal. The diminished amount of type I collagen in bone appears to reduce the amount of bone that can be made and leads to brittle bones.</p>
            <p>The two general outcomes of pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> are either a decrease in the amount of type I procollagen produced or the production of some abnormal type I procollagen molecules.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="oi.COL1A2">
            <title>
              <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>
            </title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> spans approximately 38 kb and comprises 52 exons (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000089.3">NM_000089.3</ext-link>). For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="oi" object-id="oi.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> The majority of variants in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> that result in perinatally lethal OI, progressively deforming OI, and common variable OI result in substitutions for glycine within the triple helical domain of the pro &#x003b1; chain. The pro &#x003b1; chains consist of an amino-terminal propeptide, a triple helical segment of 1014 amino acids in which glycine is in every third position and prolines preceding glycine residues are generally hydroxylated as are some lysyl residues in the Y-position of the Gly-X-Y triplet. Glycine, the smallest amino acid, must be in the third position to allow proper chain folding to occur. When substituted, the propagation of the triple helix is delayed, additional post-translation modification occurs, and some of the assembled trimers are never secreted. The consequence of these pathogenic variants is that a diminished amount of type I procollagen is secreted and some of the protein in the matrix has an abnormal structure. The clinical consequence appears to result from the position of the substituted glycine, the chain in which the substitution occurs, and the nature of the substituting amino acid. Perinatally lethal OI, progressively deforming OI, and common variable OI can also result from short deletions or duplications of single amino acids or Gly-X-Y triplets and from exon-skipping events within <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>. The relationship between genotype and phenotype is complex, although it appears that pathogenic variants closer to the 5' end of the coding sequence that affect the amino-terminal ends of the triple helical domains are likely to have milder clinical phenotypes. This is probably the reflection of chain association occurring at the carboxyl-terminal end of the chain so that a small part of the molecule is affected. Much is still to be learned about the final pathways of molecular pathogenesis.</p>
            <p>The pathogenic variants in most families are unique; only a few recurrent variants (mostly CpG dinucleotides) are seen in more than one family.</p>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product:</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> encodes the 1366-amino acid pro &#x003b1; 2 chain of type 1 collagen whose triple helix comprises two &#x003b1; 1 chains and one &#x003b1; 2 chain. Type 1 is a fibril-forming collagen found in most connective tissues and is abundant in bone, cornea, dermis, and tendon</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product:</bold> The general outcome of pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic> is the production of some abnormal type I procollagen molecules.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="oi.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="oi.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="oi.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="oi.REF.ablin.1990.1035">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ablin</surname>
                    <given-names>DS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Greenspan</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reinhart</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grix</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1990</year>
                <article-title>Differentiation of child abuse from osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
                <volume>154</volume>
                <fpage>1035</fpage>
                <lpage>46</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2108539</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.ablin.1997.111">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ablin</surname>
                    <given-names>DS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sane</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>Non-accidental injury: confusion with temporary brittle bone disease and mild osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Radiol</source>
                <volume>27</volume>
                <fpage>111</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9028840</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.adami.2003.126">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adami</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gatti</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Colapietro</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fracassi</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Braga</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rossini</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tato</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Intravenous neridronate in adults with osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>
                <volume>18</volume>
                <fpage>126</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12510813</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.antoniazzi.2010.479">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Antoniazzi</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Monti</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Venturi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Franceschi</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Doro</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gatti</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zamboni</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tat&#x000f2;</surname>
                    <given-names>L.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>GH in combination with bisphosphonate treatment in osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Endocrinol.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>163</volume>
                <fpage>479</fpage>
                <lpage>87</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20592128</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.astr_m.2002.356">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Astr&#x000f6;m</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Soderhall</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>Beneficial effect of long term intravenous bisphosphonate treatment of osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
                <volume>86</volume>
                <fpage>356</fpage>
                <lpage>64</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11970931</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.bank.1999.1054">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bank</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robins</surname>
                    <given-names>SP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wijmenga</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Breslau-Siderius</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bardoel</surname>
                    <given-names>AF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van der Sluijs</surname>
                    <given-names>HA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pruijs</surname>
                    <given-names>HE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>TeKoppele</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Defective collagen crosslinking in bone, but not in ligament or cartilage, in Bruck syndrome: indications for a bone-specific telopeptide lysyl hydroxylase on chromosome 17.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                <volume>96</volume>
                <fpage>1054</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9927692</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.basel.2009.375">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Basel</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steiner</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta: recent findings shed new light on this once well-understood condition.</article-title>
                <source>Genet Med.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>375</fpage>
                <lpage>85</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19533842</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.ben_amor.2011">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ben Amor IM, Glorieux FH, Rauch F. Genotype-phenotype correlations in autosomal dominant osteogenesis imperfecta. J Osteoporos. 2011;2011:540178.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.bishop.2010.32">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bishop</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harrison</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ahmed</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shaw</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eastell</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Campbell</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knowles</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hill</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hall</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chapman</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sprigg</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rigby</surname>
                    <given-names>A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A randomized, controlled dose-ranging study of risedronate in children with moderate and severe osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>J Bone Miner Res.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>25</volume>
                <fpage>32</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19580461</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.byers.1992.269">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byers</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steiner</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1992</year>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Annu Rev Med</source>
                <volume>43</volume>
                <fpage>269</fpage>
                <lpage>82</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1580589</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.byers.1988.237">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byers</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsipouras</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonadio</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Starman</surname>
                    <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schwartz</surname>
                    <given-names>RC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1988</year>
                <article-title>Perinatal lethal osteogenesis imperfecta (OI type II): a biochemically heterogeneous disorder usually due to new mutations in the genes for type I collagen.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>42</volume>
                <fpage>237</fpage>
                <lpage>48</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3341380</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.cabral.2007.396">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cabral</surname>
                    <given-names>WA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Makareeva</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Letocha</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scribanu</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fertala</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steplewski</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Keene</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Persikov</surname>
                    <given-names>AV</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Leikin</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marini</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Y-position cysteine substitution in type I collagen (alpha1(I)R888C/p.R1066C) is associated with osteogenesis imperfect/Ehlers-Danlos syndrome phenotype.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat</source>
                <volume>28</volume>
                <fpage>396</fpage>
                <lpage>405</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17206620</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.carty.1988.350">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carty</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1988</year>
                <article-title>Brittle or battered.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
                <volume>63</volume>
                <fpage>350</fpage>
                <lpage>2</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3284477</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.cepollaro.1999.129">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cepollaro</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gonnelli</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pondrelli</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Montagnani</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martini</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bruni</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gennari</surname>
                    <given-names>C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta: bone turnover, bone density, and ultrasound parameters.</article-title>
                <source>Calcif Tissue Int.</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>65</volume>
                <fpage>129</fpage>
                <lpage>32</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10430645</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.charnas.1993.2603">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Charnas</surname>
                    <given-names>LR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marini</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1993</year>
                <article-title>Communicating hydrocephalus, basilar invagination, and other neurologic features in osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology</source>
                <volume>43</volume>
                <fpage>2603</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8255464</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.chien.2002.593">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chien</surname>
                    <given-names>YH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chu</surname>
                    <given-names>SY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hsu</surname>
                    <given-names>CC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hwu</surname>
                    <given-names>WL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>Pamidronate treatment of severe osteogenesis imperfecta in a newborn infant.</article-title>
                <source>J Inherit Metab Dis</source>
                <volume>25</volume>
                <fpage>593</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12638943</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.cole.1987.76">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cole</surname>
                    <given-names>DE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carpenter</surname>
                    <given-names>TO</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1987</year>
                <article-title>Bone fragility, craniosynostosis, ocular proptosis, hydrocephalus, and distinctive facial features: a newly recognized type of osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr</source>
                <volume>110</volume>
                <fpage>76</fpage>
                <lpage>80</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3794889</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.cole.1992.112">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cole</surname>
                    <given-names>WG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patterson</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonadio</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Campbell</surname>
                    <given-names>PE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fortune</surname>
                    <given-names>DW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1992</year>
                <article-title>The clinicopathological features of three babies with osteogenesis imperfecta resulting from the substitution of glycine by valine in the pro alpha 1 (I) chain of type I procollagen.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>29</volume>
                <fpage>112</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1613761</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.cole.1995.284">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cole</surname>
                    <given-names>WG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dalgleish</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1995</year>
                <article-title>Perinatal lethal osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>32</volume>
                <fpage>284</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7643358</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.cremin.1982.35">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremin</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goodman</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spranger</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beighton</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1982</year>
                <article-title>Wormian bones in osteogenesis imperfecta and other disorders.</article-title>
                <source>Skeletal Radiol</source>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>35</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7079781</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.cubert.2001.66">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cubert</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cheng</surname>
                    <given-names>EY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mack</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pepin</surname>
                    <given-names>MG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byers</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta: mode of delivery and neonatal outcome.</article-title>
                <source>Obstet Gynecol.</source>
                <year>2001</year>
                <volume>97</volume>
                <fpage>66</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152910</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.deodhar.1994.463">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Deodhar</surname>
                    <given-names>AA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Woolf</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1994</year>
                <article-title>Bone density measurement in osteogenesis imperfecta may well be important.</article-title>
                <source>Postgrad Med J</source>
                <volume>70</volume>
                <fpage>463</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8029175</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.dittrich.2007.2120">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dittrich</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heidbreder</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rohsbach</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schmalhorst</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nassenstein</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maintz</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ringelstein</surname>
                    <given-names>EB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nabavi</surname>
                    <given-names>DG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kuhlenb&#x000e4;umer</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Connective tissue and vascular phenotype in patients with cervical artery dissection.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>68</volume>
                <fpage>2120</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17562832</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.doi.2007.226">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Doi</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishimura</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ohta</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kubo</surname>
                    <given-names>T.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Stapes surgery in Japanese patients with osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Adv Otorhinolaryngol</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>65</volume>
                <fpage>226</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17245052</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.dwan.2014.cd005088">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dwan</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Phillipi</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steiner</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Basel</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Bisphosphonate therapy for osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <month>Jul</month>
                <day>23</day>
                <volume>7</volume>
                <fpage>CD005088</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25054949</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.emery.2012">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Emery AEH, Rimoin DL. <italic toggle="yes">2012 Recommendations of the International Committee for Constitutional Disorders of the Skeleton.</italic> Elsevier; 2012.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.falk.2003.573">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Falk</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heeger</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lynch</surname>
                    <given-names>KA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DeCaro</surname>
                    <given-names>KR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bohach</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gibson</surname>
                    <given-names>KS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Warman</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Intravenous bisphosphonate therapy in children with osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatrics</source>
                <volume>111</volume>
                <fpage>573</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12612238</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.faqeih.2009.461">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Faqeih</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roughley</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glorieux</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rauch</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta type III with intracranial hemorrhage and brachydactyly associated with mutations in exon 49 of COL1A2.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>149A</volume>
                <fpage>461</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19208385</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.glorieux.1998.947">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glorieux</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bishop</surname>
                    <given-names>NJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Plotkin</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chabot</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lanoue</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Travers</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998</year>
                <article-title>Cyclic administration of pamidronate in children with severe osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>339</volume>
                <fpage>947</fpage>
                <lpage>52</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9753709</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.gong.2001.513">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gong</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Slee</surname>
                    <given-names>RB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fukai</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rawadi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roman-Roman</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reginato</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cundy</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glorieux</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lev</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zacharin</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oexle</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marcelino</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Suwairi</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heeger</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sabatakos</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Apte</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adkins</surname>
                    <given-names>WN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Allgrove</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arslan-Kirchner</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Batch</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beighton</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Black</surname>
                    <given-names>GC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boles</surname>
                    <given-names>RG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boon</surname>
                    <given-names>LM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Borrone</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brunner</surname>
                    <given-names>HG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carle</surname>
                    <given-names>GF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dallapiccola</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Floege</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Halfhide</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hall</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hennekam</surname>
                    <given-names>RC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hirose</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jans</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Juppner</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kim</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Keppler-Noreuil</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kohlschuetter</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>LaCombe</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lambert</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lemyre</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Letteboer</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peltonen</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ramesar</surname>
                    <given-names>RS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Romanengo</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Somer</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steichen-Gersdorf</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steinmann</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sullivan</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Superti-Furga</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Swoboda</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van den Boogaard</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van Hul</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vikkula</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Votruba</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zabel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garcia</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baron</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Olsen</surname>
                    <given-names>BR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Warman</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>LDL receptor-related protein 5 (LRP5) affects bone accrual and eye development.</article-title>
                <source>Cell</source>
                <volume>107</volume>
                <fpage>513</fpage>
                <lpage>23</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719191</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.gong.1996.146">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gong</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vikkula</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boon</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beighton</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ramesar</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peltonen</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Somer</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hirose</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dallapiccola</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Swoboda</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zabel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Superti-Furga</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steinmann</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brunner</surname>
                    <given-names>HG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jans</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boles</surname>
                    <given-names>RG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adkins</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van den Boogaard</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Olsen</surname>
                    <given-names>BR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Warman</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>Osteoporosis-pseudoglioma syndrome, a disorder affecting skeletal strength and vision, is assigned to chromosome region 11q12-13.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>59</volume>
                <fpage>146</fpage>
                <lpage>51</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8659519</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.grant.1996.203">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grant</surname>
                    <given-names>SF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reid</surname>
                    <given-names>DM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blake</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Herd</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fogelman</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ralston</surname>
                    <given-names>SH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>Reduced bone density and osteoporosis associated with a polymorphic Sp1 binding site in the collagen type I alpha 1 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>203</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8841196</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.hayes.1999.357">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayes</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Parker</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ell</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sillence</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Basilar impression complicating osteogenesis imperfecta type IV: the clinical and neuroradiological findings in four cases.</article-title>
                <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
                <volume>66</volume>
                <fpage>357</fpage>
                <lpage>64</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10084535</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.horton.1980.19">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horton</surname>
                    <given-names>WA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dockery</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sillence</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rimoin</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1980</year>
                <article-title>An embedding method for histochemical studies of undecalcified skeletal growth plate.</article-title>
                <source>Stain Technol</source>
                <volume>55</volume>
                <fpage>19</fpage>
                <lpage>29</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6158142</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.hortop.1986.54">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hortop</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsipouras</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hanley</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maron</surname>
                    <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shapiro</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1986</year>
                <article-title>Cardiovascular involvement in osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Circulation</source>
                <volume>73</volume>
                <fpage>54</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3940669</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.jin.2011.911">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jin</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Evangelou</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ioannidis</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ralston</surname>
                    <given-names>SH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Polymorphisms in the 5' flank of COL1A1 gene and osteoporosis: meta-analysis of published studies.</article-title>
                <source>Osteoporos Int.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>22</volume>
                <fpage>911</fpage>
                <lpage>21</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20798928</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.jones.1993.333">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jones</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baughman</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Multiple idiopathic mandibular bone cysts in a patient with osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol.</source>
                <year>1993</year>
                <volume>75</volume>
                <fpage>333</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8469544</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.kuurila.2002.939">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kuurila</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaitila</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Johansson</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grenman</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>Hearing loss in Finnish adults with osteogenesis imperfecta: a nationwide survey.</article-title>
                <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
                <volume>111</volume>
                <fpage>939</fpage>
                <lpage>46</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12389865</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.kuurila.2004.187">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kuurila</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pynnonen</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grenman</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Stapes surgery in osteogenesis imperfecta in Finland.</article-title>
                <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>113</volume>
                <fpage>187</fpage>
                <lpage>93</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15053199</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.lee.1995.1352">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>JH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gamble</surname>
                    <given-names>JG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moore</surname>
                    <given-names>RE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rinsky</surname>
                    <given-names>LA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1995</year>
                <article-title>Gastrointestinal problems in patients who have type-III osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>
                <volume>77</volume>
                <fpage>1352</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7673285</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.levin.1985.257">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Levin</surname>
                    <given-names>LS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wright</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byrd</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Greenway</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dorst</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Irani</surname>
                    <given-names>RN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pyeritz</surname>
                    <given-names>RE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Young</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laspia</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta with unusual skeletal lesions: report of three families.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>1985</year>
                <volume>21</volume>
                <fpage>257</fpage>
                <lpage>69</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4014312</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.lund.1999.1083">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lund</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Molgaard</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Muller</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Skovby</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Bone mineral content and collagen defects in osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Acta Paediatr</source>
                <volume>88</volume>
                <fpage>1083</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10565454</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.malfait.2007.387">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Symoens</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Backer</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hermanns-L&#x000ea;</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sakalihasan</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lapi&#x000e8;re</surname>
                    <given-names>CM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Three arginine to cysteine substitutions in the pro-alpha (I)-collagen chain cause Ehlers-Danlos syndrome with a propensity to arterial rupture in early adulthood.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>28</volume>
                <fpage>387</fpage>
                <lpage>95</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17211858</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.mann.2001.899">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mann</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hobson</surname>
                    <given-names>EE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stewart</surname>
                    <given-names>TL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grant</surname>
                    <given-names>SFA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robins</surname>
                    <given-names>SP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aspden</surname>
                    <given-names>RM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ralston</surname>
                    <given-names>SH. A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>COL1A1 Sp1 binding site polymorphism predisposes to osteoporotic fracture by affecting bone density and quality.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Invest.</source>
                <year>2001</year>
                <volume>107</volume>
                <fpage>899</fpage>
                <lpage>907</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11285309</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.mann.2003.711">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mann</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ralston</surname>
                    <given-names>SH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Meta-analysis of COL1A1 Sp1 polymorphism in relation to bone mineral density and osteoporotic fracture.</article-title>
                <source>Bone.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>32</volume>
                <fpage>711</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12810179</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.marini.2003.237">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marini</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hopkins</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glorieux</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chrousos</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gundberg</surname>
                    <given-names>CM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reing</surname>
                    <given-names>CM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Positive linear growth and bone responses to growth hormone treatment in children with types III and IV osteogenesis imperfecta: high predictive value of the carboxyterminal propeptide of type I procollagen.</article-title>
                <source>J Bone Miner Res</source>
                <volume>18</volume>
                <fpage>237</fpage>
                <lpage>43</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12568401</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.marini.1997.746">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marini</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gerber</surname>
                    <given-names>NL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta. Rehabilitation and prospects for gene therapy.</article-title>
                <source>JAMA</source>
                <volume>277</volume>
                <fpage>746</fpage>
                <lpage>50</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9042848</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.marlowe.2002.382">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marlowe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pepin</surname>
                    <given-names>MG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byers</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>Testing for osteogenesis imperfecta in cases of suspected non- accidental injury.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>39</volume>
                <fpage>382</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12070242</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.mayer.1996.552">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayer</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rubin</surname>
                    <given-names>BS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Starman</surname>
                    <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byers</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>Spontaneous multivessel cervical artery dissection in a patient with a substitution of alanine for glycine (G13A) in the alpha 1 (I) chain of type I collagen.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology</source>
                <volume>47</volume>
                <fpage>552</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8757037</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.mckusick.1972">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">McKusick VA. Osteogenesis imperfecta. In: McKusick VA. <italic toggle="yes">Heritable Disorders of Connective Tissue</italic>. 4 ed. St Louis, MO: Mosby; 1972.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.mcneeley.2012.553">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McNeeley</surname>
                    <given-names>MF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dontchos</surname>
                    <given-names>BN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laflamme</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hubka</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sadro</surname>
                    <given-names>CT</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>Aortic dissection in osteogenesis imperfecta: case report and review of the literature.</article-title>
                <source>Emerg Radiol.</source>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>553</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22527359</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.mcpherson.1997.28">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McPherson</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clemens</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>Bruck syndrome (osteogenesis imperfecta with congenital joint contractures): review and report on the first North American case.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>70</volume>
                <fpage>28</fpage>
                <lpage>31</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9129737</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.nishimura.1996.717">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishimura</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haga</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ikeuchi</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aoki</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yamato</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Fragile bone syndrome associated with craniognathic fibro-osseous lesions and abnormal modeling of the tubular bones: report of two cases and review of the literature.</article-title>
                <source>Skeletal Radiol.</source>
                <year>1996</year>
                <volume>25</volume>
                <fpage>717</fpage>
                <lpage>22</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8958616</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.nuytinck.2000.1398">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nuytinck</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Freund</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lagae</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pierard</surname>
                    <given-names>GE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hermanns-Le</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>Classical Ehlers-Danlos syndrome caused by a mutation in type I collagen.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>66</volume>
                <fpage>1398</fpage>
                <lpage>402</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10739762</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.otsuru.2012.1933">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Otsuru</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gordon</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shimono</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jethva</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marino</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Phillips</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hofmann</surname>
                    <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Veronesi</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dominici</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iwamoto</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horwitz</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>Transplanted bone marrow mononuclear cells and MSCs impart clinical benefit to children with osteogenesis imperfecta through different mechanisms</article-title>
                <source>Blood.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>120</volume>
                <fpage>1933</fpage>
                <lpage>41</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22829629</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.paterson.1984.1694">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Paterson</surname>
                    <given-names>CR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McAllion</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stellman</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1984</year>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta after the menopause.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>310</volume>
                <fpage>1694</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6727948</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.paterson.1994.104">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Paterson</surname>
                    <given-names>CR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mole</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1994</year>
                <article-title>Bone density in osteogenesis imperfecta may well be normal.</article-title>
                <source>Postgrad Med J</source>
                <volume>70</volume>
                <fpage>104</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8170878</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.plotkin.2004.16">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Plotkin</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004</year>
                <article-title>Syndromes with congenital brittle bones.</article-title>
                <source>BMC Pediatr</source>
                <volume>4</volume>
                <fpage>16</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15339338</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.plotkin.2000.1846">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Plotkin</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rauch</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bishop</surname>
                    <given-names>NJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Montpetit</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ruck-Gibis</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Travers</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glorieux</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>Pamidronate treatment of severe osteogenesis imperfecta in children under 3 years of age.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
                <volume>85</volume>
                <fpage>1846</fpage>
                <lpage>50</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10843163</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.rajpar.2002.2559">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rajpar</surname>
                    <given-names>MH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koch</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Davies</surname>
                    <given-names>RM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mellody</surname>
                    <given-names>KT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kielty</surname>
                    <given-names>CM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dixon</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>Mutation of the signal peptide region of the bicistronic gene DSPP affects translocation to the endoplasmic reticulum and results in defective dentine biomineralization.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>2559</fpage>
                <lpage>65</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12354781</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.rauch.2000.581">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rauch</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Travers</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Parfitt</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glorieux</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>Static and dynamic bone histomorphometry in children with osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Bone</source>
                <volume>26</volume>
                <fpage>581</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10831929</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.sillence.1994.427">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sillence</surname>
                    <given-names>DO</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1994</year>
                <article-title>Craniocervical abnormalities in osteogenesis imperfecta: genetic and molecular correlation.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Radiol</source>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>427</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7700720</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.sillence.1979.101">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sillence</surname>
                    <given-names>DO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Senn</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Danks</surname>
                    <given-names>DM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1979</year>
                <article-title>Genetic heterogeneity in osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>16</volume>
                <fpage>101</fpage>
                <lpage>16</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">458828</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.stein.1977.637">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stein</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kloster</surname>
                    <given-names>FE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1977</year>
                <article-title>Valvular heart disease in osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Am Heart J</source>
                <volume>94</volume>
                <fpage>637</fpage>
                <lpage>41</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">143883</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.steiner.1996.542">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steiner</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pepin</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byers</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>Studies of collagen synthesis and structure in the differentiation of child abuse from osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr</source>
                <volume>128</volume>
                <fpage>542</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8618190</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.symoens.2004.e96">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Symoens</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nuytinck</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Legius</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Met&#x0003e;Val substitution in a highly conserved region of the pro-alpha1(I) collagen C-propeptide domain causes alternative splicing and a mild EDS/OI phenotype.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>41</volume>
                <fpage>e96</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15235039</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.uitterlinden.1998.1016">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Uitterlinden</surname>
                    <given-names>AG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burger</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yue</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McGuigan</surname>
                    <given-names>FE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grant</surname>
                    <given-names>SF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hofman</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Leeuwen</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pols</surname>
                    <given-names>HA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ralston</surname>
                    <given-names>SH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998</year>
                <article-title>Relation of alleles of the collagen type Ialpha1 gene to bone density and the risk of osteoporotic fractures in postmenopausal women.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>338</volume>
                <fpage>1016</fpage>
                <lpage>21</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9535665</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.van_der_rijt.2003.717">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van der Rijt</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cremers</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Stapes surgery in osteogenesis imperfecta: results of a new series.</article-title>
                <source>Otol Neurotol</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>717</fpage>
                <lpage>22</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14501445</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.van_dijk.2012.11">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Dijk</surname>
                    <given-names>FS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byers</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dalgleish</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maugeri</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rohrbach</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Symoens</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sistermans</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pals</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>EMQN best practice guidelines for the laboratory diagnosis of osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>11</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829228</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.van_dijk.2011.1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Dijk</surname>
                    <given-names>FS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cobben</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kariminejad</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maugeri</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nikkels</surname>
                    <given-names>PGJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Rijn</surname>
                    <given-names>RR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pals</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta: a review with clinical examples.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Syndromol</source>
                <volume>2</volume>
                <fpage>1</fpage>
                <lpage>20</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22570641</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.van_dijk.2010.736">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Dijk</surname>
                    <given-names>FS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huizer</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kariminejad</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marcelis</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Plomp</surname>
                    <given-names>AS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Terhal</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meijers-Heijboer</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Weiss</surname>
                    <given-names>MM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Rijn</surname>
                    <given-names>RR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cobben</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pals</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Complete COL1A1 allele deletions in osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Genet Med.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>12</volume>
                <fpage>736</fpage>
                <lpage>41</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21113976</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.vetter.1989.184">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vetter</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maierhofer</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Muller</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lang</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Teller</surname>
                    <given-names>WM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brenner</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frohneberg</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Worsdorfer</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1989</year>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta in childhood: cardiac and renal manifestations.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>
                <volume>149</volume>
                <fpage>184</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2693094</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.viljoen.1989.122">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viljoen</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Versfeld</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beighton</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1989</year>
                <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta with congenital joint contractures (Bruck syndrome).</article-title>
                <source>Clin Genet</source>
                <volume>36</volume>
                <fpage>122</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2766569</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.ward.2011.355">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ward</surname>
                    <given-names>LM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rauch</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Whyte</surname>
                    <given-names>MP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>D'Astous</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gates</surname>
                    <given-names>PE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grogan</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lester</surname>
                    <given-names>EL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McCall</surname>
                    <given-names>RE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pressly</surname>
                    <given-names>TA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sanders</surname>
                    <given-names>JO</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steiner</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sullivan</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tyerman</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith-Wright</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Verbruggen</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heyden</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lombardi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glorieux</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Alendronate for the treatment of pediatric osteogenesis imperfecta: a randomized placebo-controlled study.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <month>Feb</month>
                <volume>96</volume>
                <fpage>355</fpage>
                <lpage>64</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21106710</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.wenstrup.1990.975">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wenstrup</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Willing</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Starman</surname>
                    <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Byers</surname>
                    <given-names>PH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1990</year>
                <article-title>Distinct biochemical phenotypes predict clinical severity in nonlethal variants of osteogenesis imperfecta.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>46</volume>
                <fpage>975</fpage>
                <lpage>82</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2339695</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="oi.REF.zeitlin.2003.1030">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeitlin</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rauch</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Plotkin</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glorieux</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Height and weight development during four years of therapy with cyclical intravenous pamidronate in children and adolescents with osteogenesis imperfecta types I, III, and IV.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatrics</source>
                <volume>111</volume>
                <fpage>1030</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12728084</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Suggested_Reading">
          <title>Suggested Reading</title>
          <ref-list id="oi.Suggested_Reading.reflist0">
            <ref id="oi.REF.byers">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Byers PH. Disorders of collagen biosynthesis and structure. In: Valle D, Beaudet AL, Vogelstein B, Kinzler KW, Antonarakis SE, Ballabio A, Gibson K, Mitchell G, eds. <italic toggle="yes">The Online Metabolic and Molecular Bases of Inherited Disease (OMMBID).</italic> New York, NY: McGraw-Hill. Chap 205. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ommbid.mhmedical.com/">online</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="oi.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="oi.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>Dr. Steiner is a pediatrician, clinical geneticist, and clinical biochemical geneticist. He specializes in inherited metabolic diseases and osteogenesis imperfecta. Dr. Steiner runs an OI clinic at Shriners Hospital in Portland for evaluation of children with OI.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Linked Clinical Research Centers</bold>
          </p>
          <p>A joint initiative from the OI Foundation and the Children&#x02019;s Brittle Bone Foundation, the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oif.org/site/PageServer?pagename=RS_lcrc">Linked Clinical Research Centers</ext-link> (LCRC) constitute a nationwide network designed to provide the highest quality of standardized medical care for people living with osteogenesis imperfecta.</p>
          <p>The first five hospitals participating in the LCRC:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Baylor Medical Center (Houston, TX)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Kennedy Krieger Institute (Baltimore, MD)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Oregon Health &#x00026; Science University/Portland Shriners (Portland, OR)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Shriners Hospital for Children (Chicago, IL)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Shriners Hospital for Children (Montreal, Quebec)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Author_History">
          <title>Author History</title>
          <p>Jessica Adsit, MS, CGC (2013-present)Donald Basel, MD, MCW (2013-present)Peter H Byers, MD; University of Washington Health Sciences Center (2003-2013)Melanie G Pepin, MS, CGC; University of Washington Health Sciences Center (2003-2013)Robert D Steiner, MD (2003-present)</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="oi.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>14 February 2013 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>28 January 2005 (me) Review posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>14 June 2003 (rs) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="oi.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Recommended testing algorithm for evaluation of osteogenesis imperfecta<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.basel.2009.375">Basel &#x00026; Steiner [2009]</xref>. Reprinted with permission from Macmillan Publishers Ltd.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oi-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="oi.F2" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Preferred diagnostic flow in OIThe approach to diagnosis is designed to maximize the likelihood that causative variants will be identified in all affected individuals or assign those without causative variants to research pools. This flow assumes that the clinical diagnosis of OI is well established according to the traditional diagnostic criteria. With clear evidence of OI from radiologic and clinical examination, further analysis should proceed according to the proposed strategy. Functional analysis consists of analysis of proteins and mRNA/cDNA from cultured fibroblasts and also includes <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> null allele testing in certain selected cases.Used by permission: Creative Commons License [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="oi.REF.van_dijk.2012.11">van Dijk et al 2012</xref>]</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oi-Image002" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
