<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="pai-1-def" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">pai-1-def</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Complete Plasminogen Activator Inhibitor 1 Deficiency</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: Complete PAI-1 Deficiency, Homozygous PAI-1 Deficiency</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Heiman</surname>
            <given-names>Meadow</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="pai-1-def.Td.aff1"/>
          <email>mheiman@IHTC.org</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gupta</surname>
            <given-names>Sweta</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="pai-1-def.Td.aff1"/>
          <email>sgupta@ihtc.org</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Khan</surname>
            <given-names>Sadiya S</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="pai-1-def.Td.aff2"/>
          <email>s-khan-1@northwestern.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vaughan</surname>
            <given-names>Douglas E</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="pai-1-def.Td.aff2"/>
          <email>d-vaughan@northwestern.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Shapiro</surname>
            <given-names>Amy D</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="pai-1-def.Td.aff1"/>
          <email>ashapiro@ihtc.org</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="pai-1-def.Td.aff1">Indiana Hemophilia &#x00026; Thrombosis Center<break/>Indianapolis, Indiana</aff>
      <aff id="pai-1-def.Td.aff2">Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine<break/>Chicago, Illinois</aff>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="bethlem" document-type="chapter">Collagen Type VI-Related Disorders</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="ccfdn" document-type="chapter">Congenital Cataracts, Facial Dysmorphism, and Neuropathy</related-object>
      <abstract id="pai-1-def.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Untreated complete plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 (PAI-1) deficiency is characterized by mild to moderate bleeding, although in some instances bleeding can be life threatening. Most commonly, delayed bleeding is associated with injury, trauma, or surgery; spontaneous bleeding does not occur. While males and females with complete PAI-1 deficiency are affected equally, females may present more frequently with clinical manifestations or earlier in life than males due to menorrhagia and postpartum hemorrhage. Fewer than ten families with complete PAI-1 deficiency have been reported to date. The incidence of complete PAI-1 deficiency is higher than expected in the genetic isolate of the Old Order Amish population of eastern and southern Indiana due to a pathogenic founder variant. In one family from this Old Order Amish population, seven individuals had cardiac fibrosis ranging from minimal-to-moderate (6 individuals) to severe (1).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of complete PAI-1 deficiency is established in a proband when PAI-1 antigen is undetectable and PAI-1 activity is lower than 1 IU/mL<sup>-1</sup> and/or biallelic <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants are identified on molecular genetic testing. Note that because the normal range of functional PAI-1 activity assay starts at zero in most laboratories, the ability to discriminate between normal and abnormal levels of activity is limited.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Management of the bleeding disorder by a team of experts in the treatment of individuals with bleeding disorders is highly recommended. Intravenous antifibrinolytics (e.g., epsilon-aminocaproic acid [EACA] and tranexamic acid) can be used for severe bleeding manifestations, including intracranial hemorrhage (with or without hematoma evacuation). Infusion of fresh-frozen plasma can be used as needed to increase PAI-1 activity prior to achieving therapeutic steady state levels of antifibrinolytics. Heavy menstrual bleeding can often be managed with antifibrinolytics or hormonal suppression therapy. Treatment of cardiac fibrosis is symptomatic.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of primary manifestations:</italic> Antifibrinolytics should be used to prevent bleeding for surgical and dental procedures, childbirth, and other invasive procedures.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Regular follow up with a team of experts in the treatment of individuals with bleeding disorders is recommended. For all individuals with complete PAI-1 deficiency, screening echocardiogram for evidence of cardiac fibrosis is recommended beginning at age 15 years with follow up for those with positive findings as indicated by a cardiologist and every two years for those with no cardiac findings at the time of the last screening.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Medications that affect coagulation including aspirin, ibuprofen, and some herbal remedies; high-risk activities such as contact sports.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> It is appropriate to clarify the genetic status of apparently asymptomatic older and younger sibs of an individual with complete PAI-1 deficiency in order to identify as early as possible those who would benefit from prompt initiation of treatment and preventive measures.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Pregnancy management:</italic> Recommendations based on published findings during pregnancies in two women with complete PAI-1 deficiency are oral administration of either tranexamic acid or EACA for intermittent bleeding in the first and second trimester, from 26 weeks&#x02019; gestation through delivery, and for at least two weeks post partum. Note: Evidence that these recommendations would be effective in all pregnancies of women with complete PAI-1 deficiency is lacking; the teratogenicity of EACA and tranexamic acid is unknown and information regarding their safety during pregnancy and lactation is limited.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>Complete PAI-1 deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing complete PAI-1 deficiency. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Once the <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, carrier testing for at-risk relatives, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk for complete PAI-1 deficiency, and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>No formal diagnostic criteria for establishing a diagnosis of complete plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 (PAI-1) deficiency have been published.</p>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Complete PAI-1 deficiency <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Medical_History">medical history</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Laboratory_Findings">laboratory findings</xref>.</p>
          <sec id="pai-1-def.Medical_History">
            <title>Medical History</title>
            <p>Bleeding disorder that typically presents as:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Delayed bleeding following injury, trauma, or surgery</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>In females, menorrhagia and abnormal bleeding with pregnancy</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Absence of other known bleeding disorders including:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>von Willebrand disease</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Factor V deficiency</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Factor X deficiency</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Factor II deficiency</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Alpha 2 antiplasmin deficiency</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Factor XIII deficiency</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Platelet function disorders (including Scott syndrome and Quebec platelet disorder)</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="pai-1-def.Laboratory_Findings">
            <title>Laboratory Findings</title>
            <p>Normal: common tests of coagulation including prothrombin time (PT), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT), and thrombin clotting time (TCT)</p>
            <p>Abnormal tests indicative of a hyperfibrinolytic state; these may include the following:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Decreased plasma plasminogen</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Decreased plasma &#x003b1;-2-antiplasmin</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Decreased plasma total and free levels of tissue-type plasminogen activator antigen (t-PA)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Shortened euglobin lysis time (ECLT) in plasma. Note: While ECLT is shortened due to excessive fibrinolysis in persons with complete PAI-1 deficiency, and ECLT and whole blood clotting assays (e.g., the thromboelastogram) can be helpful in diagnosis of hyperfibrinolytic states, these tests are insufficient to confirm or exclude the diagnosis of complete PAI-1 deficiency.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>PAI-1 specific assays:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>PAI-1 antigen assay (to determine the level of PAI-1 antigen) can be helpful in identifying complete PAI-1 deficiency if no PAI-1 is produced, but is not helpful if dysfunctional protein is produced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.gupta.2014">Gupta et al 2014</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>PAI-1 activity assay can be used to exclude a diagnosis of complete PAI-1 deficiency when PAI-1 activity levels are clearly within the normal range. Because the normal range of the functional PAI-1 activity assay starts at zero in most laboratories, the ability to discriminate between normal and abnormal levels of activity is limited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1997.204">Fay et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.mehta.2008.1255">Mehta &#x00026; Shapiro 2008</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Note: If the PAI-1 antigen level is normal and PAI-1 activity is decreased, the phenotype is referred to as &#x0201c;qualitative PAI-1deficiency,&#x0201d; the clinical significance of which is unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1997.204">Fay et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.mehta.2008.1255">Mehta &#x00026; Shapiro 2008</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of complete PAI-1 deficiency <bold>is established</bold> in a proband when [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1997.204">Fay et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2011.1200">Iwaki et al 2011</xref>]:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>PAI-1 antigen is undetectable and PAI-1 activity is lower than 1 IU/mL</p>
              <p>Note: (1) Because the majority of PAI-1 activity assays are used to detect increased PAI-1 activity rather than decreased PAI-1 activity, they lack the sensitivity to differentiate between low normal activity and complete deficiency. Thus, a PAI-1 activity level of zero is often reported to be within the normal limits. (2) PAI-1 activity also demonstrates diurnal variation: because higher levels are observed in the morning and lower levels in the afternoon, the activity should be assayed in a sample drawn in the morning.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>AND/OR</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Biallelic <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants are identified on molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us">Table 1</xref>). See also <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold> and use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Single-gene testing</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> is performed first. If only one or no <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variant is identified, gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis can be considered; however, to date no <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications have been reported.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Targeted analysis for the <xref ref-type="table" rid="pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed">c.699_700dupTA</xref> pathogenic variant can be performed first in individuals from the Old Order Amish community of eastern and southern Indiana. Note: This variant has not been identified in other Old Order Amish populations.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of the condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting identification of pathogenic variants in genes that do not explain the underlying phenotype.</p>
          <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
          <table-wrap id="pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Plasminogen Activator Inhibitor 1 (PAI-1) Deficiency</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with Pathogenic Variants&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_us_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None reported <sup>5</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="pai1-def" object-id="pai1-def.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>No data on detection rate of gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis are available.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Untreated complete plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 (PAI-1) deficiency is characterized by mild to moderate bleeding, although in some instances bleeding can be life-threatening. Most commonly, delayed bleeding is associated with injury, trauma, or surgery; spontaneous bleeding episodes such as those observed in classic <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hemo-a" document-type="chapter">hemophilia A</related-object> and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hemo-b" document-type="chapter">hemophilia B</related-object> do not occur.</p>
          <p>While males and females with complete PAI-1 deficiency are affected equally, females may present more frequently with clinical manifestations or earlier in life than males, due to menorrhagia and postpartum hemorrhage. In addition, females experience bleeding with pregnancy and have difficulty carrying a pregnancy to term.</p>
          <p><bold>Bleeding disorder.</bold> Mucocutaneous bleeding, a hallmark of complete PAI-1 deficiency, includes oral bleeding, epistaxis and &#x02013; in females &#x02013; menorrhagia and postpartum bleeding.</p>
          <p>Post-traumatic bleeding can include joint bleeds and hematomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.schleef.1989.1747">Schleef et al 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.di_val.1991.528">Di&#x000e9;val et al 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.minowa.1999.286">Minowa et al 1999</xref>]. Affected members of the kindred from the Old Order Amish community of eastern and southern Indiana developed knee and elbow hemarthroses after minor trauma, extensive subperiosteal bleeding after minor jaw trauma, and epidural hematoma (in an infant) after a head injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1997.204">Fay et al 1997</xref>].</p>
          <p>The male reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.zhang.2005.79">Zhang et al [2005]</xref> experienced soft tissue hematomas of the leg and hip following minor leg trauma that required treatment; he subsequently manifested muscle atrophy.</p>
          <p>Post-surgical bleeding has been reported in individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis of complete PAI-1 deficiency:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>A child age five years experienced postoperative bleeding following surgical repair of a ventricular septal defect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2011.1200">Iwaki et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A member of the Old Order Amish community had delayed bleeding after surgical repair of an inguinal hernia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1997.204">Fay et al 1997</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Delayed bleeding was reported after total hip arthroplasty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.hirose.2016.e237">Hirose et al 2016</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Prolonged bleeding after dental extraction has been reported in individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis of complete PAI-1 deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1997.204">Fay et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2011.1200">Iwaki et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p>A palatal hemorrhage complicated a dental abscess, requiring hospitalization and transfusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1992.1729">Fay et al 1992</xref>].</p>
          <p>Prolonged wound healing occurred in one individual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2011.1200">Iwaki et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p>Menorrhagia is a consistent characteristic of complete PAI-1 deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.minowa.1999.286">Minowa et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.mehta.2008.1255">Mehta &#x00026; Shapiro 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2011.1200">Iwaki et al 2011</xref>]. In some instances treatment with transfusion of packed red blood cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.mehta.2008.1255">Mehta &#x00026; Shapiro 2008</xref>] or whole blood is required [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2011.1200">Iwaki et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p>In one woman rupture of an ovarian follicle resulted in hemoperitoneum requiring hospitalization, treatment with antifibrinolytics, and red cell transfusion.</p>
          <p>Pregnancy can be complicated by sporadic antenatal bleeding, preterm labor, postpartum bleeding, and miscarriage. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.gupta.2014">Gupta et al [2014]</xref> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rarecoagulationdisorders.org/diseases/plasminogen-activator-inhibitor-type-1-deficiency/disease-overview-2">full text</ext-link>) followed two women with PAI-1 deficiency through a total of seven pregnancies: six live born premature infants and one miscarriage. Bleeding, which began between eight and 19 weeks&#x02019; gestation and recurred prior to delivery, was treated with epsilon-aminocaproic acid (EACA). Postpartum bleeding was treated with EACA for up to six weeks (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Pregnancy_Management">Pregnancy Management</xref>).</p>
          <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2012.e161">Iwaki et al [2012]</xref> also reported on three pregnancies in a woman with complete PAI-1 deficiency in which antenatal bleeding, preterm labor, and miscarriage were complications.</p>
          <p><bold>Cardiac fibrosis.</bold> Cardiac fibrosis has only been reported in an Old Order Amish kindred with complete PAI-1 deficiency, which is &#x02013; to the authors&#x02019; knowledge &#x02013; the largest number of affected individuals with this finding reported to date [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.flevaris.2017">Flevaris et al 2017</xref>; Author, personal observation]. Of the seven individuals with cardiac fibrosis, one had severe involvement and six had minimal to moderate cardiac fibrosis between ages 15 and 35 years. Thus, to date, information about cardiac fibrosis in complete PAI-1 deficiency is limited.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>Because data on the phenotype associated with biallelic <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants are limited, no genotype-phenotype correlations can be made at this time.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>Complete plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 (PAI-1) deficiency, the topic of this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>, is defined as undetectable PAI-1 antigen levels and undetectable PAI-1 activity. Complete PAI-1 deficiency may also be referred to as &#x0201c;quantitative PAI-1 deficiency&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;homozygous PAI-1 deficiency.&#x0201d;</p>
          <p>Qualitative PAI-1 deficiency, not addressed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>, refers to normal PAI-1 antigen levels and decreased PAI-1 activity and is thought to be associated with either a heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variant (i.e., the carrier state for an autosomal recessive disorder) or compound heterozygosity for variants that produce a reduced amount of protein that is nonetheless sufficient to avoid complete deficiency. The clinical significance of qualitative PAI-1 deficiency is unknown. See also <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>The prevalence of complete PAI-1 deficiency is unknown, in large part because of the inability of the majority of tests of PAI-1 activity to differentiate between low normal activity and complete deficiency (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">Establishing the Diagnosis</xref>).</p>
          <p>Fewer than ten families with complete PAI-1 deficiency have been reported to date.</p>
          <p>Complete PAI-1 deficiency has no known racial or ethnic predominance. It has been reported in North America, Europe, and Asia.</p>
          <p>Of note, the incidence of complete PAI-1 deficiency is higher than expected in the genetic isolate of the Old Order Amish population of eastern and southern Indiana due to a pathogenic founder variant (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>). To date, this pathogenic variant has not been found in other Old Order Amish communities.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Di">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No other phenotypes are known to be associated with biallelic <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <table-wrap id="pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Disorders Associated with Mild to Moderate Bleeding (often Associated with Injury, Surgery, or Dental Procedures) to Consider in the Differential Diagnosis of Complete PAI-1 Deficiency</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disorder&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene(s)</th>
                <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOI</th>
                <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical Feature Unique to Differential Diagnosis Disorder</th>
                <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Related <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> / OMIM Entry</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alpha-2 antiplasmin deficiency</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">SERPINF2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal PLI assay&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/262850">262850</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor XIII deficiency</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">F13A1, F13B</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low factor XIII level</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/613225">613225</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor II deficiency</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">F2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low factor II level</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/613679">613679</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor V deficiency</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">F5</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low factor V level</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/227400">227400</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor X deficiency</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">F10</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low factor X level</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/227600">227600</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_1" rowspan="6" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Platelet function defects</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">GP1BA</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_4" rowspan="6" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">Abnormal platelet studies</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/177820">177820</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">GP1BB</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/231200">231200</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">GP9</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ANO6</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/262890">262890</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ITGA2B</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omim.org/entry/187800">187800</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ITGB3</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">von Willebrand disease (VWD)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">VWF</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD, AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal VWD lab evaluation</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.disorders_associated_with_mi_1_1_1_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="von-willebrand" document-type="chapter">von Willebrand Disease</related-object>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>MOI = mode of inheritance</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AD = autosomal dominant</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AR = autosomal recessive</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.2.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>Disorders are listed alphabetically.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.2.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>Alpha-2 antiplasmin deficiency. Moderate bleeding seen in alpha-2 antiplasmin deficiency is not characteristically associated with injury, surgery, or dental procedures.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Evaluations_Following_Initial">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with complete plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 (PAI-1) deficiency, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Questions to elicit a patient&#x02019;s history of:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Epistaxis</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Poor wound healing</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Bleeding in association with injury or trauma</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Bleeding with dental extractions</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Additional oral bleeding</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Post-surgical bleeding</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>In females:</p>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Heavy menstrual bleeding</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Postpartum bleeding</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Bleeding during pregnancy</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Preterm delivery</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Bleeding in association with ovulation</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>History of therapies tried in the past and the response to each specific therapy</p>
              <p>Note that response to antifibrinolytic therapy supports the diagnosis of complete PAI-1 deficiency (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Treatment_of_Manifestations">Treatment of Manifestations</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation by a hematologist with training in hemostasis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p><bold>Bleeding disorder.</bold> Management by a team of experts in the treatment of individuals with bleeding disorders is highly recommended. In the US, such teams are often identified through the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/hemophilia/HTC.html">federally funded hemophilia treatment center network</ext-link>.</p>
          <p>Severe bleeding manifestations, including intracranial hemorrhage (with or without hematoma evacuation) have been successfully managed with intravenous antifibrinolytics. Response to both epsilon-aminocaproic acid and tranexamic acid have been documented.</p>
          <p>If PAI-1 activity needs to be increased prior to achieving the therapeutic steady state level of antifibrinolytics, infusion of fresh-frozen plasma (FFP) (10-15 mL/kg) can be used. Duration of use of FFP is individualized based on clinical course and response to therapy. Note: The use of FFP does not appear to be effective in pregnancy for the prevention of bleeding in women with complete PAI-1 deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2012.e161">Iwaki et al 2012</xref>]. Fresh-frozen plasma to replace PAI-1 during pregnancy may be difficult due to the PAI-1 level achieved with plasma, the volume required, and the need for repeated infusion, all of which may be associated with risk of volume overload and/or infusion reactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.gupta.2014">Gupta et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p>Heavy menstrual bleeding can often be effectively managed with antifibrinolytics or hormonal suppression therapy (oral contraceptives).</p>
          <p>Occasionally, patients with complete PAI-1 deficiency experience excessive menstrual bleeding or bleeding following a procedure or trauma that requires infusion of packed red blood cells to manage the acute blood loss.</p>
          <p>Education regarding bleeding manifestations and when to seek treatment includes the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>For females, anticipatory counseling regarding onset of menses and potential complications</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Prompt reporting of injuries and planned procedures to allow early initiation of treatment to prevent significant bleeding</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Cardiac fibrosis</bold>. There is currently no specific treatment for cardiac fibrosis associated with complete PAI-1 deficiency; treatment is symptomatic.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Prevention_of_Primary_Manifest">
          <title>Prevention of Primary Manifestations</title>
          <p>Antifibrinolytics should be used to prevent bleeding for surgical and dental procedures, childbirth, and other invasive procedures. Antifibrinolytics can be administered IV, PO, or topically, the latter especially during dental procedures.</p>
          <p>Women who have heavy menstrual bleeding often benefit from continuous or intermittent prophylactic use of the antifibrinolytics tranexamic acid and epsilon-aminocaproic acid.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p><bold>Bleeding disorder.</bold> Regular follow up with a team of experts in the treatment of individuals with bleeding disorders is recommended. Such teams are often identified through the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/hemophilia/HTC.html">federal hemophilia treatment center network</ext-link> in the US.</p>
          <p>For menstruating females:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular monitoring: hemoglobin and/or hematocrit and iron studies including ferritin for possible iron deficiency and/or anemia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of the effectiveness of therapeutic interventions such as antifibrinolytics or hormonal suppressive agents (oral contraceptives)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Cardiac fibrosis.</bold> Because of clinical experience (albeit limited to date) with cardiac fibrosis in persons with complete PAI-1 deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.flevaris.2017">Flevaris et al 2017</xref>; Author, personal observation], screening echocardiogram can be considered beginning at age 15 years. In those with no cardiac findings, follow-up screening in two years is indicated; and in those with cardiac findings, follow up yearly or more frequently if indicated by a cardiologist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.ghosh.2010.1200">Ghosh et al 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.ghosh.2013.e63825">Ghosh et al 2013</xref>; Author, personal observation].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>The following should be avoided:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Medications that affect coagulation including aspirin, ibuprofen, and some herbal remedies</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>High-risk activities such as contact sports</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Ris">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>It is appropriate to clarify the genetic status of apparently asymptomatic older and younger sibs of an individual with complete PAI-1 deficiency in order to identify as early as possible those who would benefit from prompt initiation of treatment and preventive measures.</p>
          <p>Evaluations can include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic testing if the <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants in the family are known;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Measurement of PAI-1 antigen levels and PAI-1 activity if the <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants in the family are not known.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Iss">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>Recommendations based on published findings during pregnancies in two women with complete PAI-1 deficiency are administration of either tranexamic acid (25 mg kg-1 per dose, maximum 1300 milligrams, orally 3-4x/day) or epsilon-aminocaproic acid (EACA) (100 mg kg-1 per dose, maximum 3 g, orally 4x/day) for intermittent bleeding in the first and second trimester, from 26 weeks&#x02019; gestation through delivery, and for at least two weeks post partum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.heiman.2014.407">Heiman et al 2014</xref>]. Note that evidence that these recommendations would be effective in all pregnancies of women with complete PAI-1 deficiency is lacking.</p>
          <p>A woman with complete PAI-1 deficiency was treated with FFP during three pregnancies at eight to 11 weeks&#x02019; gestation two to three times per week; treatment was increased to daily at 20-28 weeks&#x02019; gestation. The first pregnancy ended in miscarriage at 19 weeks. The second and third pregnancies were delivered at 32 and 27 weeks&#x02019; gestation, respectively, as a result of uncontrollable contractions and placental abruption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2012.e161">Iwaki et al 2012</xref>].</p>
          <p>Of note, the teratogenicity of EACA and tranexamic acid is unknown and information regarding their safety during pregnancy and lactation is limited. There is a need to establish dosing guidelines for the use of antifibrinolytics during pregnancy and the postpartum period.</p>
          <p>To access further information on medication use during pregnancy, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mothertobaby.org/">www.mothertobaby.org</ext-link>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Complete plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 (PAI-1) deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected individual are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variant).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing complete PAI-1 deficiency.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing complete PAI-1 deficiency.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Offspring of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The offspring of an individual with complete PAI-1 deficiency are obligate heterozygotes (carriers) for a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1.</italic></p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The incidence of PAI-1 deficiency is higher than expected in the genetic isolate of the Old Order Amish population of eastern and southern Indiana, increasing the risk that an affected individual may have a reproductive partner who is heterozygous for a <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variant (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Prevalence">Prevalence</xref>). The offspring of an affected individual and a heterozygous reproductive partner are at 50% risk of being affected and 50% risk of being heterozygous.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier of a <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Carrier_Heterozygote_Detection">
          <title>Carrier (Heterozygote) Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants in the family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Iss">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pai-1-def.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Ris">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected, are carriers, or are at risk of being carriers. This includes issues related to pregnancy in affected women and the risk to the fetus due to risk for prematurity.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplan">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for complete PAI-1 deficiency are possible.</p>
          <p>Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions about prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <p>
          <bold>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</bold>
        </p>
        <p>PAI-1, a protein that is a member of the serine protease inhibitor (SERPIN) superfamily, is involved in a variety of pathophysiologic systems including embryogenesis, angiogenesis, ovulation, inflammation, and tumor metastasis. These observations suggest that the plasminogen activation system is an important mediator of tissue remodeling and cell migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.gupta.2014">Gupta et al 2014</xref>] (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rarecoagulationdisorders.org/diseases/plasminogen-activator-inhibitor-type-1-deficiency/disease-overview-2">full text</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>In hemostasis, PAI regulates fibrinolysis (i.e., the degradation of thrombi) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.gupta.2014">Gupta et al 2014</xref>]. PAI-1 is an inhibitor of tissue type plasminogen activators (t-PA) and urokinase type plasminogen activators (u-PA), which convert plasminogen to plasmin, the primary protease responsible for fibrinolysis. Thus, complete PAI-1 deficiency results in excessive fibrinolysis manifesting as mild to moderate bleeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.heiman.2014.407">Heiman et al 2014</xref>]. Physiologic fibrinolysis occurs exclusively on the clot surface within a blood vessel and not in the circulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.gupta.2014">Gupta et al 2014</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pai-1-def.F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
        <p>Heterozygous pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> may be associated with qualitative PAI-1 deficiency (i.e., normal PAI-1 antigen levels and decreased PAI-1 activity), the clinical significance of which is unknown. Thus, the significance of reports of families with qualitative PAI-1 deficiency and a heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> variant should be interpreted with caution because (1) the PAI-1 activity assays used in these families lack the sensitivity to differentiate between low normal activity and complete deficiency, and (2) the <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> variants identified are of uncertain clinical significance (i.e., some variants reported as pathogenic may actually be benign).</p>
        <p>Although beyond the scope of diagnostic laboratories, studies to determine the functional consequences of a <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> variant may be of value in these circumstances. Of note, in vitro expression analyses demonstrated that the c.699_700dupTA variant of the Old Order Amish community resulted in the synthesis of an insoluble, unstable protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1992.1729">Fay et al 1992</xref>]. However, currently there are no clinically useful functional PAI-1 assays. Note: A fibrinolysis assay with a euglobulin clot lysis time is not sensitive or specific to PAI-1.</p>
        <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> spans approximately 12 kb and comprises nine exons. A variety of regulatory elements have been identified in <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic>, including AP-1 sites, a glucocorticoid response element, a VLDL response site, and two Sp1 sites that appear to mediate glucose responsiveness. See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="pai-1-def" object-id="pai-1-def.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold> for a detailed summary of gene and protein information.</p>
        <p><bold>Modulator.</bold> The <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> c.-820_-817G(4_5) (commonly known as 4G/5G) benign variant is a common insertion/deletion of four or five G-nucleotide residues in the <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> promoter region; the 4G allele is associated with higher plasma PAI-1 activity. An elevation in plasma PAI-1 activity leads to depressed fibrinolytic activity and a theoretically increased risk for arterial and venous thrombosis, a significant risk factor for coronary artery disease, myocardial infarction, and recurrent miscarriage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.huang.2017.1">Huang et al 2017</xref>]. This benign variant is mentioned only to point out that testing for the 4G/5G variant will <italic toggle="yes">not</italic> aid in diagnosing an individual with complete PAI-1 deficiency.</p>
        <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> The first individual reported to have a bleeding disorder resulting from biallelic <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants was a child from the Old Order Amish community of eastern and southern Indiana who was homozygous for a dinucleotide insertion in exon 4 (c.699_700dupTA), resulting in a frameshift leading to a premature stop codon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1992.1729">Fay et al 1992</xref>]. Subsequently in this Old Order Amish community: (1) eleven additional individuals with a bleeding disorder have been determined to be homozygous for this pathogenic variant, and (2) 96 individuals heterozygous for this pathogenic variant &#x02013; none of whom experienced bleeding &#x02013; have been identified [Indiana Hemophilia and Thrombosis Center, unpublished data].</p>
        <p>Since 1992 two additional <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> pathogenic variants associated with a bleeding disorder have been reported:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>c.43G&#x0003e;A.</bold> A Chinese man age 34 years with a lifelong history of bleeding associated with surgery and trauma had a heterozygous missense <italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> variant; the authors ultimately concluded that a second pathogenic variant was present but undetectable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.zhang.2005.79">Zhang et al 2005</xref>].</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>c.356dupC.</bold> A woman age 47 years with a lifelong history of major bleeding (including extreme menorrhagia and post-surgical and postpartum bleeding) and impaired wound healing had an undetectable PAI-1 antigen level. She was homozygous for a 1-bp duplication leading to a frameshift and a premature stop codon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2011.1200">Iwaki et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <table-wrap id="pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 3. </label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic toggle="yes">SERPINE1</italic> Variants Discussed in This <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic></p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variant Classification</th>
                <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change (Alias) <sup>1</sup></th>
                <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></th>
                <th id="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Modulator</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.-820_-817G(4_5)&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup><break/>(4G/5G)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_4" rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000602.4">NM_000602.4</ext-link>
                  <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_000593.1">NP_000593.1</ext-link>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Pathogenic</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.43G&#x0003e;A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ala15Thr</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">c.356dupC</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ile120AspfsTer42</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">c.699_700dupTA</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_pai-1-def.T.serpine1_variants_discussed_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Thr234IlefsTer45</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.3.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>Variant designation that does not conform to current naming conventions</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.3.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>Numbering relative to full-length protein</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="pai-1-def.TF.3.3">
              <label>3. </label>
              <p>Not associated with the complete PAI-1 deficiency phenotype but can affect measured PAI-1 activity levels. A 1-bp guanine deletion/insertion variant in promoter (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_ref.cgi?rs=rs587776796">rs587776796</ext-link>) associated with higher transcription and activity levels and other phenotypes, including coronary artery disease (see OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/173360">173360</ext-link>).</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The full-length gene product, PAI-1, is a 47-kd protein of 402 amino acids in length including the 23-residue signal peptide. The active mature form of PAI-1 in plasma is 379 amino acids in length.</p>
        <p>The key functional domains of the full-length protein are:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>The Arg-Met reactive site at residues 369-370;</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>A vitronectin binding site;</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Glycosylation sites at residues 232, 288, and 352.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> PAI-1 deficiency may result from either complete plasma protein deficiency (absence of PAI-1 activity and antigen) as in the kindred described above or a dysproteinemic state with presence of the antigen but absence of activity.</p>
        <p>The loss-of-function pathogenic variant c.699-700 dup TA resides in exon 4 of the coding sequence at amino acid 210, resulting in a frame shift and formation of a premature stop codon and the synthesis of a truncated, non-functional PAI-1 protein.</p>
        <p>The c.43G&#x0003e;A variant in the signal peptide may partly impair secretion of PAI-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.zhang.2005.79">Zhang et al 2005</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="pai-1-def.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.di_val.1991.528">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Di&#x000e9;val</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nguyen</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gross</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Delobel</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kruithof</surname>
                    <given-names>EK</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A lifelong bleeding disorder associated with deficiency of plasminogen activator inhibitor type 1.</article-title>
                <source>Blood.</source>
                <year>1991</year>
                <volume>77</volume>
                <fpage>528</fpage>
                <lpage>32</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1899347</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1997.204">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fay</surname>
                    <given-names>WP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Parker</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Condrey</surname>
                    <given-names>LR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shapiro</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Human plasminogen activator inhibitor -1 (PAI-1) deficiency: characterization of a large kindred with a null mutation in the PAI-1 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Blood.</source>
                <year>1997</year>
                <volume>90</volume>
                <fpage>204</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9207454</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.fay.1992.1729">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fay</surname>
                    <given-names>WP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shapiro</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shih</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schleef</surname>
                    <given-names>RR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ginsburg</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Brief report: complete deficiency of plasminogen activator inhibitor type 1 due to a frameshift mutation.</article-title>
                <source>NEJM</source>
                <year>1992</year>
                <volume>327</volume>
                <fpage>1729</fpage>
                <lpage>33</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1435917</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.flevaris.2017">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Flevaris</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khan</surname>
                    <given-names>SS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eren</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schuldt</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shah</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gupta</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shapiro</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Burridge</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ghosh</surname>
                    <given-names>AK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vaughan</surname>
                    <given-names>DE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>PAI-1 controls cardiomyocyte TGF-&#x003b2; and cardiac fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Circulation.</source>
                <year>2017</year>
                <month>June</month>
                <day>6</day>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28588076</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.ghosh.2010.1200">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ghosh</surname>
                    <given-names>AK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bradham</surname>
                    <given-names>WS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gleaves</surname>
                    <given-names>LA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Taeye</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Murphy</surname>
                    <given-names>SB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Covington</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vaughan</surname>
                    <given-names>DE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Genetic deficiency of plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 promotes cardiac fibrosis in aged mice.</article-title>
                <source>Circulation.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>122</volume>
                <fpage>1200</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20823384</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.ghosh.2013.e63825">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ghosh</surname>
                    <given-names>AK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Murphy</surname>
                    <given-names>SB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kishore</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vaughan</surname>
                    <given-names>DE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Global gene expression profiling PAI-1 knockout murine heart and kidney: Molecular basis of cardiac-selective fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>PLoS One.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>e63825</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23724005</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.gupta.2014">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="web">Gupta S, Sealls W, Shapiro AD. Plasminogen Activator Inhibitor Type 1 Deficiency &#x02013; Disease Overview. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rarecoagulationdisorders.org/diseases/plasminogen-activator-inhibitor-type-1-deficiency/disease-overview-2">online</ext-link>. 2014. Accessed 8-1-17.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.heiman.2014.407">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heiman</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gupta</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shapiro</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The obstetric, gynaecological and fertility implications of homozygous PAI-1 deficiency: single-centre experience.</article-title>
                <source>Haemophilia.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>407</fpage>
                <lpage>12</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24261743</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.hirose.2016.e237">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hirose</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takedani</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kubota</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kinkawa</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Noguchi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Total hip arthroplasty and total knee arthroplasty in a patient with congenital deficiency of plasminogen activator inhibitor-1.</article-title>
                <source>Haemophilia.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>22</volume>
                <fpage>e237</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27030314</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.huang.2017.1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tang</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Q</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lao</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pan</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hu</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhao</surname>
                    <given-names>J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 polymorphism confers a genetic contribution to the risk of spontaneous abortion: an updated meta-analysis.</article-title>
                <source>Reprod Sci.</source>
                <year>2017</year>
                <issue>Jan</issue>
                <fpage>1</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28395596</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2012.e161">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iwaki</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nagahashi</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Umemura</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Terao</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kanayama</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The first report of uncontrollable subchorionic retroplacental haemorrhage inducing preterm labour in complete PAI-1 deficiency in a human.</article-title>
                <source>Thromb. Res.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>129</volume>
                <fpage>e161</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22099705</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.iwaki.2011.1200">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iwaki</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tanaka</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miyawaki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Suzuki</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takamatsu</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsushita</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Umemura</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Urano</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kojima</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Terao</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kanayama</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Life-threatening hemorrhage and prolonged wound healing are remarkable phenotypes manifested by complete plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 deficiency in humans.</article-title>
                <source>J Thromb Haemost.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>9</volume>
                <fpage>1200</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21486382</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.kohler.2000.1792">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kohler</surname>
                    <given-names>HP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grant</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Plasminogen-activator inhibitor type 1 and coronary artery disease.</article-title>
                <source>NEJM</source>
                <year>2000</year>
                <volume>342</volume>
                <fpage>1792</fpage>
                <lpage>801</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10853003</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.mehta.2008.1255">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mehta</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shapiro</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Plasminogen activator inhibitor type 1 deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Haemophilia.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>1255</fpage>
                <lpage>60</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19141166</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.minowa.1999.286">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Minowa</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takahashi</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tanaka</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Naganuma</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ida</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maki</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoshioka</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Four cases of bleeding diathesis in children due to congenital plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 deficiency.</article-title>
                <source>Haemostasis.</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>29</volume>
                <fpage>286</fpage>
                <lpage>91</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10754381</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.schleef.1989.1747">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schleef</surname>
                    <given-names>RR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Higgins</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pillemer</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Levitt</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Bleeding diathesis due to decreased functional activity of type 1 plasminogen activator inhibitor.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Invest.</source>
                <year>1989</year>
                <volume>83</volume>
                <fpage>1747</fpage>
                <lpage>52</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2496147</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pai-1-def.REF.zhang.2005.79">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>ZY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>ZY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dong</surname>
                    <given-names>NZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bai</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ruan</surname>
                    <given-names>CG</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A case of deficiency of plasma plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 related to Ala15Thr mutation in its signal peptide.</article-title>
                <source>Blood Coagul Fibrinolysis.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>16</volume>
                <fpage>79</fpage>
                <lpage>84</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15650551</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pai-1-def.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="pai-1-def.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>3 August 2017 (bp) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>30 June 2016 (mh) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="pai-1-def.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Plasminogen activators &#x02013; urokinase plasminogen activator (u-PA) and tissue plasminogen activator (t-PA) &#x02013; circulate in plasma as a reversible complex with PAI-1. When the fibrin clot is formed, plasminogen and t-PA or u-PA bind to the clot and form plasmin, resulting in lysis of the cross-linked fibrin to fibrin degradation products. PAI-1 also binds to fibrin and when bound, can irreversibly inhibit plasminogen activators. From <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pai-1-def.REF.kohler.2000.1792">Kohler &#x00026; Grant [2000]</xref>. Copyright 2016; reproduced with permission of Massachusetts Medical Society.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pai-1-def-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
