<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="retinoblastoma" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">retinoblastoma</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Retinoblastoma</title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Lohmann</surname>
            <given-names>Dietmar R</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Institut f&#x000fc;r Humangenetik, Universit&#x000e4;tsklinikum Essen<break/>Universit&#x000e4;t Duisburg-Essen<break/>Essen, Germany</aff>
          <email>dietmar.lohmann@uni-due.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gallie</surname>
            <given-names>Brenda L</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Professor, University of Toronto<break/>Head, Cancer Informatics<break/>Ontario Cancer Institute/Princess Margaret Hospital<break/>University Health Network <break/>Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff>
          <email>brenda@gallie.ca</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2000-07-18" date-type="created">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2000</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2015-11-19" date-type="updated">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2005-01-21" date-type="revised">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="papr" document-type="chapter">Renal Coloboma Syndrome</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="rcdp" document-type="chapter">Rhizomelic Chondrodysplasia Punctata Type 1</related-object>
      <abstract id="retinoblastoma.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
          <p>Retinoblastoma (Rb) is a malignant tumor of the developing retina that occurs in children, usually before age five years. Rb develops from cells that have cancer-predisposing variants in both copies of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic>. Rb may be unifocal or multifocal. About 60% of affected individuals have unilateral Rb with a mean age of diagnosis of 24 months; about 40% have bilateral Rb with a mean age of diagnosis of 15 months. Heritable retinoblastoma is an autosomal dominant susceptibility for Rb. Individuals with heritable retinoblastoma are also at increased risk of developing non-ocular tumors.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of Rb is usually established by examination of the fundus of the eye using indirect ophthalmoscopy. Imaging studies can be used to support the diagnosis and stage the tumor. The diagnosis of heritable retinoblastoma is established in a proband with Rb or retinoma and a family history of Rb or by detection of a germline pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">RB1.</italic></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Early diagnosis and treatment of Rb and non-ocular tumors can reduce morbidity and increase longevity; care is best provided by multidisciplinary teams of specialists including ophthalmology, pediatric oncology, pathology, and radiation oncology. Treatment options depend on tumor stage, number of tumor foci (unifocal, unilateral multifocal, or bilateral), localization and size of the tumor(s) within the eye(s), presence of vitreous seeding, the potential for useful vision, the extent and kind of extraocular extension, and the resources available. Treatment options include enucleation; cryotherapy; laser, systemic, or local ocular chemotherapy including intra-arterial chemotherapy combined with or followed by laser or cryotherapy; radiation therapy using episcleral plaques; and, as a last resort, external beam radiotherapy.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary manifestations:</italic> If possible, radiation (including x-ray, CT scan, and external beam radiation) should be avoided in individuals with heritable Rb to minimize the lifetime risk of developing late-onset second cancers.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> In children known to have an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> germline pathogenic variant: eye examination under anesthesia every three to four weeks until age six months, then less frequently until age three years. Clinical examinations with cooperative children are performed every three to six months until age seven years, then annually and eventually biannually for life. Individuals who have unilateral Rb without an identified heterozygous germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant are at risk for low-level mosaicism and should have regular clinical examination of the eyes, including clinical ultrasound. Individuals with retinomas are followed with retinal examinations and imaging every one to two years. To detect second non-ocular tumors in individuals with retinoblastoma, physicians and parents should promptly evaluate complaints of bone pain or lumps because of the high risk for sarcomas and other cancers; however, effective screening protocols have not yet been developed.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Limiting exposures to DNA-damaging agents (radiation, tobacco, and UV light) may reduce the excess cancer risks in survivors of heritable retinoblastoma.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> Molecular genetic testing for early identification of asymptomatic at-risk children in a family reduces the need for costly screening procedures in those at-risk family members who have not inherited the pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>Heritable retinoblastoma is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Individuals with heritable retinoblastoma have a heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> or inherited germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant. Offspring of affected individuals have a 50% chance of inheriting the pathogenic variant. Prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk is possible if the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Guidelines for diagnosis and care of children and families affected by retinoblastoma have been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF3">Canadian Retinoblastoma Society 2009</xref>] (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cos-sco.ca/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/COS_RetinoblastomaCPGs_Dec09.pdf">full text</ext-link>).</p>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Retinoblastoma <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Leukocoria (white pupil)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Strabismus</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Change in eye appearance</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Reduced visual acuity</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Heritable retinoblastoma</bold>
<bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following clinical and family history:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Any individual with a diagnosis of retinoblastoma, including unilateral (unifocal and multifocal) and bilateral involvement</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>An individual with a retinoma</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>An individual with a family history of retinoblastoma</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Establishing_the_Diagnosi">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of retinoblastoma <bold>is established</bold> in a proband by retinal examination with full pupillary dilation by an ophthalmologist or optometrist. Confirmation of the diagnosis and determination of the disease extent is accomplished by examination under anesthesia. Ocular imaging can help confirm the diagnosis. Pathology is not required. Note: Biopsy can cause the tumor to spread beyond the eye, endangering the life of the individual.</p>
          <p>The diagnosis of <bold>heritable retinoblastoma is established</bold> in a proband with retinoblastoma (Rb) or retinoma and a family history of Rb. The majority of individuals with Rb do not have a family history of the disorder. Therefore identification of a heterozygous germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant on molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi">Table 1</xref>) is necessary to determine if the Rb is heritable in index cases and to allow for early diagnosis and screening for relatives at risk of Rb.</p>
          <p>Molecular testing approaches to identify individuals with <bold>heritable retinoblastoma</bold> can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold> and use of a <bold>multi-gene panel.</bold></p>
          <p>
            <bold>Single-gene testing</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Individuals with bilateral, unilateral familial, or unilateral multifocal Rb.</bold> Sequence analysis and gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> are performed on peripheral blood DNA. Note: Targeted analysis for pathogenic variants at methylated CpG dinucleotides may be offered by some laboratories.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Individuals with unilateral unifocal Rb and a negative family history</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>If tumor tissue is not available, sequence analysis and gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> are performed on peripheral blood DNA.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>If tumor tissue is available, sequence analysis and gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> are performed on tumor DNA. If pathogenic variants are identified, DNA from blood is tested for the presence of these variants. If no pathogenic variants are identified, methylation analysis of the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> promoter CpG island is performed to identify epigenetic inactivation of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> due to hypermethylation of the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> promoter. If no hypermethylation is identified at the promoter, DNA from tumor is tested for the presence of amplification of <italic toggle="yes">MYCN</italic>, which is the cause of Rb in the absence of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variants in about 1.5% of individuals with isolated unilateral retinoblastoma.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> may also be considered. However, as no locus heterogeneity is known for heritable retinoblastoma, evaluation of the analytic data is confined to variants that alter <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic>.</p>
          <table-wrap id="retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Heritable Retinoblastoma</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Germline Pathogenic Variant&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_1" rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germline, tumor</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70%-75%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germline, tumor</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8%-16%&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Targeted analysis for pathogenic variants</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germline, tumor</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25%&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Methylation analysis</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See footnote 7</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">MYCN</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See footnote 8</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="retinoblastoma" object-id="retinoblastoma.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="retinoblastoma.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Testing for loss of heterozygosity in tumors. Comparative genotyping of polymorphic loci within and flanking <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> in DNA from peripheral blood and tumor can reveal that loss of the normal allele (hemizygosity) with or without duplication (homozygosity) of the mutated allele constitutes the somatic pathogenic variant.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.1.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>Pathogenic variants that result in premature termination due to CpG-transitions account for 25% of pathogenic variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2009.842">Rushlow et al 2009</xref>].</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.1.7">
                <label>7. </label>
                <p>Hypermethylation of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> promoter (which silences gene expression) is observed in 10%-12% of tumors from individuals with sporadic, unilateral retinoblastoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.zeschnigk.2004.e125">Zeschnigk et al 2004</xref>]. In these individuals, analysis of the promoter methylation status in DNA from tumor is needed to identify the two inactive <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> alleles that triggered tumor development.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.1.8">
                <label>8. </label>
                <p>About 1.5% of children with sporadic unilateral Rb have high-level <italic toggle="yes">MYCN</italic> amplification on tumor tissue testing but no pathogenic variants leading to inactivation of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2013.327">Rushlow et al 2013</xref>].</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <table-wrap id="retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 2. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Probability of a Germline Pathogenic Variant Being Present in a Proband with Retinoblastoma Based on Family History and Tumor Presentation</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_1">Family History</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="3" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Rb Presentation</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_3" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_3">Probability that an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> Germline Pathogenic Variant is Present</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Unilateral</th>
                  <th headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_2" id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Bilateral</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1" id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Multifocal</th>
                  <th headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1" id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unifocal</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Positive&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">+</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Negative&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Close to 100%&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">+</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14%-95%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.probability_of_a_germli_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~14%</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.2.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>Positive = more than one affected family member (10% of retinoblastoma)</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.2.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>Negative = only one affected individual in the family (90% of retinoblastoma)</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.2.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variants are identified by conventional molecular testing in 90%-97% of simplex cases with bilateral involvement; the remaining 5% may have translocations, deep intronic splice variants, or low-level mosaic pathogenic variants which may or may not be in the germline.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p>Note: (1) If neither <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant identified in tumor tissue is found in the DNA of non-tumor cells (constitutional DNA), the affected individual has a low probability of having an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> germline pathogenic variant. (2) Because blood mosaicism as low as 20% can usually be detected by conventional molecular analysis such as sequencing, the failure to detect an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant in constitutional DNA reduces but cannot eliminate the probability that the individual has an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant in his/her germline.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p><bold>Retinoblastoma (Rb).</bold> The most common presenting sign is a white pupillary reflex (leukocoria). Strabismus is the second most common presenting sign and may accompany or precede leukocoria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.abramson.2003.1248">Abramson et al 2003</xref>]. Unusual presenting signs include glaucoma, orbital cellulitis, uveitis, hyphema, or vitreous hemorrhage. Most affected children are diagnosed before age five years. Atypical manifestations are more frequent in older children.</p>
          <p>Probands with Rb usually present in one of the following clinical settings:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Negative family history and unilateral Rb (60% of probands)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Negative family history and bilateral Rb (30% of probands)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Positive family history and unilateral or bilateral Rb (~10% of probands). For individuals with a positive family history who undergo clinical surveillance via serial retinal examinations, tumors are often identified in the first month of life.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Chromosome deletion involving band 13q14. Up to 5% of all index cases with unifocal Rb and 7.5% of all index cases with multifocal Rb have a chromosome deletion of 13q14. Such chromosome abnormalities are often associated with developmental delay and birth defects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.mitter.2011.947">Mitter et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.cast_ra.2013.460">Cast&#x000e9;ra et al 2013</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Retinoblastoma is:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Unilateral</bold> if only one eye is affected by Rb. About 60% of affected individuals have a unilateral Rb with a mean age at diagnosis of 24 months. Usually, in individuals with unilateral Rb the tumor is also unifocal, i.e., only a single tumor is present. Some individuals have multifocal tumors in one eye (unilateral multifocal Rb). Intraocular seeding may mimic true multifocal tumor growth. In most persons with unilateral Rb without a family history, the tumor is large and it is not possible to determine if a single tumor is present.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Bilateral</bold> if both eyes are affected by Rb. About 40% of affected individuals have bilateral Rb with a mean age at diagnosis of 15 months. In most children with bilateral tumors, both eyes are affected at the time of initial diagnosis. In individuals with bilateral Rb both eyes may show multiple tumors. Some children who are initially diagnosed with unilateral Rb later develop a tumor in the contralateral unaffected eye.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Trilateral</bold> if bilateral (or, rarely, unilateral) Rb and a pinealoblastoma co-occur.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Retinoma and associated eye lesions.</bold> Benign retinal tumors (called retinoma) that have undergone spontaneous growth arrest may present within retinal scars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.dimaras.2008.1363">Dimaras et al 2008</xref>]. Calcified phthisic eyes may result from spontaneous regression of Rb associated with vascular occlusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.valverde.2002.277">Valverde et al 2002</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Pinealoblastomas</bold> occur in "retina-like" tissue in the pineal gland of the brain. Co-occurrence of pinealoblastomas or primitive neuroectodermal tumors and Rb is referred to as trilateral Rb. Pinealoblastoma is rare and usually fatal, unlike Rb of the eye, which is generally curable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.de_jong.2014.1157">de Jong et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Other tumors.</bold> There is an increased risk for other specific extraocular primary neoplasms (collectively called second primary tumors). Most of the second primary tumors are osteosarcomas, soft tissue sarcomas (mostly leiomyosarcomas and rhabdomyosarcomas), or melanomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.kleinerman.2007.24">Kleinerman et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.marees.2008.1771">Marees et al 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.kleinerman.2012.950">Kleinerman et al 2012</xref>]. These tumors usually manifest in adolescence or adulthood. The incidence of second primary tumors is increased to more than 50% in individuals with Rb who have received external beam radiation therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.wong.1997.1262">Wong et al 1997</xref>]. Survivors of heritable retinoblastoma who are not exposed to high-dose radiotherapy have a high lifetime risk of developing a late-onset cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.fletcher.2004.357">Fletcher et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.kleinerman.2012.950">Kleinerman et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.dommering.2012b.225">Dommering et al 2012b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.temming.2015.1799">Temming et al 2015</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.GenotypePhenotype_Correla">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>In the majority of families with heritable retinoblastoma, all members who have inherited the germline pathogenic variant develop multiple tumors in both eyes. It is not unusual to find, however, that the founder (i.e., the first person in the family to have Rb) has only unilateral Rb. Most of these families segregate <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> null alleles that are altered by frameshift or nonsense variants. With few specific exceptions, <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> null alleles show nearly complete penetrance (&#x0003e;99%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.lohmann.1996.940">Lohmann et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.sippel.1998.610">Sippel et al 1998</xref>].</p>
          <p>Fewer than 10% of families show a "low penetrance" phenotype with reduced expressivity (i.e., increased prevalence of unilateral Rb) and incomplete penetrance (i.e., &#x02264;25%). This low penetrance phenotype is usually associated with mutated <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> alleles showing in-frame or missense changes, distinct splice site variants, certain indel variants in exon 1, or pathogenic variants in the promoter region.</p>
          <p>A third category of families shows differential penetrance depending on the parental origin of the pathogenic allele (parent-of-origin effect) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.klutz.2002.174">Klutz et al 2002</xref>].</p>
          <p>Cytogenetically visible deletions involving 13q14 that also result in deletions of additional genes in the same chromosome region as <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> may cause developmental delay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.cast_ra.2013.460">Cast&#x000e9;ra et al 2013</xref>] and mild-to-moderate facial dysmorphism. As sizeable deletions of 13q14 show reduced expressivity, a considerable proportion of individuals with such deletions show unilateral Rb only; some of these children develop no tumors at all [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.mitter.2011.947">Mitter et al 2011</xref>]. Contiguous loss of <italic toggle="yes">MED4</italic>, which is located centromeric to <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic>, explains reduced expressivity in individuals with large deletions that include both <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">MED4</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.dehainault.2014.5243">Dehainault et al 2014</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="retinoblastoma.GenotypePhenotype_Correla">Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>Glioma retinae is a historical name for retinoblastoma.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>The incidence of Rb is estimated at between 1:15,000 and 1:20,000 live births [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.moll.1997.559">Moll et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.seregard.2004.1228">Seregard et al 2004</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.Genetically_Related_Allel">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Several ocular conditions of childhood can clinically simulate retinoblastoma:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Sporadic congenital disorders including <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="norrie" document-type="chapter">persistent hyperplastic primary vitreous</related-object> and Coats disease (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/300216">300216</ext-link>)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Hereditary disorders including <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="tuberous-sclerosis" document-type="chapter">tuberous sclerosis</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="norrie" document-type="chapter">Norrie disease</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="i-p" document-type="chapter">incontinentia pigmenti</related-object>, familial exudative vitreoretinopathy (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fevr" document-type="chapter">Autosomal Dominant Familial Exudative Vitreoretinopathy</related-object>), and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="vhl" document-type="chapter">von Hippel-Lindau disease</related-object></p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Ocular infestation by <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara canis</italic></p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <p>Guidelines for retinoblastoma (Rb) care have been developed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF3">Canadian Retinoblastoma Society 2009</xref>] (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cos-sco.ca/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/COS_RetinoblastomaCPGs_Dec09.pdf">full text</ext-link>).</p>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Evaluations_Following_Ini">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with Rb, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Prior to the planning of therapy, the extent of the tumor within and outside the eye should be determined. Each affected eye is assigned a classification, depending on the extent of disease and the risk that the cancer has spread outside the eye. Extent of the tumor is estimated by clinical examination under anesthetic and ultrasound or MRI, particularly focusing on the tumor-optic nerve relationship. Head MRI is also useful to evaluate for a pinealoblastoma, indicating trilateral retinoblastoma.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>For very large tumors with risk factors for extraocular disease, bone marrow aspiration and examination of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) may also be performed at diagnosis, or performed when pathologic examination of the enucleated eye reveals optic nerve invasion or significant risks for extraocular extension.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If Rb has spread outside the eye, the stage of cancer will need to be evaluated to determine the most appropriate care of the child.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In those individuals with a family history of Rb, and in uncommon circumstances in which the child presents with strabismus or poor vision, the retinal tumors may be small and detected on clinical examination under anesthesia.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a medical geneticist and/or genetic counselor is indicated.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Treatment_of_Manifestatio">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Goals of treatment are first preservation of life, and then of sight. As optimal treatment may be complex, specialists skilled in the treatment of Rb from various fields including ophthalmology, pediatric oncology, pathology and radiation oncology collaborate to deliver optimized care.</p>
          <p>In addition to eye classification and tumor stage, choice of treatment depends on many factors, including the number of tumor foci (unifocal, unilateral multifocal, or bilateral), localization and size of the tumor(s) within the eye(s), presence of vitreous seeding, the potential for useful vision, the extent and kind of extraocular extension, and the resources available.</p>
          <p>Treatment options for the eye include enucleation; cryotherapy; laser, systemic, or local ocular chemotherapy including intra-arterial chemotherapy combined with or followed by laser or cryotherapy; radiation therapy using episcleral plaques; and, as a last resort, external beam radiotherapy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Prevention_of_Secondary_C">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>If possible, any radiation (including x-ray, CT scan, and external beam radiation) should be avoided to minimize the lifetime risk of developing late-onset second cancers. Such tests should only be used if absolutely necessary in essential health care.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Further information regarding medical surveillance for those who have had or are at risk of developing Rb is available in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cos-sco.ca/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/COS_RetinoblastomaCPGs_Dec09.pdf">guidelines for retinoblastoma care</ext-link>.</p>
          <p><bold>Detection of subsequent Rb after initial diagnosis.</bold> Following successful treatment, children require frequent follow-up examination for early detection of newly arising intraocular tumors:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>It is recommended that children known to have an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> germline pathogenic variant have an eye examination under anesthesia every three to four weeks until age six months, then less frequently until age three years. Clinical examinations with cooperative children are performed every three to six months until age seven years, then annually and eventually biannually for life.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Individuals who have unilateral Rb without an identified heterozygous germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant are at risk for low-level mosaicism and can develop a tumor in the other eye [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2009.842">Rushlow et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.temming.2013.475">Temming et al 2013</xref>]. This risk is small enough that examination under anesthesia may be replaced with regular clinical examination of the eyes, including clinical ultrasound (a simple, noninvasive procedure).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Individuals with retinomas (premalignant retinal lesions associated with Rb) are followed with retinal examinations and imaging every one to two years, to detect any change early.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Detection of second non-ocular tumors in individuals with retinoblastoma.</bold> Because of the high risk for second cancers, including sarcomas, melanoma, and specific other cancers, prompt investigation of any signs or symptoms is indicated. Total body MRI at regular intervals is under investigation to determine when the technology will be specific and sensitive enough for screening for second cancers in persons with a heterozygous germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.AgentsCircumstances_to_Av">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>It has been suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.fletcher.2004.357">Fletcher et al [2004]</xref> that cancer risks in survivors of heritable retinoblastoma may be reduced by limiting exposure to DNA-damaging agents (radiotherapy, tobacco, and UV light). It is plausible that cancer risks in these individuals may be reduced by limiting exposure to chemotherapy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Evaluation_of_Relatives_a">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>The American Society of Clinical Oncologists identifies heritable retinoblastoma as a Group 1 disorder, i.e., a hereditary syndrome for which genetic testing is considered part of the standard management for at-risk family members [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF2">American Society of Clinical Oncology 2003</xref>]. It is appropriate to evaluate apparently asymptomatic <bold>at-risk</bold> relatives of an affected individual in order to identify as early as possible those who would benefit from eye examination by an experienced ophthalmologist and allow for early identification of a retinoblastoma.</p>
          <p>Evaluations can include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic testing if the pathogenic variant in the family is known, which reduces the need for costly screening procedures in those at-risk family members who have not inherited the pathogenic variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.noorani.1996.301">Noorani et al 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.richter.2003.253">Richter et al 2003</xref>];</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Eye examinations by an ophthalmologist experienced in the treatment of retinoblastoma starting directly after birth as described above (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="retinoblastoma.Surveillance">Surveillance</xref>, <bold>Detection of subsequent Rb after initial diagnosis</bold>. Young or uncooperative children may require examination under anesthesia.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="retinoblastoma.Related_Genetic_Counselin">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Therapies_Under_Investiga">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There are not many clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Heritable retinoblastoma is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband.</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Some individuals diagnosed with heritable retinoblastoma have an affected parent.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A proband with heritable retinoblastoma may have the disorder as the result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant. The majority of individuals with heritable retinoblastoma and no family history of retinoblastoma have the disorder as the result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in leukocyte DNA of either parent, two possible explanations are germline mosaicism in a parent or a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant in the proband. The incidence of mosaicism is approximately 6%. Mosaicism may be detected by sensitive methods such as allele-specific PCR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2009.842">Rushlow et al 2009</xref>] or next-generation sequencing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.chen.2014.384">Chen et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic testing is recommended for the parents of a proband with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant. If the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant in the proband is not known, recommendations for the evaluation of parents of a proband include examination by an ophthalmologist knowledgeable about retinoblastoma (Rb), retinoma, and retinoblastoma-associated eye lesions.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The family history of some individuals diagnosed with heritable retinoblastoma may appear to be negative because of failure to recognize the disorder in family members (retinoma), low-level mosaicism, or reduced penetrance. Therefore, an apparently negative family history cannot be confirmed unless appropriate clinical evaluation and/or molecular genetic testing have been performed on the parents of the proband. In approximately 10% of individuals with a heterozygous germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant who represent simplex cases, one of the proband&#x02019;s unaffected parents also has the pathogenic variant. In most cases this is a mosaic or heterozygous &#x0201c;reduced penetrance&#x0201d; pathogenic variant, such as a missense variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2009.842">Rushlow et al 2009</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the proband with Rb has the disorder as the result of a mosaic <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant, the parents do not have the pathogenic variant.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Note: If the parent is the individual in whom the pathogenic variant first occurred, s/he may have somatic mosaicism for the variant and have fewer (unilateral) or no retinoblastomas.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to sibs of a proband depends on the phenotype and the genetic status of the parents.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband and the proband have bilateral Rb, the risk to the sibs is almost 50%. In rare families with "familial low-penetrance Rb" the risk for tumor development in a sib with the germline pathogenic variant is reduced.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When the parents are clinically unaffected, the risk to the sibs of a proband appears to be low (i.e.,1%-2%; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel">Table 3</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The sibs of a proband with clinically unaffected parents are still at increased risk for heritable retinoblastoma because of the possibility of reduced penetrance in a parent.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, the risk to sibs is low but greater than that of the general population because of the possibility of germline mosaicism. Thus, it is recommended that each sib be tested for the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant identified in the proband.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the proband clearly shows mosaicism for an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> cancer-predisposing variant in non-cancer cells such as leukocyte DNA, it is assumed that the pathogenic variant arose as a post-zygotic event and that neither parent has an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> germline pathogenic variant. The risk to the sibs is not increased and thus the testing of sibs for the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant identified in the proband is not warranted.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If molecular genetic testing is not available or is uninformative, empiric risks based on tumor presentation (i.e., unifocal or multifocal) and family history can be used (<xref ref-type="table" rid="retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel">Table 3</xref>). The low, but not negligible, risk to sibs of a proband with a negative family history presumably reflects the presence of either a germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant with reduced penetrance in one parent or somatic mosaicism (that includes the germline) for an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant in one parent.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent has a cytogenetically detectable balanced chromosome 13 translocation or rearrangement, the sibs are at increased risk of inheriting an unbalanced chromosome rearrangement.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Each child of an individual with heritable retinoblastoma has a 50% chance of inheriting the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>If the proband has bilateral Rb and no family history of Rb, the presence of a germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> cancer-predisposing variant is assumed and the risk to each offspring of inheriting the pathogenic variant is 50%. Predictive DNA testing in offspring is possible if the cancer-predisposing <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> variant has been identified in the proband.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the proband has had unilateral multifocal Rb and no family history of Rb, recurrence risk to offspring is lower [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.sippel.1998.610">Sippel et al 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2009.842">Rushlow et al 2009</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to offspring of a proband with unilateral unifocal disease and a negative family history is 6%, reflecting the possibility that the proband has mosaicism for a pathogenic variant or a germline <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant associated with milder phenotypic expression. In families with "familial low-penetrance Rb" the risk for tumor development in persons with the low-penetrance <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> allele is lower than the 95% observed with highly penetrant <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> &#x0201c;null&#x0201d; alleles.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variants that have been detected in tumor tissue are not detected in DNA from leukocytes of the proband, there is an estimated 1.2% chance that the proband has germline mosaicism for one of the pathogenic variants identified in the tumor tissue. The offspring of the proband are at a 0.6% risk of inheriting a germline pathogenic variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.richter.2003.253">Richter et al 2003</xref>]. Molecular genetic testing in offspring must check for both of the pathogenic variants identified in the tumor of the proband.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If one of the pathogenic variants identified in the tumor is mosaic in DNA from leukocytes of the proband, the level of germline involvement is uncertain. All offspring should be checked for the pathogenic variant identified in leukocyte DNA.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Empiric Risks for Development of Retinoblastoma in Sibs and Offspring of a Proband when an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> Germline Pathogenic Variant Has Not Been Identified</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="3" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Tumor Presentation in Index Case</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_2" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_2">Family History</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_3" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_3">Risk to Sibs of an Index Case</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_4" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_4">Risk to Offspring of an Index Case</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_1" id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Bilateral</th>
                  <th headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1" id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Unilateral</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2" id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Multifocal</th>
                  <th headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2" id="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unifocal</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2%&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1%-2%&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6%-50%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~1%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_1 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_2_2 hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_retinoblastoma.T.empiric_risks_for_devel_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.3.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>If there is no unaffected sib [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.draper.1992.211">Draper et al 1992</xref>]</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="retinoblastoma.TF.3.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>In families with unilateral Rb, penetrance varies widely.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p>
            <bold>Other family members of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to other family members depends on the status of the proband's parents.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent is affected, his or her family members may be at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Related_Genetic_Counselin">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="retinoblastoma.Evaluation_of_Relatives_a">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p><bold>Predictive testing</bold> for at-risk asymptomatic adult family members requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant in the family.</p>
          <p><bold>Considerations in families with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant.</bold> When neither parent of a proband with heritable retinoblastoma has the pathogenic variant or clinical evidence of the disorder, the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant is likely <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>. However, other possible non-medical explanations that could be explored include alternate paternity or maternity (e.g., with assisted reproduction) or undisclosed adoption.</p>
          <p><bold>Genetic cancer risk assessment and counseling.</bold> For a comprehensive description of the medical, psychosocial, and ethical ramifications of identifying at-risk individuals through cancer risk assessment with or without molecular genetic testing, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancer.gov/about-cancer/causes-prevention/genetics/risk-assessment-pdq">Cancer Genetics Risk Assessment and Counseling &#x02013; for health professionals</ext-link> (part of PDQ<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, National Cancer Institute).</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.dommering.2012a.216">Dommering et al 2012a</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals. If possible, DNA extracted from white blood cells and DNA extracted from tumor should be stored.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Prenatal_Testing">
          <title>Prenatal Testing</title>
          <p>When there is a family history of Rb, various options are available to optimize management of an at-risk pregnancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF3">Canadian Retinoblastoma Society 2009</xref>]</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk may be available from a clinical laboratory that offers either testing of this gene or custom prenatal testing.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant is identified in the fetus, ultrasound examination may be used to identify medium-sized intraocular tumors. If tumors are present, preterm delivery to enable early treatment may be considered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.sahgal.2006.628">Sahgal et al 2006</xref>]. Even if no tumors are visible on obstetric ultrasound, delivery of the fetus at 36 weeks&#x02019; gestation may be recommended, as 30% of babies with an <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant will have a tiny vision-threatening tumor [Authors, unpublished data].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant has not been identified in an affected family member, prenatal ultrasound or MRI may reveal a moderately large Rb in the eye of an affected fetus; however, these tests are not sensitive enough to detect small Rb tumors.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions about prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
          <p><bold>Preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)</bold> may be an option for some families in which the <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Molecular_Genetic_Pathoge">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>With very rare exceptions, tumor development starts from cells that do not have a normal <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> allele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2013.327">Rushlow et al 2013</xref>]. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="retinoblastoma.F1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold> Twenty-seven exons are transcribed and spliced into a 4.7-kb mRNA. There is no indication of functional alternative splicing. A frequently used reference sequence for the transcript is <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000321.2">NM_000321.2</ext-link>. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="retinoblastoma" object-id="retinoblastoma.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
          <p><bold>Benign allelic variants.</bold> No frequent polymorphic sites within the 2.7-kb open reading frame are known, but there are intronic variants, two highly polymorphic microsatellites (Rb1.20, Rbi2), and one minisatellite (RBD).</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> More than 2500 nucleotide variants have been observed in white blood-cell DNA of individuals with retinoblastoma or in tumors; more than 1700 are archived (see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="retinoblastoma" object-id="retinoblastoma.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Locus Specific</bold>). The majority of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> pathogenic variants result in a premature termination codon, usually through single base substitutions, frameshift variants, or out-of-frame exon skipping caused by splice site variants. Pathogenic variants have been found scattered throughout exon 1 to exon 25 of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> and its promoter region. In a single family, a possible pathogenic variant in exon 27 was identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.mitter.2009.55">Mitter et al 2009</xref>]. Recurrent pathogenic variants are observed at methylated CpG dinucleotides that are part of CGA codons or the splice donor site of intron 12. Other important types of pathogenic variants are complex rearrangements and deletions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.albrecht.2005.437">Albrecht et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2009.842">Rushlow et al 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.cast_ra.2013.460">Cast&#x000e9;ra et al 2013</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> encodes a ubiquitously expressed nuclear protein that is involved in cell cycle regulation (G1 to S transition). The RB protein is phosphorylated by members of the cyclin-dependent kinase (cdk) system prior to the entry into S-phase. On phosphorylation, the binding activity of the pocket domain is lost, resulting in the release of cellular proteins. For a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.dick.2013.297">Dick &#x00026; Rubin [2013]</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.dimaras.2015">Dimaras et al [2015]</xref>.</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> lead to the expression of proteins that have lost cell cycle-regulating functions. Retention of partial activities has been observed in proteins resulting from pathogenic variants that are associated with low-penetrance retinoblastoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.lohmann.1994.349">Lohmann et al 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.bremner.1997.556">Bremner et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="retinoblastoma.REF.otterson.1997.12036">Otterson et al 1997</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Published_GuidelinesConse">
          <title>Published Guidelines/Consensus Statements</title>
          <ref-list id="retinoblastoma.Published_GuidelinesConse.reflist0">
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF1">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">American Society of Clinical Oncology. Policy statement update: genetic testing for cancer susceptibility. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jco.ascopubs.org/content/28/5/893.long">online</ext-link>; registration or institutional access required. 2010. Accessed 2-10-16.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF2">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">American Society of Clinical Oncology. Statement on genetic testing for cancer susceptibility. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jco.ascopubs.org/cgi/content/full/21/12/2397">online</ext-link>. 2003. Accessed 2-10-16.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF3">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Canadian Retinoblastoma Society. National Retinoblastoma Strategy Canadian Guidelines for Care: Strat&#x000e9;gie th&#x000e9;rapeutique du r&#x000e9;tinoblastome guide clinique canadien. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cos-sco.ca/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/COS_RetinoblastomaCPGs_Dec09.pdf">online</ext-link>. 2009. Accessed 2-10-16.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="retinoblastoma.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.abramson.2003.1248">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abramson</surname>
                    <given-names>DH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beaverson</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sangani</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vora</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>TC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hochberg</surname>
                    <given-names>HM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kirszrot</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ranjithan</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Screening for retinoblastoma: presenting signs as prognosticators of patient and ocular survival.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatrics.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>112</volume>
                <fpage>1248</fpage>
                <lpage>55</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654593</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.albrecht.2005.437">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Albrecht</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ansperger-Rescher</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sch&#x000fc;ler</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeschnigk</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Spectrum of gross deletions and insertions in the RB1 gene in patients with retinoblastoma and association with phenotypic expression.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>26</volume>
                <fpage>437</fpage>
                <lpage>45</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16127685</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF6">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">American Society of Clinical Oncology. Statement on genetic testing for cancer susceptibility. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jco.ascopubs.org/cgi/content/full/21/12/2397">online</ext-link>. 2003. Accessed 2-10-16.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.bremner.1997.556">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bremner</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Du</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Connolly-Wilson</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bridge</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ahmad</surname>
                    <given-names>KF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mostachfi</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rushlow</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dunn</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Deletion of RB exons 24 and 25 causes low-penetrance retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>1997</year>
                <volume>61</volume>
                <fpage>556</fpage>
                <lpage>70</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9326321</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.canadian_retinoblastoma_society.2009.s1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <collab>Canadian Retinoblastoma Society</collab>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>National Retinoblastoma Strategy Canadian Guidelines for Care: Strat&#x000e9;gie th&#x000e9;rapeutique du r&#x000e9;tinoblastome guide clinique canadien.</article-title>
                <source>Can J Ophthalmol.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>44</volume>
                <fpage>S1</fpage>
                <lpage>88</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20237571</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.cast_ra.2013.460">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cast&#x000e9;ra</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dehainault</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Michaux</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lumbroso-Le Rouic</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aerts</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Doz</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pelet</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Couturier</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stoppa-Lyonnet</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gauthier-Villars</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houdayer</surname>
                    <given-names>C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Fine mapping of whole RB1 gene deletions in retinoblastoma patients confirms PCDH8 as a candidate gene for psychomotor delay.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>21</volume>
                <fpage>460</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22909775</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.chen.2014.384">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moran</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Richards-Yutz</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Toorens</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gerhart</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ganguly</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shields</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ganguly</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Enhanced sensitivity for detection of low-level germline mosaic RB1 mutations in sporadic retinoblastoma cases using deep semiconductor sequencing.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>35</volume>
                <fpage>384</fpage>
                <lpage>91</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24282159</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.de_jong.2014.1157">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Jong</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kors</surname>
                    <given-names>WA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Graaf</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castelijns</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kivela</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moll</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Trilateral retinoblastoma: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title>
                <source>The lancet oncology.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>15</volume>
                <fpage>1157</fpage>
                <lpage>67</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25126964</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.dehainault.2014.5243">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dehainault</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garancher</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cast&#x000e9;ra</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cassoux</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aerts</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Doz</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Desjardins</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lumbroso</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Montes de Oca</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Almouzni</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stoppa-Lyonnet</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pouponnot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gauthier-Villars</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houdayer</surname>
                    <given-names>C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The survival gene MED4 explains low penetrance retinoblastoma in patients with large RB1 deletion.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>23</volume>
                <fpage>5243</fpage>
                <lpage>50</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24858910</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.dick.2013.297">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dick</surname>
                    <given-names>FA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rubin</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Molecular mechanisms underlying RB protein function.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>297</fpage>
                <lpage>306</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23594950</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.dimaras.2015">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Dimaras H, Corson D, Cobrinik D, White A, Zhao J, Munier FL, Abramson DH, Shields CL, Chantada GL, Njuguna F, Gallie BL. Retinoblastoma. Nature Reviews Disease Primers. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/articles/nrdp201521">online</ext-link>. 2015. Accessed 2-10-16.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.dimaras.2008.1363">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dimaras</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khetan</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Halliday</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Orlic</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prigoda</surname>
                    <given-names>NL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Piovesan</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marrano</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Corson</surname>
                    <given-names>TW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eagle</surname>
                    <given-names>RC</given-names>
                    <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Squire</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Loss of RB1 induces non-proliferative retinoma: increasing genomic instability correlates with progression to retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>17</volume>
                <fpage>1363</fpage>
                <lpage>72</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18211953</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.dommering.2012a.216">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dommering</surname>
                    <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garvelink</surname>
                    <given-names>MM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moll</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Dijk</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Imhof</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meijers-Heijboer</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Henneman</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Reproductive behavior of individuals with increased risk of having a child with retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Genet.</source>
                <year>2012a</year>
                <volume>81</volume>
                <fpage>216</fpage>
                <lpage>23</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21954974</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.dommering.2012b.225">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dommering</surname>
                    <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marees</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van der Hout</surname>
                    <given-names>AH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Imhof</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meijers-Heijboer</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ringens</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Leeuwen</surname>
                    <given-names>FE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moll</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>RB1 mutations and second primary malignancies after hereditary retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Fam Cancer.</source>
                <year>2012b</year>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>225</fpage>
                <lpage>33</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22205104</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.draper.1992.211">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Draper</surname>
                    <given-names>GJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sanders</surname>
                    <given-names>BM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brownbill</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hawkins</surname>
                    <given-names>MM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Patterns of risk of hereditary retinoblastoma and applications to genetic counselling.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Cancer.</source>
                <year>1992</year>
                <volume>66</volume>
                <fpage>211</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1637670</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.fletcher.2004.357">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fletcher</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Easton</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gilham</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jay</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peto</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lifetime risks of common cancers among retinoblastoma survivors.</article-title>
                <source>J Natl Cancer Inst.</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>96</volume>
                <fpage>357</fpage>
                <lpage>63</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14996857</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.kleinerman.2007.24">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kleinerman</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tucker</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abramson</surname>
                    <given-names>DH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seddon</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tarone</surname>
                    <given-names>RE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fraumeni</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Risk of soft tissue sarcomas by individual subtype in survivors of hereditary retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>J Natl Cancer Inst.</source>
                <year>2007</year>
                <volume>99</volume>
                <fpage>24</fpage>
                <lpage>31</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17202110</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.kleinerman.2012.950">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kleinerman</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yu</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Little</surname>
                    <given-names>MP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abramson</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seddon</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tucker</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Variation of second cancer risk by family history of retinoblastoma among long-term survivors.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Oncol.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>30</volume>
                <fpage>950</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22355046</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.klutz.2002.174">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Klutz</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brockmann</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A parent-of-origin effect in two families with retinoblastoma is associated with a distinct splice mutation in the RB1 gene.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2002</year>
                <volume>71</volume>
                <fpage>174</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12016586</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.lohmann.1994.349">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brandt</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>H&#x000f6;pping</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Passarge</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horsthemke</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Distinct RB1 gene mutations with low penetrance in hereditary retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>1994</year>
                <volume>94</volume>
                <fpage>349</fpage>
                <lpage>54</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7927327</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.lohmann.1996.940">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brandt</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>H&#x000f6;pping</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Passarge</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horsthemke</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The spectrum of RB1 germ-line mutations in hereditary retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>1996</year>
                <volume>58</volume>
                <fpage>940</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8651278</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.marees.2008.1771">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marees</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moll</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Imhof</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Boer</surname>
                    <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ringens</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Leeuwen</surname>
                    <given-names>FE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Risk of second malignancies in survivors of retinoblastoma: more than 40 years of follow-up.</article-title>
                <source>J Natl Cancer Inst.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>100</volume>
                <fpage>1771</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19066271</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.mitter.2009.55">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mitter</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rushlow</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nowak</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ansperger-Rescher</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Identification of a mutation in exon 27 of the RB1 gene associated with incomplete penetrance retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Fam Cancer.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>55</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18509746</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.mitter.2011.947">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mitter</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ullmann</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Muradyan</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Klein-Hitpass</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kanber</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ounap</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaulisch</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Genotype-phenotype correlations in patients with retinoblastoma and interstitial 13q deletions.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>947</fpage>
                <lpage>58</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21505449</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.moll.1997.559">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moll</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kuik</surname>
                    <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bouter</surname>
                    <given-names>LM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Den Otter</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bezemer</surname>
                    <given-names>PD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koten</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Imhof</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kuyt</surname>
                    <given-names>BP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tan</surname>
                    <given-names>KE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Incidence and survival of retinoblastoma in The Netherlands: a register based study 1862-1995.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Ophthalmol.</source>
                <year>1997</year>
                <volume>81</volume>
                <fpage>559</fpage>
                <lpage>62</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9290369</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.noorani.1996.301">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Noorani</surname>
                    <given-names>HZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khan</surname>
                    <given-names>HN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Detsky</surname>
                    <given-names>AS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Cost comparison of molecular versus conventional screening of relatives at risk for retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>1996</year>
                <volume>59</volume>
                <fpage>301</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8755916</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.otterson.1997.12036">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Otterson</surname>
                    <given-names>GA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>WD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coxon</surname>
                    <given-names>AB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khleif</surname>
                    <given-names>SN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaye</surname>
                    <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Incomplete penetrance of familial retinoblastoma linked to germ-line mutations that result in partial loss of RB function.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source>
                <year>1997</year>
                <volume>94</volume>
                <fpage>12036</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9342358</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.richter.2003.253">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Richter</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vandezande</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sutherland</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Han</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Panton</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Branco</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Sensitive and efficient detection of RB1 gene mutations enhances care for families with retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>72</volume>
                <fpage>253</fpage>
                <lpage>69</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12541220</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2009.842">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rushlow</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Piovesan</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prigoda-Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>NL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marchong</surname>
                    <given-names>MN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clark</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Detection of mosaic RB1 mutations in families with retinoblastoma.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>30</volume>
                <fpage>842</fpage>
                <lpage>51</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19280657</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.rushlow.2013.327">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rushlow</surname>
                    <given-names>DE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mol</surname>
                    <given-names>BM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kennett</surname>
                    <given-names>JY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yee</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pajovic</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Th&#x000e9;riault</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prigoda-Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>NL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spencer</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dimaras</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Corson</surname>
                    <given-names>TW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pang</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Massey</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Godbout</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jiang</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zacksenhaus</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Paton</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moll</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houdayer</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raizis</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Halliday</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lam</surname>
                    <given-names>WL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boutros</surname>
                    <given-names>PC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dorsman</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Characterisation of retinoblastomas without RB1 mutations: genomic, gene expression, and clinical studies.</article-title>
                <source>Lancet Oncol.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>327</fpage>
                <lpage>34</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23498719</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.sahgal.2006.628">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sahgal</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Millar</surname>
                    <given-names>BA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Michaels</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jaywant</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chan</surname>
                    <given-names>HS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heon</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laperriere</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Focal stereotactic external beam radiotherapy as a vision-sparing method for the treatment of peripapillary and perimacular retinoblastoma: preliminary results.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol)</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>18</volume>
                <fpage>628</fpage>
                <lpage>34</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17051954</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.seregard.2004.1228">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seregard</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lundell</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Svedberg</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kivel&#x000e4;</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Incidence of retinoblastoma from 1958 to 1998 in Northern Europe: advantages of birth cohort analysis.</article-title>
                <source>Ophthalmology.</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>111</volume>
                <fpage>1228</fpage>
                <lpage>32</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15177976</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.sippel.1998.610">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sippel</surname>
                    <given-names>KC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fraioli</surname>
                    <given-names>RE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>GD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schalkoff</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sutherland</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dryja</surname>
                    <given-names>TP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Frequency of somatic and germ-line mosaicism in retinoblastoma: implications for genetic counseling.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>1998</year>
                <volume>62</volume>
                <fpage>610</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9497263</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.temming.2015.1799">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Temming</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viehmann</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arendt</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eisele</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spix</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bornfeld</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sauerwein</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>J&#x000f6;ckel</surname>
                    <given-names>KH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Pediatric second primary malignancies after retinoblastoma treatment.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>62</volume>
                <fpage>1799</fpage>
                <lpage>804</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25970657</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.temming.2013.475">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Temming</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Viehmann</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Biewald</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Sporadic unilateral retinoblastoma or first sign of bilateral disease?</article-title>
                <source>Br J Ophthalmol.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>97</volume>
                <fpage>475</fpage>
                <lpage>80</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23355526</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.valverde.2002.277">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valverde</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pandya</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heon</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goh</surname>
                    <given-names>TS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gallie</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chan</surname>
                    <given-names>HS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Retinoblastoma with central retinal artery thrombosis that mimics extraocular disease.</article-title>
                <source>Medical and pediatric oncology.</source>
                <year>2002</year>
                <volume>38</volume>
                <fpage>277</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11920797</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.wong.1997.1262">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wong</surname>
                    <given-names>FL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boice</surname>
                    <given-names>JD</given-names>
                    <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abramson</surname>
                    <given-names>DH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tarone</surname>
                    <given-names>RE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kleinerman</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stovall</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goldman</surname>
                    <given-names>MB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seddon</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tarbell</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fraumeni</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                    <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>FP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Cancer incidence after retinoblastoma. Radiation dose and sarcoma risk.</article-title>
                <source>JAMA</source>
                <year>1997</year>
                <volume>278</volume>
                <fpage>1262</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9333268</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="retinoblastoma.REF.zeschnigk.2004.e125">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeschnigk</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>B&#x000f6;hringer</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Price</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Onadim</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Massh&#x000f6;fer</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lohmann</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A novel real-time PCR assay for quantitative analysis of methylated alleles (QAMA): analysis of the retinoblastoma locus.</article-title>
                <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>32</volume>
                <fpage>e125</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15353561</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="retinoblastoma.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Author_History">
          <title>Author History</title>
          <p>Norbert Bornfeld, MD; University of Essen (2000-2004) Brenda L Gallie, MD (2004-present) Bernhard Horsthemke, PhD; University of Essen (2000-2004) Dietmar R Lohmann, MD (2000-present) Eberhard Passarge, MD; University of Essen (2000-2004)</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="retinoblastoma.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>19 November 2015 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>28 March 2013 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>10 June 2010 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>7 May 2007 (me) Comprehensive update posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>21 January 2005 (dl) Revision: Risk to offspring of a proband</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>28 December 2004 (me) Comprehensive update posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>21 January 2003 (me) Comprehensive update posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>18 July 2000 (me) Review posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>21 January 1999 (dl) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="retinoblastoma.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Schematic of the molecular genetic mechanisms that result in non-heritable and heritable retinoblastoma (Rb). The development of Rb is initiated if both alleles of <italic toggle="yes">RB1</italic> are mutated. In non-heritable Rb, both pathogenic variants (first and second variant) occur in somatic cells (somatic variants). Note: The pathogenic variants are not detected (two normal alleles, RB RB) in DNA from constitutional cells (e.g., from peripheral blood). In heritable Rb, only the second mutation is a somatic event. Independent second pathogenic variants give rise to independent tumor foci (multifocal Rb tumors). The first pathogenic variant is inherited via the germline (either a new germline variant or a pathogenic allele inherited from a parent). Note: In constitutional cells, the affected individual is heterozygous (RB rb) for the mutated allele.In some affected individuals the first pathogenic variant has occurred during embryonal development. Note: The affected individual is a somatic mosaic for the first pathogenic variant. Tumors may develop from cells that belong to the mutated sector that stems from the cell in which the first pathogenic variant has occurred.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="retinoblastoma-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
