<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="actg2-dis" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">actg2-dis</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title><italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-Related Disorders</title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wangler</surname>
            <given-names>Michael F</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="actg2-dis.Tc.aff1"/>
          <email>michael.wangler@bcm.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Beaudet</surname>
            <given-names>Arthur L</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="actg2-dis.Tc.aff1"/>
          <email>abeaudet@bcm.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="actg2-dis.Tc.aff1">Department of Molecular and Human Genetics<break/>Baylor College of Medicine<break/>Houston, Texas</aff>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="dupl22q11" document-type="chapter">22q11.2 Duplication</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="adamtsl4-eyes" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">ADAMTSL4-</italic>Related Eye Disorders</related-object>
      <abstract id="actg2-dis.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characeristics</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders are a subset of visceral myopathy with variable involvement of the bladder and intestine. Bladder involvement can range from neonatal megacystis and megaureter (with its most extreme form of prune belly syndrome) at the more severe end, to recurrent urinary tract infections and bladder dysfunction at the milder end. Chronic bladder dysfunction carries a high risk for urinary tract infections, dilation of the upper urinary tract, and impaired renal function. Intestinal involvement can range from malrotation, neonatal manifestations of microcolon, megacystic microcolon intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome (MMIHS), and chronic intestinal pseudoobstruction (CIPO) in neonates, children, and adults. Affected infants (with or without evidence of intestinal malrotation) often present with feeding intolerance and findings of non-mechanical bowel obstruction that persist after successful surgical correction of malrotation. Individuals who develop manifestations of CIPO in later childhood or adulthood often experience episodic waxing and waning of bowel motility. They may undergo frequent abdominal surgeries (perhaps related to malrotation or adhesions causing mechanical obstruction) resulting in resection of dilated segments of bowel, often becoming dependent on total parenteral nutrition (TPN).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder is established in a proband by the presence of a heterozygous pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2.</italic></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Management requires a multidisciplinary approach that includes primary care providers, gastroenterologists, general surgeons, urologists, nephrologists, dieticians, and social workers. Chronic bladder dysfunction typically requires management by a urologist and can involve routine urinary catheterization or diversion to reduce the risk of dilation of the upper urinary tract and associated risk for urinary tract infection and renal functional impairment. CIPO typically requires management by a gastroenterologist and nutritionist familiar with intestinal motility disorders.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> Clean and safe practices in the use of indwelling intravenous catheters for administration of TPN and bladder catheterization can help prevent infections. Surgical procedures associated with general anesthesia can produce a post-surgical ileus which can persist for an extended period.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Should be individualized taking into account:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The association between urinary tract infections and chronic bladder dysfunction and the increased risk for dilation of the upper urinary tract, and renal functional impairment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Need for routine evaluation of liver function in those dependent on long-term TPN.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> For those with CIPO, high-fat foods (&#x0003e;30% of total calories) and consumption of lactose and fructose may worsen abdominal bloating and discomfort.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> Presymptomatic diagnosis and treatment is warranted in relatives at risk as early diagnosis may help prevent unnecessary surgery for symptoms of intestinal obstruction and may allow early evaluation of bladder function, the urinary tract (for evidence of dilation), and renal function.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Pregnancy management:</italic> When a fetus at risk for an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder has evidence of bladder distention on prenatal ultrasound examination, consultation with a maternal fetal medicine specialist is recommended.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">ACTG2-</italic>related disorders are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. While the exact proportion of inherited vs <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variants is unknown, current data suggest that <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variants are common. Each child of an individual with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder has a 50% chance of inheriting the pathogenic variant. Although penetrance of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders appears to be complete, the severity of clinical findings can vary within a family. Prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk is possible if the <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.GeneReview_Scope">
        <title><italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> Scope</title>
        <table-wrap id="actg2-dis.Td" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.Td_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-Related Disorders: Included Phenotypes&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.Td_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Megacystis-microcolon-intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome (MMIHS)</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Prune belly sequence</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>Chronic intestinal pseudoobstruction (CIPO)</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>For synonyms and outdated names see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="actg2-dis.Nomenclature">Nomenclature</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="actg2-dis.TF.d.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p>For other genetic causes of these phenotypes see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="actg2-dis.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p><italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders are a subset of visceral myopathy with variable involvement of the bladder and intestine.</p>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders should be suspected in individuals with bladder and/or intestinal involvement that can range in a continuum from severe in neonates to more mild in older children and adults.</p>
          <p><bold>Bladder involvement</bold> can range from neonatal megacystis and megaureter (with its most extreme form of prune belly syndrome) at the more severe end to recurrent urinary tract infections and bladder dysfunction at the milder end. Chronic bladder dysfunction has a high risk of urinary tract infections, dilation of the upper urinary tract, and impaired renal function.</p>
          <p>Suggestive bladder findings:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Prenatal ultrasound revealing megacystis, defined according to trimester [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.fievet.2014.185">Fievet et al 2014</xref>]:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>First trimester: bladder diameter &#x0003e;6 mm</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Second and third trimesters: enlarged bladder with failure to empty within 45 minutes</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In neonates: prune-belly sequence (megacystis with lack of abdominal wall musculature, cryptorchidism in males, and distention of the upper urinary tract) in association with impaired gastrointestinal motility</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Postnatal ultrasound examination or cystogram revealing an enlarged bladder</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In individuals of any age: unexplained chronic functional bladder impairment of voiding without mechanical blockage</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Intestinal involvement</bold> can range from malrotation, neonatal manifestations of microcolon, and megacystis microcolon intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome (MMIHS) to chronic intestinal pseudoobstruction (CIPO) in neonates, infants, children, and adults.</p>
          <p>Suggestive intestinal findings:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Neonatal bilious emesis, abdominal distention, and feeding intolerance</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Intestinal malrotation and long-term intestinal motility problems often resulting in chronic abdominal pain and constipation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Neonatal microcolon</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In individuals of any age: chronic intestinal pseudoobstruction (CIPO) (i.e., unexplained chronic functional intestinal obstruction involving small bowel and/or colon without evidence of mechanical blockage).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Suggested specific diagnostic findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.gabbard.2013.307">Gabbard &#x00026; Lacy 2013</xref>]:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Symptoms lasting &#x0003e;6 months, or &#x0003e;2 months from birth</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evidence of delayed GI transit and/or decreased GI motility</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Imaging studies that do not show mechanical obstruction</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Radiographic documentation of dilated bowel, air fluid levels without fixed obstruction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.rudolph.1997.102">Rudolph et al 1997</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder is established in a proband by the presence of a heterozygous pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Between 50% and 70% of individuals with a clinical diagnosis of MMIHS and a significant but unknown fraction of individuals with a diagnosis of CIPO have a heterozygous pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> missense variant.</p>
          <p>Molecular testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold> and use of a <bold>multi-gene panel.</bold></p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> is performed first. Deletion/duplication analysis may be considered if no pathogenic variant is found; however, all pathogenic variants identified to date are missense variants, and no exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications have been identified as a cause of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="actg2-dis.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be used. Note: The genes included and sensitivity of multi-gene panels vary by laboratory and over time. For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-Related Disorders</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Pathogenic Variant Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/23&#x000a0;<sup>3,&#x000a0;4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None detected to date</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="actg2-dis.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="actg2-dis" object-id="actg2-dis.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="actg2-dis.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="actg2-dis.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="actg2-dis.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>2/2 probands in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.thorson.2014.737">Thorson et al [2014]</xref>, 15/15 probands with <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al [2014]</xref>, 3/3 probands in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.tuzovic.2015.296">Tuzovic et al [2015]</xref>, the case/family reports of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">Lehtonen et al [2012]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.holla.2014.533">Holla et al [2014]</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.klar.2015.1679">Klar et al [2015]</xref></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="actg2-dis.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>All pathogenic variants identified to date are missense.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="actg2-dis.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Examples of methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, and multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>A number of clinical phenotypes characterized by smooth muscle dysfunction affecting bowel and bladder (including diagnoses such as megacystis-microcolon-intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome [MMIHS] and chronic intestinal pseudoobstruction [CIPO]) have been described and reported in detail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.puri.2005.58">Puri &#x00026; Shinkai 2005</xref>]. At this time it is not known what percentage of the phenotypes reported before 2012 were caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> versus other causes.</p>
          <sec id="actg2-dis.Molecularly_Confirmed_ACTG2Rel">
            <title>Molecularly Confirmed <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-Related Disorders</title>
            <p>Because <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variants have only recently been identified as a cause of MMIHS, CIPO, and similar phenotypes, the number of affected individuals reported to date is small [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">Lehtonen et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.holla.2014.533">Holla et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.thorson.2014.737">Thorson et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>]. (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes">Table 2</xref>.) Thus, current understanding of the breadth of the phenotype and natural history of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders is limited, but expected to evolve over time.</p>
            <p>Individuals with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder experience functional defects of smooth muscle involving both bladder and bowel. General clinical patterns include neonates with a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant who experience severe functional impairment of bowel and bladder consistent with MMIHS, and individuals with an inherited (familial) <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant who experience later-onset CIPO. Individuals with <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders usually have normal intellect.</p>
            <table-wrap id="actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 2. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Summary of Bladder and Intestinal Findings in Individuals with Molecularly Confirmed <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-Related Disorders</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1">Finding</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="4" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Study</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.sipponen.2009.437">Sipponen et al [2009]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">Lehtonen et al [2012]</xref></th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.thorson.2014.737">Thorson et al [2014]</xref>
                    </th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.holla.2014.533">Holla et al [2014]</xref>
                    </th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al [2014]</xref>
                    </th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.klar.2015.1679">Klar et al [2015]</xref>
                    </th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Bladder</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prenatal or postnatal megacystis</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not Reported</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Prune belly syndrome</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not Reported</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Chronic functional impairment</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not Reported</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                      <bold>Intestinal</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microcolon</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not Reported</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Bilious emesis or inability to tolerate feeds as a neonate</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not reported</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not Reported</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">History of abdominal surgery</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Dependent on parenteral nutrition</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (intermittent)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">CIPO</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <bold><italic toggle="yes">De novo</italic> cases (# of families)</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (10)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Dominant familial cases (# of families)</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (1)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (3)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (1)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Undetermined inheritance cases (# of families)</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                      <bold>Total molecularly confirmed cases (total # of families)</bold>
                    </td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (1)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_2 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (15)</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_1_3 hd_h_actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes_1_1_2_5" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (1)</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p><bold>Urologic.</bold> From a recent series the majority of individuals with a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant had prenatal or postnatal megacystis and approximately one third had had a vesicoamniotic shunt placed prenatally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p>Prune belly syndrome, characterized by lack of abdominal wall musculature, cryptorchidism in males, and distention of the urinary tract, was reported in one male with MMIHS and a <italic toggle="yes">de novo ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p>Chronic bladder functional impairment seen in the majority of individuals with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant can require lifelong bladder catheterization.</p>
            <p><bold>Gastrointestinal.</bold> The majority of neonates with a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant are unable to tolerate feedings. Likewise, intestinal malrotation is common and while many undergo a Ladd surgical procedure, many experience persistent symptoms of bowel obstruction after surgical recovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p>Affected individuals can experience episodic improvement of bowel motility, loss of bowel motility over time, or waxing and waning of reduced bowel motility. Affected individuals may undergo frequent abdominal surgeries (perhaps related to malrotation or presumed adhesions causing mechanical obstruction) resulting in resection of dilated segments of bowel.</p>
            <p>In many families with a dominantly inherited <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant and waxing and waning CIPO, affected individuals report lifelong gastrointestinal discomfort and symptoms with episodes resulting in surgery and hospitalization. These individuals can survive to an advanced age.</p>
            <p><bold>Long-term survival.</bold> Long-term survival in those with a <italic toggle="yes">de novo ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant usually requires total parenteral nutrition and urinary catheterization or diversion. Most long-term survivors have ileostomies.</p>
            <p>Large series of individuals with MMIHS reported before the molecular basis of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders was known suggested that long-term survival was uncommon because the majority die in childhood or infancy of sepsis, organ failure, and/or malnutrition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.gosemann.2011.1041">Gosemann &#x00026; Puri 2011</xref>]. In contrast, in families with an inherited <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant, some family members with the pathogenic variant have MMIHS and others with the same variant have milder phenotypes, living into adolescence and early adulthood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p>It is not clear whether differences in prognosis for individuals with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2-</italic>related disorder compared to those with MMIHS of unknown cause reflect advances in medical management of parenteral nutrition or other factors.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="actg2-dis.Smooth_Muscle_Dysfunction_incl">
            <title>Smooth Muscle Dysfunction (including MMIHS and CIPO) of Unknown Cause</title>
            <p>Several studies have explored the clinical features of individuals with MMIHS and CIPO, but the proportion due to an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant versus other causes is not known. Therefore, these studies may encompass patient populations that combine <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders and those of other etiologies.</p>
            <p><bold>Urologic.</bold> Prenatal ultrasound examination is reported to identify megacystis in 88% and gastrointestinal abnormalities in 24% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.tuzovic.2014.74">Tuzovic et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p>Radiographic studies after delivery could reveal megacystis, hydronephrosis, vesicoureteral reflux, and/or the presence of microcolon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.ballisty.2013.454">Ballisty et al 2013</xref>].</p>
            <p>Although urinary obstruction and its potential adverse effect on renal function are often a concern in individuals with MMIHS, the long-term consequences for kidney function are not known. In one report of 709 individuals with fetal dilation of the urinary tract of diverse causes (e.g., posterior urethral valves and other types of mechanical obstruction not consistent with MMIHS), 17 instances of MMIHS were identified among 98 individuals with megacystis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.alhazmi.2012.649">Al-Hazmi et al 2012</xref>]. In this series, almost 30% (86/289) of those with severe fetal urinary tract dilatation had an abnormal serum creatinine concentration at age two years.</p>
            <p><bold>Gastrointestinal.</bold> Chronic intestinal pseudoobstruction (CIPO) has been reported at ages ranging from infancy to adulthood. After onset, progression to severe digestive dysfunction can range from one to 46 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.de_giorgio.2011.787">De Giorgio et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            <p>Some individuals with CIPO may undergo exploratory laparotomy without identification of an obstructive lesion.</p>
            <p><bold>Pathology.</bold> Numerous histopathologic studies on infants with MMIHS have had variable or inconsistent results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.puri.2005.58">Puri &#x00026; Shinkai 2005</xref>]. Findings have included alterations in ganglion cells (rare), vacuolar degeneration in the smooth muscle layer with connective tissue infiltration between muscle cells in bowel and bladder, excess muscle glycogen, and absent or reduced smooth muscle actin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.puri.2005.58">Puri &#x00026; Shinkai 2005</xref>].</p>
            <p>Visceral myopathy reveals the presence of vacuoles or fibrous replacement in the smooth muscle layer (muscularis propria) in a full-thickness intestinal biopsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.huang.2013b.699">Huang et al 2013b</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>No genotype-phenotype correlations have been identified.</p>
          <p>To date all reported <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variants have been missense variants, many of which affect arginine residues of the &#x003b3;-2 actin protein. The same missense variants have been seen across the phenotypic spectrum from neonatal MMIHS to later-onset chronic intestinal pseudoobstruction. Of note, disease caused by a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant is often more severe than inherited disease.</p>
          <p>Heterozygous null variants may be benign; however, this is not known with certainty.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>Thus far, penetrance of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2-</italic>related disorders appears to be complete, as no family members heterozygous for a known <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant have been noted to be completely symptom free. However, the clinical severity can range within a family, and mildly affected individuals may not be aware of the diagnosis. Examples: (1) one individual (in a multi-generation Finnish family) with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant reported episodic mild abdominal pain but no surgery and no signs of visceral myopathy at age 19 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">Lehtonen et al 2012</xref>]; (2) one individual diagnosed with &#x0201c;spastic colon&#x0201d; and irritable bowel syndrome had not required surgery or intervention in middle age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>Megacystis-microcolon-intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome (MMIHS) may also be referred to as familial visceral myopathy or Berdon syndrome.</p>
          <p>The broad term &#x0201c;hollow visceral myopathy&#x0201d; includes phenotypically related disorders caused by pathogenic variants in other genes (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">ACTA2</italic>), and, therefore, should not be used as a synonym for <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.milewicz.2010.2437">Milewicz et al 2010</xref>].</p>
          <p>Prune belly sequence may also be referred to as Eagle-Barrett syndrome.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>To date 47 individuals (from 23 families) have been reported to have a molecularly confirmed <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">Lehtonen et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.holla.2014.533">Holla et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.thorson.2014.737">Thorson et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>]. (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="actg2-dis.T.summary_of_bladder_and_intes">Table 2</xref>.)</p>
          <p>A total of 227 individuals with MMIHS were reported between 1976 and 2011 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.gosemann.2011.1041">Gosemann &#x00026; Puri 2011</xref>]. The proportion with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder is unknown.</p>
          <p>It is estimated that 100 individuals per year in the United States are diagnosed with CIPO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.de_giorgio.2011.787">De Giorgio et al 2011</xref>]. The proportion with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder is unknown.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Di">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Since many individuals with visceral myopathy with variable involvement of the bladder and intestine do not have an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant, mutation of other genes must contribute to the etiology of this phenotype (<xref ref-type="table" rid="actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d">Table 3</xref>). Because mydriasis has been noted in some individuals with MMIHS (megacystis-microcolon-intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.mcclelland.2013.271">McClelland et al 2013</xref>] but not in those with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder, the presence of mydriasis may suggest a differ disorder.</p>
        <table-wrap id="actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 3. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Inherited Disorders in the Differential Diagnosis for <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-Related Disorders</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th>
                <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inheritance</th>
                <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe GI or GU Involvement or Both</th>
                <th id="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distinguishing Clinical Features</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">MYH11</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patent ductus arteriosus in one individual</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ACTA2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vascular aneurysms and dissections, patent ductus arteriosus, mydriasis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">FLNA</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XL</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GI</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Periventricular heterotopia in males, seizures in females</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">TYMP</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GI</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mngie" document-type="chapter">MNGIE</related-object>: ptosis, ophthalmoplegia and ophthalmoparesis, hearing loss, neuropathy</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">EDNRB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">EDN3</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">SOX10</italic></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD or AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GI</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waardenburg syndrome with pigmentary abnormalities</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">SGOL1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GI</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAID: sick sinus syndrome, atrial dysrhythmias</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">RAD21</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GI</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mungan syndrome: Barrett esophagus, megaduodenum, cardiac abnormalities</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">CHRM3</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GU</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior urethral valves and prune belly syndrome</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">CHRNA3, CHRNB2, CHRNB4</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GU</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_actg2-dis.T.inherited_disorders_in_the_d_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse models with mydriasis and megacystis</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>GI = gastrointestinal</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>GU = genitourinary</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AR = autosomal recessive</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AD = autosomal dominant</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>XL = X-linked</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>NA = not applicable</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>MNGIE = mitochondrial neurogastrointestinal encephalopathy</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>CAID = chronic atrial and intestinal dysrhythmia</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">MYH11</italic></bold>. Mutation of this gene was identified in a child with MMIHS and patent ductus arteriosus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.gauthier.2015.1266">Gauthier et al 2015</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">ACTA2</italic>.</bold> This multisystemic smooth muscle dysfunction syndrome due to a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">ACTA2</italic> pathogenic variant is characterized by dysfunction of smooth muscle cells throughout the body, leading to severe and highly penetrant vascular diseases that include <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="taa" document-type="chapter">thoracic aortic aneurysms and aortic dissections</related-object>, patent ductus arteriosus, stenosis and dilatation of cerebral vessels, mydriasis, periventricular white matter hyperintensities on MRI, and pulmonary hypertension, as well as features characteristic of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders such as hypotonic bladder and malrotation and hypo-peristalsis of the gut [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.milewicz.2010.2437">Milewicz et al 2010</xref>]. Prune-belly sequence can also be associated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.richer.2012.664">Richer et al 2012</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">FLNA</italic>.</bold> Pathogenic variants in this X-linked gene have been reported in association with intestinal pseudoobstruction, as well as its commonly recognized phenotypes: <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="x-pvh" document-type="chapter">X-linked periventricular heterotopia</related-object>, a neuronal migration disorder with early lethality in affected males and seizures in affected females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.gargiulo.2007.751">Gargiulo et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.kapur.2010.1528">Kapur et al 2010</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">TYMP</italic>.</bold>
<related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mngie" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial neurogastrointestinal encephalopathy</related-object> (MNGIE) disease is characterized by: progressive gastrointestinal dysmotility and cachexia manifesting as early satiety, nausea, dysphagia, gastroesophageal reflux, postprandial emesis, episodic abdominal pain and/or distention, and diarrhea; ptosis/ophthalmoplegia or ophthalmoparesis; hearing loss; and demyelinating peripheral neuropathy manifesting as paresthesias (tingling, numbness, and pain) and symmetric and distal weakness more prominently affecting the lower extremities. The order in which manifestations appear is unpredictable. Onset is usually between the first and fifth decades. Direct evidence of MNGIE disease is provided by increase in plasma thymidine concentration &#x0003e;3 &#x000b5;mol/L and increase in plasma deoxyuridine concentration &#x0003e;5 &#x000b5;mol/L.</p>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">SGOL1</italic>.</bold> Chronic atrial and intestinal dysrhythmia (CAID) is the constellation of sick sinus syndrome (SSS) with aberrant sinus node pacing in the heart and intestinal pseudoobstruction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.chetaille.2014.1245">Chetaille et al 2014</xref>]. Bladder involvement was not reported. Atrial dysrhythmias have not been observed in <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2-</italic> related disorders.</p>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">RAD21.</italic></bold>
<italic toggle="yes">T</italic>he combination of CIPO, Barrett esophagus, and cardiac abnormalities caused by biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">RAD21</italic> is called Mungan syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.bonora.2015.771">Bonora et al 2015</xref>]. Bladder involvement has not been reported. Cardiac abnormalities and Barrett esophagus have not been observed in <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2-</italic> related disorders.</p>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">CHRM3</italic></bold><italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Prune belly syndrome with megacystis has been reported with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">CHRM3</italic>, a muscarinic acetylcholine receptor subunit. Gastrointestinal symptoms were not reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.weber.2005.1036">Weber et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.weber.2011.668">Weber et al 2011</xref>].</p>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">CHRNA3</italic>,</bold>
<bold><italic toggle="yes">CHRNB2</italic>,</bold> and <bold><italic toggle="yes">CHRNB4</italic>.</bold> Although these nicotinic acetylcholine receptors have not been associated with MMIHS in humans, they may be reasonable candidates based on findings in mouse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.xu.1999a.5746">Xu et al 1999a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.xu.1999b.9298">Xu et al 1999b</xref>].</p>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Other_Causes_of_Bowel_Obstruct">
          <title>Other Causes of Bowel Obstruction</title>
          <p>In neonates, the clinical presentation of intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome can mimic other causes of bowel obstruction, such as Hirschsprung disease.</p>
          <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hirschsprung-ov" document-type="chapter"><bold>Hirschsprung (HSCR) disease</bold></related-object> (or congenital intestinal aganglionosis) is characterized by complete absence of neuronal ganglion cells from a portion of the intestinal tract at birth. The aganglionic segment includes the distal rectum and a variable length of contiguous proximal intestine. Rarely, the aganglionosis extends into the small bowel or even more proximally to encompass the entire bowel (total intestinal aganglionosis). HSCR disease may occur as an isolated finding or as part of a multisystem disorder. Affected infants frequently present in the first two months of life with findings of impaired intestinal motility such as failure to pass meconium within the first 48 hours of life, constipation, emesis, abdominal pain or distention, and occasionally diarrhea. The finding in HSCR disease that distinguishes it from <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders is congenital intestinal aganglionosis, characterized by complete absence of neuronal ganglion cells from a portion of the intestinal tract. Additional research is needed to determine if some cases of HSCR can be caused by pathogenic variants of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>.</p>
          <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hirschsprung-ov" document-type="chapter"><bold>Waardenburg syndrome type IV</bold></related-object>
<bold>(WS4)</bold> is the combination of pigmentary abnormalities, hearing loss, and Hirschsprung disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.jan.2008.744">Jan et al 2008</xref>] caused by mutation of one of the following genes: <italic toggle="yes">EDNRB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">EDN3</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">SOX10</italic>. Inheritance can be either autosomal dominant (mutation of <italic toggle="yes">EDNRB</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">EDN3</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">SOX10</italic>) or autosomal recessive (mutation of <italic toggle="yes">EDNRB</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">EDN3</italic>).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Evaluations_Following_Initial">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder (which can range from megacystis-microcolon-intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome [MMIHS] to chronic intestinal pseudoobstruction [CIPO]), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Clinical genetics consultation with complete family history</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Urologic.</bold> Consultation with an expert in in pediatric urology whose evaluation may include studies of upper and lower urinary tract and renal function</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Gastrointestinal.</bold> Consultation with an expert in pediatric gastroenterology whose evaluation may include radiologic studies of the gastrointestinal tract based on the symptoms and onset. Of note, most individuals with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder will have undergone extensive radiographic imaging prenatally and/or in the neonatal period including evaluation for gastrointestinal distention and/or microcolon. However, if not performed at the time of diagnosis, studies to clarify the extent of disease could include abdominal x-rays, abdominal CT, transit studies (i.e., small bowel contrast studies), and/or endoscopy. Manometry (which typically shows reduced or absent contractions) can be used as an adjunct in the evaluation to quantify the degree of hypoperistalsis and extent of gastrointestinal dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.ambartsumyan.2014.16">Ambartsumyan &#x00026; Rodriguez 2014</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Nutrition.</bold> Consultation with a specialist in pediatric nutrition that includes plotting of height and weight on standardized growth charts and assessments of dietary intake, body mass index, and nutritional status (measurement of albumin and prealbumin, and tests of liver function)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Children with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder require multidisciplinary management with specialists in pediatric gastroenterology, nutrition, urology, surgery, clinical genetics, and occupational therapy, among others. Adults with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder require similar multidisciplinary care.</p>
          <p>Treatment for <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders remains supportive.</p>
          <p><bold>Urologic manifestations.</bold> Management of bladder dysfunction by an urologist is recommended.</p>
          <p>A clear link has been established between fetal urinary tract dilation such as megacystis and long-term impairment of renal function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.alhazmi.2012.649">Al-Hazmi et al 2012</xref>]. Patients are frequently dependent on bladder management with diversion, catheterization, and/or voiding schedules. In addition, clean and safe practices in the use of indwelling intravenous catheters and bladder catheterization can help prevent infections.</p>
          <p>In a review of 14 patients with visceral myopathy evaluated prior to the discovery of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.ghavamian.1997.1286">Ghavamian et al [1997]</xref> noted that clean intermittent catheterization decreased the frequency of urinary tract infection and observed that surgical approaches (construction of a catheterizable channel or a vesicostomy) were also therapeutic options.</p>
          <p>In a review of 39 children with CIPO reported before the discovery of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2,</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lapointe.2002.1768">Lapointe et al [2002]</xref> identified megacystis in 26 and hydronephrosis in 14. They noted that urologic intervention to ensure adequate bladder emptying was important to reduce the risk of urinary tract infections and to preserve long-term renal function. Urologic treatment (at some point in their care) included voiding with abdominal pressure (14 children), intermittent catheterization (10), and antibiotic prophylaxis (17).</p>
          <p><bold>Gastrointestinal manifestations.</bold> Management by a gastroenterologist and nutritionist familiar with intestinal motility disorders is recommended. Patients are frequently dependent on total parenteral nutrition (TPN) (see review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.gabbard.2013.307">Gabbard &#x00026; Lacy [2013]</xref>).</p>
          <p>Complications of long-term TPN can be progressive and include irreversible cholestasis, hepatic dysfunction, central line infections, and thromboembolic events. For this reason, individuals with an intestinal disorder that requires long-term TPN (like those seen in <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders) have undergone multi-visceral transplantation including liver and intestine. In the series of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.gosemann.2011.1041">Gosemann &#x00026; Puri [2011]</xref> in which 12 individuals underwent such multivisceral transplants, TPN could be discontinued in the majority; however, bladder catheterization was still required.</p>
          <p>Isolated intestinal transplantation has also been reported in one individual with MMIHS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.huang.2013a.e4">Huang et al 2013a</xref>].</p>
          <p>Of note, use of pro-kinetic agents such as 5HT<sub>4</sub> agonists has resulted in anecdotal evidence of improvement in bowel function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">Lehtonen et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>], as well as failure to improve in bowel function in MMIHS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.hiradfar.2013.may31">Hiradfar et al 2013</xref>] and some cases of molecularly confirmed <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related MMIHS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Prevention_of_Secondary_Compli">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Establishing the correct diagnosis of an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder may help avoid unnecessary exploratory laparotomies for unexplained episodes of apparent intestinal obstruction (i.e., CIPO).</p>
          <p>Surgical procedures associated with general anesthesia can produce a post-surgical ileus which can persist for an extended period.</p>
          <p>Clean and safe practices in the use of indwelling intravenous catheters for administration of TPN and bladder catheterization can help prevent infections.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Surveillance should be individualized using a multidisciplinary approach.</p>
          <p>Surveillance should take into account the link between fetal urinary tract dilation and long-term increased risk for impaired renal function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.alhazmi.2012.649">Al-Hazmi et al 2012</xref>].</p>
          <p>Long-term dependence on parenteral nutrition requires routine surveillance of liver function.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>For those with CIPO, high-fat foods (&#x0003e;30% of total calories) and consumption of lactose and fructose may worsen abdominal bloating and discomfort [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.gabbard.2013.307">Gabbard &#x00026; Lacy 2013</xref>].</p>
          <p>No drugs are known to exacerbate the smooth muscle functional defect in <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Ris">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>Using molecular genetic testing for the <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant identified in an affected family member, it is appropriate to evaluate relatives at risk as early diagnosis may help prevent unnecessary surgery for symptoms of intestinal obstruction and may allow early evaluation of bladder and renal function, and the urinary tract for evidence of dilation.</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="actg2-dis.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Iss">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>When a fetus at risk for an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder has evidence of bladder distention on prenatal ultrasound examination, consultation with a maternal fetal medicine specialist is recommended. Of note, in some fetuses with prenatal detection of megacystis, vesicoamniotic shunts have been performed. The rationale for this has been questioned [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.tuzovic.2014.74">Tuzovic et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p>Among the limited number of mothers with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder reported, some instances of poor labor progression and weak uterine contractions have been noted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.klar.2015.1679">Klar et al 2015</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Some individuals diagnosed with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder have an affected parent. Among 23 probands reported to date, six had an affected parent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">Lehtonen et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.klar.2015.1679">Klar et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A proband with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder may have the condition as the result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant. Among the 23 probands reported to date, 14 had a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.holla.2014.533">Holla et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.thorson.2014.737">Thorson et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">Wangler et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.tuzovic.2015.296">Tuzovic et al 2015</xref>]. In two other probands it was unknown if the pathogenic variant was <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> or inherited.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in leukocyte DNA of either parent, two possible explanations are a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant in the proband or germline mosaicism in a parent (observed in one of the 23 families reported to date [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.tuzovic.2015.296">Tuzovic et al 2015</xref>]).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recommendations for the evaluation of parents of a proband with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant include physical examination, a medical history <italic toggle="yes">w</italic>ith emphasis on signs of intestinal obstruction as an infant and/or chronic constipation, and molecular genetic testing.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The family history of some individuals diagnosed with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder may appear to be negative because of a milder phenotypic presentation, failure to recognize the disorder in family members, early death of the parent before the onset of symptoms, or late onset of the disease in the affected parent. Therefore, an apparently negative family history cannot be confirmed until appropriate evaluations have been performed.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: If the parent is the individual in whom the <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant first occurred s/he may have somatic mosaicism for the <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant and may be mildly/minimally affected.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to the sibs of the proband depends on the genetic status of the proband&#x02019;s parents.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband is affected, the risk to the sibs is 50%.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Although penetrance of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders appears to be complete, the severity of clinical findings can vary within a family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">Lehtonen et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.klar.2015.1679">Klar et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When the parents are clinically unaffected, the risk to the sibs of a proband appears to be low.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, the risk to sibs is low but greater than that of the general population because of the possibility of germline mosaicism (observed in one of the 23 families reported to date [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.tuzovic.2015.296">Tuzovic et al 2015</xref>]).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Each child of an individual with an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder has a 50% chance of inheriting the pathogenic variant. Although penetrance of <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders appears to be complete, the severity of clinical findings can vary within a family.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Other family members</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to other family members depends on the status of the proband's parents.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent is affected, his or her family members may be at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Iss">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="actg2-dis.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Ris">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p><bold>Predictive testing</bold> for at-risk asymptomatic adult family members requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant in the family.</p>
          <p><bold>Considerations in families with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant.</bold> When neither parent of a proband with an autosomal dominant condition has the pathogenic variant or clinical evidence of the disorder, it is likely that the proband has a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant. However, possible non-medical explanations including alternate paternity or maternity (e.g., with assisted reproduction) or undisclosed adoption could also be explored.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplan">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for an <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorder are possible. Note, however, that clinical severity cannot be accurately predicted by family history or molecular genetic testing.</p>
          <p>Although affected individuals are intellectually normal, <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders can be severe (e.g., MMIHS) and families may seek prenatal diagnosis. Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. While most centers would consider decisions about prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> spans approximately 27 kb and has a total of nine exons, eight of which are coding. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="actg2-dis" object-id="actg2-dis.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
        <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> To date all the pathogenic variants reported in <italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic>-related disorders are missense variants. Many of these affect arginine residues.</p>
        <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">ACTG2</italic> encodes &#x003b3;-2 actin, an enteric actin protein.</p>
        <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> The abnormal proteins are hypothesized to affect actin filament polymerization and smooth muscle contraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.thorson.2014.737">Thorson et al 2014</xref>]. Aggregation of the &#x003b3;-2 actin molecules may also occur [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">Lehtonen et al 2012</xref>]. Structural data on actin molecules support the role of some of the mutated amino acids in actin polymerization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="actg2-dis.REF.graceffa.2003.34172">Graceffa &#x00026; Dominguez 2003</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <p>Literature Cited</p>
        <ref-list id="actg2-dis.References.reflist0">
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.alhazmi.2012.649">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Al-Hazmi</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dreux</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Delezoide</surname>
                  <given-names>AL</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dommergues</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lortat-Jacob</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Oury</surname>
                  <given-names>JF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>El-Ghoneimi</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Muller</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Outcome of prenatally detected bilateral higher urinary tract obstruction or megacystis: sex-related study on a series of 709 cases.</article-title>
              <source>Prenat Diagn.</source>
              <year>2012</year>
              <volume>32</volume>
              <fpage>649</fpage>
              <lpage>54</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22544566</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.ambartsumyan.2014.16">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ambartsumyan</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Gastrointestinal motility disorders in children.</article-title>
              <source>Gastroenterol Hepatol (N Y)</source>
              <year>2014</year>
              <volume>10</volume>
              <fpage>16</fpage>
              <lpage>26</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24799835</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.ballisty.2013.454">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ballisty</surname>
                  <given-names>MM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Braithwaite</surname>
                  <given-names>KA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Shehata</surname>
                  <given-names>B. M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dickson</surname>
                  <given-names>P. N.</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Imaging findings in megacystis-microcolon-intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome.</article-title>
              <source>Pediatr Radiol.</source>
              <year>2013</year>
              <volume>43</volume>
              <fpage>454</fpage>
              <lpage>9</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22926452</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.bonora.2015.771">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bonora</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bianco</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cordeddu</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bamshad</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Francescatto</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dowless</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Stanghellini</surname>
                  <given-names>V</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cogliandro</surname>
                  <given-names>RF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lindberg</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mungan</surname>
                  <given-names>Z</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cefle</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ozcelik</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Palanduz</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ozturk</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gedikbasi</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gori</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Pippucci</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Graziano</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Volta</surname>
                  <given-names>U</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Caio</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Barbara</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>D'amato</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Seri</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Katsanis</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Romeo</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>De Giorgio</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Mutations in RAD21 disrupt regulation of APOB in patients with chronic intestinal pseudo-obstruction.</article-title>
              <source>Gastroenterology.</source>
              <year>2015</year>
              <volume>148</volume>
              <fpage>771</fpage>
              <lpage>82.e11</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25575569</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.chetaille.2014.1245">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chetaille</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Preuss</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Burkhard</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cote</surname>
                  <given-names>JM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Houde</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Castilloux</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Piche</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gosset</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Leclerc</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wunnemann</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Thibeault</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gagnon</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Galli</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tuck</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hickson</surname>
                  <given-names>GR</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>El Amine</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Boufaied</surname>
                  <given-names>I</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lemyre</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>De Santa Barbara</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Faure</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jonzon</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cameron</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dietz</surname>
                  <given-names>HC</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gallo-Mcfarlane</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Benson</surname>
                  <given-names>DW</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Moreau</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Labuda</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Zhan</surname>
                  <given-names>SH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Shen</surname>
                  <given-names>Y</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jomphe</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jones</surname>
                  <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bakkers</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Andelfinger</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Mutations in SGOL1 cause a novel cohesinopathy affecting heart and gut rhythm.</article-title>
              <source>Nat Genet.</source>
              <year>2014</year>
              <volume>46</volume>
              <fpage>1245</fpage>
              <lpage>9</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25282101</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.de_giorgio.2011.787">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>De Giorgio</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cogliandro</surname>
                  <given-names>RF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Barbara</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Corinaldesi</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Stanghellini</surname>
                  <given-names>V</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Chronic intestinal pseudo-obstruction: clinical features, diagnosis, and therapy.</article-title>
              <source>Gastroenterol Clin North Am.</source>
              <year>2011</year>
              <volume>40</volume>
              <fpage>787</fpage>
              <lpage>807</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22100118</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.fievet.2014.185">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Fievet</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Faure</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Coze</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Harper</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Panait</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Braunstein</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Carson</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gorincour</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chaumoitre</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Guys</surname>
                  <given-names>JM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Alessandrini</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>D'ercole</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Merrot</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Fetal megacystis: etiologies, management, and outcome according to the trimester.</article-title>
              <source>Urology.</source>
              <year>2014</year>
              <volume>84</volume>
              <fpage>185</fpage>
              <lpage>90</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24745800</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.gabbard.2013.307">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gabbard</surname>
                  <given-names>SL</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lacy</surname>
                  <given-names>BE</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Chronic intestinal pseudo-obstruction.</article-title>
              <source>Nutr Clin Pract.</source>
              <year>2013</year>
              <volume>28</volume>
              <fpage>307</fpage>
              <lpage>16</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23612903</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.gargiulo.2007.751">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gargiulo</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Auricchio</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Barone</surname>
                  <given-names>MV</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cotugno</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Reardon</surname>
                  <given-names>W</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Milla</surname>
                  <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ballabio</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ciccodicola</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Auricchio</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Filamin A is mutated in X-linked chronic idiopathic intestinal pseudo-obstruction with central nervous system involvement.</article-title>
              <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
              <year>2007</year>
              <volume>80</volume>
              <fpage>751</fpage>
              <lpage>8</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17357080</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.gauthier.2015.1266">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gauthier</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ouled Amar Bencheikh</surname>
                  <given-names>B</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hamdan</surname>
                  <given-names>FF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Harrison</surname>
                  <given-names>SM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Baker</surname>
                  <given-names>LA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Couture</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Thiffault</surname>
                  <given-names>I</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ouazzani</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Samuels</surname>
                  <given-names>ME</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                  <given-names>GA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rouleau</surname>
                  <given-names>GA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Michaud</surname>
                  <given-names>JL</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Soucy</surname>
                  <given-names>JF</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>A homozygous loss-of-function variant in MYH11 in a case with megacystis-microcolon-intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome.</article-title>
              <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
              <year>2015</year>
              <volume>23</volume>
              <fpage>1266</fpage>
              <lpage>8</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25407000</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.ghavamian.1997.1286">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ghavamian</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wilcox</surname>
                  <given-names>DT</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Duffy</surname>
                  <given-names>PG</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Milla</surname>
                  <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>The urological manifestations of hollow visceral myopathy in children.</article-title>
              <source>J Urol.</source>
              <year>1997</year>
              <volume>158</volume>
              <fpage>1286</fpage>
              <lpage>90</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9258196</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.gosemann.2011.1041">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gosemann</surname>
                  <given-names>JH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Puri</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Megacystis microcolon intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome: systematic review of outcome.</article-title>
              <source>Pediatr Surg Int.</source>
              <year>2011</year>
              <volume>27</volume>
              <fpage>1041</fpage>
              <lpage>6</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21792650</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.graceffa.2003.34172">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Graceffa</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dominguez</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Crystal structure of monomeric actin in the ATP state. Structural basis of nucleotide-dependent actin dynamics.</article-title>
              <source>J Biol Chem.</source>
              <year>2003</year>
              <volume>278</volume>
              <fpage>34172</fpage>
              <lpage>80</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12813032</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.hiradfar.2013.may31">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hiradfar</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Shojaeian</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dehghanian</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hajian</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Megacystis microcolon intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome.</article-title>
              <source>BMJ Case Rep.</source>
              <volume>2013</volume>
              <fpage>May31</fpage>
              <year>2013</year>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23729700</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.holla.2014.533">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Holla</surname>
                  <given-names>OL</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bock</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Busk</surname>
                  <given-names>OL</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Isfoss</surname>
                  <given-names>BL</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Familial visceral myopathy diagnosed by exome sequencing of a patient with chronic intestinal pseudo-obstruction.</article-title>
              <source>Endoscopy.</source>
              <year>2014</year>
              <volume>46</volume>
              <fpage>533</fpage>
              <lpage>7</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24777424</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.huang.2013a.e4">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Huang</surname>
                  <given-names>CM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tseng</surname>
                  <given-names>SH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Weng</surname>
                  <given-names>CC</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chen</surname>
                  <given-names>Y</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Isolated intestinal transplantation for megacystis microcolon intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome: case report.</article-title>
              <source>Pediatr Transplant.</source>
              <year>2013a</year>
              <volume>17</volume>
              <fpage>E4</fpage>
              <lpage>8</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23167913</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.huang.2013b.699">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Huang</surname>
                  <given-names>CM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wang</surname>
                  <given-names>HM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Zheng</surname>
                  <given-names>CH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Li</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Xie</surname>
                  <given-names>JW</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wang</surname>
                  <given-names>JB</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lin</surname>
                  <given-names>JX</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lu</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Tumor size as a prognostic factor in patients with node-negative gastric cancer invading the muscularis propria and subserosa (pT2-3N0M0 stage).</article-title>
              <source>Hepatogastroenterology.</source>
              <year>2013b</year>
              <volume>60</volume>
              <fpage>699</fpage>
              <lpage>703</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23159390</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.jan.2008.744">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jan</surname>
                  <given-names>IA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Stroedter</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Haq</surname>
                  <given-names>AU</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Din</surname>
                  <given-names>ZU</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Association of Shah-Waardenburgh syndrome: a review of 6 cases.</article-title>
              <source>J Pediatr Surg.</source>
              <year>2008</year>
              <volume>43</volume>
              <fpage>744</fpage>
              <lpage>7</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18405726</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.kapur.2010.1528">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kapur</surname>
                  <given-names>RP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Robertson</surname>
                  <given-names>SP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hannibal</surname>
                  <given-names>MC</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Finn</surname>
                  <given-names>LS</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Morgan</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Van Kogelenberg</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Loren</surname>
                  <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Diffuse abnormal layering of small intestinal smooth muscle is present in patients with FLNA mutations and x-linked intestinal pseudo-obstruction.</article-title>
              <source>Am J Surg Pathol.</source>
              <year>2010</year>
              <volume>34</volume>
              <fpage>1528</fpage>
              <lpage>43</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20871226</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.klar.2015.1679">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Klar</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Raykova</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gustafson</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tothova</surname>
                  <given-names>I</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ameur</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wanders</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Dahl</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Phenotypic expansion of visceral myopathy associated with ACTG2 tandem base substitution.</article-title>
              <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
              <year>2015</year>
              <volume>23</volume>
              <fpage>1679</fpage>
              <lpage>83</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25782675</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.lapointe.2002.1768">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lapointe</surname>
                  <given-names>SP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rivet</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Goulet</surname>
                  <given-names>O</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Fekete</surname>
                  <given-names>CN</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lortat-Jacob</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Urological manifestations associated with chronic intestinal pseudo-obstructions in children.</article-title>
              <source>J Urol.</source>
              <year>2002</year>
              <volume>168</volume>
              <fpage>1768</fpage>
              <lpage>70</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12352356</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.lehtonen.2012.1482">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lehtonen</surname>
                  <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sipponen</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tojkander</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Karikoski</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jarvinen</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Laing</surname>
                  <given-names>NG</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lappalainen</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Aaltonen</surname>
                  <given-names>LA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tuupanen</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Segregation of a missense variant in enteric smooth muscle actin gamma-2 with autosomal dominant familial visceral myopathy.</article-title>
              <source>Gastroenterology.</source>
              <year>2012</year>
              <volume>143</volume>
              <fpage>1482</fpage>
              <lpage>91.e3</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22960657</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.mcclelland.2013.271">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>McClelland</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Walsh</surname>
                  <given-names>RD</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chikwava</surname>
                  <given-names>KR</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Johnson</surname>
                  <given-names>MP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mattei</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Liu</surname>
                  <given-names>GT</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Congenital Mydriasis Associated With Megacystis Microcolon Intestinal Hypoperistalsis Syndrome.</article-title>
              <source>J Neuroophthalmol.</source>
              <year>2013</year>
              <volume>33</volume>
              <fpage>271</fpage>
              <lpage>5</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23636104</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.milewicz.2010.2437">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Milewicz</surname>
                  <given-names>DM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ostergaard</surname>
                  <given-names>JR</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ala-Kokko</surname>
                  <given-names>LM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Khan</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Grange</surname>
                  <given-names>DK</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mendoza-Londono</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bradley</surname>
                  <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Olney</surname>
                  <given-names>AH</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ades</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Maher</surname>
                  <given-names>JF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Guo</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Buja</surname>
                  <given-names>LM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kim</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hyland</surname>
                  <given-names>JC</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Regalado</surname>
                  <given-names>ES</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>De novo ACTA2 mutation causes a novel syndrome of multisystemic smooth muscle dysfunction.</article-title>
              <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
              <year>2010</year>
              <volume>152A</volume>
              <fpage>2437</fpage>
              <lpage>43</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20734336</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.puri.2005.58">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Puri</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Shinkai</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Megacystis microcolon intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome.</article-title>
              <source>Semin Pediatr Surg.</source>
              <year>2005</year>
              <volume>14</volume>
              <fpage>58</fpage>
              <lpage>63</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15770589</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.richer.2012.664">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Richer</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Milewicz</surname>
                  <given-names>DM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gow</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>De Nanassy</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Maharajh</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Miller</surname>
                  <given-names>E</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Oppenheimer</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Weiler</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>O'connor</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>R179H mutation in ACTA2 expanding the phenotype to include prune-belly sequence and skin manifestations.</article-title>
              <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
              <year>2012</year>
              <volume>158A</volume>
              <fpage>664</fpage>
              <lpage>8</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22302747</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.rudolph.1997.102">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rudolph</surname>
                  <given-names>CD</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hyman</surname>
                  <given-names>PE</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Altschuler</surname>
                  <given-names>SM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Christensen</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Colletti</surname>
                  <given-names>RB</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cucchiara</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Di Lorenzo</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Flores</surname>
                  <given-names>AF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hillemeier</surname>
                  <given-names>AC</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>McCallum</surname>
                  <given-names>RW</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Vanderhoof</surname>
                  <given-names>JA</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of chronic intestinal pseudo-obstruction in children: report of consensus workshop.</article-title>
              <source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr.</source>
              <year>1997</year>
              <volume>24</volume>
              <fpage>102</fpage>
              <lpage>12</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9093995</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.sipponen.2009.437">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sipponen</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Karikoski</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nuutinen</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Markkola</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kaitila</surname>
                  <given-names>I</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Three-generation familial visceral myopathy with alpha-actin-positive inclusion bodies in intestinal smooth muscle.</article-title>
              <source>J Clin Gastroenterol.</source>
              <year>2009</year>
              <volume>43</volume>
              <fpage>437</fpage>
              <lpage>43</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19098683</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.thorson.2014.737">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Thorson</surname>
                  <given-names>W</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Diaz-Horta</surname>
                  <given-names>O</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Foster</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                  <suffix>2nd</suffix>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Spiliopoulos</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Quintero</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Farooq</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Blanton</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tekin</surname>
                  <given-names>M.</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>De novo ACTG2 mutations cause congenital distended bladder, microcolon, and intestinal hypoperistalsis.</article-title>
              <source>Hum Genet.</source>
              <year>2014</year>
              <volume>133</volume>
              <fpage>737</fpage>
              <lpage>42</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24337657</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.tuzovic.2014.74">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tuzovic</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Anyane-Yeboa</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mills</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Glassberg</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Miller</surname>
                  <given-names>R.</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Megacystis-microcolon-intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome: case report and review of prenatal ultrasonographic findings.</article-title>
              <source>Fetal Diagn Ther.</source>
              <year>2014</year>
              <volume>36</volume>
              <fpage>74</fpage>
              <lpage>80</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24577413</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.tuzovic.2015.296">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tuzovic</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Tang</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Miller</surname>
                  <given-names>RS</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rohena</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Shahmirzadi</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gonzalez</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Li</surname>
                  <given-names>X</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Leduc</surname>
                  <given-names>CA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Guo</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wilson</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mills</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Glassberg</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Rotterdam</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sepulveda</surname>
                  <given-names>AR</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Zeng</surname>
                  <given-names>W</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chung</surname>
                  <given-names>WK</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Anyane-Yeboa</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>New insights into the genetics of fetal megacystis: ACTG2 mutations, encoding x03B3;-2 smooth muscle actin in megacystis microcolon intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome (Berdon syndrome).</article-title>
              <source>Fetal Diagn Ther.</source>
              <year>2015</year>
              <volume>38</volume>
              <fpage>296</fpage>
              <lpage>306</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25998219</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.wangler.2014.e1004258">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wangler</surname>
                  <given-names>MF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gonzaga-Jauregui</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gambin</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Penney</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Moss</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chopra</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Probst</surname>
                  <given-names>FJ</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Xia</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Yang</surname>
                  <given-names>Y</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Werlin</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Eglite</surname>
                  <given-names>I</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kornejeva</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bacino</surname>
                  <given-names>CA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Baldridge</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Neul</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lehman</surname>
                  <given-names>EL</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Larson</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Beuten</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Muzny</surname>
                  <given-names>DM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jhangiani</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gibbs</surname>
                  <given-names>RA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lupski</surname>
                  <given-names>JR</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Beaudet</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Heterozygous de novo and inherited mutations in the smooth muscle actin (ACTG2) gene underlie megacystis-microcolon-intestinal hypoperistalsis syndrome.</article-title>
              <source>PLoS Genet.</source>
              <year>2014</year>
              <volume>10</volume>
              <fpage>e1004258</fpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24676022</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.weber.2005.1036">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Weber</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mir</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Schlingmann</surname>
                  <given-names>KP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nurnberg</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Becker</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kara</surname>
                  <given-names>PE</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ozkayin</surname>
                  <given-names>N</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Konrad</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nurnberg</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Gene locus ambiguity in posterior urethral valves/prune-belly syndrome.</article-title>
              <source>Pediatr Nephrol.</source>
              <year>2005</year>
              <volume>20</volume>
              <fpage>1036</fpage>
              <lpage>42</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15912376</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.weber.2011.668">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Weber</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Thiele</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mir</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Toliat</surname>
                  <given-names>MR</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sozeri</surname>
                  <given-names>B</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Reutter</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Draaken</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ludwig</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Altmuller</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Frommolt</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Stuart</surname>
                  <given-names>HM</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ranjzad</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hanley</surname>
                  <given-names>NA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jennings</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Newman</surname>
                  <given-names>WG</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wilcox</surname>
                  <given-names>DT</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Thiel</surname>
                  <given-names>U</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Schlingmann</surname>
                  <given-names>KP</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Beetz</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hoyer</surname>
                  <given-names>PF</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Konrad</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nurnberg</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Woolf</surname>
                  <given-names>AS</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Muscarinic acetylcholine receptor M3 mutation causes urinary bladder disease and a prune-belly-like syndrome.</article-title>
              <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
              <year>2011</year>
              <volume>89</volume>
              <fpage>668</fpage>
              <lpage>74</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22077972</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.xu.1999a.5746">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Xu</surname>
                  <given-names>W</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gelber</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Orr-Urtreger</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Armstrong</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lewis</surname>
                  <given-names>RA</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Ou</surname>
                  <given-names>CN</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Patrick</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Role</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>De Biasi</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Beaudet</surname>
                  <given-names>AL</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Megacystis, mydriasis, and ion channel defect in mice lacking the alpha3 neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptor.</article-title>
              <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source>
              <year>1999a</year>
              <volume>96</volume>
              <fpage>5746</fpage>
              <lpage>51</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10318955</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="actg2-dis.REF.xu.1999b.9298">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal">
              <person-group>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Xu</surname>
                  <given-names>W</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Orr-Urtreger</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Nigro</surname>
                  <given-names>F</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gelber</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sutcliffe</surname>
                  <given-names>CB</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Armstrong</surname>
                  <given-names>D</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Patrick</surname>
                  <given-names>JW</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Role</surname>
                  <given-names>LW</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Beaudet</surname>
                  <given-names>AL</given-names>
                </name>
                <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>De Biasi</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
                </name>
              </person-group>
              <article-title>Multiorgan autonomic dysfunction in mice lacking the beta2 and the beta4 subunits of neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors.</article-title>
              <source>J Neurosci.</source>
              <year>1999b</year>
              <volume>19</volume>
              <fpage>9298</fpage>
              <lpage>305</lpage>
              <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10531434</pub-id>
            </element-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="actg2-dis.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Web pages</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.texaschildrens.org/find-a-doctor/michael-f-wangler-md">www.texaschildrens.org/find-a-doctor/michael-f-wangler-md</ext-link>
              </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bcm.edu/departments/molecular-and-human-genetics/?pmid=10579">www.bcm.edu/departments/molecular-and-human-genetics/?pmid=10579</ext-link>
              </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Authors&#x02019; research.</bold> The authors are currently using the latest technology including exome sequencing to understand rare Mendelian disorders including disorders of intestinal motility.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="actg2-dis.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>11 June 2015 (me) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>15 July 2014 (mw) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
