<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="bpan" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">bpan</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Beta-Propeller Protein-Associated Neurodegeneration</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: BPAN, Neurodegeneration with Brain Iron Accumulation 5 (NBIA5)</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gregory</surname>
            <given-names>Allison</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <aff>Oregon Health &#x00026; Science University<break/>Portland, Oregon</aff>
          <email>gregorya@ohsu.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kurian</surname>
            <given-names>Manju A</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>University College London<break/>London, United Kingdom</aff>
          <email>manju.kurian@ucl.ac.uk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Haack</surname>
            <given-names>Tobias</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Helmholtz Zentrum &#x00026; Technische Universit&#x000e4;t M&#x000fc;nchen<break/>Munich, Germany</aff>
          <email>tobias.haack@helmholtz-muenchen.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hayflick</surname>
            <given-names>Susan J</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Oregon Health &#x00026; Science University<break/>Portland, Oregon</aff>
          <email>hayflick@ohsu.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hogarth</surname>
            <given-names>Penelope</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Oregon Health &#x00026; Science University<break/>Portland, Oregon</aff>
          <email>hogarthp@ohsu.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="bvd" document-type="chapter">Best Vitelliform Macular Dystrophy</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="b-thal" document-type="chapter">Beta-Thalassemia</related-object>
      <abstract id="bpan.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration (BPAN) is typically characterized by early-onset seizures, infantile-onset global developmental delay, intellectual disability, absent to limited expressive language, motor dysfunction (ataxia), and abnormal behaviors often similar to autism spectrum disorder. Seizure types including generalized (absence, tonic, atonic, tonic-clonic and myoclonic), focal with impaired consciousness, and epileptic spasms, as well as epileptic syndromes (West syndrome and Lennox Gastaut syndrome) can be seen. With age seizures tend to resolve or become less prominent, whereas cognitive decline and movement disorders (progressive parkinsonism and dystonia) emerge as characteristic findings.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of BPAN is established by identifying on molecular genetic testing:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>In females. A heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> germline pathogenic variant;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In males. Either a hemizygous <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant or partial deletion of <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Somatic mosaicism has been reported in rare females (and possibly in 1 male).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Seizure management, tailored to the individual, may include antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), ketogenic diet, and/or vagus nerve stimulation. Global developmental delays and intellectual disability are managed in infancy and early childhood with early intervention programs and in school-age children with individual education programs. Consultation with a developmental pediatrician to ensure appropriate services is recommended. Discussion about transition plans including financial, vocation/employment, and medical arrangements should begin at age 12 years. Consider alternative means of communication, such as an Augmentative and Alternative Communication (AAC) program, for individuals who have expressive language difficulties. Motor dysfunction in childhood is managed with physical therapy to maximize mobility and to reduce the risk for later-onset orthopedic complications (e.g., contractures, scoliosis, hip dislocation). Occupational therapy may aid in writing, feeding, grooming, and dressing. For those with feeding difficulties, feeding therapy may be considered. For individuals with social/behavioral difficulties, consider applied behavior analysis (ABA) therapy, medical management strategies in conjunction with a developmental specialist, and pediatric psychiatry consultation to address aggressive or destructive behaviors. In adolescents/adults with parkinsonism, dystonia, and spasticity, the usual pharmacologic agents can be considered with the caveat that these therapies could exacerbate the cognitive deficits that also occur in this age group. Children with abnormal behaviors may qualify for and benefit from interventions used in treatment of autism spectrum disorder.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Routine follow up by a neurologist for medication management and interval assessment of ambulation, seizure activity, speech, and evidence of swallowing dysfunction. For those receiving dopaminergic drugs (for parkinsonism), monitor for adverse neuropsychiatric effects and disabling motor fluctuations and dyskinesias.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Pregnancy management:</italic> Use of AEDs during pregnancy for women with a seizure disorder is generally recommended, despite an increased risk for adverse fetal outcome associated with some AEDs. Discussion of the risks and benefits of using a given antiepileptic medication during pregnancy ideally should take place prior to conception. Transitioning to a lower-risk medication may be possible.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>BPAN is inherited in an X-linked manner; to date, most affected individuals have been female, and the vast majority are simplex cases (i.e., a single occurrence in a family) resulting from a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant. The exceptions include two familial cases, one with presumed maternal germline mosaicism and one with transmission of a <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant by a phenotypically normal mother who demonstrated significantly skewed X-chromosome inactivation. Females with the typical BPAN phenotype do not reproduce. In rare instances, a female who is mildly affected may reproduce. Affected males do not reproduce. Once the <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for BPAN are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="bpan.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>No formal diagnostic criteria for beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration (BPAN) have been published.</p>
        <sec id="bpan.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>BPAN <bold>should be suspected</bold> in an individual with the following <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Clinical_Findings">clinical</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.MRI_Findings">MRI</xref> findings.</p>
          <sec id="bpan.Clinical_Findings">
            <title>Clinical Findings</title>
            <p><bold>Seizures</bold> characterized by the following:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>
                  <bold>Features</bold>
                </p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Onset in early childhood</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Development of multiple seizure types</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Seizures worse in early childhood, lessening with age</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>
                  <bold>Types</bold>
                </p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Generalized (absence, tonic, atonic, tonic-clonic and myoclonic)</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Focal seizures with impaired consciousness</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Epileptic spasms</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>
                  <bold>Syndromes</bold>
                </p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>West syndrome</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Lennox Gastaut syndrome</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Early-onset epilepsy with intellectual disability</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Global developmental disability / intellectual disability</bold> (with minimal or absent expressive language) that is relatively stable in childhood, followed by progressive loss of cognitive function beginning in adolescence or early adulthood</p>
            <p><bold>Progressive parkinsonism and dystonia</bold>, beginning in adolescence or early adulthood</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal behaviors</bold> that overlap with Rett syndrome, including stereotypic hand movements, bruxism when awake, and abnormal sleep patterns</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="bpan.MRI_Findings">
            <title>MRI Findings</title>
            <p>Nonspecific hypomyelination and thin corpus callosum are seen in early childhood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.rathore.2014.574">Rathore et al 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.khalifa.2015.381">Khalifa &#x00026; Naffaa 2015</xref>; Hogarth, unpublished data] and evolve to highly specific signal abnormalities in later childhood, adolescence, or early adulthood:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>T<sub>2</sub>-weighted or iron-sensitive sequences reveal hypointense signal in the substantia nigra and globus pallidus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="bpan.F1">Figure 1</xref>). Note: Although less prominent than in older individuals, this finding is documented in children as young as age five years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.ichinose.2014.175">Ichinose et al 2014</xref>; Hogarth, unpublished data].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>T<sub>1</sub>-weighted sequences show a hyperintense &#x0201c;halo&#x0201d; surrounding a central linear region of signal hypointensity within the substantia nigra and cerebral peduncles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="bpan.F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Cerebellar or cerebral atrophy may also be present at any age.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of BPAN <bold>is usually established in</bold>
<bold>a</bold>
<bold>female proband</bold> by identification of a heterozygous pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> by molecular genetic testing (<xref ref-type="table" rid="bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in">Table 1</xref>). Note: Somatic mosaicism has been documented in leukocyte DNA of healthy mothers of affected male sibs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.dufke.2014">Dufke et al 2014</xref>] and affected male/female sibs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016a.1080">Zarate et al 2016a</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Genetic_Counseling">Genetic Counseling</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>).</p>
          <p>The diagnosis of BPAN <bold>is established in</bold>
<bold>a male proband</bold> by identification of a hemizygous pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> by molecular genetic testing (<xref ref-type="table" rid="bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in">Table 1</xref>). Of note:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>A <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> 19.9-kb deletion that includes part of <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic>, all of an adjacent gene, and part of a third gene has been reported in a severely affected male [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.abidi.2016.615">Abidi et al 2016</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In three families with recurrence of BPAN in sibs, affected males had inherited a germline pathogenic variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.dufke.2014">Dufke et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016a.1080">Zarate et al 2016a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nakashima.2016.653">Nakashima et al 2016</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Apparent somatic mosaicism for a <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant in a male has been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.haack.2012.1144">Haack et al 2012</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Genetic_Counseling">Genetic Counseling</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing approaches can include a combination of <bold>gene-targeted testing</bold> (multi-gene panel or single-gene testing) and <bold>genomic testing</bold> (comprehensive genome sequencing) depending on the phenotype.</p>
          <p>Gene-targeted testing requires the clinician to determine which gene(s) are likely involved, whereas genomic testing may not. In some cases, the phenotype of BPAN may be distinctive enough to warrant single gene-targeted testing (see <bold>Option 1</bold>), whereas those with a phenotype that is indistinguishable from many other inherited disorders with intellectual disability and neurologic findings (including seizures) are more likely to be diagnosed using genomic testing (see <bold>Option 2</bold>).</p>
          <p><bold>Option 1.</bold>
<bold>Gene-targeted testing.</bold> When the clinical and MRI findings suggest the diagnosis of BPAN, molecular genetic testing to consider includes the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> is performed first. If no pathogenic variant is found, gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis could be considered.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>)</p>
              <p>Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of the condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting secondary findings. (3) For this disorder a multi-gene panel that also includes deletion/duplication analysis is recommended (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in">Table 1</xref>). (4) If somatic mosaicism is suspected, discuss with the testing laboratory the ability of their methodology to detect mosaicism.</p>
              <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Option 2. Genomic testing.</bold> When the phenotype is indistinguishable from many other inherited disorders with intellectual disability and neurologic findings (including seizures), molecular genetic testing to consider includes the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Comprehensive genome sequencing</bold> (when available) including exome sequencing and genome sequencing. Note: These methods are generally suboptimal for detection of somatic mosaicism due to insufficient read depth of coverage. For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> for inherited disorders with intellectual disability and neurologic findings</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Beta Propeller Protein-Associated Neurodegeneration (BPAN)</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Pathogenic Variant&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3,&#x000a0;4</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;99%&#x000a0;<sup>5,&#x000a0;6</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_bpan.T.molecular_genetic_testing_used_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">See footnote 8</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="bpan.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="bpan" object-id="bpan.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="bpan.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="bpan.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="bpan.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>Lack of amplification by PCR prior to sequence analysis can suggest a putative (multi)exon or whole-gene deletion on the X chromosome in affected males; confirmation requires additional testing by gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="bpan.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>The failure to detect a pathogenic variant in a proband using sequence-based testing could be due to somatic mosaicism in a male or female or &#x02013; theoretically &#x02013; a heterozygous (multi)exon <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> deletion in a female (not reported in a female to date).</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="bpan.TF.1.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.pontkingdon.2012.41">Pont-Kingdon et al [2012]</xref>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="bpan.TF.1.7">
                <label>7. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="bpan.TF.1.8">
                <label>8. </label>
                <p>One <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> 19.9-kb deletion that includes part of <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.abidi.2016.615">Abidi et al 2016</xref>].</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="bpan.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="bpan.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration (BPAN) typically presents with seizures, infantile-onset global developmental delay, intellectual disability, absent to limited expressive language, and abnormal behaviors with Rett syndrome-like features. During adolescence and early adulthood (mean age 25 years; range 15-37 years) some of the hallmark childhood features (e.g., seizures) resolve or become less prominent, while cognitive decline and progressive parkinsonism and dystonia emerge as characteristic findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nishioka.2015">Nishioka et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p>The majority of individuals with BPAN are female; however, some males have been reported. Significant phenotypic variability is observed in both males and females.</p>
          <p>With increasing use of genomic testing, individuals with BPAN now tend to be identified at younger ages than those originally described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.haack.2012.1144">Haack et al [2012]</xref>.</p>
          <sec id="bpan.Core_Clinical_Features">
            <title>Core Clinical Features</title>
            <p><bold>Seizures</bold> are common during childhood, often starting as febrile seizures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nishioka.2015">Nishioka et al 2015</xref>]. Seizures are frequently multiform and include focal seizures with impaired consciousness, epileptic spasms [Hogarth, personal communication], and generalized seizures, including absence, atonic, myoclonic, and tonic-clonic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>].</p>
            <p>One young boy included in a cohort of children with early-onset epileptic encephalopathy had a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> deletion of <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> and two contiguous genes (<italic toggle="yes">CCDC120</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PRAF2</italic>) and clinical findings consistent with BPAN (brain iron accumulation, dystonia, and spastic tetraparesis) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.abidi.2016.615">Abidi et al 2016</xref>].</p>
            <p>Although seizures often require pharmacologic treatment and may be intractable, they often resolve or become less prominent with age.</p>
            <p><bold>Global developmental disability / intellectual disability.</bold> Individuals with BPAN typically have global developmental delay as children. The majority of children with BPAN have no expressive language; some develop limited language. Rarely, girls with BPAN can be high functioning with normal or nearly normal language development and less severe learning disabilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.long.2015.e714">Long et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            <p>Onset of progressive dementia occurs between adolescence and early to middle adulthood (mean age 25 years; range 15-37 years) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>]. Similar neurologic decline was observed in seven affected Japanese women between ages 29 to 39 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nishioka.2015">Nishioka et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            <p>In some instances, parents of children with BPAN have reported regression during early childhood; however, it is not clear whether this is due to the underlying disease, unrecognized seizures, or both [Hogarth, personal communication]. The aggressive epilepsy profile eventually seen in some children with BPAN may itself contribute to cognitive dysfunction, as in other epileptic encephalopathies.</p>
            <p><bold>Motor dysfunction.</bold> Children are typically clumsy and have a broad-based or ataxic gait. Some never learn to walk; others who achieve walking eventually become non-ambulatory. Some have mild spasticity that generally does not require treatment.</p>
            <p>Fine motor skills are also impaired. Some also have limited purposeful hand use (reminiscent of <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rett" document-type="chapter">Rett syndrome</related-object>) that can contribute to functional impairments such as difficulty with dressing and use of utensils.</p>
            <p><bold>The neurologic deterioration</bold> that occurs during adolescence and early to middle adulthood also includes onset of movement disorders, dystonia, and parkinsonism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nishioka.2015">Nishioka et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            <p>Dystonia often starts in the upper extremities.</p>
            <p>Parkinsonism is characterized by prominent bradykinesia, rigidity, freezing of gait, and postural instability. Tremor is not as common as in other forms of parkinsonism.</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal behaviors</bold> that overlap with Rett syndrome include lack of purposeful hand movements, stereotypic hand movements such as repetitive midline hand-wringing, bruxism when awake, abnormal sleep patterns, features of autism spectrum disorder, and diminished response to pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.haack.2012.1144">Haack et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.ohba.2014.292">Ohba et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.khalifa.2015.381">Khalifa &#x00026; Naffaa 2015</xref>]. Some young girls have been noted to have episodes of deep breathing during waking hours [Authors, personal observation]. Several individuals with BPAN have been diagnosed with autism spectrum disorder &#x02013; due in part to their limited language and social skills [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.verhoeven.2014.332">Verhoeven et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="bpan.Other_Features">
            <title>Other Features</title>
            <p><bold>Disordered sleep.</bold> Many families report that because their young children with BPAN have difficulty falling asleep and staying asleep, they sleep for only short periods of time. When performed, sleep studies revealed shortened mean sleep latency and abnormal REM sleep, hypersomnolence, hyposomnolence, and &#x02018;dance-like&#x02019; movements of the extremities with sleep onset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>]. Unrecognized nocturnal seizure activity may contribute to abnormal sleep patterns.</p>
            <p>Some adults with BPAN continue to have sleep difficulties or develop new manifestations such as waking and vocalizing during the night. Two of seven Japanese women had sleep problems as adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nishioka.2015">Nishioka et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Ophthalmologic findings</bold> including bilateral partial retinal colobomas, high myopia, astigmatism with myopia, spontaneous retinal detachment, and patchy loss of the pupillary ruff were observed in seven of 23 individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>].</p>
            <p>Bilateral optic atrophy has been described in one individual who also had bilateral sensorineural hearing loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.rathore.2014.574">Rathore et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Feeding and nutritional issues</bold>. Some infants and young children have feeding difficulties, most commonly texture sensitivity, oropharyngeal dysfunction, and aspiration. In some instances, GE reflux in young children has also required medical management. The neurologic deterioration that occurs in adolescence to early or middle adulthood frequently involves progressive feeding difficulty related to cognitive decline, dystonia, and parkinsonism and often results in significant weight loss.</p>
            <p><bold>Neuropathologic features.</bold> Findings in a woman who died from pneumonia at age 27 years included mild cerebellar atrophy, thinned cerebral peduncles, and dark gray-brown appearance of the substantia nigra and (to a lesser extent) the globus pallidus. The substantia nigra and globus pallidus stained strongly for iron and demonstrated numerous axonal spheroids &#x02013; both findings consistent with the pathology of other types of neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation. Numerous tau-positive neurofibrillary tangles were seen in several regions; no beta-amyloid plaques or Lewy bodies were observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>].</p>
            <p>In a second, more advanced case the findings were similar, but with more extensive neuronal loss and tau pathology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.paudel.2015.39">Paudel et al 2015</xref>]. Recent, unpublished findings by the authors suggest a more complex pathology.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="bpan.BPAN_in_Affected_Males_and_Females">
            <title>BPAN in Affected Males and Females</title>
            <p>Although <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> is X-linked and in females is subject to X-chromosome inactivation, the clinical features of BPAN follow a pattern that is somewhat atypical for an X-linked disorder: while there are far fewer affected males than females, the phenotype is similar in the two sexes.</p>
            <p>In the original report of 20 individuals, the three affected males had pathogenic variants predicted to render the protein nonfunctional (all frameshifts leading to premature stop codons). One of these males had evidence suggestive of somatic mosaicism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.haack.2012.1144">Haack et al 2012</xref>]. A hypothesis of somatic mosaicism of a <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant can explain both the viability of these males and the similarity of their phenotype to that of affected heterozygous females who are functionally mosaic due to X-chromosome inactivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.haack.2012.1144">Haack et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.saitsu.2013.445">Saitsu et al 2013</xref>].</p>
            <p>Males with germline pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> were originally predicted to be non-viable, but five such males from three families have since been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.dufke.2014">Dufke et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nakashima.2016.653">Nakashima et al 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016b.1095">Zarate et al 2016b</xref>]. Two families had missense variants while the other had a 3-bp in-frame deletion.</p>
            <p>The overall paucity of affected males relative to females suggests that germline pathogenic variants are rare in males and that affected male conceptuses are less likely to survive than female conceptuses. In two sets of male-female sibs with inherited <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variants, the males were more severely affected than the females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nakashima.2016.653">Nakashima et al 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016a.1080">Zarate et al 2016a</xref>]; of note, one female showed strongly skewed X-chromosome inactivation with the abnormal allele being preferentially active [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016a.1080">Zarate et al 2016a</xref>].</p>
            <p>In summary, the following factors are all proposed to contribute to the variability in phenotype and to the predominance of affected females relative to males:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Somatic mosaicism in both sexes</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Skewed X-chromosome inactivation in females</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>The specific type of pathogenic variant</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>Germline nonsense variants are predicted to lead to non-viable males. The vast majority of pathogenic variants are <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> and private.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>The BPAN phenotype was recognized in the initial (2002) version of <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pkan" document-type="chapter">Pantothenate Kinase-Associated Neurodegeneration</related-object> and in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.gregory.2009.73">Gregory et al [2009]</xref>; however, naming it in a manner consistent with other forms of neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation (NBIA) had to await discovery of the associated gene.</p>
          <p>Although referenced in the literature, the term SENDA (static encephalopathy with neurodegeneration in adulthood) is no longer favored [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.gregory.2011.254">Gregory &#x00026; Hayflick 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.kruer.2012.407">Kruer et al 2012</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>Similar to other forms of <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nbia-ov" document-type="chapter">neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation</related-object> (NBIA), BPAN is an ultra-rare disorder. Approximately 45 affected individuals have been reported in the literature to date.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="bpan.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disorde">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="bpan.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>In childhood, the core clinical features of BPAN &#x02013; seizures, developmental/intellectual disability, movement disorders, and behavioral abnormalities &#x02013; are highly variable between individuals and lack specificity, overlapping with many other genetic and sporadic (non-genetic) disorders. Early in the disease course, imaging abnormalities are similarly nonspecific, particularly if iron-sensitive sequences are not employed. The differential diagnosis at this stage is therefore broad, and includes <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rett" document-type="chapter">Rett syndrome</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="angelman" document-type="chapter">Angelman syndrome</related-object>, alpha-fucosidosis, and the epileptic encephalopathies of infancy and childhood:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Dravet syndrome</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>West syndrome</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Epilepsy with electrical status during slow-wave sleep</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Gelastic epilepsy</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Kozhevnikov-Rasmussen syndrome</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Landau-Kleffner syndrome</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Early infantile epileptic encephalopathy (See <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/phenotypicSeries/PS308350">Epileptic encephalopathy, early infantile: OMIM Phenotypic Series</ext-link> to view genes associated with this phenotype in OMIM.)</p>
            <p>Note: Like BPAN, the epileptic encephalopathies present with multiple seizure types in the first months or years of life and are associated with severe neurocognitive deficits. Note that specific eponyms are applied to a particular clinical and electrographic profile and do not imply a specific etiology: many genetic and non-genetic etiologies can result in a given epilepsy syndrome.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>If imaging reveals basal ganglia hypointensity on iron-sensitive sequences, the differential diagnosis narrows to the NBIA disorders and imaging phenocopies. These disorders can generally be distinguished from BPAN and each other by specific clinical and imaging features. See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nbia-ov" document-type="chapter">Neurodegeneration with Brain Iron Accumulation Disorders Overview</related-object>.</p>
        <p>Clinical features and the presence of high brain iron on MRI distinguish BPAN from other forms of childhood- or early adult-onset dystonia-parkinsonism, such as <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pink1-pd" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">PINK1-</italic>related Parkinson disease</related-object> and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="jpd" document-type="chapter">parkin-type Parkinson disease</related-object>.</p>
        <p>Neuropathologic findings (see Clinical Description, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Other_Features">Other Features</xref>) can help distinguish BPAN from other forms of NBIA.</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>In BPAN the pathologic changes found in the substantia nigra dominate those found in the globus pallidus (consistent with MRI findings), in contrast to other forms of NBIA in which the globus pallidus is more involved.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>BPAN can be distinguished by the lack of &#x003b1;-synuclein pathology that is abundant in MPAN and PLAN.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="bpan.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="bpan.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diagn">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration (BPAN), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Complete neurologic examination and developmental assessment including evaluation of motor function, speech/language, swallowing, and sleep</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>EEG monitoring, including sleep EEG, for any child with features (by history or observation) to suggest overt or occult seizures. Early referral to a neurology epilepsy sub-specialist is recommended if hypsarrhythmia or another aggressive electrographic pattern is found on EEG.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessments by specialists in physical, occupational, and/or speech therapy</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ophthalmologic examination</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of nutrition by a nutritionist or dietician</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p><bold>Seizures.</bold> As seizure severity and complexity varies widely, management should be tailored to the individual.</p>
          <p>Some children with BPAN may have no evidence of seizures or experience only rare febrile events and require no ongoing pharmacologic intervention. Others have severe, refractory epilepsy with multiple seizure types warranting the involvement of specialists in pediatric epilepsy and consideration of multiple therapeutic modalities, including antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), ketogenic diet, and/or vagus nerve stimulation.</p>
          <p>Short-term treatment with ACTH, prednisolone, or vigabatrin should be considered early in the care of a child with epileptic spasms, based on the guidelines in the US consensus report from the International League Against Epilepsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.pellock.2010.2175">Pellock et al 2010</xref>].</p>
          <p>Education of parents regarding common seizure presentations is appropriate. For information on non-medical interventions and coping strategies for parents or caregivers of children diagnosed with epilepsy, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epilepsy.com/sites/core/files/atoms/files/English_Toolkit_updated%202014.pdf"><underline>Epilepsy</underline> &#x00026; My Child Toolkit</ext-link>.</p>
          <sec id="bpan.Global_Developmental_DisabilityInte">
            <title>Global Developmental Disability/Intellectual Disability</title>
            <p><bold>For ages 0-3 years.</bold> Referral to an early intervention program is recommended for access to occupational, physical, speech, and feeding therapy. In the United States, early intervention is a nationwide federally funded program available in all states.</p>
            <p><bold>For ages 3-5 years.</bold> In the United States, developmental preschool through the local public school district is recommended. An evaluation will occur before placement to determine needed services and therapies and will be subsequently written into an individualized education plan (IEP).</p>
            <p><bold>For ages 5-21 years.</bold> In the United States, an individualized education program (IEP) should be developed by the local public school district based on each individuals&#x02019; level of function. Affected children are permitted to remain in the public school district until age 21.</p>
            <p><bold>For all ages.</bold> In the United States, individuals are protected under IDEA (Individuals with Disabilities Education Act) and should receive <bold>free and appropriate public education</bold> in the <bold>least restricted environment</bold>.</p>
            <p>Consultation with a developmental pediatrician is recommended to ensure that appropriate community, state, and educational agencies are involved and to support parents in maximizing quality of life. Developmental pediatricians can also provide assistance with transition to adulthood.</p>
            <p>Consideration of private supportive therapies based on the affected individual&#x02019;s needs is recommended. Specific recommendations regarding type of therapy can be made by a developmental pediatrician.</p>
            <p>Consider alternative means of communication for individuals who have expressive language difficulties, such as an Augmentative and Alternative Communication (AAC) evaluation.</p>
            <p>In the United States, enrollment in DDA (Developmental Disabilities Administration) is recommended. DDA is a public agency that provides services and support to qualified individuals. Eligibility differs by state but is typically determined by diagnosis and/or associated cognitive/adaptive disabilities.</p>
            <p>In the United States, families with limited income and resources may also qualify for supplemental security income (SSI) for their child with a disability.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="bpan.Motor_Dysfunction">
            <title>Motor Dysfunction</title>
            <p><bold>Gross motor dysfunction.</bold> Physical therapy is recommended to maximize mobility and to reduce the risk for later-onset orthopedic complications (e.g., contractures, scoliosis, hip dislocation).</p>
            <p>Consider use of durable medical equipment as needed (e.g., wheelchairs, walkers, bath chairs, orthotics, adaptive strollers)</p>
            <p>For muscle tone abnormalities including hypertonia or dystonia, consider involving appropriate specialists to aid in management of baclofen, Botox<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> anti-parkinsonian medications, or orthopedic procedures.</p>
            <p><bold>Fine motor dysfunction.</bold> Occupational therapy is recommended for difficulty with fine motor skills that affect adaptive function (e.g., writing, feeding, grooming, and dressing).</p>
            <p><bold>Oral motor dysfunction.</bold> Assuming that the indvidual is safe to eat by mouth, feeding therapy (typically from an occupational or speech therapist) is recommended for affected individuals who have difficulty feeding due to poor oral motor control.</p>
            <p><bold>Parkinsonism.</bold> Involvement of a neurologist specializing in movement disorders may be helpful once parkinsonism emerges in adolescents/adults.</p>
            <p>In the treatment of parkinsonism, dystonia, and spasticity the usual pharmacologic agents can be considered with the caveat that these therapies could exacerbate the cognitive deficits that also occur in this age group.</p>
            <p>Pharmacologic treatment of parkinsonism with dopaminergic medications usually has an initial striking benefit in males and females with improved motor function, affect, appetite, and interest in activities, followed by equally consistent disabling motor fluctuations (&#x0201c;on-off&#x0201d; phenomena) and dyskinesias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">Hayflick et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.hogarth.2015.1">Hogarth 2015</xref>].</p>
            <p>As cognitive deficits progress in those with advanced disease, carbidopa/levodopa formulations may carry a lower risk of adverse neuropsychiatric effects than dopamine agonists. Amantadine may be helpful for dyskinesias, but also carries a risk (especially in higher doses) of adverse psychiatric effects such as hallucinations and agitation.</p>
            <p>Pharmacologic treatment of dystonia and spasticity can include (if indicated) clonazepam or other benzodiazepines, oral baclofen, intramuscular botulinum toxin, and a trial of intrathecal baclofen. Trihexyphenydyl may also be useful for dystonia but may worsen cognitive dysfunction in advanced stages of the disease.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="bpan.SocialBehavioral_Difficulties">
            <title>Social/Behavioral Difficulties</title>
            <p>Children may qualify for and benefit from interventions used in treatment of autism spectrum disorder, including applied behavior analysis (ABA). ABA therapy is individualized therapy targeted to each child&#x02019;s behavioral, social, and adaptive strengths and weaknesses and is typically performed one on one with a board-certified behavior analyst.</p>
            <p>Consultation with a developmental pediatrician may be helpful in guiding parents through appropriate behavioral management strategies or providing prescription medications when necessary.</p>
            <p>Concerns about serious aggressive or destructive behavior can be addressed by a pediatric psychiatrist.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="bpan.Other_Features_1">
            <title>Other Features</title>
            <p><bold>Disordered sleep.</bold> Pharmacologic treatment of sleep abnormalities with melatonin, chloral hydrate, or benzodiazepines may be indicated.</p>
            <p><bold>Ophthalmologic findings.</bold> Eye findings are treated in a routine manner.</p>
            <p>
              <bold>Other</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Use of a liquid nutritional supplement to help maintain weight as needed</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>A gastric feeding tube to help maintain adequate weight (which becomes more difficult with disease progression) and to reduce the risk of aspiration pneumonia, if indicated</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Monitoring for complications of gastroesophageal reflux disease with institution of pharmacologic management if indicated. There are no data on the efficacy of fundoplication in BPAN.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Over-the-counter fiber supplements and/or stool softeners to treat constipation, which is likely caused by a combination of immobility, diet, and medications</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Regular pulmonary hygiene to manage risk for pulmonary complications; tracheostomy as indicated when secretions are difficult to manage</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Routine follow up by a neurologist for medication management and interval assessment of ambulation, seizure activity, speech, and swallowing. Often done every three to six months, follow up may be annual for those who are more stable.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>For those receiving dopaminergic drugs (for parkinsonism), monitoring for adverse neuropsychiatric effects and disabling motor fluctuations and dyskinesias</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Follow-up ophthalmologic examination every one to two years</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="bpan.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>Because women with mild manifestations of BPAN could potentially reproduce, the potential for teratogenic effects of medication taken during pregnancy needs to be considered.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Because BPAN falls in the category of <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nbia-ov" document-type="chapter">NBIA</related-object> and because individuals with BPAN have high brain iron, the possibility of chelation therapy is sometimes raised. The chelator deferiprone is currently under investigation for treatment of another NBIA disorder, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01741532?term=PKAN&#x00026;rank=2">PKAN</ext-link>. However, to date there is no evidence that iron chelation initiated early in the disease course prevents or delays the parkinsonian degeneration in adulthood or otherwise alters the course of PKAN. Nonetheless, results of these studies may inform its use in BPAN and/or lead to additional clinical trials.</p>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="bpan.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="bpan.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration (BPAN) is inherited in an X-linked manner. To date, most individuals with BPAN have been female. Data suggest that one male with BPAN had apparent somatic mosaicism for a <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.haack.2012.1144">Haack et al 2012</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p><bold>Parents of a proband.</bold> To date, the vast majority of reported individuals with BPAN have been simplex cases (i.e., a single occurrence in a family) and have had a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
          <p>Recommended parental molecular genetic testing when a proband has an identified <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Female proband.</bold> Molecular genetic testing of both parents</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Male proband.</bold> Molecular genetic testing of the mother only; the father of a male proband will neither have the disorder nor be hemizygous for the <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>If a woman has more than one affected child and no other affected relatives, she most likely has germline (and possibly somatic) mosaicism.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Presumed maternal germline mosaicism has been reported in a family with two affected sibs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016a.1080">Zarate et al 2016a</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>In a second family, a phenotypically normal mother had the same <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant as her sons with significant X-chromosome inactivation skewed towards the normal allele in her leukocyte DNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.dufke.2014">Dufke et al 2014</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> To date, nearly all affected individuals have had a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant, suggesting a low risk to sibs.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Female proband.</bold> The risk to sibs depends on the genetic status of the parents.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Male proband.</bold> The risk to sibs depends on the genetic status of the mother.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>If a proband represents a simplex case (i.e., a single occurrence in a family) and if the <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant cannot be detected in the parent&#x02019;s leukocyte DNA (female proband) or in the mother&#x02019;s leukocyte DNA (male proband), the risk to sibs is presumed to be slightly greater than that of the general population (though still &#x0003c;1%) because of the possibility of germline mosaicism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016a.1080">Zarate et al 2016a</xref>].</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Offspring of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Female proband.</bold> Females with the typical BPAN phenotype do not reproduce. In rare cases, a female who is mildly affected may reproduce.</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>One very mildly affected female with somatic and, presumably, germline mosaicism has reproduced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016a.1080">Zarate et al 2016a</xref>]. The likelihood that a mildly affected female with somatic and germline mosaicism would transmit a pathogenic variant to offspring may be less than 50% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.haack.2012.1144">Haack et al 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016a.1080">Zarate et al 2016a</xref>]. However, the potential reduction in recurrence risk is not quantifiable. Male fetuses are less likely to survive than female fetuses.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>One very mildly affected female with skewed X-chromosome inactivation in leukocyte DNA favoring the normal <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> allele has reproduced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.dufke.2014">Dufke et al 2014</xref>]. In this instance, the chance to transmit the pathogenic variant to offspring is 50%. A male conceptus may be less likely to survive.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Male proband.</bold> Affected males do not reproduce.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Given that most probands with BPAN reported to date have the disorder as a result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant, the risk to other family members is presumed to be low.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of genetic status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to parents of affected individuals.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplantatio">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for BPAN are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="bpan.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="bpan.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> contains 12 exons; the first two are non-coding. The longest transcript variant is <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_007075.3">NM_007075.3</ext-link>; a variant transcript <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001029896.1">NM_001029896.1</ext-link> has an alternate 5&#x02019;UTR and lacks an in-frame three-nucleotide segment in the coding region, thus encoding a protein isoform with one less internal amino acid. See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="bpan" object-id="bpan.molgen.TA">Table A, Gene</related-object> for details on transcript variants.</p>
        <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> Pathogenic variants have been documented in coding exons 3 to 12. All categories of variants have been reported including missense, nonsense, splicing, and intragenic deletion/insertion (i.e., indel) (<related-object source-id="gene" document-id="bpan" object-id="bpan.molgen.TA">Table A, HGMD</related-object>). Of note, a 3-bp in-frame deletion has been reported in male/female sibs and their mother, who was mosaic for this variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.zarate.2016b.1095">Zarate et al 2016b</xref>]. Apparent mosaicism was also found in an affected male [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.haack.2012.1144">Haack et al 2012</xref>].</p>
        <p>The majority of reported variants are predicted to be loss-of-function variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.haack.2013.85">Haack et al 2013</xref>]; the pathogenic basis for missense variants and the 3-bp in-frame deletion are unclear.</p>
        <p>Additionally, a 19.9-kb <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>, non-mosaic deletion of <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> exons 3-12 as well as two adjacent genes <italic toggle="yes">CCDC120</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">PRAF2</italic> (partial and complete deletion, respectively) was reported in an affected male [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.abidi.2016.615">Abidi et al 2016</xref>].</p>
        <p>Nearly all pathogenic variants are <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>; most are unique and appear to occur across ethnic groups at the same frequency.</p>
        <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> encodes WD repeat domain phosphoinositide-interacting protein 4 (WIPI4), which has WD40 repeat units. WIPI4 is a member of a large family of proteins with repeating units containing a conserved core of 40+ amino acids that terminate with tryptophan-aspartate (W-D) residues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.li.2001.2085">Li &#x00026; Roberts 2001</xref>]. These proteins assume a highly symmetric, seven-bladed, beta-propeller platform structure; hence the name of the disorder, beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration (BPAN). This structure supports specific protein-protein interactions and has a putative role in autophagy. Specifically WIPI4 is implicated in binding &#x02013; or associating &#x02013; with the known autophagy proteins ATG2A and ATG2B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.proikascezanne.2004.9314">Proikas-Cezanne et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.behrends.2010.68">Behrends et al 2010</xref>]; however, the exact role of <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> in the autophagic process remains to be elucidated.</p>
        <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Lymphoblasts and brain tissue from individuals with <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic> pathogenic variants demonstrate evidence of dysregulation of autophagic flux [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.saitsu.2013.445">Saitsu et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.paudel.2015.39">Paudel et al 2015</xref>]. A growing body of literature suggests dysregulation of autophagy as a mechanism in the pathophysiology of neurodegeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nassif.2012.78">Nassif &#x00026; Hetz 2012</xref>]. In normal neurons, basal autophagy helps maintain protein quality control and organellar homeostasis. It has been proposed that injured or stressed cells rely on autophagy to clear damaged cell components and other by-products, and that neurons are particularly vulnerable to defects in autophagy because of the large expanse of dendritic and axonal cytoplasm that must be traversed in order to reach lysosomes concentrated near the cell body [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bpan.REF.nixon.2013.983">Nixon 2013</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="bpan.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="bpan.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="bpan.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="bpan.REF.abidi.2016.615">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abidi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mignon-Ravix</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cacciagli</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Girard</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Milh</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Villard</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Early-onset epileptic encephalopathy as the initial clinical presentation of WDR45 deletion in a male patient.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>615</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26173968</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.behrends.2010.68">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Behrends</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sowa</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gygi</surname>
                    <given-names>SP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harper</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Network organization of the human autophagy system.</article-title>
                <source>Nature.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>466</volume>
                <fpage>68</fpage>
                <lpage>76</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20562859</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.dufke.2014">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="web">Dufke A, Grasshoff U, Dufke C, Kalscheuer V, Schroeder C, Beck-Wodl S, Tzschach A, Nagele T, Riess O, Bauer P, Krageloh-Mann I. NGS based whole X-exome analysis reveals a familial WDR45 missense mutation in 3 males with intellectual disability and brain iron accumulation. Abstract P08.53-S. Milan, Italy: European Society of Human Genetics Conference. 2014. Abstract available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.eshg.org/fileadmin/www.eshg.org/conferences/2014/ESHG2014Abstracts1.pdf">online</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.gregory.2011.254">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gregory</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Genetics of neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation.</article-title>
                <source>Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>254</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21286947</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.gregory.2009.73">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gregory</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Polster</surname>
                    <given-names>BJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Clinical and genetic delineation of neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>46</volume>
                <fpage>73</fpage>
                <lpage>80</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18981035</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.haack.2012.1144">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haack</surname>
                    <given-names>TB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hogarth</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kruer</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gregory</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wieland</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schwarzmayr</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Graf</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sanford</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meyer</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kara</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cuno</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harik</surname>
                    <given-names>SI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dandu</surname>
                    <given-names>VH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nardocci</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zorzi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dunaway</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tarnopolsky</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Skinner</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frucht</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hanspal</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schrander-Stumpel</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>H&#x000e9;ron</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mignot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garavaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hardy</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Strom</surname>
                    <given-names>TM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boddaert</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houlden</surname>
                    <given-names>HH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kurian</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meitinger</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prokisch</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Exome sequencing reveals de novo WDR45 mutations causing a phenotypically distinct, X-linked dominant form of NBIA.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>91</volume>
                <fpage>1144</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23176820</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.haack.2013.85">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haack</surname>
                    <given-names>TB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hogarth</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gregory</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prokisch</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>BPAN: the only X-linked dominant NBIA disorder.</article-title>
                <source>Int Rev Neurobiol.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>110</volume>
                <fpage>85</fpage>
                <lpage>90</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24209435</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.hayflick.2013.1708">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kruer</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gregory</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haack</surname>
                    <given-names>TB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kurian</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houlden</surname>
                    <given-names>HH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boddaert</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sanford</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harik</surname>
                    <given-names>SI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dandu</surname>
                    <given-names>VH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nardocci</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zorzi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dunaway</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tarnopolsky</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Skinner</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Holden</surname>
                    <given-names>KR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frucht</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hanspal</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schrander-Stumpel</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mignot</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>H&#x000e9;ron</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saunders</surname>
                    <given-names>DE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaminska</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lin</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lascelles</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cuno</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meyer</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garavaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Silva</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Crisp</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lunt</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carey</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hardy</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meitinger</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prokisch</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hogarth</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>&#x003b2;-Propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration: a new X-linked dominant disorder with brain iron accumulation.</article-title>
                <source>Brain.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>136</volume>
                <fpage>1708</fpage>
                <lpage>17</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23687123</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.hogarth.2015.1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hogarth</surname>
                    <given-names>P.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation: diagnosis and management.</article-title>
                <source>J Mov Disord.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>1</fpage>
                <lpage>13</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25614780</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.ichinose.2014.175">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ichinose</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miwa</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Onohara</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Obi</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shindo</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saitsu</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takiyama</surname>
                    <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Characteristic MRI findings in beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration (BPAN).</article-title>
                <source>Neurol Clin Pract.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>4</volume>
                <fpage>175</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24790802</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.khalifa.2015.381">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khalifa</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Naffaa</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Exome sequencing reveals a novel WDR45 frameshift mutation and inherited POLR3A heterozygous variants in a female with a complex phenotype and mixed brain MRI findings.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Med Genet.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>58</volume>
                <fpage>381</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26096995</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.kruer.2012.407">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kruer</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boddaert</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schneider</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houlden</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gregory</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    <given-names>JC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rooney</surname>
                    <given-names>WD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hogarth</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Neuroimaging features of neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation.</article-title>
                <source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>33</volume>
                <fpage>407</fpage>
                <lpage>14</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21920862</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.li.2001.2085">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roberts</surname>
                    <given-names>R.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>WD-repeat proteins: structure characteristics, biological function, and their involvement in human diseases.</article-title>
                <source>Cell Mol Life Sci.</source>
                <year>2001</year>
                <volume>58</volume>
                <fpage>2085</fpage>
                <lpage>97</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11814058</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.long.2015.e714">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Long</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abdeen</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Geraghty</surname>
                    <given-names>MT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hogarth</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Venkateswaran</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Novel WDR45 mutation and pathognomonic BPAN imaging in a young female with mild cognitive delay.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatrics.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>136</volume>
                <fpage>e714</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26240209</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.nakashima.2016.653">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakashima</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takano</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsuyusaki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoshitomi</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shimono</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aoki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kato</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aida</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mizuguchi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miyatake</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miyake</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Osaka</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saitsu</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>N.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>WDR45 mutations in three male patients with West syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>61</volume>
                <fpage>653</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27030146</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.nassif.2012.78">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nassif</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hetz</surname>
                    <given-names>C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Autophagy impairment: a crossroad between neurodegeneration and tauopathies.</article-title>
                <source>BMC Biol.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>78</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22999309</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.nishioka.2015">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nishioka K, Oyama G, Yoshino H, Li Y, Matsushima T, Takeuchi C, Mochizuki Y, Mori-Yoshimura M, Murata M, Yamasita C, Nakamura N, Konishi Y, Ohi K, Ichikawa K, Terada T, Obi T, Funayama M, Saiki S, Hattori N. High frequency of beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration (BPAN) among patients with intellectual disability and young-onset parkinsonism. Neurobiol Aging. 2015;36:2004.e9-15.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.nixon.2013.983">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nixon</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The role of autophagy in neurodegenerative disease.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Med.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>983</fpage>
                <lpage>97</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23921753</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.ohba.2014.292">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ohba</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nabatame</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iijima</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishiyama</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsurusaki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakashima</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miyake</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tanaka</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ozono</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saitsu</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>N.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>De novo WDR45 mutation in a patient showing clinically Rett syndrome with childhood iron deposition in brain.</article-title>
                <source>J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>59</volume>
                <fpage>292</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24621584</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.paudel.2015.39">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Paudel</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wiethoff</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bandopadhyay</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>de Silva</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houlden</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Holton</surname>
                    <given-names>JL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Neuropathology of Beta-propeller protein associated neurodegeneration (BPAN): a new tauopathy.</article-title>
                <source>Acta Neuropathol Commun.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>3</volume>
                <fpage>39</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26123052</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.pellock.2010.2175">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pellock</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hrachovy</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shinnar</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baram</surname>
                    <given-names>TZ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bettis</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dlugos</surname>
                    <given-names>DJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gaillard</surname>
                    <given-names>WD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gibson</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Holmes</surname>
                    <given-names>GL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nordl</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>O'Dell</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shields</surname>
                    <given-names>WD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Trevathan</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wheless</surname>
                    <given-names>JW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Infantile spasms: a U.S. consensus report.</article-title>
                <source>Epilepsia.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <volume>51</volume>
                <fpage>2175</fpage>
                <lpage>89</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20608959</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.pontkingdon.2012.41">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pont-Kingdon</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gedge</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wooderchak-Donahue</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schrijver</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Weck</surname>
                    <given-names>KE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kant</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oglesbee</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bayrak-Toydemir</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lyon</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Design and analytical validation of clinical DNA sequencing assays.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>136</volume>
                <fpage>41</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22208486</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.proikascezanne.2004.9314">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Proikas-Cezanne</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Waddell</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gaugel</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frickey</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lupas</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nordheim</surname>
                    <given-names>A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>WIPI-1alpha (WIPI49), a member of the novel 7-bladed WIPI protein family, is aberrantly expressed in human cancer and is linked to starvation-induced autophagy.</article-title>
                <source>Oncogene.</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>23</volume>
                <fpage>9314</fpage>
                <lpage>25</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15602573</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.rathore.2014.574">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rathore</surname>
                    <given-names>GS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaaf</surname>
                    <given-names>CP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stocco</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Novel mutation of the WDR45 gene causing beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration.</article-title>
                <source>Mov Disord.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>29</volume>
                <fpage>574</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24610255</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.saitsu.2013.445">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saitsu</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishimura</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Muramatsu</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kodera</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kumada</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sugai</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kasai-Yoshida</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sawaura</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishida</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoshino</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ryujin</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoshioka</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishiyama</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kondo</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsurusaki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakashima</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miyake</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arakawa</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kato</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mizushima</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>N.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>De novo mutations in the autophagy gene WDR45 cause static encephalopathy of childhood with neurodegeneration in adulthood.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>45</volume>
                <fpage>445</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23435086</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.verhoeven.2014.332">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Verhoeven</surname>
                    <given-names>WM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Egger</surname>
                    <given-names>JI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koolen</surname>
                    <given-names>DA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yntema</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Olgiati</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Breedveld</surname>
                    <given-names>GJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonifati</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van de Warrenburg</surname>
                    <given-names>BP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration (BPAN), a rare form of NBIA: novel mutations and neuropsychiatric phenotype in three adult patients.</article-title>
                <source>Parkinsonism Relat Disord.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>332</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24368176</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.zarate.2016a.1080">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zarate</surname>
                    <given-names>YA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jones</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jones</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Millan</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Juusola</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vertino-Bell</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                    <given-names>GB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kruer</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lessons from a pair of siblings with BPAN.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2016a</year>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>1080</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26577041</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="bpan.REF.zarate.2016b.1095">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zarate</surname>
                    <given-names>YA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jones</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jones</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Millan</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Juusola</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vertino-Bell</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                    <given-names>GB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kruer</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Lessons from a pair of siblings with BPAN.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2016b</year>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>1095</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27307113</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="bpan.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="bpan.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>The NBIAcure website, developed and maintained by Drs. Susan Hayflick and Penny Hogarth and their team, contains up-to-date information about BPAN and the other NBIA disorders, geared for lay persons, clinicians, and researchers. Information about current research and opportunities to enroll online are available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nbiacure.org/">here</ext-link>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Acknowledgments">
          <title>Acknowledgments</title>
          <p>Research reported in this publication was supported by a grant awarded to Dr. Hogarth by the <italic toggle="yes">National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences</italic> of the National Institutes of Health under award number <italic toggle="yes">UL1TR000128</italic>. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="bpan.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>16 February 2017 (bp) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>9 February 2016 (ag) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="bpan.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>T<sub>2</sub>-weighted sequences demonstrating globus pallidus hypointensity (A) and hypointensity of the substantia nigra (B). In BPAN, the substantia nigra is usually more hypointense relative to the globus pallidus, indicating higher levels of iron. Note: The illustrated findings are not typically present in early childhood, when imaging may be normal or show only hypomyelination, a thin corpus callosum, or cerebral/cerebellar volume loss.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bpan-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="bpan.F2" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>T<sub>1</sub> imaging demonstrates the hyperintense halo surrounding a central linear band of hypointensity in the substantia nigra and cerebral peduncles.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="bpan-Image002" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
