<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="dfn-myop" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">dfn-myop</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Deafness and Myopia Syndrome</title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ordonez</surname>
            <given-names>Jessica</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS, CGC</degrees>
          <aff>Miami Cancer Institute<break/>Baptist Health South Florida<break/>Miami, Florida</aff>
          <email>jessicaord@baptisthealth.net</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Tekin</surname>
            <given-names>Mustafa</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Dr John T Macdonald Foundation<break/>Department of Human Genetics<break/>John P Hussman Institute for Human Genomics<break/>Miami, Florida</aff>
          <email>mtekin@med.miami.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia" document-type="chapter">DYT1 Early-Onset Isolated Dystonia</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="ddon" document-type="chapter">Deafness-Dystonia-Optic Neuronopathy Syndrome</related-object>
      <abstract id="dfn-myop.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Deafness and myopia (DFNMYP) syndrome is characterized by bilateral, congenital or prelingual deafness (sensorineural hearing loss or auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder) and high myopia (&#x0003e;-6 diopters). In individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis reported to date, hearing loss was progressive and severity ranged from moderate to profound. Vestibular testing was normal. Myopia was diagnosed at infancy or early childhood.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis is established in a proband by identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> on molecular genetic testing.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> For hearing loss: use of hearing habilitation devices including hearing aids and vibrotactile hearing tools; cochlear implantation may be considered in individuals with severe-to-profound sensorineural hearing loss and auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder; enrollment in appropriate early-intervention and educational programs for the hearing impaired. For myopia: routine correction of refractive error.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> ENT and audiology evaluations at least yearly; regular speech and language evaluation to monitor language development; regular ophthalmology evaluations to monitor for potential complications from high myopia; yearly evaluations by a clinical geneticist familiar with hereditary forms of deafness.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Known environmental factors for hearing loss (e.g., loud noises) and ototoxic medications.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> If the <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> pathogenic variants in the family are known, molecular genetic testing can be used to clarify the genetic status of at-risk sibs. If a molecular diagnosis has not been established, clinical audiology and ophthalmology evaluations should be considered for at-risk sibs.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>DFNMYP syndrome is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Carrier testing for at-risk relatives and prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk are possible if the <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Deafness and myopia (DFNMYP) syndrome <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Moderate-to-profound, bilateral, congenital or prelingual sensorineural hearing loss or auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder (sensorineural hearing loss originates from problems in the inner ear or the auditory nerve). Auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder is characterized by normal outer hair cell function (present otoacoustic emissions [OAE] and/or cochlear microphonic), suggesting that the hearing loss results from abnormal inner hair cells, synapses, or auditory nerve function that can be demonstrated with an absent or abnormal auditory brain stem response (ABR) test.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>High myopia (g&#x0003e;-6 diopters)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Nondysmorphic facial appearance and normal temporal bone structure</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>No neurologic, connective tissue, or other ocular manifestations</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>No formal clinical diagnostic criteria have been established for DFNMYP syndrome.</p>
          <p>The diagnosis of DFNMYP <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with the above <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfn-myop.Suggestive_Findings">suggestive findings</xref>; identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> on molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use">Table 1</xref>) confirms the diagnosis.</p>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold>, use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>, and <bold>more comprehensive genomic testing</bold>:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> is performed first. Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis can be considered if only one or no pathogenic variant is found. However, to date, no large <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> deletions or duplications have been reported.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfn-myop.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of a condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting identification of pathogenic variants in genes that do not explain the underlying phenotype. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing-based tests.</p>
              <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>More comprehensive genomic testing</bold> (when available) including exome sequencing, mitochondrial sequencing, and genome sequencing may be considered. Such testing may provide or suggest a diagnosis not previously considered (e.g., mutation of a different gene or genes that results in a similar clinical presentation). For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Deafness and Myopia Syndrome</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with Pathogenic Variants&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/4&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.molecular_genetic_testing_use_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None reported&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="dfn-myop.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dfn-myop" object-id="">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfn-myop.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfn-myop.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfn-myop.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfn-myop.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.tekin.2013.2094">Tekin et al [2013]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.morlet.2014.e95">Morlet et al [2014]</xref></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfn-myop.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="dfn-myop.TF.1.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.tekin.2013.2094">Tekin et al [2013]</xref>
                </p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Deafness and myopia (DFNMYP) syndrome was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.tekin.2013.2094">Tekin et al [2013]</xref> in nine individuals with only deafness and myopia from three families, of Turkish, Greek, and Amish ancestry; all nine were found to be homozygous for <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> pathogenic variants.</p>
          <p><bold>Sensorineural hearing loss (SNHL)</bold> was bilateral in all affected individuals, congenital in one and prelingual in 8/9. SNHL was progressive and required hearing aids in all. Severity of hearing loss ranged from moderate (2/9) to severe (5/9) to profound (2/9).</p>
          <p>Sensorineural hearing loss progressed from moderate to profound by early adulthood in nine additional affected individuals from an endogamous Amish population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.morlet.2014.e95">Morlet et al 2014</xref>]. An auditory neuropathy-spectrum disorder characterized by absent middle-ear muscle reflexes (MEMRs) and otoacoustic emissions (OAEs), large and prolonged cochlear microphonics (CMs), desynchronized auditory brain stem responses (ABRs), and progressive pure tone hearing loss was described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.morlet.2014.e95">Morlet et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p>Affected individuals had normal gross motor development. None had balance problems, vertigo, or dizziness. Vestibular testing and temporal bone CT were normal in one affected individual from each family.</p>
          <p><bold>Myopia</bold> was diagnosed in infancy or early childhood in seven individuals on whom data were available. Myopia was severe in all seven individuals (range: -6 to -11 diopters) and required corrective lenses. Although no details of myopia treatment or complications were available, none of the potential complications of high myopia was observed in any of the reported individuals at the time of reporting.</p>
          <p><bold>Life span</bold> does not appear to be altered in individuals with DFNMYP syndrome; however, the oldest individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis are only in their late 30s.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>All reported individuals to date with DFNMYP syndrome have homozygous nonsense <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> variants. No significant differences in clinical phenotype have been associated with specific genotypes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>Due to the rarity of the syndrome, no prevalence estimates have been established.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Dis">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic>.</p>
        <p>Sporadic tumors (including papillary thyroid tumors) occurring as single tumors in the absence of any other findings of deafness and myopia syndrome may have somatic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> that are <bold>not</bold> present in the germline. In these circumstances predisposition to these tumors is not heritable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.heiliger.2012.409">Heiliger et al 2012</xref>]. For more details, see Molecular Genetics, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfn-myop.Cancer_and_Benign_Tumors">Cancer and Benign Tumors</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="deafness-overview" document-type="chapter">Hereditary Deafness and Hearing Loss Overview</related-object>.</p>
        <p>Disorders with deafness and myopia to specifically consider include the following:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="stickler" document-type="chapter"><bold>Stickler syndrome</bold></related-object><bold>,</bold> a clinically variable connective tissue disorder characterized by ocular, auditory, skeletal, and orofacial anomalies. Ocular findings typically include high myopia with cataracts and retinal detachment. Hearing loss is conductive and sensorineural. Severity of hearing loss is variable and may be progressive. Stickler syndrome, caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">COL2A1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL11A1</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">COL11A2</italic>, is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner; Stickler syndrome caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">COL9A1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL9A2</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">COL9A3</italic> is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Although myopia and sensorineural hearing loss are part of DFNMYP syndrome, individuals with DFNMYP syndrome do not manifest the skeletal and craniofacial findings traditionally seen in individuals with Stickler syndrome.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="donnai" document-type="chapter"><bold>Donnai-Barrow syndrome</bold></related-object>
<bold>(DBS),</bold> a multiple congenital anomaly syndrome characterized by typical craniofacial features, ocular findings, sensorineural hearing loss, brain anomalies, intellectual disability, and congenital diaphragmatic hernia and/or omphalocele. High myopia is typically accompanied by retinal detachment, progressive vision loss, and iris coloboma. Hearing loss may be progressive and variable in severity. The constellation of craniofacial findings typically includes marked ocular hypertelorism, large anterior fontanelle, wide metopic suture, widow&#x02019;s peak in anterior hairline, depressed nasal bridge, short nose, and posteriorly rotated ears. DBS can be caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">LRP2</italic> and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. In contrast to individuals with DFNMYP syndrome, individuals with DBS have multiple congenital anomalies and craniofacial and neurologic findings in addition to myopia and hearing loss.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Evaluations_Following_Initial_D">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with deafness and myopia (DFNMYP) syndrome, the following evaluations are recommended if they have not already been completed:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Audiology evaluation for sensorineural hearing loss and auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ophthalmology evaluation for myopia and other ocular comorbidities</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation by early intervention/educational programs for the hearing impaired including baseline speech and language assessment in children</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>Appropriate treatment includes the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Implementation of hearing habilitation devices including hearing aids and vibrotactile hearing tools as needed</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consideration of cochlear implantation (CI) in individuals with severe-to-profound sensorineural hearing loss and auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder. Although no CI has been reported among individuals with deafness and myopia syndrome, favorable outcome of CI has been reported in children with auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.breneman.2012.5">Breneman et al 2012</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Enrollment in early intervention programs and educational programs for the hearing impaired to maximize long-term speech and language outcomes</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Routine correction of refractive error</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>The following are appropriate:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>ENT and audiology evaluations at least yearly</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular speech and language evaluation to monitor language development</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Regular ophthalmology evaluations to monitor for potential complications from high myopia including cataracts, glaucoma, and retinal detachment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Yearly evaluations by a clinical geneticist familiar with hereditary forms of deafness</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Individuals with hearing loss should avoid the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Known environmental factors for hearing loss (e.g., loud noises)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ototoxic medications</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>It is appropriate to evaluate older and younger sibs of a proband in order to identify as early as possible those who would benefit from prompt treatment of hearing loss and myopia. Evaluations can include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Molecular genetic testing if the <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> pathogenic variants in the family are known;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Clinical audiology and ophthalmology evaluations if a molecular diagnosis has not been established.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfn-myop.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issu">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Deafness and myopia (DFNMYP) syndrome is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected child are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> pathogenic variant).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Although low myopia (&#x0003c;-3 diopters) of early and adult onset has been reported among some carrier parents, <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> heterozygotes are not at risk of developing hearing loss or the high myopia characteristic of DFNMYP syndrome.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are generally asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> The offspring of an individual with DFNMYP syndrome are obligate heterozygotes (carriers) for a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic>.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier of a <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Carrier_Heterozygote_Detection">
          <title>Carrier (Heterozygote) Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> pathogenic variants in the family.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issu">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="dfn-myop.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected, are carriers, or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimplant">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible.</p>
          <p>Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions about prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> contains two exons; exon 1 is non-coding. The full-length transcript spans 6.6 kb (6,562 bp) of genomic DNA. The cDNA <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_032229.2">NM_032229.2</ext-link> comprises 4199 bp encoding 841 amino acids. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dfn-myop" object-id="dfn-myop.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold>.</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> Three <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> pathogenic variants, all nonsense, have been described in DFNMYP syndrome. The c.1240C&#x0003e;T variant has been observed more than once among the Amish.</p>
          <table-wrap id="dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 2. </label>
            <caption>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> Pathogenic Variants Discussed in This <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic></p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.541C&#x0003e;T</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg181Ter</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_3" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_032229.2">NM_032229.2</ext-link>
                    <break/>
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_115605.2">NP_115605.2</ext-link>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.890C&#x0003e;A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ser297Ter</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1240C&#x0003e;T</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_dfn-myop.T.slitrk6_pathogenic_variants_d_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gln414Ter</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK</italic> family of genes encodes six neuronal transmembrane proteins &#x02012; mainly found in neural tissue &#x02012; that modulate neurite outgrowth and synaptic development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.aruga.2003.727">Aruga 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.aruga.2003.117">Aruga &#x00026; Mikoshiba 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.takahashi.2012.389">Takahashi et al 2012</xref>].</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> has an extracellular N-terminal domain that contains two leucine-rich domains highly homologous to SLIT domains; it also has a transmembrane domain and an intracellular C-terminus with two conserved tyrosine phosphorylation sites homologous to receptor sites from the NTRK-neurotrophin family. The expression of <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> in the inner ear promotes innervation and survival of sensory neurons.</p>
          <p>Unlike other members of the <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK</italic> family, which are broadly expressed in developing mouse brain, <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> is differentially expressed in the auditory system during embryonic and postnatal life; expression is strongest in the inner ear, and modest in the thalamus and lateral geniculate nucleus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.beaubien.2009.3285">Beaubien &#x00026; Cloutier 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.katayama.2009.e7786">Katayama et al 2009</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> The reported pathogenic variants (which impair cell surface expression and synapse-inducing activity of SLITRK6) did not trigger nonsense-mediated mRNA decay, produced truncated products, and are predicted to result in loss of function. However, the possibility of a toxic gain-of-function mechanism from misdirection to the intracellular space from loss of an intracellular C-terminal domain cannot be excluded [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.morlet.2014.e95">Morlet et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <sec id="dfn-myop.Cancer_and_Benign_Tumors">
            <title>Cancer and Benign Tumors</title>
            <p>Copy number changes were analyzed from human papillary thyroid cancerous tumors (PTC) using array CGH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="dfn-myop.REF.heiliger.2012.409">Heiliger et al 2012</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">SLITRK6</italic> deletions were detected in 16% of PTC samples compared to normal tissue. Deletions were not detected in PTC samples from a transgenic mouse model for thyroid neoplasia.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="dfn-myop.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.aruga.2003.727">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aruga</surname>
                    <given-names>J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Slitrk6 expression profile in the mouse embryo and its relationship to that of Nlrr3.</article-title>
                <source>Gene Expr Patterns.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>3</volume>
                <fpage>727</fpage>
                <lpage>33</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14643680</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.aruga.2003.117">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aruga</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mikoshiba</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Identification and characterization of Slitrk, a novel neuronal transmembrane protein family controlling neurite outgrowth.</article-title>
                <source>Mol Cell Neurosci.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <fpage>117</fpage>
                <lpage>29</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14550773</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.beaubien.2009.3285">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beaubien</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cloutier</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Differential expression of Slitrk family members in the mouse nervous system.</article-title>
                <source>Dev Dyn.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>238</volume>
                <fpage>3285</fpage>
                <lpage>96</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19924824</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.breneman.2012.5">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Breneman</surname>
                    <given-names>AI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gifford</surname>
                    <given-names>RH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dejong</surname>
                    <given-names>MD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Cochlear implantation in children with auditory neuropathy spectrum disorder: long-term outcomes.</article-title>
                <source>J Am Acad Audiol.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>23</volume>
                <fpage>5</fpage>
                <lpage>17</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22284837</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.heiliger.2012.409">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heiliger</surname>
                    <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hess</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vitagliano</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Salerno</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Braselmann</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Salvatore</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ugolini</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Summerer</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bogdanova</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Unger</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thomas</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santoro</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zitzelsberger</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Novel candidate genes of thyroid tumourigenesis identified in Trk-T1 transgenic mice.</article-title>
                <source>Endocr Relat Cancer.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>409</fpage>
                <lpage>21</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22454401</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.katayama.2009.e7786">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Katayama</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zine</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ota</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Inoue</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fritzsch</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aruga</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Disorganized innervation and neuronal loss in the inner ear of Slitrk6-deficient mice.</article-title>
                <source>PLoS One.</source>
                <year>2009</year>
                <volume>4</volume>
                <fpage>e7786</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936227</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.morlet.2014.e95">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morlet</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rabinowitz</surname>
                    <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Looney</surname>
                    <given-names>LR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Riegner</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Greenwood</surname>
                    <given-names>LA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sherman</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Achilly</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhu</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoo</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>O'Reilly</surname>
                    <given-names>RC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jinks</surname>
                    <given-names>RN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Puffenberger</surname>
                    <given-names>EG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heaps</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morton</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Strauss</surname>
                    <given-names>KA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>A homozygous SLITRK6 nonsense mutation is associated with progressive auditory neuropathy in humans.</article-title>
                <source>Laryngoscope.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>124</volume>
                <fpage>E95</fpage>
                <lpage>103</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23946138</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.takahashi.2012.389">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takahashi</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Katayama</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sohya</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miyamoto</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prasad</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ota</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yasuda</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aruga</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Craig</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Selective control of inhibitory synapse development by Slitrk3-PTP&#x003b4; trans-synaptic interaction.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Neurosci.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>15</volume>
                <fpage>389</fpage>
                <lpage>98</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22286174</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.tekin.2013.2094">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tekin</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chioza</surname>
                    <given-names>BA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Diaz-Horta</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cross</surname>
                    <given-names>HE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Duman</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kokotas</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moore-Barton</surname>
                    <given-names>HL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sakoori</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ota</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Odaka</surname>
                    <given-names>YS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Foster</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                    <suffix>2nd</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cengiz</surname>
                    <given-names>FB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tokgoz-Yilmaz</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tekeli</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grigoriadou</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Petersen</surname>
                    <given-names>MB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sreekantan-Nair</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gurtz</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Xia</surname>
                    <given-names>XJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pandya</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Patton</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Young</surname>
                    <given-names>JI</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aruga</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Crosby</surname>
                    <given-names>AH</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>SLITRK6 mutations cause myopia and deafness in humans and mice.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Invest.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>123</volume>
                <fpage>2094</fpage>
                <lpage>102</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23543054</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Suggested_Reading">
          <title>Suggested Reading</title>
          <ref-list id="dfn-myop.Suggested_Reading.reflist0">
            <ref id="dfn-myop.REF.yuge.2011.544">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yuge</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kataoka</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoshida</surname>
                    <given-names>AC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Itoh</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aggarwal</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mori</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blackshaw</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shimogori</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Region-specific gene expression in early postnatal mouse thalamus.</article-title>
                <source>J Comp Neurol.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>519</volume>
                <fpage>544</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21192083</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="dfn-myop.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>Hussman Institute of Human Genomics: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hihg.med.miami.edu/deafness/">Genetic Studies of Deafness</ext-link></p>
          <p>Division of Clinical and Translation Genetics: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://medgen.med.miami.edu/clinical-and-translational-genetics/deafness-clinic">Deafness Clinic</ext-link></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Acknowledgments">
          <title>Acknowledgments</title>
          <p>This work was supported by an NIH/NIDCD grant R01DC009645 to MT.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="dfn-myop.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>14 September 2017 (sw) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>15 January 2015 (me) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>8 September 2015 (jo) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
