<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="eds3" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">eds3</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome, Hypermobility Type</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: Benign Joint Hypermobility Syndrome, EDS Hypermobility Type, EDS Type III, Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome Type III, Joint Hypermobility Syndrome</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Levy</surname>
            <given-names>Howard P</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Department of Medicine, Division of General Internal Medicine<break/>McKusick-Nathans Institute of Genetic Medicine<break/>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine<break/>Baltimore, Maryland</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2004-10-22" date-type="created">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2016-03-31" date-type="updated">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2010-12-14" date-type="revised">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="eds" document-type="chapter">Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome, Classic Type</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="eds6" document-type="chapter">Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome, Kyphoscoliotic Form</related-object>
      <abstract id="eds3.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), hypermobility type is generally considered the least severe type of EDS, although significant complications, primarily musculoskeletal, can and do occur. The skin is often soft and may be mildly hyperextensible. Subluxations and dislocations are common; they may occur spontaneously or with minimal trauma and can be acutely painful. Degenerative joint disease is common. Chronic pain, distinct from that associated with acute dislocations, is a serious complication of the condition and can be both physically and psychologically disabling. Easy bruising is common. Functional bowel disorders are likely underrecognized. Autonomic dysfunction, such as orthostatic intolerance, may also be seen. Aortic root dilation is typically of a mild degree with no increased risk of dissection in the absence of significant dilation. Psychological dysfunction, psychosocial impairment, and emotional problems are common.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of EDS, hypermobility type is based entirely on clinical evaluation and family history. In EDS, hypermobility type, the gene(s) in which mutation is causative are unknown and unmapped.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Physical therapy tailored to the individual; assistive devices (braces to improve joint stability; wheelchair or scooter to offload stress on lower-extremity joints; suitable mattress to improve sleep quality); pain medication tailored to symptoms; appropriate therapy for gastritis/reflux /delayed gastric emptying/irritable bowel syndrome; psychological and/or pain-oriented counseling.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of primary manifestations:</italic> Low-resistance exercise to increase both core and extremity muscle tone for improved joint stability; appropriate writing utensils to reduce finger and hand strain.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> Calcium, vitamin D, low-impact weight-bearing exercise to maximize bone density.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> DEXA every other year if bone loss is confirmed.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Pregnancy management</italic>: Labor and delivery may progress very rapidly, even in primigravid women. There is no clear advantage to vaginal vs cesarean delivery. Pregnant women with known aortic root dilation should have an echocardiogram in each trimester.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> High-impact activity increases the risk of acute subluxation/dislocation, chronic pain, and osteoarthritis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>EDS, hypermobility type is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Most individuals diagnosed with the syndrome have an affected parent. The proportion of cases caused by a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant is unknown. Each child of an individual with EDS, hypermobility type has a 50% chance of inheriting the disorder. Because the gene(s) and pathogenic variant(s) responsible for EDS, hypermobility type have not been identified, prenatal testing is not possible</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="eds3.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="eds3.Suggestive_findings">
          <title>Suggestive findings</title>
          <p>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), hypermobility type <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with joint laxity with soft skin and easy bruising. Other organ systems (especially gastrointestinal and cardiovascular) are frequently involved. None of these features is specific to EDS.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of EDS, hypermobility type is based entirely on clinical evaluation and family history. The criteria listed below reflect the guidelines proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.beighton.1998.31">Beighton et al [1998]</xref> as modified by the author's experience.</p>
          <sec id="eds3.Major_Diagnostic_Criteria">
            <title>Major Diagnostic Criteria</title>
            <p>The following criteria should all be met to establish a diagnosis of EDS, hypermobility type.</p>
            <p><bold>Joint hypermobility.</bold> One point is scored for each of the following:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Passive dorsiflexion of each fifth finger greater than 90&#x000b0;</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Passive apposition of each thumb to the flexor surface of the forearm</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Hyperextension of each elbow greater than 10&#x000b0;</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Hyperextension of each knee greater than 10&#x000b0;</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Ability to place the palms flat on the floor with the knees fully extended</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>Joint hypermobility is often confirmed by a score of five or more on the nine-point Beighton scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.beighton.1973.413">Beighton et al 1973</xref>], although some individuals with objective joint laxity score fewer than five points. The sensitivity and specificity of examination for joint hypermobility and Beighton scoring depends in part on the individual's age, gender, and medical history as well as the examiner&#x02019;s technique.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Young children (especially age &#x02264;5 years) tend to be very flexible and are therefore difficult to assess.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Women are typically more flexible than men.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Joint flexibility decreases with age, progression of arthritis, and sometimes surgery or trauma. A history of former joint laxity or clinical demonstration of substantial laxity in multiple joints is sometimes accepted in lieu of a positive Beighton score in such cases. This reduces diagnostic specificity, so should be considered only if the family history and other minor criteria are strongly suggestive.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Standardized methods of performing the Beighton tests have not been established. In an effort to maximize specificity, the author&#x02019;s practice is to restrict measurement of fifth finger dorsiflexion to the metacarpophalangeal joint (as opposed to cumulative extension of the metacarpophalangeal plus interphalangeal joints), measure elbow and knee extension with a goniometer, and assure that the knees are fully extended and the palms are completely flat on the floor near the feet for the final point.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Soft skin with normal or only slightly increased extensibility</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Soft skin is subjectively assessed, preferably in an area in which moisturizer has not been applied.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Skin hyperextensibility is assessed at a site lacking excess or loose skin and without evidence of prior trauma by gently pulling until resistance is met. An ideal location is the volar surface of the distal forearm or wrist, where the upper limit of normal extensibility is 1-1.5 cm. Extensor surfaces of joints have excess skin and should not be used.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Absence of fragility or other significant skin or soft-tissue abnormalities.</bold> Findings that suggest a different type of EDS include the following:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Spontaneous or easily induced skin cuts or tears</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Spontaneous or easily induced tears or ruptures of arteries, intestines, uterus or other internal organs</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Surgical complications, such as arterial rupture or sutures tearing through tissues and failing to hold</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Spontaneous wound dehiscence</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Recurrent or incisional hernias</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Significant skin hyperextensibility (&#x0003e;1.5 cm on the volar wrist)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Thin, translucent skin</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Atrophic ("cigarette paper") scars (although mildly atrophic scars may be seen even in normal individuals, especially in areas subject to physical stress, such as extensor surfaces and the abdominal wall)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Molluscoid pseudotumors</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Minor_Diagnostic_Criteria">
            <title>Minor Diagnostic Criteria</title>
            <p>The following criteria are supportive of but not sufficient to establish a diagnosis of EDS, hypermobility type:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Positive family history of EDS, hypermobility type (or family history of joint laxity), without significant skin or soft tissue fragility, in a pattern consistent with autosomal dominant inheritance</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Recurrent dislocation or subluxation of multiple joints</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Chronic joint, limb, and/or back pain</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Easy bruising</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Functional bowel disorders (functional gastritis, irritable bowel syndrome)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Neurally mediated hypotension or postural orthostatic tachycardia</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>High, narrow palate</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Dental crowding</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Testing">
          <title>Testing</title>
          <p>The etiology of EDS, hypermobility type is unknown. Genetic heterogeneity is likely. There are currently no biochemical or genetic tests clinically available to confirm or rule out a diagnosis of EDS, hypermobility type.</p>
          <p>If a patient&#x02019;s personal or family history is suggestive of one of the other types of EDS or another hereditary disorder of connective tissue or arterial fragility syndrome (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="eds3.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>), analysis of an associated gene or multi-gene connective tissue disease panel may be appropriate. Failure to identify a pathogenic variant with such multiple gene testing reduces the likelihood of an arterial fragility syndrome, but does not completely rule it out, especially in the setting of a positive personal or family history of arterial fragility. Negative testing for an arterial fragility syndrome also does not confirm a diagnosis of EDS, hypermobility type. Therefore, such testing is not recommended in the absence of specific suggestive signs, symptoms, or family history.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="eds3.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="eds3.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Note: Clinical distinction between the hypermobility and classic types of EDS is sometimes very difficult. With the exception of skin and soft tissue complications, much of the information in this section is derived from publications that collectively analyzed patients with the hypermobility and classic types, without specifying whether or not there was any difference in manifestations between the two types.</p>
          <p>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), hypermobility type is generally considered the least severe type of EDS, although significant complications, primarily musculoskeletal, do occur. Clinical variability is substantial. Most individuals who seek medical care are female. Pain and major joint complications are much less common among affected males. This bias may result from differences between men and women with respect to pain perception and inherent joint stability, as well as the effects of sex hormones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010b.2406">Castori et al 2010b</xref>].</p>
          <sec id="eds3.Skin">
            <title>Skin</title>
            <p>The skin is often soft and may be mildly hyperextensible.</p>
            <p>Piezogenic papules (small herniations of subcutaneous fat through the underlying dermis of the heel occurring only with weight bearing) are common but rarely painful.</p>
            <p>Keratosis pilaris may be more common than in the general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>].</p>
            <p>Subcutaneous spheroids and molluscoid pseudotumors are not features of this EDS type.</p>
            <p>Clinically significant skin morbidity does not occur; its presence should prompt consideration of alternative diagnoses.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Musculoskeletal">
            <title>Musculoskeletal</title>
            <p><bold>Joint instability.</bold> Joint laxity and instability and excessive joint motion are frequently evident on routine activity, even in the absence of overt subluxation or dislocation.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Subluxations and dislocations are common. They may occur spontaneously or with minimal trauma and can be acutely painful. Reduction often occurs spontaneously or can be accomplished by the affected individual or a bystander. For most affected individuals, medical intervention for an acute dislocation is not usually necessary, but pain can last for hours or days after an event.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>All sites can be involved, including the extremities, vertebral column, costo-vertebral and costo-sternal joints, clavicular articulations, and temporomandibular joints.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Sprains or twisting of the ankles and buckling or &#x0201c;giving out&#x0201d; of the knees are common.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Iliotibial band syndrome or &#x0201c;snapping hip&#x0201d; is a common symptom, often perceived by the affected individual as hip joint instability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.branson.2011.259">Branson et al 2011</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Temporomandibular dysfunction ("TMJ syndrome") is relatively common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.hagberg.2004.178">Hagberg et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.de_coster.2005.298">De Coster et al 2005</xref>], and can be thought of as a specific example of joint degeneration and osteoarthritis.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Females tend to have more substantial laxity than males.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Younger individuals tend to have more substantial laxity than older individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Tendinitis and bursitis may occur [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010b.1339">Rombaut et al 2010b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011b.1106">Rombaut et al 2011b</xref>], especially greater trochanteric bursitis in those with iliotibial band syndrome. EDS does not directly cause inflammation, and these problems are likely secondary to joint instability.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Osteoarthritis.</bold> Degenerative joint disease occurs at a younger age than in the general population, possibly because of chronic joint instability resulting in increased mechanical stress.</p>
            <p><bold>Bone density.</bold> There is very limited and contradictory evidence regarding bone mineral density in EDS, hypermobility type. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.dolan.1998.630">Dolan et al [1998]</xref> found bone density to be reduced by up to 0.9 SD in patients with EDS compared to healthy controls, but that study did not look specifically at patients with the hypermobility type of EDS. Compared to age- and sex-matched controls, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.gulbahar.2006.511">Gulbahar et al [2006]</xref> reported bone density reduction of up to 0.5 SD among premenopausal women with joint hypermobility syndrome (now considered identical to EDS, hypermobility type). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.carbone.2000.388">Carbone et al [2000]</xref> found no difference in bone density between women with EDS, hypermobility type and normal controls after adjusting for height, weight, and physical activity.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Pain">
            <title>Pain</title>
            <p>Chronic pain, distinct from that associated with acute dislocations, is a serious complication of the condition and can be both physically and psychosocially disabling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.sacheti.1997.88">Sacheti et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.hagberg.2004.178">Hagberg et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010a.289">Rombaut et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.voermans.2010a.370">Voermans et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011b.1106">Rombaut et al 2011b</xref>].</p>
            <p>It is variable in age of onset (as early as adolescence or as late as the 5<sup>th</sup>-6th decade), number of sites, duration, quality, severity, and response to therapy.</p>
            <p>Severity is typically greater than expected based on physical and radiologic examinations.</p>
            <p>Severity sometimes correlates with degree of joint instability and with sleep impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.voermans.2010a.370">Voermans et al 2010a</xref>].</p>
            <p>Fatigue and sleep disturbance are frequently associated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010b.1339">Rombaut et al 2010b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.voermans.2010a.370">Voermans et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.voermans.2010b.267">Voermans et al 2010b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011b.1106">Rombaut et al 2011b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2012b.1584">Rombaut et al 2012b</xref>]. Affected individuals are often diagnosed with chronic fatigue syndrome, fibromyalgia, depression, hypochondriasis, and/or malingering prior to recognition of joint laxity and establishment of the correct underlying diagnosis.</p>
            <p>Headaches, especially migraine, are common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010b.1339">Rombaut et al 2010b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011b.1106">Rombaut et al 2011b</xref>]. Cervical muscle tension, temporomandibular dysfunction, and stress are some of the likely contributing factors.</p>
            <p>Several recognizable pain syndromes are likely:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Muscular or myofascial pain,</bold> localized around or between joints, often described as aching, throbbing, or stiff in quality, may be attributable to myofascial spasm, and palpable spasm with tender points (consistent with fibromyalgia) is often demonstrable, especially in the paravertebral musculature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010b.1339">Rombaut et al 2010b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011b.1106">Rombaut et al 2011b</xref>]. Myofascial spasm possibly occurs in response to chronic joint instability, but this has not been systematically studied. Myofascial release often provides temporary relief.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Neuropathic pain,</bold> variably described as electric, burning, shooting, numb, tingling, or hot or cold discomfort, may occur in a radicular or peripheral nerve distribution or may appear to localize to an area surrounding one or more joints [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.camerota.2011.e2">Camerota et al 2011</xref>]. Nerve conduction studies are usually non-diagnostic. Skin biopsy may reveal reduction or absence of small nerve fibers, but may be normal. One hypothesis is that neuropathic pain may result from direct nerve impingement (e.g., by subluxed vertebrae, herniated discs, vertebral osteoarthritis, or peripheral joint subluxations). In addition, there may be mild-to-moderate nerve compression within areas of myofascial spasm. Neither of these possibilities has been evaluated clinically.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Osteoarthritic pain</bold> occurs later in life (but earlier than in the general population) and typically presents as aching pain in the joints, frequently associated with stiffness. It is often exacerbated by stasis and by resistance and/or highly repetitive activity.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Hematologic">
            <title>Hematologic</title>
            <p>Easy bruising is quite common, frequently without obvious trauma or injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.anstey.1991.155">Anstey et al 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.de_paepe.2004.491">De Paepe &#x00026; Malfait 2004</xref>]. Mildly prolonged bleeding, epistaxis, bleeding from the gums (especially after dental extraction) and menometrorrhagia may also occur.</p>
            <p>The underlying cause of the hematologic manifestations is unknown.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Bleeding time may or may not be prolonged, but no consistent abnormalities of coagulation factors, von Willebrand factor or platelet number, release or aggregation have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.anstey.1991.155">Anstey et al 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.mast.2009.230">Mast et al 2009</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Capillary fragility and/or impaired soft tissue integrity may play a role [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.de_paepe.2004.491">De Paepe &#x00026; Malfait 2004</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Gastrointestinal">
            <title>Gastrointestinal</title>
            <p>Functional bowel disorders are common and underrecognized, affecting 33%-67% of individuals with EDS, hypermobility types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.levy.1999.a69">Levy et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>].</p>
            <p>Gastroesophageal reflux and gastritis may be symptomatic despite maximal doses of proton pump inhibitors with additional H2-blockers and acid-neutralizing medications.</p>
            <p>Early satiety and delayed gastric emptying may occur and may be exacerbated by opioid (and other) medications.</p>
            <p>Irritable bowel syndrome may manifest with diarrhea and/or constipation, associated with abdominal cramping and rectal mucus.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Cardiovascular">
            <title>Cardiovascular</title>
            <p><bold>Autonomic dysfunction.</bold> Many affected individuals report atypical chest pain, palpitations at rest or on exertion, and/or orthostatic intolerance with syncope or near syncope [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rowe.1999.494">Rowe et al 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.gazit.2003.33">Gazit et al 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.mathias.2011.22">Mathias et al 2011</xref>]. Holter monitoring usually shows normal sinus rhythm, but sometimes reveals premature atrial complexes or paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia. Tilt table testing may reveal neurally mediated hypotension (NMH) and/or postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS).</p>
            <p><bold>Raynaud syndrome and acrocyanosis</bold> occur at an increased frequency, which may be another manifestation of autonomic dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Aortic root dilation,</bold> usually of a mild degree, occurs in 11%-33% of individuals with EDS, hypermobility type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.wenstrup.2002.112">Wenstrup et al 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.mcdonnell.2006.129">McDonnell et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.atzinger.2011.826">Atzinger et al 2011</xref>]. The severity appears to be much less than occurs in <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="marfan" document-type="chapter">Marfan syndrome</related-object>, and there is no increased risk of aortic dissection in the absence of significant dilation. Dilation onset is in childhood and is usually stable over time. It is unlikely to progress or to develop later in life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.atzinger.2011.826">Atzinger et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Mitral valve prolapse (MVP)</bold> was previously considered a common feature of EDS. Rigorous evaluations using modern diagnostic criteria have been inconsistent, with some studies showing no increase in the frequency of clinically significant MVP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.dolan.1997.459">Dolan et al 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.mcdonnell.2006.129">McDonnell et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.atzinger.2011.826">Atzinger et al 2011</xref>] and others showing an MVP frequency of 28%-67% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.camerota.2014.981">Camerota et al 2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.kozanoglu.2015">Kozanoglu et al 2015</xref>]. It is possible that mild MVP not meeting diagnostic criteria (and therefore not requiring special monitoring or treatment) may also explain some of the atypical chest pain and palpitations.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.OralDental">
            <title>Oral/Dental</title>
            <p>High, narrow palate and dental crowding are nonspecific features of most heritable disorders of connective tissue. Bifid uvula, submucous cleft palate, and overt cleft palate are not manifestations of EDS, hypermobility type, and should prompt consideration of alternative diagnoses (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="eds3.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>).</p>
            <p>Periodontal disease (friability, gingivitis, gum recession) is no longer considered a unique subtype of EDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.beighton.1998.31">Beighton et al 1998</xref>]. The frequency of periodontal manifestations is probably increased but hasn&#x02019;t been adequately studied specifically in the hypermobility type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.hagberg.2004.178">Hagberg et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.de_coster.2005.298">De Coster et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.de_felice.2004.429">De Felice et al [2004]</xref> reported an abnormally complex oral microvascular network in 12 individuals with classic or hypermobility type EDS; potential correlation of this with periodontal disease has not been reported.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.ObstetricGynecologic">
            <title>Obstetric/Gynecologic</title>
            <p>Pregnancy may be complicated by rapid labor and delivery (&#x0003c;4 hours), with small studies suggesting a frequency of 28%-36% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2012.2176">Castori et al 2012</xref>].</p>
            <p>Joint laxity and pain typically increase throughout gestation, especially in the third trimester, as normally occurs during pregnancy in unaffected women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.volkov.2007.51">Volkov et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2012.2176">Castori et al 2012</xref>].</p>
            <p>There is no clear advantage to vaginal vs cesarean delivery. Cesarean delivery may reduce the risk of hip dislocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.volkov.2007.51">Volkov et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.dutta.2011.306413">Dutta et al 2011</xref>], but carries the same risk for surgical complications as in the general population.</p>
            <p>There is no increase in risk for cervical incompetence, and no evidence to support use of prophylactic cerclage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.volkov.2007.51">Volkov et al 2007</xref>].</p>
            <p>No other pregnancy complications are associated with EDS, hypermobility type.</p>
            <p>Pelvic prolapse, dysmenorrhea, and dyspareunia occur at increased frequency in the hypermobility type of EDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.mcintosh.1995.559">McIntosh et al 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2012.2176">Castori et al 2012</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Psychiatric">
            <title>Psychiatric</title>
            <p>Psychological dysfunction, psychosocial impairment, and emotional problems are common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.hagberg.2004.178">Hagberg et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>].</p>
            <p>Specific manifestations may include depression, anxiety, affective disorder, low self-confidence, negative thinking, hopelessness, and desperation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.hagberg.2004.178">Hagberg et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.baezavelasco.2011.1131">Baeza-Velasco et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.branson.2011.259">Branson et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>].</p>
            <p>Fatigue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.voermans.2010b.267">Voermans et al 2010b</xref>] and pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>] exacerbate the psychological dysfunction.</p>
            <p>Psychological distress exacerbates pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.baezavelasco.2011.1131">Baeza-Velasco et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.branson.2011.259">Branson et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            <p>Fear of pain and/or joint instability may lead to avoidance behavior (kinesiophobia) and exacerbate dysfunction and disability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.baezavelasco.2011.1131">Baeza-Velasco et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.branson.2011.259">Branson et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            <p>Affected individuals may feel misunderstood, disbelieved, marginalized, and alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.baezavelasco.2011.1131">Baeza-Velasco et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            <p>Resentment, distrust, and hostility may develop between the affected individual/family and the healthcare team (in both directions), adversely affecting the therapeutic relationship [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.branson.2011.259">Branson et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Ocular">
            <title>Ocular</title>
            <p>Detailed and systematic evaluation of ocular findings in 44 eyes of 22 individuals with EDS, hypermobility type was compared to age- and gender-matched controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.gharbiya.2012.593">Gharbiya et al 2012</xref>]. Findings included the following:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Subjective and objective measures of xerophthalmia were rare, but more common in EDS, hypermobility type than controls. It is unknown whether this represents an intrinsic feature of EDS or possibly an indirect association (e.g., a side effect of medication).</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Clinically insignificant minor lens opacities were found in 13% of EDS eyes, compared to none among controls.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>High myopia (more than -6.0 diopters) and vitreous degeneration were found in 16% of EDS eyes and none of the controls. There was no difference in frequency of mild or moderate myopia between EDS and control eyes.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>There was no significant difference in axial length of the globe between EDS and control eyes.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>EDS eyes averaged slightly increased corneal curvature compared to controls, but there was no overt keratoconus.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Neurologic__Neuromuscular">
            <title>Neurologic &#x00026; Neuromuscular</title>
            <p>Delayed onset and/or resistance to local anesthesia is a frequent complaint [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.hakim.2005.84">Hakim et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>].</p>
            <p>Dysautonomia may manifest as functional bowel disorders, cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction, and/or Raynaud syndrome/acrocyanosis.</p>
            <p>Poor balance is common, with increased incidence of falls and occasionally fear of falling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011c.1432">Rombaut et al 2011c</xref>].</p>
            <p>Diminished joint position sense has been reported at the knees, but not the shoulders. Vibration sensation is normal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010a.289">Rombaut et al 2010a</xref>].</p>
            <p>It is unclear whether or not weakness is an associated feature. Some studies suggest normal muscle strength [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010b.1339">Rombaut et al 2010b</xref>], while others have demonstrated decreased ankle power [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.galli.2011.1663">Galli et al 2011</xref>], reduced passive muscle tension, and increased Achilles tendon compliance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2012a.766">Rombaut et al 2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2012b.1584">Rombaut et al 2012b</xref>]. One study reported lower-extremity weakness, but the findings could also be explained by reduced motor effort secondary to pain and/or fatigue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2012b.1584">Rombaut et al 2012b</xref>].</p>
            <p>Individuals with EDS, hypermobility type tend to have a slower-than-normal gait with shorter gait length [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.cimolin.2011.1722">Cimolin et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.galli.2011.1663">Galli et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011c.1432">Rombaut et al 2011c</xref>].</p>
            <p>Kinematic studies are normal at the hips and knees [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.galli.2011.1663">Galli et al 2011</xref>], but the ankles demonstrate excess plantar flexion at ground contact and decreased dorsiflexion during motion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.cimolin.2011.1722">Cimolin et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.galli.2011.1663">Galli et al 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rigoldi.2012.1437">Rigoldi et al 2012</xref>].</p>
            <p>In a series of 2813 individuals with Chiari malformation type 1, 12.7% were felt to also have a hereditary disorder of connective tissue, including many with EDS, hypermobility type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.milhorat.2007.601">Milhorat et al 2007</xref>]. Among patients with independently confirmed EDS, Chiari malformation was found in only one (4.7%) of 21 patients with the hypermobility type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">Castori et al 2010a</xref>] and one (5.5%) of 18 patients with headache and unspecified types of EDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.jacome.1999.791">Jacome 1999</xref>]. The incidence of Chiari malformation among individuals with EDS has not been systematically studied, and the clinical relevance of this potential association is uncertain.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Disability">
            <title>Disability</title>
            <p>Functional and psychosocial impairment are common, manifesting with decreased sport-related physical activity, diminished health-related quality of life, and significant impact on daily function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010b.1339">Rombaut et al 2010b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.voermans.2010a.370">Voermans et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011b.1106">Rombaut et al 2011b</xref>].</p>
            <p>Pain, fatigue, and sleep disturbance all may contribute to disability and functional impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010b.1339">Rombaut et al 2010b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.voermans.2010a.370">Voermans et al 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">Rombaut et al 2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.voermans.2011.706">Voermans &#x00026; Knoop 2011</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Other">
            <title>Other</title>
            <p><bold>Fragility of soft tissues</bold> with spontaneous ruptures or tears of internal organs is, by definition, not a feature of EDS, hypermobility type. Such manifestations should prompt consideration of other hereditary connective tissue disorders (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="eds3.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>).</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>Penetrance is believed to be 100%, although expressivity is extremely variable, and careful examination may be required to demonstrate typical features, especially in adult men who have never experienced a major joint complication or significant pain.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Anticipation">
          <title>Anticipation</title>
          <p>Anticipation is not believed to occur.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>The 1997 Villefranche conference [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.beighton.1998.31">Beighton et al 1998</xref>] simplified the classification and nomenclature of the Ehlers Danlos syndromes. The former EDS type III was renamed the hypermobility type.</p>
          <p>The "benign familial articular hypermobility syndrome" and &#x0201c;joint hypermobility syndrome&#x0201d; are now generally agreed to be identical to EDS, hypermobility type and no longer thought to represent unique conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.grahame.1999.188">Grahame 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.tinkle.2009.2368">Tinkle et al 2009</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>The prevalence of EDS, hypermobility type is unknown, with estimates ranging between 1:5,000 and 1:20,000. Given the clinical variability and low probability of affected males being ascertained, the prevalence is likely much higher than estimated. EDS, hypermobility type may be the most common heritable disorder of connective tissue.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="eds3.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p>All types of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS) share some degree of joint laxity and skin/soft tissue manifestations.</p>
        <p>The other forms of EDS are distinguished by additional connective tissue manifestations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.beighton.1998.31">Beighton et al 1998</xref>]:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="eds" document-type="chapter"><bold>EDS, classic type</bold></related-object> includes skin and soft tissue fragility. Mild presentations of the classic type may be mistaken for the hypermobility type, including similar degrees of joint laxity, pain, pelvic prolapse, dyspareunia, and manifestations in the hematologic, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, and dental systems. The diagnosis is sometimes revised from hypermobility to classic when the individual or a family member later develops more significant skin and soft tissue manifestations. Among individuals with all of the skin features of classic EDS, including dystrophic scarring, more than 90% have an identifiable pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">COL5A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL5A2</italic>, the two genes encoding type V collagen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.symoens.2012.1485">Symoens et al 2012</xref>]. In individuals with milder skin manifestations (but still more than typically seen in the hypermobility type), no consistent pathogenic variants in any genes have been found. The diagnosis is usually established on clinical grounds. Demonstration of a pathogenic variant confirms the diagnosis, although failure to identify a pathogenic variant does not rule it out. EDS, classic type is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>In <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="eds4" document-type="chapter"><bold>EDS, vascular type</bold></related-object>
<bold>(vEDS),</bold> the joint laxity is predominantly in small joints, as opposed to the generalized laxity typically observed in the hypermobility type. The vascular type also usually manifests thin, translucent skin, fragility of skin and soft tissue, and atrophic scarring. Predisposition to spontaneous rupture of hollow organs (primarily arteries, intestines, and uterus) is a hallmark of the vascular type, but not all patients with the vascular type develop such complications. A family history of unexplained sudden death is potentially consistent with catastrophic internal organ rupture and could be sufficient to prompt diagnostic testing for the vascular type, especially if the event(s) occurred in a first-degree relative, multiple second-degree relatives, and/or at a young age (e.g., &#x0003c;50 years). Nonspecific venous and hematologic abnormalities including varicose veins, hemorrhoids, easy bruising, and bleeding diathesis are not suggestive of vEDS, and should not prompt additional evaluation for this type. Dysfunction and/or deficiency of type III collagen, caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">COL3A1</italic>, is responsible for all cases of vEDS. The diagnosis of vEDS is based on clinical findings and usually confirmed by molecular genetic testing, although biochemical (protein-based) testing can also be used to demonstrate a structural or quantitative abnormality in type III collagen. vEDS is almost always inherited in an autosomal dominant manner but rare examples of biallelic inheritance have been reported.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="eds6" document-type="chapter"><bold>EDS, kyphoscoliotic form</bold></related-object> and <bold>dermatosparaxis</bold> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/225410">OMIM</ext-link>) are autosomal recessive, rare, and distinguished by more severe skin manifestations and other features. EDS, kyphoscoliotic form is caused by deficient activity of the enzyme procollagen-lysine, 2-oxoglutarate 5-dioxygenase 1 <italic toggle="yes">(PLOD1</italic>: lysyl hydroxylase 1); the diagnosis can be established by demonstration of an increased ratio of deoxypyridinoline to pyridinoline crosslinks in urine measured by HPLC, assay of lysyl hydroxylase enzyme activity in skin fibroblasts, or molecular genetic testing of <italic toggle="yes">PLOD1</italic>.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>EDS, arthrochalasia type</bold> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/130060">OMIM</ext-link>) is autosomal dominant, rare, and distinguished by congenital hip dislocation and more severe skin manifestations. Pathogenic variants occur in exon 6 of <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>, causing impaired cleavage of the amino terminal propeptide of the corresponding type 1 procollagen molecules.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Tenascin-X deficiency</bold> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/606408">OMIM</ext-link>) resulting from compound heterozygous or homozygous <italic toggle="yes">TNXB</italic> mutation/deletion has been reported in individuals with an autosomal recessive form of EDS manifesting joint laxity, hyperextensible skin, and easy bruising with normal wound healing and absence of atrophic scarring. Some, but not all, also have <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="cah" document-type="chapter">congenital adrenal hyperplasia</related-object> as a result of contiguous gene deletion involving <italic toggle="yes">CYP21A2</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.bristow.2005.24">Bristow et al 2005</xref>]. Heterozygous mutation of <italic toggle="yes">TNXB</italic> has been reported in a small subset of individuals with joint laxity and soft skin typical of EDS, hypermobility type, but skin hyperextensibility, easy bruising and other hematologic manifestations are not part of this phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.zweers.2003.214">Zweers et al 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.zweers.2005.330">Zweers et al 2005</xref>]. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">TNXB</italic> could be considered in persons with joint laxity in the absence of easy bruising or skin hyperextensibility.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>Joint laxity</bold> is a nonspecific manifestation of dozens of other disorders and syndromes. Functionally, joint hypermobility may be the result of ligamentous laxity (as in the heritable disorders of connective tissue and skeletal dysplasias) or hypotonia (as in mitochondrial diseases and other neuromuscular conditions). It can be difficult to distinguish between these mechanisms of pathology, especially in adults.</p>
        <p>Most of the following disorders are easily distinguished from EDS by characteristic features and/or involvement of systems other than the joints and skin, but mild presentations can sometimes be misdiagnosed as EDS, hypermobility type.</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="marfan" document-type="chapter"><bold>Marfan syndrome</bold></related-object> results in additional skeletal, ocular, cardiovascular, pulmonary, and skin/integument manifestations beyond those seen in EDS. Specific clinical criteria are available to establish a diagnosis of Marfan syndrome, and it can be confirmed by demonstration of a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">FBN1</italic>. Joint hypermobility is common in the <bold>MASS phenotype</bold> (myopia, mitral valve prolapse, mild aortic root dilatation, striae, and minor skeletal manifestations of Marfan syndrome; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/604308">OMIM</ext-link>), also caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">FBN1</italic>. Sometimes individuals with hypermobility EDS can have a Marfanoid build and as such resemble individuals with Marfan syndrome or a Marfan-related disorder. However, application of the clinical diagnostic criteria for Marfan syndrome and <italic toggle="yes">FBN1</italic> molecular analysis allow differentiation of these conditions. Marfan syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="loeys-dietz" document-type="chapter"><bold>Loeys-Dietz syndrome</bold></related-object>
<bold>(LDS)</bold> is characterized by vascular findings (cerebral, thoracic, and abdominal arterial aneurysms and/or dissections) and skeletal manifestations (pectus excavatum or pectus carinatum, scoliosis, joint laxity, arachnodactyly, talipes equinovarus). Approximately 75% of affected individuals have LDS type I with craniofacial manifestations (widely spaced eyes, bifid uvula/cleft palate, craniosynostosis); approximately 25% have LDS type II with systemic manifestations of LDSI but minimal or absent craniofacial features. LDSI and LDSII form a clinical continuum. The presentation often mimics Marfan syndrome or EDS, vascular type, but prior to detection of the arterial abnormalities, individuals may be misdiagnosed with classic or hypermobility type EDS. The diagnosis is established by detection of a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">TGFBR1</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">TGFBR2</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SMAD3</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">TGFB2</italic>. LDS is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="arterial-t" document-type="chapter"><bold>Arterial tortuosity syndrome</bold></related-object>
<bold>(ATS),</bold> in addition to aneurysm, dissection, tortuosity, and stenosis of larger and medium-sized arteries, manifests craniofacial and skeletal features similar to Loeys-Dietz syndrome. In contrast to dominantly inherited connective tissue disorders predisposing to arterial fragility (vascular EDS, Marfan syndrome, and LDS), ATS is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. A diagnosis of ATS is confirmed by identifying biallelic (homozygous or compound heterozygous) pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC2A10</italic> in an individual with generalized arterial tortuosity and other typical features.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="sgs" document-type="chapter"><bold>Shprintzen-Goldberg syndrome</bold></related-object>
<bold>(SGS)</bold> is distinguished by cardinal features of craniosynostosis and mild-to-moderate intellectual disability. Cerebral abnormalities may include hydrocephalus, dilatation of the lateral ventricles, and Chiari 1 malformation. Aortic root dilation may occur, but less commonly than in Marfan syndrome or LDS. Some additional characteristic findings include C1/C2 spine malformation, reduced subcutaneous fat, abdominal wall defects, and cryptorchidism in males. SGS is confirmed in individuals with typical findings by identifying a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">SKI</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">SKI</italic>-related SGS is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="stickler" document-type="chapter"><bold>Stickler syndrome</bold></related-object><bold>.</bold> Distinguishing features include sensorineural hearing loss, vitreoretinal abnormalities, and cleft palate. Six genes have been associated with Stickler syndrome. However, a few families with features of Stickler syndrome are not linked to any of these loci; thus, pathogenic variants in other genes may also cause the disorder. Stickler syndrome is diagnosed based on clinical features. In many affected individuals and families the diagnosis can be confirmed by molecular genetic testing, although a negative test does not rule out the diagnosis. Stickler syndrome caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">COL2A1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL11A1</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">COL11A2</italic> is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner; Stickler syndrome caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">COL9A1</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">COL9A2</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">COL9A3</italic> is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="williams" document-type="chapter"><bold>Williams syndrome</bold></related-object>
<bold>(WS)</bold> is a contiguous gene deletion syndrome characterized by cardiovascular disease (elastin arteriopathy, peripheral pulmonary stenosis, supravalvular aortic stenosis, hypertension), distinctive facies, connective tissue abnormalities, intellectual disability (usually mild), a specific cognitive profile, unique personality characteristics, growth abnormalities, and endocrine abnormalities (hypercalcemia, hypercalciuria, hypothyroidism, and early puberty). The mainstay for diagnosis is detection of the contiguous gene deletion of the Williams-Beuren syndrome critical region (WBSCR) that encompasses the elastin gene (<italic toggle="yes">ELN</italic>). More than 99% of individuals with the clinical diagnosis of WS have this contiguous gene deletion, which can be detected using fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) or deletion/duplication analysis. Supravalvular aortic stenosis (SVAS) is caused by mutation (rather than deletion) of <italic toggle="yes">ELN</italic>. Individuals with either deletion or mutation of <italic toggle="yes">ELN</italic> have joint laxity, but the classic elastin arteriopathy is not seen in any type of EDS. WS is transmitted in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Aarskog-Scott syndrome (faciogenital dysplasia)</bold> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/305400">OMIM</ext-link>) is an X-linked condition resulting from mutation of <italic toggle="yes">FGD1</italic>. The most significant distinguishing feature is shawl scrotum, which may become less obvious in adulthood. Widow's peak, short upturned nose, other dysmorphic features, and the inheritance pattern can be additional diagnostic clues. Intellectual disability, which is not associated with any of the types of EDS, is sometimes present.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fragilex" document-type="chapter"><bold>Fragile X syndrome</bold></related-object> is not typically confused with EDS, hypermobility type. When a full pathogenic variant of <italic toggle="yes">FMR1</italic> is present, fragile X syndrome is characterized by moderate intellectual disability in affected males and mild intellectual disability in affected females. Males may have a characteristic appearance (large head, long face, prominent forehead and chin, protruding ears), joint laxity, and large testes (post-puberty). However, premutation carriers may have joint laxity and EDS-like skin findings without other major manifestations. Family history of intellectual disability, premature ovarian failure, and/or fragile X tremor/ataxia syndrome is helpful when present. The frequency of <italic toggle="yes">FMR1</italic> premutation among individuals diagnosed clinically with EDS, hypermobility type has not been studied, but fragile X syndrome has not been reported among offspring of women with EDS, hypermobility type. Fragile X syndrome is inherited in an X-linked manner.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="achondroplasia" document-type="chapter"><bold>Achondroplasia</bold></related-object> and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hypochondroplasia" document-type="chapter"><bold>hypochondroplasia</bold></related-object> are distinguished by short stature with characteristic skeletal features (marked in achondroplasia, milder in hypochondroplasia). Achondroplasia can be diagnosed by characteristic clinical and radiographic findings in most affected individuals. Molecular genetic testing reveals a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">FGFR3</italic> in 99% of individuals with achondroplasia and about 70% of individuals with hypochondroplasia. However, it is clear that locus heterogeneity exists for hypochondroplasia because pathogenic variants in other as-yet unidentified genes can result in similar, if not identical, phenotypes. Achondroplasia and hypochondroplasia are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="oi" document-type="chapter"><bold>Osteogenesis imperfecta</bold></related-object>
<bold>(OI)</bold> is distinguished by the presence of fractures and, in some cases, dentinogenesis imperfecta (grey or brown teeth). Biochemical testing (i.e., analysis of the structure and quantity of type I collagen synthesized in vitro by cultured dermal fibroblasts) detects abnormalities in 98% of individuals with OI type II, about 90% with OI type I, about 84% with OI type III, and about 84% with OI type IV. About 90% of individuals with OI types I, II, III, and IV (but none with OI types V, VI, and VII) have an identifiable pathogenic variant in either <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">COL1A2</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">COL1A1/COL1A2</italic>-related OI is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mt-overview" document-type="chapter"><bold>Mitochondrial myopathies</bold></related-object> may cause joint hypermobility as a result of hypotonia, rather than the ligamentous laxity assumed to be the underlying mechanism in hereditary disorders of connective tissue. It can be difficult to distinguish between ligamentous laxity and hypotonia on physical exam, especially in adolescents and adults. Other features of mitochondrial disease that overlap with those seen in EDS, hypermobility type include headache, neuropathy, myopathy, and autonomic dysfunction. Gastrointestinal dysmotility may also occur in mitochondrial disorders, especially <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mngie" document-type="chapter"><bold>Mitochondrial neurogastrointestinal encephalopathy disease</bold></related-object>.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Many other <bold>neuromuscular disorders</bold> can also cause hypotonia, neuropathy, autonomic dysfunction, functional gastrointenstinal abnormalities, and other features overlapping with EDS, hypermobility type. Since there are currently no laboratory tests available to definitively confirm or rule out EDS, hypermobility type, it is important to thoroughly consider the possibility of a mitochondrial or other neuromuscular disorder in the differential diagnosis.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Aneuploidies,</bold> including <bold>Down</bold>, <bold>Turner</bold>, and <bold>Klinefelter syndromes,</bold> are usually easily recognized based on dysmorphic features and/or intellectual disability. Small duplications or deletions may be less clinically obvious, but could be suggested by reduced fertility or recurrent pregnancy loss.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>Chronic pain</bold> and <bold>fatigue</bold> are common in the general population, and the differential diagnosis of those symptoms is very long. Some conditions that may overlap with or complicate EDS, hypermobility type:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>A subset of individuals with <bold>fibromyalgia</bold> and/or <bold>chronic fatigue syndrome</bold> may have EDS as the underlying etiology, but not all patients with chronic pain and/or fatigue have EDS.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="celiac" document-type="chapter"><bold>Celiac disease</bold></related-object> may coexist with EDS or be misdiagnosed as EDS. Common features may include pain, fatigue, functional gastrointestinal disorders, and cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Vitamin D deficiency</bold> may also cause or exacerbate pain and fatigue.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fmf" document-type="chapter"><bold>Familial Mediterranean fever</bold></related-object>
<bold>(FMF)</bold> most classically presents with episodic abdominal pain associated with fever, but low-grade fever may not be detected and the manifestations could be confused with irritable bowel syndrome. Joint pain may also occur in FMF.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>Clinically, the <bold>hematologic manifestations</bold> of EDS mimic <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="von-willebrand" document-type="chapter"><bold>von Willebrand disease</bold></related-object> and respond to similar treatments, but von Willebrand factor and platelet number are almost always normal. Easy bruising and prolonged bleeding alone are insufficient to establish a diagnosis of EDS, and the diagnostic evaluation of such problems should also consider von Willebrand disease, idiopathic thrombocytopenia purpura, and other hemorrhagic conditions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="eds3.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="eds3.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diagn">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), hypermobility type, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Thorough history and physical examination, especially for musculoskeletal, skin, cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, and oral/dental manifestations</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of prior experience with mechanical, pharmacologic, and/or surgical treatment of pain and joint instability, as well as current degree of pain and disability</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Baseline echocardiogram to evaluate aortic root diameter, as adjusted for age and body surface area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.campens.2014.914">Campens et al 2014</xref>]. <bold>Significant aortic enlargement and/or other cardiac abnormalities should prompt consideration of alternative diagnoses</bold>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>The following evaluations should not be routine, but may be appropriate in some situations:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>For individuals with significant orthostatic intolerance and/or tachycardia, consider tilt-table testing to help confirm postural orthostatic tachycardia and/or neurally mediated hypotension. However, treatment of the symptoms may not differ based on the outcome, so tilt-table testing is optional. It is also sometimes appropriate to rule out adrenocortical insufficiency.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If irritable bowel syndrome is suspected, consider formal gastroenterology consultation and possible endoscopy to rule out other treatable diagnoses. <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="celiac" document-type="chapter">Celiac disease</related-object>, inflammatory bowel disease, and other causes of malabsorption or bowel dysfunction are not associated with EDS, but may be coexisting diagnoses.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) is appropriate at any age if height loss greater than one inch is documented or x-rays are suggestive of osteopenia. Screening DEXA in those without suggestive signs or symptoms is not currently recommended.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a history of severe or prolonged bleeding is present, consider hematologic evaluation for <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="von-willebrand" document-type="chapter">von Willebrand disease</related-object>, thrombocytopenia, or other bleeding diathesis. Although pathophysiologically unrelated, these conditions may coexist with hypermobility type EDS and exacerbate the hematologic manifestations.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>For individuals with significant pain and/or fatigue, screen for and correction of other potential causes, including (but not limited to) vitamin D deficiency, vitamin B<sub>12</sub> deficiency, folate deficiency, iron deficiency, celiac disease, or hypothyroidism.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When needed, the pain management recommendations <xref ref-type="sec" rid="eds3.Treatment_of_Manifestations">below</xref> can be implemented by any member of the care team who feels confident enough to do so, or evaluation by a pain management specialist could be considered.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If there is suspicion of Chiari malformation, consider cerebral MRI, possibly with CSF flow studies.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Clinical genetics consultation is appropriate if there is uncertainty about the diagnosis or for assistance in evaluation and management.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <sec id="eds3.Physical_Therapy">
            <title>Physical Therapy</title>
            <p>Myofascial release (any physical therapy modality that reduces spasm) provides short-term relief of pain, lasting hours to days. While the duration of benefit is short and it must be repeated frequently, this pain relief may be critical to facilitate participation in toning exercise for stabilization of the joints. Modalities must be tailored to the individual; a partial list includes heat, cold, massage, ultrasound, electrical stimulation, acupuncture, acupressure, biofeedback, and conscious relaxation.</p>
            <p>Low-resistance muscle toning exercise can improve joint stability and reduce future subluxations, dislocations, and pain. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="eds3.Prevention_of_Primary_Manifestation">Prevention of Primary Manifestations</xref>.</p>
            <p>Transvaginal pelvic physical therapy and myofascial release (in which massage or ultrasound is applied to the pelvic musculature via a transvaginal approach) may improve dyspareunia, abdominal pain, back pain, and sometimes radicular lower-extremity pain.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Assistive_Devices">
            <title>Assistive Devices</title>
            <p>Braces are useful to improve joint stability. Orthopedists, rheumatologists, and physical therapists can assist in recommending appropriate devices for commonly problematic joints such as knees and ankles. Shoulders and hips present more of a challenge for external bracing. Occupational therapists may be consulted for ring splints (to stabilize interphalangeal joints) and wrist or wrist/thumb braces in affected individuals with small joint instability. A soft neck collar, if tolerated, may help with neck pain and headaches.</p>
            <p>A wheelchair or scooter may be necessary to offload stress on lower-extremity joints. Special wheelchair customizations such as lightweight and/or motorized chairs, seat pads, and specialized wheels and wheel grasps may be necessary to accommodate pelvic and upper-extremity issues.</p>
            <p>A waterbed, adjustable air mattress, or viscoelastic foam mattress (and/or pillow) may provide increased support with improved sleep quality and less pain.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Pain_Medication">
            <title>Pain Medication</title>
            <p>Pain medication is frequently underprescribed, and should be tailored to the individual's subjective symptoms and objective measures of pain, not to physical examination or radiologic findings. Individuals with mild to moderate pain may get sufficient relief from as-needed use. Those with more significant pain typically require higher doses and combinations of multiple medications. Prevention or control of pain with regularly scheduled dosing is often more successful than acute treatment with as-needed dosing. Many clinicians recruit a pain management specialist, but pain can be managed by the primary physician if desired.</p>
            <p>Note: All of the following dose recommendations are for adults without hepatic or renal disease; adjustments may be necessary for other populations.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>Acetaminophen, 4000 mg daily in three or four divided doses, will not completely alleviate pain but is a useful and well-tolerated adjunct in combination with other agents. Acetaminophen is often present in combination with other analgesic medications and cold/flu preparations, and careful attention should be paid to the total daily dose to avoid exceeding 4000 mg/day.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>NSAIDs (nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs) (e.g., ibuprofen, naproxen, meloxicam, nabumetone) should be titrated to the maximum dose or as tolerated by upper gastrointestinal symptoms. NSAIDs are particularly useful for arthralgia, myalgia, and secondary inflammatory conditions (e.g. bursitis, tendinitis, costochodritis, or post-dislocation pain). Bruising is not a contraindication to NSAID therapy, but occasionally requires dose reduction or change to a Cox-2 inhibitor.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Cox-2 inhibitors (e.g., celecoxib) in maximal doses are no stronger than dose-equivalent NSAIDS, but may be better tolerated and thus more effective.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Topical lidocaine as a cream or patch is sometimes useful for localized areas of pain. Topical capsaicin is of questionable utility, but is safe.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Skeletal muscle relaxants are useful in combination with all of the above to treat myofascial spasm. They are also sometimes helpful in treating neuropathic pain. Metaxalone may be the least sedating, but all are potentially limited by sedation. There is theoretic risk that skeletal muscle relaxants can increase joint instability by reducing muscle tone. This is not a contraindication to their use, but does justify monitoring for potential complications.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Magnesium, either topically as Epsom salt baths or orally in any form, may also reduce muscle spasm and pain. No specific formulation or dosage has been established as superior to any other. The most common adverse effects &#x02013; sedation, nausea, abdominal pain, and diarrhea &#x02013; are more likely to occur with oral rather than topical supplementation.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Tricyclic antidepressants are often effective for neuropathic pain, with additional benefits of mild sedation (for those with sleep disturbance) and a little mood elevation. Constipation, a common side effect, can be managed with fluids, fiber, stool softeners, and laxatives. For those with diarrhea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome, the constipating effect may be therapeutic. Typical doses are nortriptyline (25-150 mg) or trazadone (50-300 mg) every evening.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Serotonin/norepinephrine receptor inhibitors (SNRIs), such as venlafaxine, desvenlafaxine, duloxetine, and milnacipran also offer combined benefit for depression and neuropathic pain. Venlaxafine may raise the blood pressure a few points, which potentially could be helpful for individuals with neurally mediated hypotension.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Some anti-seizure medications are also effective for neuropathic pain and can be used in addition to tricyclic and/or SNRI antidepressants. All require gradual titration before reaching therapeutic levels. Gabapentin should be titrated as tolerated up to at least 1200 mg/3x/day before declaring failure, but is often limited by sedation and/or gastrointestinal side effects. Pregabalin can be dosed twice or three times daily up to a total daily dose of at least 300 mg, and tends to be better tolerated than gabapentin. Topiramate and lamotrigine have also been used successfully.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Short courses of steroids can be very effective for controlling acute flares of pain associated with secondary inflammation. EDS is not an intrinsically inflammatory condition, and there is no role for chronic steroid use.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Glucosamine and chondroitin may help to prevent or treat osteoarthritis in the general population. They have not been studied specifically in EDS, but are not contraindicated.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Cannabinoids such as dronabinol and (where legal) marijuana may be helpful for several different types of pain. Their benefits should be weighed against the potential for dependency and/or psychoactive effects.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Tramadol can be added to acetaminophen plus an NSAID or Cox-2 inhibitor before resorting to opioids. Nausea is the most common side effect.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Opioids are effective for both myofascial pain and neuropathic pain, but should be reserved for use after failing the above medications. They should be administered in conjunction with all of the above, except tramadol, in order to minimize total opioid requirements. Since they are typically used chronically (or at least several months), the primary formulation should be long acting (e.g., sustained-release oxycodone or morphine or topical fentanyl patch) with short-acting forms of the same drug used as needed for breakthrough pain. Routine use of two or more daily doses of a short-acting form should prompt an increase in the long-acting dose or another adjustment to the pain regimen.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Benzodiazepines may offer some short-term reduction in muscle spasm, but are poor choices for long-term muscle relaxation and carry high risk of tolerance, dependency, and addiction. Routine use of benzodiazepines is not recommended.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p>
              <bold>Medication precautions</bold>
            </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>It is critically important to evaluate all potential sources of acetaminophen and assure that total daily use does not exceed 4000 mg.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Abrupt cessation of anti-seizure medications can precipitate a seizure. When discontinuing, they should be tapered gradually.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Chronic opioid use can result in tolerance and dependency with escalating dose requirements and diminishing effect. Narcotic bowel syndrome can also develop, and may be confused with irritable bowel syndrome.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>Serotonin syndrome can occur when combining multiple serotonergic medications, such as tramadol, tricyclic antidepressants, SNRI antidepressants, anti-seizure medications, and opiods. Symptoms and signs may include agitation, restlessness, tremor, hyperreflexia, ataxia, confusion, irritability, nausea, diarrhea, hyperthermia, tachycardia, hyper/hypotension, and/or diaphoresis. Severity can range from mild to life threatening. Many of these manifestations overlap those associated with EDS, making diagnosis difficult. Some individuals find mild-to-moderate serotonergic symptoms acceptable in order to achieve adequate pain control.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Surgery_and_Other_Procedures">
            <title>Surgery and Other Procedures</title>
            <p>Many individuals will have undergone several orthopedic procedures prior to diagnosis. These often include joint debridement, tendon relocations, capsulorraphy, and arthroplasty. The degree of stabilization and pain reduction, overall patient satisfaction, and duration of improvement are variable, but usually less than in individuals without EDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.aldridge.2003.e41">Aldridge et al 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rose.2004.190">Rose et al 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011b.1106">Rombaut et al 2011b</xref>]. In general, orthopedic surgery should be delayed in favor of physical therapy and bracing. When surgery is performed, the affected individual and physician should cautiously anticipate some improvement but expect less than optimal results. There is one report of long-term improvement in shoulder stability with Achilles tendon allograft reconstruction of the joint capsule in an individual with EDS, hypermobility type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.chaudhury.2012.e1">Chaudhury et al 2012</xref>]. It is not yet known if this approach will be successful in other affected individuals. Unlike the classic and vascular types of EDS, the hypermobility type is not associated with increased risk for perioperative skin and soft tissue complications.</p>
            <p>Prolotherapy, in which saline and/or other irritants are injected in tendons or around joints to induce scar formation and increase stability, has not been objectively studied. It is probably safe and probably subject to the same limitations as orthopedic surgery.</p>
            <p>Anesthetic/corticosteroid injections for localized areas of pain and acute inflammation are often helpful, but cannot be repeated indefinitely. "Dry needling" without injection of any material sometimes provides similar benefit.</p>
            <p>Anesthetic nerve blocks can provide temporary relief of neuropathic pain. These are sometimes followed by surgical nerve root destruction and/or implantable stimulators (sensory or motor), with variable results.</p>
            <p>Constant intrathecal delivery of anesthetic and/or opioid medication may reduce the need for oral/systemic medications, but should only be considered as a last resort.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Bone_Density">
            <title>Bone Density</title>
            <p>Therapy is the same as for any other individual with low bone density, including supplementation of calcium and vitamin D. Simple weight-bearing exercise, such as walking or use of an elliptical trainer, should not be overlooked as a means to help maintain bone density as well as improve resting muscle tone.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Hematologic_1">
            <title>Hematologic</title>
            <p>Easy and spontaneous bruising does not require treatment, and does not require avoidance of NSAIDs.</p>
            <p>For severe bleeding (e.g., epistaxis, menometrorrhagia) or operative prophylaxis, desmopressin acetate (ddAVP) is often beneficial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.stine.1997.156">Stine &#x00026; Becton 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.mast.2009.230">Mast et al 2009</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Gastrointestinal_1">
            <title>Gastrointestinal</title>
            <p>Gastritis and reflux symptoms may require intensive therapy, including proton pump inhibitor twice daily before meals, high-dose H2-blocker at bedtime (e.g., famotidine 20-40 mg or ranitidine 150-300 mg), sucralfate one gram four times daily, and over-the-counter acid-neutralizing agents. Other treatable causes, such as <italic toggle="yes">H. pylori</italic> infection, should be investigated. Upper endoscopy is indicated for resistant symptoms, but frequently is normal other than chronic gastritis.</p>
            <p>Delayed gastric emptying should be identified if present and treated the same way as in patients without EDS. Assistance from a gastroenterologist experienced in managing GI dysmotility can be helpful.</p>
            <p>Irritable bowel syndrome is treated as usual with dietary modification, fiber, antispasmodics, antidiarrheals, and laxatives as needed. Lubiprostone is a motility enhancer that may be helpful for those with constipation only. Tricyclic antidepressants may be helpful for persons with both neuropathic pain and diarrhea.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Cardiovascular_1">
            <title>Cardiovascular</title>
            <p>Beta-blockade is rarely necessary, but should be considered for progressive aortic enlargement. Rarely, severe enlargement (&#x0003e;4.5-5.0 cm) requires surgical evaluation. When such severe enlargement is noted, other hereditary disorders of connective tissue should be considered (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="eds3.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>).</p>
            <p>Neurally mediated hypotension and postural orthostatic tachycardia are treated as usual, with avoidance of sudden postural change, consideration of lower-extremity and/or abdominal compression garments, exercise to increase muscle tone, supplementation of sodium and water to expand the blood volume, and sometimes pharmacologic treatment with beta-blockers, midodrine, fludrocortisone, and/or other medications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.mathias.2011.22">Mathias et al 2011</xref>]. Commercially available electrolyte tablets can be added to water to facilitate oral expansion of blood volume.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Dental">
            <title>Dental</title>
            <p>Orthodontic and palatal corrections may tend to relapse, requiring prolonged use of a retainer.</p>
            <p>Periodontal disease should be identified and treated.</p>
            <p>Temporomandibular joint laxity and dysfunction are difficult to treat. There are no specific interventions of proven benefit. Intra-oral devices are sometimes helpful. Oral rest (minimization of chewing and talking), local myofascial release, and muscle relaxant medications may be beneficial for acute flares. Surgical intervention is often disappointing and should be considered only as a last resort.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="eds3.Psychiatric_1">
            <title>Psychiatric</title>
            <p>Validation of the affected individual's symptoms can be immensely helpful, as many with EDS, hypermobility type have been accused of malingering or diagnosed with primary psychiatric disorders by previous physicians.</p>
            <p>Establishing trust, rapport, and a supportive relationship between patient and provider is important. Emphasis should be placed on chronic, rather than acute, pain management. Distraction and hypnosis are often helpful [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.branson.2011.259">Branson et al 2011</xref>].</p>
            <p>Depression is a common result of the chronic pain, disability, and other complications. Psychological and/or pain-oriented counseling can improve adaptation to and acceptance of these issues and the necessary physical limitations. Cognitive behavioral therapy can be particularly beneficial, but requires active patient participation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.baezavelasco.2011.1131">Baeza-Velasco et al 2011</xref>]. Antidepressants are also of great benefit. Many individuals initially resist a diagnosis of or therapy for depression because of concern that their problems are being written off as purely psychiatric.</p>
            <p>Consumer support groups are available and can be very beneficial.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Prevention_of_Primary_Manifestation">
          <title>Prevention of Primary Manifestations</title>
          <p>Improved joint stability may be achieved by low-resistance exercise to increase muscle <bold>tone</bold> (subconscious resting muscle contraction), as opposed to muscle <bold>strength</bold> (voluntary force exerted at will). Emphasis should be placed on both core and extremity muscle tone. Examples include walking, bicycling, low-impact aerobics, swimming or water exercise, and simple range-of-motion exercise without added resistance. Core toning activities, such as balance exercises and repetitive motions focusing on the abdominal, lumbar, and interscapular muscles, are also important. Progress should be made by gradually increasing repetitions, frequency, or duration, not resistance. It often takes months or years for significant progress to be recognized.</p>
          <p>Wide-grip writing utensils can reduce strain on finger and hand joints. An unconventional grasp of a writing utensil, gently resting the shaft in the web between the thumb and index finger and securing the tip between the distal interphalangeal joints or middle phalanges of the index and third fingers (rather than using the tips of the fingers), results in substantially reduced axial stress to the interphalangeal, metacarpophalangeal, and carpometacarpal joints. These adjustments frequently result in marked reduction of pain in the index finger and at the base of the thumb.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complicatio">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Calcium (500-600 mg/2x/day), vitamin D (400 or more units daily), and low-impact weight bearing exercise should be encouraged to maximize bone density.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>DEXA should be repeated approximately every other year if bone loss is confirmed. Otherwise, routine population surveillance of bone density is all that is necessary.</p>
          <p>Annual echocardiography is not necessary in those with a normal initial echocardiogram [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.atzinger.2011.826">Atzinger et al 2011</xref>]. In children and adolescents with a normal aortic root diameter, it is the author's practice to repeat every two to three years until young adulthood (age ~25 years). If the aortic root diameter is increased or accelerating faster than body surface area, more frequent monitoring is appropriate. In adults with a normal aortic root diameter, no further monitoring is needed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Joint hyperextension may <bold>not</bold> need to be avoided. In a randomized controlled trial of physical therapy among 26 children and adolescents with joint hypermobility and knee pain, those allowed to exercise into hyperextension had similar improvement in pain score and better improvement in psychosocial score compared to those restricted to neutral joint position [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.pacey.2013.30">Pacey et al 2013</xref>].</p>
          <p>Resistance exercise can exacerbate joint instability and pain. In general, it is preferable to increase the number of repetitions of exercise rather than to increase the resistance.</p>
          <p>High-impact activity increases the risk for acute subluxation/dislocation, chronic pain, and osteoarthritis. Some sports, such as tackle football, are therefore contraindicated. However, most sports and activities are acceptable with appropriate precautions.</p>
          <p>Chiropractic adjustment is not strictly contraindicated, but must be performed cautiously to avoid iatrogenic subluxations or dislocations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>All first-degree relatives are at a 50% risk of having EDS, hypermobility type, and may wish to undergo formal clinical assessment. Those without significant clinical manifestations may not benefit directly from knowing that they are affected, but may benefit from knowing that their children are at risk. Evaluation of children under age ten years (and especially under age 5 years) is difficult because of the normal joint laxity in that age group.</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="eds3.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>Labor and delivery may progress very rapidly. Even in primigravid women, any perception of labor should be taken seriously and she should promptly report to her intended place of delivery.</p>
          <p>There is no clear advantage to vaginal vs. cesarean delivery. Cesarean delivery may reduce the risk of hip dislocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.volkov.2007.51">Volkov et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.dutta.2011.306413">Dutta et al 2011</xref>], but carries the same risk for surgical complications as in the general population.</p>
          <p>There is no increase in risk for cervical incompetence, and no evidence to support use of prophylactic cerclage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="eds3.REF.volkov.2007.51">Volkov et al 2007</xref>].</p>
          <p>Pregnant women with known aortic dilation should have an echocardiogram in each trimester. Echocardiography is not needed if the aortic root is normal prior to pregnancy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Other_1">
          <title>Other</title>
          <p><bold>Vitamin C</bold> is a cofactor for cross-linking of collagen fibrils. Supplementation with up to 500 mg daily may improve some of the manifestations, but this has not been studied. Higher doses are likely excreted and probably offer no additional clinical benefit.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="eds3.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="eds3.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), hypermobility type is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Most individuals diagnosed with EDS, hypermobility type have an affected parent, although a careful history and examination of the parents is often necessary to recognize that, despite absence of serious complications, one and sometimes both parents have current or prior history of joint laxity, easy bruising, and soft skin.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A proband with EDS, hypermobility type may have the disorder as the result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant. The proportion of cases caused by a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant is unknown.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recommendations for the evaluation of parents of a proband with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant include a careful history and physical examination seeking current or prior history of joint laxity, easy bruising, and soft skin.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Although most individuals diagnosed with EDS, hypermobility type have an affected parent, the family history may appear to be negative because of failure to recognize the disorder in family members.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> The risk to the sibs of the proband depends on the genetic status of the proband's parents:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband is affected, the risk to the sibs is 50%.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When the parents are clinically unaffected, the risk to the sibs of a proband appears to be low.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Each child of an individual with EDS, hypermobility type has a 50% chance of inheriting the same pathogenic variant (and thus the same type of EDS). However, because of marked clinical variability, it is difficult to predict severity among affected offspring.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> The risk to other family members depends on the genetic status of the proband's parents: if a parent is affected, his or her family members may be at risk.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="eds3.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>It is worthwhile to emphasize to affected individuals and family members that EDS, hypermobility type does not evolve into any of the other types, either in the affected individual or in their offspring, and that the hypermobility type does not confer increased risk for early mortality.</p>
          <p><bold>Considerations in families with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant</bold>. When neither parent of a proband with an autosomal dominant condition has clinical evidence of the disorder, the pathogenic variant is likely <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>. However, non-medical explanations including alternate paternity or maternity (e.g., with assisted reproduction) and undisclosed adoption could also be explored.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration could be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Prenatal_Testing">
          <title>Prenatal Testing</title>
          <p>Because the gene(s) and pathogenic variant(s) responsible for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, hypermobility type have not been identified, prenatal testing is not possible at this time.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="eds3.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="eds3.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="eds3.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>No pathogenic variants in any genes have yet been associated with EDS, hypermobility type.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="eds3.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="eds3.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="eds3.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="eds3.REF.aldridge.2003.e41">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aldridge</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    <suffix>3rd</suffix>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Perry</surname>
                    <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Osbahr</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Speer</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Thermal capsulorraphy of bilateral glenohumeral joints in a pediatric patient with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Arthroscopy</source>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>E41</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724665</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.anstey.1991.155">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Anstey</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayne</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Winter</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Van de Pette</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pope</surname>
                    <given-names>FM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1991</year>
                <article-title>Platelet and coagulation studies in Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Dermatol.</source>
                <volume>125</volume>
                <fpage>155</fpage>
                <lpage>63</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1911298</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.atzinger.2011.826">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Atzinger</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meyer</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khoury</surname>
                    <given-names>PR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gao</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tinkle</surname>
                    <given-names>BT</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Cross-sectional and longitudinal assessment of aortic root dilation and valvular anomalies in hypermobile and classic Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>158</volume>
                <fpage>826</fpage>
                <lpage>830.e1</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21193204</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.baezavelasco.2011.1131">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baeza-Velasco</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>G&#x000e9;ly-Nargeot</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bulbena Vilarrasa</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bravo</surname>
                    <given-names>JF</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Joint hypermobility syndrome: problems that require psychological intervention.</article-title>
                <source>Rheumatol Int.</source>
                <volume>31</volume>
                <fpage>1131</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21373784</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.beighton.1998.31">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beighton</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steinmann</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsipouras</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wenstrup</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998</year>
                <article-title>Ehlers-Danlos syndromes: revised nosology, Villefranche, 1997. Ehlers-Danlos National Foundation (USA) and Ehlers-Danlos Support Group (UK).</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>77</volume>
                <fpage>31</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9557891</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.beighton.1973.413">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beighton</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Solomon</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Soskolne</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1973</year>
                <article-title>Articular mobility in an African population.</article-title>
                <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>
                <volume>32</volume>
                <fpage>413</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4751776</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.branson.2011.259">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Branson</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kozlowska</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaczynski</surname>
                    <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roesler</surname>
                    <given-names>TA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Managing chronic pain in a young adolescent girl with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Harv Rev Psychiatry.</source>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>259</fpage>
                <lpage>70</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21916827</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.bristow.2005.24">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bristow</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carey</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Egging</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schalkwijk</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Tenascin-X, collagen, elastin, and the Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet C Semin Med Genet.</source>
                <volume>139C</volume>
                <fpage>24</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16278880</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.camerota.2014.981">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Camerota</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castori</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celletti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Colotto</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Amato</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Colella</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Curione</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Danese</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>Heart rate, conduction and ultrasound abnormalities in adults with joint hypermobility syndrome/Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, hypermobility type.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Rheumatol</source>
                <volume>33</volume>
                <fpage>981</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24752348</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.camerota.2011.e2">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Camerota</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celletti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castori</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grammatico</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Padua</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Neuropathic pain is a common feature in Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Pain Symptom Manage.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>41</volume>
                <fpage>e2</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21145199</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.campens.2014.914">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Campens</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Demulier</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Groote</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vandekerckhove</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Wolf</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roman</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Devereux</surname>
                    <given-names>RB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Backer</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Reference values for echocardiographic assessment of the diameter of the aortic root and ascending aorta spanning all age categories.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Cardiol.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>114</volume>
                <fpage>914</fpage>
                <lpage>20</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25092193</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.carbone.2000.388">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carbone</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tylavsky</surname>
                    <given-names>FA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bush</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koo</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Orwoll</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cheng</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Bone density in Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Osteoporos Int</source>
                <year>2000</year>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>388</fpage>
                <lpage>92</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10912839</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.castori.2010a.556">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castori</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Camerota</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celletti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Danese</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santilli</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saraceni</surname>
                    <given-names>VM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grammatico</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010a</year>
                <article-title>Natural history and manifestations of the hypermobility type Ehlers-Danlos syndrome: a pilot study on 21 patients.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <volume>152A</volume>
                <fpage>556</fpage>
                <lpage>64</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20140961</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.castori.2010b.2406">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castori</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Camerota</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celletti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grammatico</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Padua</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010b</year>
                <article-title>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome hypermobility type and the excess of affected females: possible mechanisms and perspectives.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <volume>152A</volume>
                <fpage>2406</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20684008</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.castori.2012.2176">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castori</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morlino</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dordoni</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celletti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Camerota</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ritelli</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morrone</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Venturini</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grammatico</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Colombi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>Gynecologic and obstetric implications of the joint hypermobility syndrome (a.k.a. Ehlers &#x02013; Danlos syndrome hypermobility type) in 82 Italian patients.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet Part A</source>
                <volume>158A</volume>
                <fpage>2176</fpage>
                <lpage>82</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22847925</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.chaudhury.2012.e1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chaudhury</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gasinu</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rodeo</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>Bilateral anterior and posterior glenohumeral stabilization using Achilles tendon allograft augmentation in a patient with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg.</source>
                <volume>21</volume>
                <fpage>e1</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22326542</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.cimolin.2011.1722">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cimolin</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Galli</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vismara</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grugni</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Camerota</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celletti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Albertini</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rigoldi</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Capodaglio</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Gait pattern in two rare genetic conditions characterized by muscular hypotonia: Ehlers-Danlos and Prader-Willi syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Res Dev Disabil.</source>
                <volume>32</volume>
                <fpage>1722</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21454046</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.de_coster.2005.298">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Coster</surname>
                    <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Martens</surname>
                    <given-names>LC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Oral health in prevalent types of Ehlers-Danlos syndromes.</article-title>
                <source>J Oral Pathol Med</source>
                <volume>34</volume>
                <fpage>298</fpage>
                <lpage>307</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817074</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.de_felice.2004.429">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Felice</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bianciardi</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dileo</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Latini</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Parrini</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004</year>
                <article-title>Abnormal oral vascular network geometric complexity in Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
                <volume>98</volume>
                <fpage>429</fpage>
                <lpage>34</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15472658</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.de_paepe.2004.491">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004</year>
                <article-title>Bleeding and bruising in patients with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome and other collagen vascular disorders.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Haematol.</source>
                <volume>127</volume>
                <fpage>491</fpage>
                <lpage>500</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15566352</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.dolan.1998.630">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dolan</surname>
                    <given-names>AL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arden</surname>
                    <given-names>NK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grahame</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spector</surname>
                    <given-names>TD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1998</year>
                <article-title>Assessment of bone in Ehlers Danlos syndrome by ultrasound and densitometry.</article-title>
                <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>
                <volume>57</volume>
                <fpage>630</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9893576</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.dolan.1997.459">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dolan</surname>
                    <given-names>AL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mishra</surname>
                    <given-names>MB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chambers</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grahame</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>Clinical and echocardiographic survey of the Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Rheumatol</source>
                <volume>36</volume>
                <fpage>459</fpage>
                <lpage>62</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9159540</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.dutta.2011.306413">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dutta</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wilson</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oteri</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Pregnancy and delivery in ehlers-danlos syndrome (hypermobility type): review of the literature.</article-title>
                <source>Obstet Gynecol Int.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <fpage>306413</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21765833</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.galli.2011.1663">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Galli</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cimolin</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rigoldi</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castori</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celletti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Albertini</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Camerota</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Gait strategy in patients with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome hypermobility type: a kinematic and kinetic evaluation using 3D gait analysis.</article-title>
                <source>Res Dev Disabil.</source>
                <volume>32</volume>
                <fpage>1663</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21420276</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.gazit.2003.33">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gazit</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nahir</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grahame</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jacob</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Dysautonomia in the joint hypermobility syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med.</source>
                <volume>115</volume>
                <fpage>33</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12867232</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.gharbiya.2012.593">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gharbiya</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moramarco</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Castori</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Parisi</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celletti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marenco</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mariani</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grammatico</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Camerota</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Ocular features in joint hypermobility syndrome/Ehlers-Danlos syndrome hypermobility type: a clinical and in vivo confocal microscopy study.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Ophthalmol.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>154</volume>
                <fpage>593</fpage>
                <lpage>600.e1</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22633352</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.grahame.1999.188">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grahame</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Joint hypermobility and genetic collagen disorders: are they related?</article-title>
                <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
                <volume>80</volume>
                <fpage>188</fpage>
                <lpage>91</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10325741</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.gulbahar.2006.511">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gulbahar</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sahin</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baydar</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bircan</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kizil</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Manisali</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Akalin</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peker</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Hypermobility syndrome increases the risk for low bone mass.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Rheumatol</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>25</volume>
                <fpage>511</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16311714</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.hagberg.2004.178">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hagberg</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berglund</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Korpe</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Andersson-Norinder</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004</year>
                <article-title>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome (EDS) focusing on oral symptoms: a questionnaire study.</article-title>
                <source>Orthod Craniofac Res.</source>
                <volume>7</volume>
                <fpage>178</fpage>
                <lpage>85</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15359504</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.hakim.2005.84">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hakim</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grahame</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Norris</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hopper</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Local anaesthetic failure in joint hypermobility syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J R Soc Med.</source>
                <volume>98</volume>
                <fpage>84</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15684369</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.jacome.1999.791">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jacome</surname>
                    <given-names>DE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Headache in Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Cephalalgia.</source>
                <year>1999</year>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>791</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10595288</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.kozanoglu.2015">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kozanoglu</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coskun Benlidayi</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eker Akilli</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tasal</surname>
                    <given-names>A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Is there any link between joint hypermobility and mitral valve prolapse in patients with fibromyalgia syndrome?</article-title>
                <source>Clin Rheumatol.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <month>Jul</month>
                <day>28</day>
                <comment>Epub ahead of print</comment>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26216348</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.levy.1999.a69">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Levy</surname>
                    <given-names>HP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayoral</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Collier</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tio</surname>
                    <given-names>TL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fracomano</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Gastroesophageal reflux and irritable bowel syndrome in classical and hypermobile Ehlers Danlos syndrome (EDS).</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>65</volume>
                <fpage>A69</fpage>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.mast.2009.230">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mast</surname>
                    <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nunes</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ruymann</surname>
                    <given-names>FB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kerlin</surname>
                    <given-names>BA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2009</year>
                <article-title>Desmopressin responsiveness in children with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome associated bleeding symptoms.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Haematol.</source>
                <volume>144</volume>
                <fpage>230</fpage>
                <lpage>3</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19036109</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.mathias.2011.22">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mathias</surname>
                    <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Low</surname>
                    <given-names>DA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iodice</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Owens</surname>
                    <given-names>AP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kirbis</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grahame</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Postural tachycardia syndrome--current experience and concepts.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Rev Neurol.</source>
                <year>2011</year>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>22</fpage>
                <lpage>34</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22143364</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.mcdonnell.2006.129">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McDonnell</surname>
                    <given-names>NB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gorman</surname>
                    <given-names>BL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mandel</surname>
                    <given-names>KW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schurman</surname>
                    <given-names>SH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Assanah-Carroll</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayer</surname>
                    <given-names>SA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Najjar</surname>
                    <given-names>SS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Francomano</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Echocardiographic findings in classical and hypermobile Ehlers-Danlos syndromes.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A</source>
                <volume>140</volume>
                <fpage>129</fpage>
                <lpage>36</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16353246</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.mcintosh.1995.559">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McIntosh</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mallett</surname>
                    <given-names>VT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Frahm</surname>
                    <given-names>JD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Richardson</surname>
                    <given-names>DA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Evans</surname>
                    <given-names>MI</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Gynecologic disorders in women with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Soc Gynecol Investig.</source>
                <year>1995</year>
                <volume>2</volume>
                <fpage>559</fpage>
                <lpage>64</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9420859</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.milhorat.2007.601">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Milhorat</surname>
                    <given-names>TH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bolognese</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishikawa</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McDonnell</surname>
                    <given-names>NB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Francomano</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Syndrome of occipitoatlantoaxial hypermobility, cranial settling, and chiari malformation type I in patients with hereditary disorders of connective tissue.</article-title>
                <source>J Neurosurg Spine.</source>
                <volume>7</volume>
                <fpage>601</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18074684</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.pacey.2013.30">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pacey</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tofts</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adams</surname>
                    <given-names>RD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munns</surname>
                    <given-names>CF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nicholson</surname>
                    <given-names>LL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2013</year>
                <article-title>Exercise in children with joint hypermobility syndrome and knee pain: a randomised controlled trial comparing exercise into hypermobile versus neutral knee extension.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Rheumatol Online J.</source>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>30</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23941143</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rigoldi.2012.1437">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rigoldi</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Galli</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cimolin</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Camerota</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Celletti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tenore</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Albertini</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012</year>
                <article-title>Gait strategy in patients with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome hypermobility type and Down syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Res Dev Disabil.</source>
                <volume>33</volume>
                <fpage>1437</fpage>
                <lpage>42</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22522202</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010a.289">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rombaut</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cools</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calders</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010a</year>
                <article-title>Joint position sense and vibratory perception sense in patients with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome type III (hypermobility type).</article-title>
                <source>Clin Rheumatol.</source>
                <volume>29</volume>
                <fpage>289</fpage>
                <lpage>95</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19937459</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rombaut.2010b.1339">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rombaut</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cools</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calders</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010b</year>
                <article-title>Musculoskeletal complaints, physical activity and health-related quality of life among patients with the Ehlers-Danlos syndrome hypermobility type.</article-title>
                <source>Disabil Rehabil.</source>
                <volume>32</volume>
                <fpage>1339</fpage>
                <lpage>45</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20156051</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011a.1979">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rombaut</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rimbaut</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Verbruggen</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Wandele</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calders</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011a</year>
                <article-title>Impairment and impact of pain in female patients with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome: a comparative study with fibromyalgia and rheumatoid arthritis.</article-title>
                <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source>
                <volume>63</volume>
                <fpage>1979</fpage>
                <lpage>87</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21391202</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011b.1106">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rombaut</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Wandele</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cools</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thijs</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calders</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011b</year>
                <article-title>Medication, surgery, and physiotherapy among patients with the hypermobility type of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil.</source>
                <volume>92</volume>
                <fpage>1106</fpage>
                <lpage>12</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21636074</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rombaut.2012a.766">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rombaut</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Wandele</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mahieu</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thijs</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Segers</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calders</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012a</year>
                <article-title>Muscle-tendon tissue properties in the hypermobility type of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</source>
                <volume>64</volume>
                <fpage>766</fpage>
                <lpage>72</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22232076</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rombaut.2012b.1584">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rombaut</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Wandele</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taes</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thijs</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calders</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2012b</year>
                <article-title>Muscle mass, muscle strength, functional performance,and physical impairment in women with the hypermobility type of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</source>
                <volume>64</volume>
                <fpage>1584</fpage>
                <lpage>92</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22556148</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rombaut.2011c.1432">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rombaut</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Wandele</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thijs</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Palmans</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calders</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011c</year>
                <article-title>Balance, gait, falls, and fear of falling in women with the hypermobility type of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</source>
                <volume>63</volume>
                <fpage>1432</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21793229</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rose.2004.190">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rose</surname>
                    <given-names>PS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hungerford</surname>
                    <given-names>DS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McFarland</surname>
                    <given-names>EG</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004</year>
                <article-title>Total knee arthroplasty in Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Arthroplasty</source>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>190</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14973862</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.rowe.1999.494">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rowe</surname>
                    <given-names>PC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barron</surname>
                    <given-names>DF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Calkins</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maumenee</surname>
                    <given-names>IH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tong</surname>
                    <given-names>PY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Geraghty</surname>
                    <given-names>MT</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1999</year>
                <article-title>Orthostatic intolerance and chronic fatigue syndrome associated with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr</source>
                <volume>135</volume>
                <fpage>494</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10518084</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.sacheti.1997.88">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sacheti</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Szemere</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bernstein</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tafas</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schechter</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsipouras</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>Chronic pain is a manifestation of the Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>88</fpage>
                <lpage>93</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9262038</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.stine.1997.156">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stine</surname>
                    <given-names>KC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Becton</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1997</year>
                <article-title>DDAVP therapy controls bleeding in Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr Hematol Oncol</source>
                <volume>19</volume>
                <fpage>156</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9149748</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.symoens.2012.1485">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Symoens</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Syx</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Malfait</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Callewaert</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Backer</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vanakker</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coucke</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Comprehensive molecular analysis demonstrates type V collagen mutations in over 90% of patients with classic EDS and allows to refine diagnostic criteria.</article-title>
                <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>33</volume>
                <fpage>1485</fpage>
                <lpage>93</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22696272</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.tinkle.2009.2368">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tinkle</surname>
                    <given-names>BT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bird</surname>
                    <given-names>HA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grahame</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lavallee</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Levy</surname>
                    <given-names>HP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sillence</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2009</year>
                <article-title>The lack of clinical distinction between the hypermobility type of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome and the joint hypermobility syndrome (a.k.a. hypermobility syndrome).</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med Genet A.</source>
                <volume>149A</volume>
                <fpage>2368</fpage>
                <lpage>70</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19842204</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.voermans.2011.706">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Voermans</surname>
                    <given-names>NC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knoop</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Both pain and fatigue are important possible determinants of disability in patients with the Ehlers-Danlos syndrome hypermobility type.</article-title>
                <source>Disabil Rehabil.</source>
                <volume>33</volume>
                <fpage>706</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21077749</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.voermans.2010a.370">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Voermans</surname>
                    <given-names>NC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knoop</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bleijenberg</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Engelen</surname>
                    <given-names>BG</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010a</year>
                <article-title>Pain in ehlers-danlos syndrome is common, severe, and associated with functional impairment.</article-title>
                <source>J Pain Symptom Manage.</source>
                <volume>40</volume>
                <fpage>370</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20579833</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.voermans.2010b.267">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Voermans</surname>
                    <given-names>NC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Knoop</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van de Kamp</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamel</surname>
                    <given-names>BC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bleijenberg</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Engelen</surname>
                    <given-names>BG</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010b</year>
                <article-title>Fatigue is a frequent and clinically relevant problem in Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Semin Arthritis Rheum.</source>
                <volume>40</volume>
                <fpage>267</fpage>
                <lpage>74</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19878973</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.volkov.2007.51">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Volkov</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nisenblat</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ohel</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gonen</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome: insights on obstetric aspects.</article-title>
                <source>Obstet Gynecol Surv</source>
                <volume>62</volume>
                <fpage>51</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17176488</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.wenstrup.2002.112">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wenstrup</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meyer</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lyle</surname>
                    <given-names>JS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoechstetter</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rose</surname>
                    <given-names>PS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Levy</surname>
                    <given-names>HP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Francomano</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>Prevalence of aortic root dilation in the Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Genet Med</source>
                <volume>4</volume>
                <fpage>112</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12180144</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.zweers.2003.214">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zweers</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bristow</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steijlen</surname>
                    <given-names>PM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dean</surname>
                    <given-names>WB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamel</surname>
                    <given-names>BC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Otero</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kucharekova</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boezeman</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schalkwijk</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Haploinsufficiency of TNXB is associated with hypermobility type of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>73</volume>
                <fpage>214</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12865992</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="eds3.REF.zweers.2005.330">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zweers</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dean</surname>
                    <given-names>WB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Kuppevelt</surname>
                    <given-names>TH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bristow</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schalkwijk</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Elastic fiber abnormalities in hypermobility type Ehlers-Danlos syndrome patients with tenascin-X mutations.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Genet.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>67</volume>
                <fpage>330</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15733269</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="eds3.Suggested_Reading">
          <title>Suggested Reading</title>
          <ref-list id="eds3.Suggested_Reading.reflist0">
            <ref id="eds3.REF.byers">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Byers PH. Disorders of collagen biosynthesis and structure. In: Scriver CR, Beaudet AL, Sly WS, Valle D, Vogelstein B, eds. <italic toggle="yes">The Online Metabolic and Molecular Bases of Inherited Disease (OMMBID).</italic> Chap 205. New York, NY: McGraw-Hill. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ommbid.mhmedical.com/">online</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="eds3.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="eds3.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>31 March 2016 (ha) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>13 September 2012 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>14 December 2010 (cd) Revision: sequence analysis of the entire coding region available on a limited basis for <italic toggle="yes">TNXB</italic> mutations</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>27 April 2010 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>1 May 2007 (me) Comprehensive update posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>22 October 2004 (me) Review posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>1 June 2004 (hpl) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
