<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="hfpoik-tmp" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">hfpoik-tmp</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Hereditary Fibrosing Poikiloderma with Tendon Contractures, Myopathy, and Pulmonary Fibrosis</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: POIKTMP</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mercier</surname>
            <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Service de G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique m&#x000e9;dicale &#x02013; CHU<break/>Nantes, France</aff>
          <email>sandra.mercier@chu-nantes.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>K&#x000fc;ry</surname>
            <given-names>S&#x000e9;bastien</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>VMD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Service de G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique m&#x000e9;dicale &#x02013; CHU<break/>Nantes, France</aff>
          <email>sebastien.kury@chu-nantes.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Barbarot</surname>
            <given-names>S&#x000e9;bastien</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Service de Dermatologie &#x02013; CHU<break/>Nantes, France</aff>
          <email>sebastien.barbarot@chu-nantes.fr</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" document-type="chapter">Hereditary Dystonia Overview</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="folate-mal" document-type="chapter">Hereditary Folate Malabsorption</related-object>
      <abstract id="hfpoik-tmp.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Hereditary fibrosing poikiloderma with tendon contractures, myopathy, and pulmonary fibrosis (POIKTMP) is characterized by the skin findings of poikiloderma (typically beginning in the first six months and mainly localized to the face), hypohidrosis with heat intolerance, mild lymphedema of the extremities, chronic erythematous and scaly skin lesions on the extremities, sclerosis of the digits, and mild palmoplantar keratoderma. Scalp hair, eyelashes, and/or eyebrows are typically sparse. Muscle contractures are usually seen in childhood and can be present as early as age two years. The majority of affected individuals develop progressive weakness of the proximal and distal muscles of all four limbs. Some adults develop progressive interstitial pulmonary fibrosis, which can be life-threatening within three to four years after respiratory symptoms appear. Other features are exocrine pancreatic insufficiency, liver impairment, hematologic abnormalities, relative short stature, and cataract.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of POIKTMP is established in a proband with early-onset poikiloderma with other findings, especially muscle contractures and/or muscle weakness and the identification of a heterozygous missense pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> on molecular genetic testing.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p>
            <italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Dermatologic: avoidance of excessive sun exposure and use of sunscreens with both UVA and UVB protection; avoidance of excessive heat exposure and control of fever, especially in early childhood; routine management of lymphedema; emollients, topical steroids for eczema-like lesions. For older individuals, pulsed dye laser may be an option for cosmesis for telangiectatic component of the rash.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Contractures and myopathy: physical therapy and exercise to promote mobility and prevent contractures.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Lung: use of self-inflating manual-ventilation bag or mechanical insufflation-exsufflation device if needed; noninvasive ventilation if needed.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Annual surveillance beginning at the time of diagnosis (adapted to the patient&#x02019;s findings): dermatologic examination, physical therapy assessment for muscle weakness and/or contractures, pulmonary function testing, assessment for orthopedic complications (contractures, especially of the Achilles tendon, and scoliosis)</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Excessive sun exposure (may exacerbate the rash), exposure to heat because of heat intolerance.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>POIKTMP is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. In approximately 50% of affected individuals the <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> pathogenic variant is inherited and in approximately 50% it is <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>. Each child of an individual with POIKTMP has a 50% chance of inheriting the <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> pathogenic variant. If the <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk for POIKTMP and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Hereditary fibrosing poikiloderma with tendon contractures, myopathy, and pulmonary fibrosis (POIKTMP) <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following clinical and imaging findings:</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Clinical</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Skin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="hfpoik-tmp.F1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="hfpoik-tmp.F2">Figure 2</xref>):</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Early-onset poikiloderma (characterized by erythema of the cheeks and face, skin atrophy, telangiectasias, and mottled pigmentation)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Hypotrichosis with sparse scalp hair, sparse or absent eyelashes and/or eyebrows</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Hypohidrosis with heat intolerance</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Mild lymphedema of the extremities</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Multiple contractures, in particular triceps surae contractures in childhood</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Myopathy with diffuse progressive muscular weakness, scoliosis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Restrictive pulmonary syndrome and/or pulmonary fibrosis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Exocrine pancreatic insufficiency</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Liver impairment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hematologic abnormalities, such as thrombocytopenia, marrow hypocellularity</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Other</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Relative short stature</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Cataract</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Nail dystrophy</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Imaging</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="hfpoik-tmp.F3">Figure 3</xref>. Muscle MRI typically shows severe diffuse fatty infiltration of the legs, especially:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>The vastus lateralis muscles (with relative sparing of the tibialis posterior); and</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>The anterior compartment of thighs (with relative sparing of posterior compartment).</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>These findings can confirm muscle involvement in asymptomatic individuals.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of POIKTMP <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with early-onset poikiloderma with other findings, especially muscle contractures and/or muscle weakness and the identification of a heterozygous pathogenic missense variant in <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> on molecular genetic testing (<xref ref-type="table" rid="hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold>, use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>, and <bold>more comprehensive</bold>
<bold>genomic testing</bold>.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> is performed first.</p>
              <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis may be performed; however, since POIKTMP likely occurs as the result of a dominant-negative genetic mechanism and since large intragenic deletions or duplications have not been reported, testing for intragenic deletions or duplications is unlikely to identify a disease-causing variant (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hfpoik-tmp.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hfpoik-tmp.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of the condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting secondary findings. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing based tests.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>More comprehensive genomic testing</bold> (when available) including whole-exome sequencing (WES) and whole-genome sequencing (WGS) may be considered if serial single-gene testing (and/or use of a multi-gene panel that includes <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic>) fails to confirm a diagnosis in an individual with features of POIKTMP. Such testing may provide or suggest a diagnosis not previously considered (e.g., mutation of a different gene or genes that results in a similar clinical presentation). For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Hereditary Fibrosing Poikiloderma with Tendon Contractures, Myopathy, and Pulmonary Fibrosis</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Pathogenic Variant&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/13&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.molecular_genetic_testing_u_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="hfpoik-tmp.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="hfpoik-tmp" object-id="hfpoik-tmp.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="hfpoik-tmp.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hfpoik-tmp.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="hfpoik-tmp.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="hfpoik-tmp.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2013.1100">Mercier et al [2013]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al [2015]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.seo.2016.858">Seo et al [2016]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.takeichi.2016">Takeichi et al [2016]</xref></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="hfpoik-tmp.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="hfpoik-tmp.TF.1.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>The spectrum of variants detected in affected individuals and functional studies [Author, unpublished observations] suggest a dominant-negative mechanism of disease; therefore, deletion/duplication testing is unlikely to detect a disease-causing variant.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Test characteristics.</bold> See <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/ejhg/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/ejhg2015205a.html">Clinical Utility Gene Card</ext-link> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.k_ry.2016">K&#x000fc;ry et al 2016</xref>] for information on test characteristics including sensitivity and specificity.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Individuals with hereditary fibrosing poikiloderma with tendon contractures, myopathy, and pulmonary fibrosis (POIKTMP) can exhibit few or many of the associated clinical features. The severity of the features (e.g., skin or muscle abnormalities) can vary. Intrafamilial clinical variability has been observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.khumalo.2006.1057">Khumalo et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.seo.2016.858">Seo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <p>Of note, the description of clinical features that follows is based on findings in the 25 affected individuals with a molecularly confirmed diagnosis published to date [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2013.1100">Mercier et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.seo.2016.858">Seo et al 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.takeichi.2016">Takeichi et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <p>Of note, three individuals reported as having a Rothmund-Thomson syndrome-like phenotype probably have an <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> pathogenic variant; however, a molecular diagnosis is not available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.lessem.1980.237">Lessem et al 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.otsu.2008.632">Otsu et al 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.meier.2012.2109">Meier &#x00026; Schwarz 2012</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Skin.</bold> Skin abnormalities are the earliest findings. Of note, skin lesions &#x02013; particularly facial poikiloderma &#x02013; improve with time.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Poikiloderma</bold> appears during early infancy, typically in the first six months. It is mainly localized to the face (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="hfpoik-tmp.F1">Figure 1</xref>). Transient exacerbations of facial erythema are seen following sun exposure. Mottled pigmentation is also a constituent part of poikiloderma.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Hypohidrosis</bold> with heat intolerance is observed in most.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Lymphedema</bold> of the lower and/or upper extremities may be present in childhood and is usually mild; it can be complicated by episodes of cellulitis.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Chronic erythematous and scaly skin lesions</bold> described as eczema-like, ichthyosis-like, or psoriasis-like lesions are often observed on the extremities.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Sclerosis</bold> of the digits and mild palmoplantar keratoderma may also be observed.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Hair/nails.</bold> Sparse scalp hair and sparse or absent eyelashes and/or eyebrows of variable severity are found in almost all affected individuals. Three affected individuals had mild nail dysplasia.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Muscle</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Muscle contractures</bold> are usually seen in childhood and can be present as early as age two years. The most commonly affected muscles are the triceps surae, leading to a shortening of the Achilles tendons and varus deformities of the feet. Contractures of upper limbs (biceps brachii and carpal extensors) are also observed.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Myopathy.</bold> The majority of affected individuals develop progressive weakness of the proximal and distal muscles of all four limbs; the first manifestations (observed in lower limbs) are proximal rather than distal. Variability of muscle weakness ranges from loss of ambulation in childhood to absence of symptoms in adulthood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2013.1100">Mercier et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.seo.2016.858">Seo et al 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.takeichi.2016">Takeichi et al 2016</xref>].</p>
              <p>Muscle weakness is generally associated with muscle atrophy and sometimes thoracolumbar scoliosis.</p>
              <p>Serum creatine kinase is either normal or slightly increased. When performed, electromyography may show a normal or myopathic pattern.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Lung.</bold> Recurrent bronchitis can be observed. Abnormal lung function with restrictive pulmonary disease is common.</p>
          <p>Some adults develop progressive interstitial pulmonary fibrosis, manifest as progressive breathlessness and dry cough; it can be life-threatening within three to four years after the first respiratory symptoms appear.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Gastrointestinal</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Pancreatic exocrine insufficiency</bold> (common in affected individuals) typically begins in childhood. Manifestations include fatty stools and diarrhea leading to chronic malabsorption of fats and lipid-soluble vitamins if not treated. Diagnosis is confirmed based on fecal elastase deficiency.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Liver impairment</bold> (reported in a few affected individuals) manifests initially as mildly elevated transaminases, alkaline phosphatase, gamma-glutamyl transferase, and/or bilirubin. One individual had hepatomegaly and cholestasis.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Other features</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Relative short stature</bold> and/or poor weight gain associated with delayed puberty have been reported.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Hematologic findings</bold> include eosinophilia or mild thrombocytopenia in some. Marrow hypocellularity was reported in a multiplex family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.seo.2016.858">Seo et al 2016</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Hypothyroidism</bold> was described in a girl age 14 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.takeichi.2016">Takeichi et al 2016</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Eye.</bold> Cataract was reported in a girl age 13 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Cognitive development and function</bold> are normal. Of note, one individual had schizophrenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al 2015</xref>], which could be an incidental association.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Histopathology</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Muscle histology</bold> shows extensive fatty infiltration. Residual muscle tissue is composed of fragmented muscle fascicles with either normal fibers or atrophic fibers with central nuclei (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="hfpoik-tmp.F4">Figure 4 A-D</xref>). No neuropathic features (i.e., normal ATPase pattern) or mitochondrial network abnormalities are found on histochemistry or immunolabelling. Western blot analysis can show a secondary reduction of calpain.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Skin histology</bold> shows a characteristic pattern of epidermal atrophy with collagen sclerosis and elastic degeneration in the superficial and deep dermis. Elastic globes in the papillary dermis are associated with a diffuse slight collagen sclerosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="hfpoik-tmp.F4">Figure 4 E-F</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Post-mortem findings</bold> of one affected member of a South African family revealed diffuse fatty infiltration and fibrosis of organs including the lungs, esophagus, and pancreas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.khumalo.2006.1057">Khumalo et al 2006</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.GenotypePhenotype_Correlation">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>POIKTMP is most frequently caused by heterozygosity for missense <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> pathogenic variants in the predicted trypsin-like cysteine/serine peptidase domain of the protein, in particular in the loop of the functional domain.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Upstream variants located outside the loop (codons 421, 430) appear to be associated with a less severe phenotype, especially regarding muscle features [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.seo.2016.858">Seo et al 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.takeichi.2016">Takeichi et al 2016</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The phenotype of pathogenic variants in codon 621 seems to be less severe than the phenotype observed with pathogenic variants in codons 625, 627, and 628 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.khumalo.2006.1057">Khumalo et al 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2013.1100">Mercier et al 2013</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Further studies are needed to confirm these preliminary genotype-phenotype correlations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>To our knowledge, the penetrance of POIKTMP is 100% with occurrence of skin features in early childhood.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>The prevalence of POIKTMP is unknown. To date only 25 individuals with molecularly confirmed POIKTMP have been reported.</p>
          <p>The condition is thought to be ubiquitous and is likely underdiagnosed.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Genetically_Related_Allelic_D">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <table-wrap id="hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Disorders to Consider in the Differential Diagnosis of Hereditary Fibrosing Poikiloderma with Tendon Contractures, Myopathy, and Pulmonary Fibrosis</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_1">Disorder <break/>Name</th>
                <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_2" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_2">Gene</th>
                <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_3" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_3">MOI</th>
                <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" colspan="3" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Clinical Features</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_1" id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup">Overlapping</th>
                <th headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4" id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Distinguishing</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_2" id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">In this disorder</th>
                <th headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_2" id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_3_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In POIKTMP</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rts" document-type="chapter">Rothmund Thomson syndrome</related-object> (RTS)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">RECQL4</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Early-onset poikiloderma</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hypotrichosis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Palmoplantar keratoderma</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_2 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Skeletal abnormalities</p></list-item><list-item><p>Dental abnormalities</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_2 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_3_2" rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Muscle contractures</p></list-item><list-item><p>Myopathy</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exocrine pancreatic insufficiency</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hereditary sclerosing poikiloderma (HSP) of Weary (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/173700">OMIM</ext-link>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD?</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Poikiloderma</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sclerosis of palms &#x00026; soles</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_2 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Linear sclerotic bands</p></list-item><list-item><p>Subcutaneous calcifications</p></list-item><list-item><p>Valvular heart disease</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="kindler" document-type="chapter">Kindler syndrome</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">FERMT1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">KIND1</italic>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Diffuse poikiloderma w/striate &#x00026; reticulate atrophy</p></list-item><list-item><p>Widespread eczema-like dermatitis</p></list-item><list-item><p>Keratotic papules of hands, feet, elbows, &#x00026; knees</p></list-item><list-item><p>Marked photosensitivity</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_2 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Skin fragility w/bullae on extremities at birth &#x00026; after minor trauma</p></list-item><list-item><p>Webbing of fingers &#x00026; toes</p></list-item><list-item><p>Esophageal &#x00026; urethral strictures</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poikiloderma w/neutropenia (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/604173">OMIM</ext-link>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">USB1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C16orf57</italic>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Early-onset poiklioderma</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hematologic features</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_1_4 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_2_2 hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.disorders_to_consider_in_th_1_1_3_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Distal-proximal limb &#x00026; central body rash</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hyperkeratotic nails</p></list-item><list-item><p>No photo or heat sensitivity</p></list-item><list-item><p>Recurrent infections</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>MOI = mode of inheritance</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AD = autosomal dominant</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AR = autosomal recessive</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Evaluations_Following_Initial">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with hereditary fibrosing poikiloderma with tendon contractures, myopathy, and pulmonary fibrosis (POIKTMP), the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Dermatologic evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical therapy assessment</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation by pulmonary specialists including pulmonary function testing to evaluate for restrictive lung disease and/or pulmonary fibrosis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Muscle MRI to evaluate for progressive muscle involvement (optional)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Blood tests:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Liver function: SGOT, SGPT, ALP, GGT</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Baseline complete blood count with differential. Individuals with clinical evidence of anemia or cytopenias should be evaluated by CBC and bone marrow biopsy if clinically indicated.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Fecal elastase level if steatorrhea is present</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ophthalmologic examination to evaluate for cataracts or other abnormalities</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Dermatologic</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Avoidance of excessive sun exposure and use of sunscreens with both UVA and UVB protection</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Pulsed dye laser can be discussed in older individuals as an option for cosmetic management of the telangiectatic component of the rash; however, no data on its use are available.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Avoidance of excessive heat exposure and control of fever, especially in the first years of life to prevent overheating</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Lymphedema management (manual lymphatic drainage, compression)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Topical treatment for eczema-like lesions (emollients, topical steroids)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Muscle</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical therapy and exercise to promote mobility and prevent contractures</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Calcium and vitamin D supplements may also be warranted in individuals with muscle weakness to prevent osteopenia.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Lung</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Use of self-inflating manual ventilation bag or mechanical insufflation-exsufflation device if needed</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Noninvasive ventilation if needed</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Pancreas.</bold> Treatment of pancreatic exocrine insufficiency with pancreatic enzyme supplementation</p>
          <p><bold>Liver.</bold> Treatment of cholestasis with ursodeoxycholic acid</p>
          <p><bold>Growth.</bold> Enteral feeding as needed</p>
          <p><bold>Cataract.</bold> Surgical removal of visually significant cataracts</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Annual surveillance beginning at the time of diagnosis (to be adapted to patient&#x02019;s symptoms):</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Dermatologic evaluation for poikiloderma, lymphedema of the limbs, eczema-like lesions, changes in the nails and hair</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical therapy assessment for muscle weakness or contractures</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Pulmonary function testing</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Blood test:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Complete blood count with differential</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Liver function testing: SGOT, SGPT, ALP, GGT</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Ophthalmologic examination</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Monitoring for orthopedic complications, especially contractures (with attention to Achilles tendon contractures) and scoliosis</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Avoid the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Excessive sun exposure, which may exacerbate the rash</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Exposure to heat because of heat intolerance secondary to hypohidrosis</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Ri">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hfpoik-tmp.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Is">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Hereditary fibrosing poikiloderma with tendon contractures, myopathy, and pulmonary fibrosis (POIKTMP) is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Approximately 50% of individuals diagnosed with POIKTMP have an affected parent, and approximately 50% have the disorder as the result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo FAM111B</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in leukocyte DNA of either parent, possible explanations include a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant in the proband or germline mosaicism in a parent. Although no instances of germline mosaicism have been reported, it remains a possibility.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to the sibs of the proband depends on the genetic status of the proband&#x02019;s parents.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband is affected, the risk to the sibs is 50%; intrafamilial clinical variability has been observed (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hfpoik-tmp.Clinical_Description">Clinical Description</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When the parents are clinically unaffected, the risk to the sibs of a proband appears to be very low.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, the risk to sibs is presumed to be slightly greater than that of the general population (though still &#x0003c;1%) because of the theoretic possibility of parental germline mosaicism.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Each child of an individual with POIKTMP has a 50% chance of inheriting the <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> pathogenic variant; intrafamilial clinical variability has been observed (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hfpoik-tmp.Clinical_Description">Clinical Description</xref>).</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> The risk to other family members depends on the status of the proband's parents: if a parent is affected, his or her family members may be at risk.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Is">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p><bold>Considerations in families with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant.</bold> When neither parent of a proband with an autosomal dominant condition has the pathogenic variant identified in the proband or clinical evidence of the disorder, the pathogenic variant is likely <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>. However, non-medical explanations including alternate paternity or maternity (e.g., with assisted reproduction) and undisclosed adoption could also be explored.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimpla">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk for POIKTMP and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible options.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesi">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> comprises four exons. The ATG transcription start is located in exon 3. See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="hfpoik-tmp" object-id="hfpoik-tmp.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene</bold> for a detailed summary of gene and protein information.</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> Reported pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> are nearly all missense and are clustered in a putative cysteine/serine trypsin-like peptidase domain of the FAM111B protein.</p>
          <p>Variants at amino acid residues p.Lys421, p.Gln430, p.Thr621, p.Thr625, p.Arg627, and p.Ser628 have been reported.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The p.Thr621Asp pathogenic variant was reported in multiple affected individuals in a familial case of POIKTMP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The pathogenic variants p.Arg627Gly and p.Ser628Asn have been identified as <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> variants in multiple affected individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2013.1100">Mercier et al 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al 2015</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Two pathogenic variants in other regions of the gene, p.Gln430Pro and p.Lys421del, have been reported to be associated with a less severe phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al 2015</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.seo.2016.858">Seo et al 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.takeichi.2016">Takeichi et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <table-wrap id="hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">FAM111B</italic> Pathogenic Variants Discussed in This <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic></p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1261_1263delAAG</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Lys421del</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_3" rowspan="6" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_198947.3">NM_198947.3</ext-link>
                    <break/>
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_945185.1">NP_945185.1</ext-link>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1289A&#x0003e;C</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gln430Pro</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1861T&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Tyr621Asp</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1874C&#x0003e;A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Thr625Asn</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1879A&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg627Gly</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1883G&#x0003e;A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hfpoik-tmp.T.fam111b_pathogenic_variants_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ser628Asn</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> The FAM111B protein is predicted to contain a trypsin-like cysteine/serine peptidase domain. A role in DNA replication is suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.aviner.2015.e1005554">Aviner et al 2015</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> The mechanism of disease for POIKTMP is not known; however, the spectrum of pathogenic variants and functional studies suggest a dominant-negative mechanism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al 2015</xref>; Author, unpublished data].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="hfpoik-tmp.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.aviner.2015.e1005554">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aviner</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shenoy</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elroy-Stein</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Geiger</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Uncovering hidden layers of cell cycle regulation through integrative multi-omic analysis.</article-title>
                <source>PLoS Genet.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>e1005554</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26439921</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.khumalo.2006.1057">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khumalo</surname>
                    <given-names>NP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pillay</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beighton</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wainwright</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Walker</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saxe</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayosi</surname>
                    <given-names>BM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bateman</surname>
                    <given-names>ED</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Poikiloderma, tendon contracture and pulmonary fibrosis: a new autosomal dominant syndrome?</article-title>
                <source>Br J Dermatol.</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>155</volume>
                <fpage>1057</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17034542</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.k_ry.2016">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>K&#x000fc;ry</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mercier</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shaboodien</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Besnard</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barbarot</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khumalo</surname>
                    <given-names>NP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayosi</surname>
                    <given-names>BM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>B&#x000e9;zieau</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>CUGC for hereditary fibrosing poikiloderma with tendon contractures, myopathy, and pulmonary fibrosis (POIKTMP).</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <month>May</month>
                <volume>24</volume>
                <issue>5</issue>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26443268</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.lessem.1980.237">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lessem</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bjerre</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Forslund</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Epilepsy and myopathy in a patient with Rothmund-Thomson's syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Acta Med Scand.</source>
                <year>1980</year>
                <volume>207</volume>
                <fpage>237</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6768225</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.meier.2012.2109">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meier</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schwarz</surname>
                    <given-names>A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Rothmund-Thomson syndrome--a single case report with systemic muscular atrophy, multiple organ fibrosis and pulmonary cachexia.</article-title>
                <source>Rheumatology (Oxford)</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>51</volume>
                <fpage>2109</fpage>
                <lpage>11</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22711845</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mercier</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>K&#x000fc;ry</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Salort-Campana</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Magot</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Agbim</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Besnard</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bodak</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bou-Hanna</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Breheret</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brunelle</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Caillon</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chabrol</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cormier-Daire</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>David</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eymard</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Faivre</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Figarella-Branger</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fleurence</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ganapathi</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gherardi</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goldenberg</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamel</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Igual</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Irvine</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Israel-Biet</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kannengiesser</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laboisse</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Caignec</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mahe</surname>
                    <given-names>JY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mallet</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>MacGowan</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McAleer</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McLean</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meni</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munnich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mussini</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nagy</surname>
                    <given-names>PL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Odel</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>O'Regan</surname>
                    <given-names>GM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pereon</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Perrier</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Piard</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Puzenat</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sampson</surname>
                    <given-names>JB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Soufir</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tanji</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thauvin</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ulane</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Watson</surname>
                    <given-names>RM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khumalo</surname>
                    <given-names>NP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayosi</surname>
                    <given-names>BM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barbarot</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bezieau</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Expanding the clinical spectrum of hereditary fibrosing poikiloderma with tendon contractures, myopathy and pulmonary fibrosis due to FAM111B mutations.</article-title>
                <source>Orphanet J Rare Dis.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>135</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26471370</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2013.1100">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mercier</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>K&#x000fc;ry</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shaboodien</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houniet</surname>
                    <given-names>DT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Khumalo</surname>
                    <given-names>NP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bou-Hanna</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bodak</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cormier-Daire</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>David</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Faivre</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Figarella-Branger</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gherardi</surname>
                    <given-names>RK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Glen</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamel</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laboisse</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Le Caignec</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindenbaum</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Magot</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Munnich</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mussini</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pillay</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rahman</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Redon</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Salort-Campana</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santibanez-Koref</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thauvin</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barbarot</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Keavney</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>B&#x000e9;zieau</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mayosi</surname>
                    <given-names>BM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in FAM111B cause hereditary fibrosing poikiloderma with tendon contracture, myopathy, and pulmonary fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2013</year>
                <volume>93</volume>
                <fpage>1100</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24268661</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.otsu.2008.632">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Otsu</surname>
                    <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moriwaki</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iki</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nozaki</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horiguchi</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kiyokane</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Early blistering, poikiloderma, hypohidrosis, alopecia and exocrine pancreatic hypofunction: a peculiar variant of Rothmund-Thomson syndrome?</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Dermatol.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>18</volume>
                <fpage>632</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18952524</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.seo.2016.858">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seo</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Walsh</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>MK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ho</surname>
                    <given-names>PA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hsu</surname>
                    <given-names>EK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sidbury</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>King</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shimamura</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>FAM111B Mutation Is Associated With Inherited Exocrine Pancreatic Dysfunction.</article-title>
                <source>Pancreas.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>45</volume>
                <fpage>858</fpage>
                <lpage>62</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26495788</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hfpoik-tmp.REF.takeichi.2016">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Takeichi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nanda</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yang</surname>
                    <given-names>HS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hsu</surname>
                    <given-names>CK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>JY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Al-Ajmi</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Akiyama</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Simpson</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McGrath</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Syndromic inherited poikiloderma due to a de novo mutation in FAM111B.</article-title>
                <source>Br J Dermatol.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <month>Jul</month>
                <day>13</day>
                <comment>Epub ahead of print</comment>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27406236</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="hfpoik-tmp.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>13 October 2016 (bp) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>1 February 2016 (sm) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="hfpoik-tmp.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Facial and scalp skin lesionsA-E. Poikiloderma and alopecia of the scalp, eyebrows, and eyelashes in childhoodF. Improvement of the facial lesions in adulthood From <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al [2015]</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hfpoik-tmp-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="hfpoik-tmp.F2" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Skin lesions of the upper and lower limbsA. Eczema-like and psoriasis-like dermatosis of the upper limbsB. Hyperpigmented regionsC-F. Chronic lymphedema of lower limbs (D, E ) and hands (C, F)E, G. Diffuse skin lesions of the lower limbs and cellulitisFrom <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al [2015]</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hfpoik-tmp-Image002" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="hfpoik-tmp.F3" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 3. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Muscle MRI (coronal images of the thighs and calves; T<sub>1</sub>-weighted sequence) A. Diffuse bright appearance of the anterior compartment of the thighs (upper images), particularly in the vastus lateralis muscles, and the posterior compartment of the calves (lower images) in an individual age seven yearsB. Relative sparing of the posterior compartment of the thighs (upper images) in an individual age 30 years with severe disease C. Specific involvement of the vastus lateralis muscles (white asterisks) with sparing of other thigh muscles in an individual age 38 yearsFrom <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al [2015]</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hfpoik-tmp-Image003" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="hfpoik-tmp.F4" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 4<break/><break/></label>
          <caption>
            <p>A-D. Muscle histology:A, B. Fatty tissue, fragmented muscle fascicles next to normal fasciclesC, D. Nonspecific myopathic changes with variation in fiber size(hematoxylin and eosin staining [H&#x00026;E]; A: x20 magnification and B-D: x100) E-F. Skin histology:E. Epidermal atrophy, scleroderma-like features with diffuse mild collagen sclerosis (H&#x00026;E; x20 magnification)F. Elastic dystrophy with formation of elastic globules (arrowheads) in the papillary dermis (Weigert staining; x150) From <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hfpoik-tmp.REF.mercier.2015.135">Mercier et al [2015]</xref></p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hfpoik-tmp-Image004" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
