<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="hyper-nfj2" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">hyper-nfj2</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Autosomal Dominant Tubulointerstitial Kidney Disease, <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-Related</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonyms: ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>; Familial Juvenile Hyperuricemic Nephropathy Type 2; Early-Onset Hyperuricemia, Anemia, and Progressive Tubulointerstitial Nephropathy; FJHN2</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kmoch</surname>
            <given-names>Stanislav</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Institute for Inherited Metabolic Disorders<break/>Prague, Czech Republic</aff>
          <email>skmoch@lf1.cuni.cz</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>&#x0017d;ivn&#x000e1;</surname>
            <given-names>Martina</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Institute for Inherited Metabolic Disorders<break/>Prague, Czech Republic</aff>
          <email>mzivna@lf1.cuni.cz</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bleyer</surname>
            <given-names>Anthony J</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, MS</degrees>
          <aff>Wake Forest University School of Medicine<break/>Winston-Salem, North Carolina</aff>
          <email>ableyer@wfubmc.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2011-04-05" date-type="created">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2015-12-29" date-type="updated">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="mckd1" document-type="chapter">Autosomal Dominant Tubulointerstitial Kidney Disease, <italic toggle="yes">MUC1</italic>-Related</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="mckd2" document-type="chapter">Autosomal Dominant Tubulointerstitial Kidney Disease<italic toggle="yes">, UMOD</italic>-Related</related-object>
      <abstract id="hyper-nfj2.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease, <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-related (ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>) (previously familial juvenile hyperuricemic nephropathy type 2 [FJHN2]) is characterized by: hypoproliferative anemia with low hemoglobin concentrations, found in most affected children by age one year; hyperuricemia and gout, found in most (not all) affected individuals; and slowly progressive chronic tubulointerstitial kidney disease. Some affected children have polyuria (excessive urine production leading to frequent urination) and enuresis. Mildly elevated serum creatinine concentration and reduced estimated glomerular filtration rate in an asymptomatic child often progresses to end-stage renal disease (ESRD) in the fourth to sixth decades of life. Of note, information on only fourteen families with this condition has been published; better understanding of the disease is likely to emerge when more families are described.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>Diagnosis is based on findings of hypoproliferative anemia (low reticulocyte count relative to hemoglobin concentration and low erythropoietin concentration), hyperuricemia (serum uric acid concentration &#x0003e;6 mg/dL), decreased fractional excretion of urinary uric acid, bland urinary sediment, and low plasma renin activity. Kidney size is normal or small with no evidence of cyst formation. <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> (encoding renin) is the only gene in which mutation is known to cause ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Anemia may be reversed by erythropoietin; acute gout typically responds well to prednisone or colchicine. Treatment of low plasma renin activity/low plasma concentration of aldosterone may be indicated prior to the development of stage III chronic kidney disease. If hyperkalemia is present, treatment with fludrocortisone or potassium restriction may be indicated. When end-stage kidney disease develops, kidney transplantation can be performed. ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> does not recur in the transplanted kidney, which produces renin in a normal manner.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of primary manifestations:</italic> Treatment of hyperuricemia with allopurinol can prevent development of gout.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Measurement of hemoglobin concentration and serum concentration of uric acid and creatinine annually starting at the time of diagnosis.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medications, especially in persons who are dehydrated. Angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors could aggravate the underlying relative renin deficit. Volume depletion and dehydration as well as high meat and seafood intake could exacerbate gout. Patients should not be on the low sodium diet that is typically used in chronic kidney disease.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> If the <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, molecular genetic testing of at-risk relatives may be considered, particularly in: children because of their increased risk for anemia; adolescents because of their increased risk for gout, which can be prevented with appropriate treatment; and relatives considering kidney donation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Each child of an affected individual has a 50% chance of inheriting the pathogenic variant. Once the pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for at-risk pregnancies is possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>Autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease, <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-related (ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>) <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with the following clinical findings:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Hypoproliferative anemia</bold> with low hemoglobin concentrations, found in most affected children by age one year as a result of low erythropoietin production</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Hemoglobin concentrations can be low (usually 9-11 g/dL).</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Reticulocyte count is low relative to the hemoglobin concentration.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Erythropoietin concentration is low.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>All other hematologic aspects are normal.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Hyperuricemia and gout,</bold> found in most (not all) affected individuals as a result of decreased renal excretion of uric acid</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Hyperuricemia (serum uric acid concentration &#x0003e;6 mg/dL) is present in 80% of affected individuals beginning in childhood.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Usually, hyperuricemia in an individual with normal kidney function corresponds to a serum concentration of uric acid &#x0003e;1 SD of the normal value for age and sex (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati">Table 1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.wilcox.1996.731">Wilcox 1996</xref>].</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Fractional excretion of urinary uric acid is decreased in the vast majority of individuals with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri">Table 2</xref>).</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Slowly progressive chronic tubulointerstitial kidney disease</bold>
              </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Urinalysis reveals a bland urinary sediment (i.e., little blood or protein). Hematuria is generally not present, and excretion of protein is &#x0003c;1 g/24h except when kidney failure is advanced.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Plasma renin is low.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Plasma aldosterone is low.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Serum potassium is mildly elevated.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Renal ultrasound shows normal to small kidney size without cysts.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Kidney biopsy (see Note):Histologic examination reveals focal tubular atrophy, secondary glomerular scarring, and interstitial fibrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.zivn_.2009.204">Zivn&#x000e1; et al 2009</xref>]. Immunostaining for renin and prorenin is markedly decreased compared to control tissues in the granular cells of the juxtaglomerular apparatus and undetectable in the tubular epithelium early in the course of the disease. In advanced stages, neither the granular cells of the juxtaglomerular apparatus or the tubular epithelium stain for renin or prorenin. Note: Kidney biopsy should NOT be performed to establish a diagnosis of ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> because it is an invasive procedure with some risk and pathologic findings are too nonspecific to reliably identify the causative disorder. Molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hyper-nfj2.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">Establishing the Diagnosis</xref>), the gold standard for diagnosis, is safer and less expensive than kidney biopsy. However, some affected individuals (or their relatives) may have undergone kidney biopsy prior to consideration of ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> as a diagnostic possibility.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>
                <bold>Autosomal dominant inheritance</bold>
              </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Serum Uric Acid Concentration in Individuals with Normal Renal Function</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_1">Age</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Serum Concentration (mg/dL)</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Males</th>
                  <th headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2" id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;5 years</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6&#x000b1;0.9</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6&#x000b1;0.9</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-10 years</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#x000b1;1.0</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#x000b1;1.0</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 years</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#x000b1;1.1</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5&#x000b1;0.9</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 years</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6&#x000b1;1.1</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5&#x000b1;0.9</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;18 years</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2&#x000b1;0.8</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_1_2 hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.serum_uric_acid_concentrati_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#x000b1;0.7</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.mikkelsen.1965.242">Mikkelsen et al [1965]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.harkness.1969.773">Harkness &#x00026; Nicol [1969]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.wilcox.1996.731">Wilcox [1996]</xref></p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <table-wrap id="hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 2. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Fractional Excretion of Urinary Uric Acid in Individuals with Normal Renal Function</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_1" colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Age</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Deviation&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_1" colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">0-6 weeks</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.1%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_1" colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">6 weeks - 1 year</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.9%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_1" colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">1-3 years</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_1" colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">3-13 years</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">&#x0003e;13 years</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_1" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_1" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Male</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3%</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.fractional_excretion_of_uri_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.stib_rkov_.2006.1301">Stib&#x0016f;rkov&#x000e1; et al [2006]</xref>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>The fractional excretion of urinary uric acid can be calculated as follows:</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>urine uric acid concentration x serum creatinine concentration &#x000f7; <break/>serum uric acid concentration x urine creatinine concentration</bold>
                </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="hyper-nfj2.TF.2.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>A fractional excretion of urate &#x0003e;1 SD below the mean suggests reduced urate excretion.</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>
<bold>is established</bold> in a proband with the identification of a heterozygous pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> by molecular genetic testing (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="hyper-nfj2.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti">Table 3</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold>, use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>, and <bold>more comprehensive</bold>
<bold>genomic testing</bold>.</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> is performed.Note: Only pathogenic missense variants and/or small insertions/deletions affecting renin biosynthesis and trafficking are expected to cause ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>, therefore, deletion/duplication testing is not indicated.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hyper-nfj2.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered. Note: The genes included and sensitivity of multi-gene panels vary by laboratory and over time.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>More comprehensive genomic testing</bold> (when available) including whole-exome sequencing (WES), whole-genome sequencing (WGS), and whole mitochondrial sequencing (WMitoSeq) may be considered if serial single-gene testing (and/or use of a multi-gene panel) fails to confirm a diagnosis in an individual with features of ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>. For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="hyper-nfj2.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Autosomal Dominant Tubulointerstitial Kidney Disease, <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-Related (ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>)</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  <th id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with a Pathogenic Variant&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>
                  </td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_hyper-nfj2.T.summary_of_molecular_geneti_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/14 families&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="hyper-nfj2.TF.3.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="hyper-nfj2" object-id="hyper-nfj2.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="hyper-nfj2.TF.3.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hyper-nfj2.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="hyper-nfj2.TF.3.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="hyper-nfj2.TF.3.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.zivn_.2009.204">Zivn&#x000e1; et al [2009]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.bleyer.2010a.366">Bleyer et al [2010a]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.beck.2011.821">Beck et al [2011]</xref></p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>Fourteen families have been identified with autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease, <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-related (ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>); therefore, the spectrum of clinical manifestations may not yet be fully appreciated.</p>
          <p><bold>First decade of life.</bold> Children with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> may first be identified at age one year when a low hemoglobin concentration is identified during routine well child care. Although the children are asymptomatic, mild kidney failure may be evident on tests of renal function at that time.</p>
          <p>Affected but as-yet undiagnosed children placed on a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID) during a febrile illness may develop acute kidney failure due to the combination of low plasma renin activity, volume depletion, and prostaglandin inhibition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.bleyer.2010a.366">Bleyer et al 2010a</xref>]. Acute kidney failure usually resolves if treated appropriately, but chronic kidney failure and anemia may first be noted at that time.</p>
          <p>Hyperuricemia with a low fractional excretion of uric acid is present in childhood but is usually asymptomatic.</p>
          <p><bold>Second decade of life.</bold> As the child enters adolescence, the anemia resolves, and the hemoglobin concentration rises into the normal range.</p>
          <p>Elevated uric acid concentrations may result in gout. Gout is associated with the acute onset of pain and erythema in the big toe, forefoot, heel, knee, or other joints. The diagnosis of gout is often missed in this condition because the gout may occur in children or young women, whereas traditional gout occurs in middle-aged men. Gout should be treated acutely with prednisone or colchicine. Gout can be prevented with long-term administration of allopurinol.</p>
          <p>Some, but not all, affected individuals have:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Polyuria and excessive urine output due to decreased urinary concentrating ability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.bleyer.2010a.366">Bleyer et al 2010a</xref>]. Polyuria present in childhood persists into adulthood.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Mildly low blood pressure;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Mildly elevated serum potassium concentration.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Adulthood.</bold> Renal function slowly worsens over time. A mildly elevated serum creatinine concentration and reduced estimated glomerular filtration rate in an asymptomatic child often progresses to end-stage renal disease (ESRD) in the fourth to sixth decades of life. Renal replacement therapy may be necessary in the fourth through seventh decades of life. Kidney transplantation cures the condition.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.GenotypePhenotype_Correlation">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>No genotype-phenotype correlations are known at the present time.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>All affected individuals who have undergone genetic testing have been found to have anemia in childhood, hyperuricemia, and chronic kidney disease.</p>
          <p>Chronic kidney disease occurs in all affected individuals, although progression may be very slow, with ESRD occurring as late as the seventh decade in some individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>According to the 2015 nomenclature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.eckardt.2015.676">Eckardt et al 2015</xref>], the term &#x0201c;autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease&#x0201d; (ADTKD) refers to the following disorders characterized by: (1) autosomal dominant inheritance; (2) slowly progressive chronic tubulointerstitial kidney disease resulting in ESRD in the third through seventh decade of life; (3) urinalysis revealing a bland urinary sediment (i.e., little blood or protein); and (4) renal ultrasound examination that is normal early in the disease course [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.bleyer.2010a.366">Bleyer et al 2010a</xref>]:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease &#x02013; <italic toggle="yes">MUC1</italic>-related (ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">MUC1</italic>; previously known as <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mckd1" document-type="chapter">medullary cystic kidney disease type 1</related-object>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.kirby.2013.299">Kirby et al 2013</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease &#x02013; <italic toggle="yes">UMOD</italic>-related (ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">UMOD</italic>; previously known as <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mckd2" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">UMOD</italic>-associated kidney disease</related-object>, familial juvenile hyperuricemic nephropathy type 1, medullary cystic kidney disease type 2 [MCKD2], or uromodulin storage disease)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease &#x02013; <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-related (ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>; previously known as familial juvenile hyperuricemic nephropathy type 2 or <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-associated kidney disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.zivn_.2009.204">Zivn&#x000e1; et al 2009</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: (1) The term "nephronophthisis/medullary cystic kidney disease (NPH/MCKD) complex" was used in the past to refer to both autosomal recessive and autosomal dominant forms of hereditary chronic tubulointerstitial disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.hildebrandt.1992.802">Hildebrandt et al 1992</xref>]. Nephronophthisis is now used to refer to a group of conditions with autosomal recessive inheritance that present in childhood with chronic kidney failure. These conditions are caused by pathogenic variants in at least 12 different genes, denoted as nephrocystins (<italic toggle="yes">NPHP1</italic>- <italic toggle="yes">NPHP11</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">NPHP1L</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.wolf.2011.181">Wolf &#x00026; Hildebrandt 2011</xref>]. Clinical characteristics include polyuria, anemia, and slowly progressive kidney failure. See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nephron-ov" document-type="chapter">Nephronophthisis</related-object>. (2) Medullary sponge kidney (MSK), associated with calcifications of the medulla of the kidney, hypercalciuria, hematuria, and tubular acidification defects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.gambaro.2006.663">Gambaro et al 2006</xref>], is not in any way related to medullary cystic kidney disease.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>Autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease, <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-related (ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>) is extremely rare, with only approximately fourteen families having been identified world-wide. Several researchers who have studied inherited kidney disease in large numbers of families with inherited kidney disease have identified only a few families with this condition.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Genetically_Related_Allelic_D">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with heterozygous pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">REN.</italic></p>
        <p>Homozygosity or compound heterozygosity for loss-of-function (null) <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> variants results in grossly normal kidneys that show loss of proximal tubular differentiation. Autosomal recessive renal tubular dysgenesis is lethal in the perinatal period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.gribouval.2005.964">Gribouval et al 2005</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="hyper-nfj2.F1">Figure 1</xref> provides a flow diagram to aid in the differential diagnosis of inherited kidney disease.</p>
        <p><bold>Hereditary glomerulonephritis.</bold> Affected individuals usually have proteinuria and/or hematuria. If blood or protein is present in the urine, consider inherited glomerulonephritis (e.g., <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="alport" document-type="chapter">Alport syndrome</related-object>). Although rare individuals with <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mckd2" document-type="chapter">ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">UMOD</italic></related-object> have been found to have proteinuria, this is uncharacteristic.</p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pkd-ad" document-type="chapter"><bold>Autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease</bold></related-object>
<bold>(ADPKD).</bold> If the urinary sediment is bland (i.e., with little blood or protein) in persons with kidney disease inherited in an autosomal dominant manner, one must exclude ADPKD, in which a large number of cysts are seen on renal ultrasound examination in affected individuals older than age 25 years.</p>
        <p><bold>Other forms of ADTKD.</bold> If the individual does not have ADPKD and the urinary sediment is bland, the two other forms of autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease to consider are the following:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mckd1" document-type="chapter">ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">MUC1</italic></related-object> is associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">MUC1</italic>. Affected individuals have slowly progressive chronic kidney disease and minimal proteinuria. An important differentiating factor is that in ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">MUC1</italic> gout usually only occurs in the setting of stage III or later chronic kidney disease. Affected individuals do not suffer from anemia or other manifestations in childhood.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mckd2" document-type="chapter">ADTKD<italic toggle="yes">-UMOD</italic></related-object>. Like ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>, this condition is associated with slowly progressive chronic kidney disease. Persons with a <italic toggle="yes">UMOD</italic>-associated kidney disease do not have anemia in childhood and do not have the mild hyperkalemia often seen in ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nephron-ov" document-type="chapter"><bold>Nephronophthisis</bold></related-object>
<bold>(NPH)</bold> is an autosomal recessive form of tubulointerstitial kidney disease. Like ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>, it is often seen in childhood and can be associated with anemia and mild hypotension. The two conditions differ in three respects: (1) ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> is usually associated with a family history of kidney disease, anemia, and gout. In nephronophthisis, a positive family history would not be expected because the disorder is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. (2) Anemia in ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> will be present from infancy, whereas anemia in nephronophthisis usually correlates with the level of kidney function. (3) The severity of kidney failure is usually much greater in nephronophthisis, with affected individuals usually requiring dialysis in their teens and early twenties. In contrast, individuals with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> usually have an eGFR &#x0003e;50 mL/min into early adulthood. NPH is associated with pathogenic variants in one of at least 19 known genes.</p>
        <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fabry" document-type="chapter"><bold>Fabry disease</bold></related-object><bold>,</bold> an X-linked disorder, results from deficient activity of the enzyme &#x003b1;-galactosidase (&#x003b1;-Gal) A and progressive lysosomal deposition of globotriaosylceramide (GL-3) in cells throughout the body. The classic form, occurring in males with &#x0003c;1% &#x003b1;-Gal A activity, usually has its onset in childhood or adolescence with periodic crises of severe pain in the extremities (acroparesthesias), the appearance of vascular cutaneous lesions (angiokeratomas), hypohidrosis, characteristic corneal and lenticular opacities, and proteinuria (usually exceeding that seen in <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mckd2" document-type="chapter">ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">UMOD</italic></related-object>). Gradual deterioration of renal function to end-stage renal disease (ESRD) usually occurs in the third to fifth decade. Males with &#x0003e;1% &#x003b1;-Gal A activity have a cardiac or renal variant phenotype. Rarely, heterozygous carrier females may have symptoms as severe as those observed in males with the classic phenotype.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Evaluations_Following_Initial">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs of an individual diagnosed with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Hemoglobin concentration to document the level of anemia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Serum uric acid concentration to identify persons at risk for gout</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A 24-hour urine collection to quantify urine output and determine if polyuria is present (although this can usually determined by history). Clinical questioning regarding enuresis (bed-wetting) or frequent thirst or urination will help establish a diagnosis of polyuria.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A standard basic metabolic panel to determine if hyperkalemia is present</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p><bold>Anemia</bold> may be reversed by treatment with erythropoietin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.zivn_.2009.204">Zivn&#x000e1; et al 2009</xref>], a medication that is given subcutaneously and managed by hematologists or pediatric nephrologists. Dose is based on response to therapy. There is no clear target at this time and it is left to the discretion of the hematologist or nephrologist. Many children have relatively mild anemia with hemoglobin levels of 10 to 11 g/dL, and can be safely followed off of erythropoietin.</p>
          <p>Note: The dose of erythropoietin will need to be reduced as hemoglobin concentration increases during adolescence.</p>
          <p><bold>Hyperuricemia/gout.</bold> Gout typically responds well to prednisone or colchicine. One should not use of nonsteroidal agents in individuals with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> because the combination of nonsteroidal agents and the low renin state in patients with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> can lead to acute kidney injury; prednisone is the preferable alternative.</p>
          <p>Prevention of future gout attacks with allopurinol or probenecid should be considered in individuals with gout. With allopurinol treatment, serum uric acid concentration returns to normal and gout attacks can be entirely prevented. Lifelong therapy with allopurinol may be required. In individuals with allergies or intolerance to allopurinol, febuxostat may be considered; however, no data on the use of this medication in <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-associated kidney disease are available.</p>
          <p><bold>Hypotension and mild hyperkalemia</bold> may be present in children and young adults with this condition. As chronic kidney disease progresses to stage III chronic kidney disease, hypertension may develop, and hyperkalemia is due not to low plasma renin activity but rather to decreased elimination of potassium by the kidneys.</p>
          <p>Therefore, treatment of low plasma renin activity/plasma concentration of aldosterone may be indicated prior to the development of stage III chronic kidney disease. Such treatment may include liberal sodium intake if the patient has mild hypotension and hyperkalemia but preserved kidney function. Dietary sodium intake of 3-4 g/day may prevent hypotension. Note: A low-sodium diet should not be used in persons with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>.</p>
          <p>If hyperkalemia is present, treatment with fludrocortisone or potassium restriction may be indicated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.bleyer.2010b.411">Bleyer et al 2010b</xref>]. Fludrocortisone treatment (0.1 mg orally/day) of one affected child with low plasma renin activity resulted in a mild rise in blood pressure, correction of mild hyperkalemia, and a significant improvement in estimated glomerular filtration rate that may have been hemodynamically mediated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.bleyer.2010b.411">Bleyer at al 2010b</xref>]. The use of fludrocortisone may also prevent hypotension that could result from volume depletion such as that associated with viral syndromes or vigorous activities associated with excessive perspiration. Note: Fludrocortisone treatment in two adults with advanced kidney disease had no clinical effect [Author, personal observation].</p>
          <p>Fludrocortisone could have the advantage of decreasing renin production (through negative feedback), and thus the production of the abnormal renin deposits. However, since blockade of the renin angiotensin system and aldosterone production has been a general treatment of chronic kidney disease, it is possible that increased serum concentration of aldosterone may increase progression of renal disease. Thus, while the use of fludrocortisone may potentially be beneficial in this condition, at present its use is at the discretion of the clinician.</p>
          <p><bold>Mineralocorticoid replacement</bold>. Recommendations regarding treatment are not evidence based due to the small number of individuals with this disorder and the limited experience treating affected individuals.</p>
          <p><bold>Renal disease.</bold> Referral to a nephrologist is indicated to monitor kidney function, evaluate for manifestations of chronic kidney disease, and prepare for renal replacement therapy when renal insufficiency occurs.</p>
          <p>Renal replacement therapies such as hemodialysis and peritoneal dialysis replace renal function but are associated with potential complications.</p>
          <p>Kidney transplantation cures ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>. The transplanted kidney does not develop the disease.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Prevention_of_Primary_Manifes">
          <title>Prevention of Primary Manifestations</title>
          <p>Treatment with erythropoietin can reverse anemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.zivn_.2009.204">Zivn&#x000e1; et al 2009</xref>].</p>
          <p>Treatment of hyperuricemia with allopurinol can prevent development of gout.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Prevention_of_Secondary_Compl">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Iron stores should be replenished as needed to treat iron deficiency (an unrelated condition) if it is present.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Measure hemoglobin concentration and serum concentration of uric acid and creatinine annually starting at the time of diagnosis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>The use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medications (NSAIDs) should be avoided, especially in persons who are dehydrated. The use of NSAIDs in a febrile child with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> precipitated acute renal failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.bleyer.2010b.411">Bleyer et al 2010b</xref>]. The use of other analgesics/antipyretics should be considered.</p>
          <p>It would appear that the use of an angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor may not be beneficial in the treatment of chronic kidney failure and could aggravate the underlying relative renin deficit.</p>
          <p>Volume depletion and dehydration may worsen hyperuricemia and lead to more frequent attacks of gout.</p>
          <p>High meat and seafood intake could exacerbate gout.</p>
          <p>Exertion under extreme conditions (e.g., physical exertion when it is hot) should be avoided.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Ri">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>It is appropriate to evaluate apparently asymptomatic relatives of an affected individual by molecular genetic testing for the familial <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant in order to identify as early as possible those who would benefit from initiation of treatment and preventive measures. Particularly important are:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Children because of their increased risk for anemia;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Adolescents because of their increased risk for gout, which can be prevented with allopurinol treatment;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Relatives interested in donating a kidney to an affected family member.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hyper-nfj2.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Is">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Pregnancy_Management">
          <title>Pregnancy Management</title>
          <p>Successful pregnancies have been documented in women with a <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant. The rate of miscarriages or other adverse outcomes was not increased.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease, <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>-related (ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>) is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Most individuals diagnosed with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> have an affected parent.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A proband with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> may have the disorder as the result of a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant. Because simplex cases (i.e., a single occurrence in a family) have not been evaluated sufficiently to determine if the pathogenic variant was <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>, the proportion of ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> caused by <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variants is unknown.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Recommendations for the evaluation of parents of a proband with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant include molecular genetic testing of the parents.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in leukocyte DNA of either parent, two possible explanations are a <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant in the proband or germline mosaicism in a parent (although no instances of germline mosaicism have been reported, it remains a possibility).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>An apparently negative family history cannot be confirmed without molecular genetic testing for the familial <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Evaluation of parents may determine that one is affected but has escaped previous diagnosis because of failure by health care professionals to recognize the disorder and/or a milder phenotypic presentation.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Parents will usually have suffered from anemia in childhood, but they may not recall this from their childhood and/or the diagnosis of anemia may have been missed at that time.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Sibs of a proband.</bold> The risk to the sibs of the proband depends on the genetic status of the proband&#x02019;s parents:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband has the <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant, the risk to the sibs of inheriting the variant is 50%.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When the parents are clinically unaffected, the risk to the sibs of a proband appears to be low.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The sibs of a proband with apparently unaffected parents are still at increased risk for ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hyper-nfj2.Penetrance">Penetrance</xref>).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant found in the proband cannot be detected in the leukocyte DNA of either parent, the risk to sibs is low, but greater than that of the general population because of the possibility of germline mosaicism.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> Each child of an individual with ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> has a 50% chance of inheriting the <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> The risk to other family members depends on the status of the proband's parents: if a parent has the <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant, his or her family members may be at risk.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Is">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="hyper-nfj2.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Ri">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p><bold>Considerations in families with an apparent <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> pathogenic variant.</bold> When neither parent of a proband has ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>, the <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant is likely <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic>. However, possible non-medical explanations including alternate paternity or maternity (e.g., with assisted reproduction) or undisclosed adoption could be explored.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected or at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimpla">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing and preimplantation genetic diagnosis for a pregnancy at increased risk for ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> are possible options.</p>
          <p>Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions regarding prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesi">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>Renin is an aspartyl protease synthesized as preprorenin which contains a signal sequence that directs endoplasmic reticulum (ER) targeting, glycosylation, and proteolytic processing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.imai.1983.7405">Imai et al 1983</xref>]. Renin cleaves angiotensinogen to angiotensin, with the subsequent stimulation of aldosterone production. The renin angiotesin system (RAS) has been found to have widespread and diverse roles, including modulating vascular tone, renal sodium and potassium handling, erythropoiesis, thirst, cardiac hypertrophy, and functioning through local RAS systems in many organs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.paul.2006.747">Paul et al 2006</xref>].</p>
          <p>In vitro studies have shown that the presence of the mutated signal peptide affects renin targeting and cotranslational translocation of preprorenin into the ER and, thus, proper biosynthesis and intracellular trafficking of prorenin. This results in ER stress, cytosolic accumulation of abnormal non-glycosylated preprorenin, accelerated autophagocytosis, and reduced growth rate. In vivo this gradually reduces viability of renin-producing juxtaglomerular cells, and results &#x02013; by as-yet undefined mechanism(s) &#x02013; in tubular atrophy, nephron loss, and chronic kidney failure, similar to that observed in mice with ablated juxtaglomerular cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.pentz.2004.r474">Pentz et al 2004</xref>].</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variants also result in decreased renin production, a goal of therapy for many chronic kidney diseases. Thus, the disease becomes its own treatment.</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> is located on chromosome 1 (genomic position chr1:204123944-204135465; according to <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/cgi-bin/hgGateway?hgsid=190618133&#x00026;clade=mammal&#x00026;org=Human&#x00026;db=hg19">GRCh37/hg19 [Feb 2009] assembly</ext-link>). The gene comprises ten exons, which are transcribed into a 1493-bp long transcript encoding for 406 amino-acid preprorenin (reference sequence <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_000537.3">NM_000537.3</ext-link>). See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="hyper-nfj2" object-id="hyper-nfj2.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object> for a detailed summary of gene and protein information.</p>
          <p><bold>Benign allelic variants.</bold> Variants in the C-terminal part of the protein have not been associated with disease and are hypothesized to be benign [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hyper-nfj2.REF.villard.1994.30307">Villard et al 1994</xref>; Bleyer &#x00026; Kmoch, unpublished data].</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> Only pathogenic missense variants and/or small insertions/deletions affecting renin biosynthesis and trafficking are expected to cause ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>. Pathogenic variants in exons 1 and 2, the exons encoding the signal peptide and propeptide, are expected to account for most pathogenic variants that result in ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic>.</p>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> Renin is normally produced by modified juxtaglomerular cells of the afferent arterioles in the macula densa of the kidney. Renin cleaves the N-terminal ten amino acids of angiotensinogen to produce angiotensin I, which is further converted to angiotensin II by angiotensin-converting enzyme. Angiotensin II stimulates aldosterone production. Through a number of mechanisms, renin and angiotensin help to maintain normal blood pressure and to lower serum potassium concentrations into the normal range.</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> ADTKD-<italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> is caused by <italic toggle="yes">REN</italic> pathogenic variants predominantly in the signal sequence of the protein renin, affecting targeting and cotranslational translocation of preprorenin into the ER. This leads to reduced expression of renin and other components of the renin angiotensin system in kidney biopsy specimens of affected individuals. It is likely that expression of the mutated proteins has a dominant toxic effect gradually reducing the viability of renin-expressing cells. This alters the intrarenal renin-angiotensin system and the functionality of the juxtaglomerular apparatus, resulting in nephron dropout and progressive kidney failure.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="hyper-nfj2.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.beck.2011.821">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beck</surname>
                    <given-names>BB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Trachtman</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gitman</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miller</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sayer</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pannes</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baasner</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hildebrandt</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wolf</surname>
                    <given-names>MT</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Autosomal dominant mutation in the signal peptide of renin in a kindred with anemia, hyperuricemia, and CKD.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Kidney Dis.</source>
                <volume>58</volume>
                <fpage>821</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21903317</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.bleyer.2010a.366">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bleyer</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hart</surname>
                    <given-names>PS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kmoch</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010a</year>
                <article-title>Hereditary interstitial kidney disease.</article-title>
                <source>Semin Nephrol</source>
                <volume>30</volume>
                <fpage>366</fpage>
                <lpage>73</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20807609</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.bleyer.2010b.411">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bleyer</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zivn&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hulkov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hodanov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vyletal</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sikora</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zivny</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sovov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hart</surname>
                    <given-names>TC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adams</surname>
                    <given-names>JN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elleder</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kapp</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haws</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cornell</surname>
                    <given-names>LD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kmoch</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hart</surname>
                    <given-names>PS</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2010b</year>
                <article-title>Clinical and molecular characterization of a family with a dominant renin gene mutation and response to treatment with fludrocortisone.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Nephrol</source>
                <volume>74</volume>
                <fpage>411</fpage>
                <lpage>22</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21084044</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.eckardt.2015.676">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eckardt</surname>
                    <given-names>KU</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alper</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Antignac</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bleyer</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chauveau</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dahan</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Deltas</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hosking</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kmoch</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rampoldi</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wiesener</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wolf</surname>
                    <given-names>MT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Devuyst</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease: diagnosis, classification, and management--A KDIGO consensus report.</article-title>
                <source>Kidney Int.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>88</volume>
                <fpage>676</fpage>
                <lpage>83</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25738250</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.gambaro.2006.663">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gambaro</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feltrin</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lupo</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonfante</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>D&#x02019;Angelo</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Antonello</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Medullary sponge kidney (Lenarduzzi-Cacchi-Ricci disease): a Padua Medical School discovery in the 1930&#x02019;s.</article-title>
                <source>Kidney Int</source>
                <volume>69</volume>
                <fpage>663</fpage>
                <lpage>70</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16395272</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.gribouval.2005.964">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gribouval</surname>
                    <given-names>O</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gonzales</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Neuhaus</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aziza</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bieth</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laurent</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bouton</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Feuillet</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Makni</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ben Amar</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laube</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Delezoide</surname>
                    <given-names>AL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bouvier</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dijoud</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ollagnon-Roman</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roume</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Joubert</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Antignac</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gubler</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Mutations in genes in the renin-angiotensin system are associated with autosomal recessive renal tubular dysgenesis.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet</source>
                <volume>37</volume>
                <fpage>964</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16116425</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.harkness.1969.773">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harkness</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nicol</surname>
                    <given-names>AD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1969</year>
                <article-title>Plasma uric acid levels in children.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
                <volume>44</volume>
                <fpage>773</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5356987</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.hildebrandt.1992.802">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hildebrandt</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Waldherr</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kutt</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brandis</surname>
                    <given-names>M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>The nephronophthisis complex: clinical and genetic aspects.</article-title>
                <source>Clin Investig.</source>
                <year>1992</year>
                <volume>70</volume>
                <fpage>802</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1450635</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.imai.1983.7405">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Imai</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miyazaki</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hirose</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hori</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayashi</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kageyama</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ohkubo</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakanishi</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Murakami</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1983</year>
                <article-title>Cloning and sequence analysis of cDNA for human renin precursor.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source>
                <volume>80</volume>
                <fpage>7405</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6324167</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.kirby.2013.299">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kirby</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gnirke</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jaffe</surname>
                    <given-names>DB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bare&#x00161;ov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pochet</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blumenstiel</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ye</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aird</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stevens</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                    <given-names>JT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cabili</surname>
                    <given-names>MN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gat-Viks</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kelliher</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Daza</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DeFelice</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>H&#x0016f;lkov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sovov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vylet'al</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Antignac</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Guttman</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Handsaker</surname>
                    <given-names>RE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Perrin</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Steelman</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sigurdsson</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Scheinman</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sougnez</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cibulskis</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Parkin</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Green</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rossin</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zody</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Xavier</surname>
                    <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pollak</surname>
                    <given-names>MR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alper</surname>
                    <given-names>SL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lindblad-Toh</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gabriel</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hart</surname>
                    <given-names>PS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Regev</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nusbaum</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kmoch</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bleyer</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lander</surname>
                    <given-names>ES</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Daly</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2013</year>
                <article-title>Mutations causing medullary cystic kidney disease type 1 lie in a large VNTR in MUC1 missed by massively parallel sequencing.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet.</source>
                <volume>45</volume>
                <fpage>299</fpage>
                <lpage>303</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23396133</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.mikkelsen.1965.242">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mikkelsen</surname>
                    <given-names>WM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dodge</surname>
                    <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valkenburg</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1965</year>
                <article-title>The distribution of serum uric acid values in a population unselected as to gout or hyperuricemia: Tecumseh, Michigan 1959-1960.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Med</source>
                <volume>39</volume>
                <fpage>242</fpage>
                <lpage>51</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14320691</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.paul.2006.747">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Paul</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Poyan Mehr</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kreutz</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Physiology of local renin-angiotensin systems.</article-title>
                <source>Physiol Rev.</source>
                <volume>86</volume>
                <fpage>747</fpage>
                <lpage>803</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16816138</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.pentz.2004.r474">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pentz</surname>
                    <given-names>ES</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moyano</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thornhill</surname>
                    <given-names>BA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sequeira Lopez</surname>
                    <given-names>ML</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gomez</surname>
                    <given-names>RA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Ablation of renin-expressing juxtaglomerular cells results in a distinct kidney phenotype.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol.</source>
                <year>2004</year>
                <volume>286</volume>
                <fpage>R474</fpage>
                <lpage>83</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14563659</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.stib_rkov_.2006.1301">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stib&#x0016f;rkov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Posp&#x000ed;silov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kmoch</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sebesta</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Analysis of excretion fraction of uric acid.</article-title>
                <source>Nucleosides Nucleotides Nucleic Acids.</source>
                <year>2006</year>
                <volume>25</volume>
                <fpage>1301</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17065111</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.villard.1994.30307">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Villard</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lalau</surname>
                    <given-names>JD</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>van Hooft</surname>
                    <given-names>IS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Derkx</surname>
                    <given-names>FH</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houot</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pinet</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Corvol</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Soubrier</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1994</year>
                <article-title>A mutant renin gene in familial elevation of prorenin.</article-title>
                <source>J Biol Chem</source>
                <volume>269</volume>
                <fpage>30307</fpage>
                <lpage>12</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7982942</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.wilcox.1996.731">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wilcox</surname>
                    <given-names>WD</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>Abnormal serum uric acid levels in children.</article-title>
                <source>J Pediatr.</source>
                <volume>128</volume>
                <fpage>731</fpage>
                <lpage>41</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8648529</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.wolf.2011.181">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wolf</surname>
                    <given-names>MT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hildebrandt</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Nephronophthisis.</article-title>
                <source>Pediatr Nephrol.</source>
                <volume>26</volume>
                <fpage>181</fpage>
                <lpage>94</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20652329</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="hyper-nfj2.REF.zivn_.2009.204">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zivn&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>H&#x0016f;lkov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matignon</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hodanov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vylet'al</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kalb&#x000e1;cov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Baresov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sikora</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blazkov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zivn&#x000fd;</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Iv&#x000e1;nek</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Str&#x000e1;neck&#x000fd;</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sovov&#x000e1;</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Claes</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lerut</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fryns</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hart</surname>
                    <given-names>PS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hart</surname>
                    <given-names>TC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Adams</surname>
                    <given-names>JN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pawtowski</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clemessy</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gasc</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>G&#x000fc;bler</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Antignac</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Elleder</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kapp</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grimbert</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bleyer</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kmoch</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2009</year>
                <article-title>Dominant renin gene mutations associated with early-onset hyperuricemia, anemia, and chronic kidney failure.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <volume>85</volume>
                <fpage>204</fpage>
                <lpage>13</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19664745</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>Dr Stanislav Kmoch (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="skmoch@lf1.cuni.cz">skmoch@lf1.cuni.cz</email>) and Dr Anthony Bleyer (<email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="ableyer@wfubmc.edu">ableyer@wfubmc.edu</email>) are actively involved in clinical research regarding individuals with renin mutations and other forms of inherited kidney disease and would be happy to communicate with individuals who have any questions regarding diagnosis or other considerations.</p>
          <p>Related website: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wakehealth.edu/Nephrology/Gout-Kidney-Disease.htm">www.wakehealth.edu/Nephrology/Gout-Kidney-Disease.htm</ext-link></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="hyper-nfj2.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>29 December 2015 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>5 April 2011 (me) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>21 December 2010 (ab) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="hyper-nfj2.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Testing strategy for inherited kidney disease &#x02013; update 2015</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="hyper-nfj2-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
