<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="kss" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">kss</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Mitochondrial DNA Deletion Syndromes</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: mtDNA Deletion Syndromes</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>DiMauro</surname>
            <given-names>Salvatore</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Department of Neurology <break/>Columbia University Medical Center<break/>New York, New York</aff>
          <email>sd12@columbia.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hirano</surname>
            <given-names>Michio</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Department of Neurology<break/>Columbia University Medical Center<break/>New York, New York</aff>
          <email>mh29@columbia.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2003</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="updated">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="revised">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="milroy" document-type="chapter">Milroy Disease</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="narp" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial DNA-Associated Leigh Syndrome and NARP</related-object>
      <abstract id="kss.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) deletion syndromes predominantly comprise three overlapping phenotypes that are usually simplex (i.e., a single occurrence in a family), but rarely may be observed in different members of the same family or may evolve in a given individual over time. The three phenotypes are Kearns-Sayre syndrome (KSS), Pearson syndrome, and progressive external ophthalmoplegia (PEO). Rarely Leigh syndrome can be a manifestation of a mtDNA deletion. KSS is a multisystem disorder defined by the triad of onset before age 20 years, pigmentary retinopathy, and PEO. In addition, affected individuals have at least one of the following: cardiac conduction block, cerebrospinal fluid protein concentration greater than 100 mg/dL, or cerebellar ataxia. Onset is usually in childhood. Pearson syndrome is characterized by sideroblastic anemia and exocrine pancreas dysfunction and is usually fatal in infancy. PEO, characterized by ptosis, paralysis of the extraocular muscles (ophthalmoplegia), oropharyngeal weakness, and variably severe proximal limb weakness, is relatively benign.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>Diagnosis of mtDNA deletion syndromes relies on presence of characteristic clinical findings and, in KSS, changes on muscle biopsy (ragged-red fibers [RRF] with the modified Gomori trichrome stain, hyperactive fibers with the succinate dehydrogenase [SDH] stain, failure of both RRF and some non-RRF to stain with the histochemical reaction for cytochrome <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> oxidase [COX]) and decreased activity of respiratory chain complexes containing mtDNA-encoded subunits in muscle extracts. In Pearson syndrome, bone marrow examination reveals ringed sideroblasts, normoblasts with excessive deposits of iron in mitochondria detected by iron stains. Mitochondrial DNA deletion syndromes are caused by mtDNA deletions ranging in size from two to ten kilobases. Approximately 90% of individuals with KSS have a large-scale (i.e., 1.1- to 10-kb) mtDNA deletion that is usually present in all tissues; however, mutated mtDNA is often undetectable in blood cells, necessitating examination of muscle. In Pearson syndrome, mtDNA deletions are usually more abundant in blood than in other tissues. In PEO, mtDNA deletions are confined to skeletal muscle.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Placement of cardiac pacemakers in individuals with cardiac conduction blocks, eyelid slings for severe ptosis, cochlear implants and hearing aids for neurosensory hearing loss, hormone replacement for endocrinopathies, dilation of the upper esophageal sphincter to alleviate cricopharyngeal achalasia, folinic acid supplementation in individuals with KSS with low CSF folic acid, replacement of pancreatic enzymes in Pearson syndrome, administration of coenzyme Q<sub>10</sub> and L-carnitine, physical and occupational therapy, and treatment of depression.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of secondary complications:</italic> Antioxidants may ameliorate damage from reactive oxygen species; percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy may improve nutritional intake and prevent aspiration pneumonia in individuals with severe dysphagia.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance</italic>: ECG and echocardiogram every six to 12 months and yearly audiometry and endocrinologic evaluation.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Drugs potentially toxic to mitochondria, including chloramphenicol, aminoglycosides, linezolide, valproic acid, nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors. Dichloroacetate (DCA), a lactate-lowering agent, causes peripheral neuropathy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>Mitochondrial DNA deletion syndromes are caused by deletion of mtDNA and, when inherited, are transmitted by maternal inheritance. The father of a proband is not at risk of having the mtDNA pathogenic variant. The mother of a proband with a mtDNA deletion syndrome is usually unaffected and does not have mtDNA deletions in her tissues; therefore, the risk to the sibs of a proband is usually extremely low. Offspring of a female proband are usually not at risk of inheriting the pathogenic variant; however, exceptions occur. Offspring of males with a mtDNA pathogenic variant are not at risk. Although prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk is theoretically possible, interpretation of test results is difficult. If the mitochondrial deletions in the family are known, prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk is possible through laboratories offering either testing for the mitochondrial deletion of interest or custom testing.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="kss.GeneReview_Scope">
        <title><italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> Scope</title>
        <table-wrap id="kss.Tc" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_kss.Tc_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrial DNA Deletion Syndromes: Included Phenotypes</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_kss.Tc_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Kearns-Sayre syndrome (KSS)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Pearson syndrome</p></list-item><list-item><p>Progressive external ophthalmoplegia (PEO)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Leigh syndrome (mtDNA deletion)</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>For synonyms and outdated names see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="kss.Nomenclature">Nomenclature</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="kss.Clinical_Diagnosis">
          <title>Clinical Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) deletion syndromes comprise the three following overlapping phenotypes, which may be observed in different members of the same family or may evolve in a given individual over time:</p>
          <p><bold>Kearns-Sayre syndrome (KSS)</bold> is a multisystemic disorder defined by the following obligatory triad:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Onset before age 20 years</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Pigmentary retinopathy. Funduscopy reveals an atypical "salt and pepper" retinopathy; ERG often reveals retinal dystrophy; and visual field testing reveals normal visual fields. In KSS, the retinopathy is usually rod-cone dystrophy that seems to behave differently from other forms of retinitis pigmentosa [Author, personal observation].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Progressive external ophthalmoplegia (PEO)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>At least one of the following must also be present:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Cardiac conduction block</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Cerebrospinal fluid protein concentration greater than 100 mg/dL</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Cerebellar ataxia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.kearns.1958.280">Kearns &#x00026; Sayre 1958</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.rowland.1983">Rowland et al 1983</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Other frequent but not invariable clinical manifestations of KSS include short stature, hearing loss, dementia, limb weakness, diabetes mellitus, hypoparathyroidism, and growth hormone deficiency.</p>
          <p><bold>Pearson syndrome</bold> is a usually fatal disorder of infancy characterized by sideroblastic anemia and exocrine pancreas dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.r_tig.1990.1601">R&#x000f6;tig et al 1990</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Progressive external ophthalmoplegia (PEO)</bold> is a mitochondrial myopathy with drooping of the eyelids (ptosis), paralysis of the extraocular muscles (ophthalmoplegia), and variably severe proximal limb weakness.</p>
          <p>A few individuals with PEO have other manifestations of KSS but do not fulfill all the clinical criteria for the diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.rowland.1983">Rowland et al 1983</xref>]. This situation is called "KSS minus" or "PEO plus."</p>
          <p><bold>Leigh syndrome</bold>, characterized by lesions of the basal ganglia and brain stem, is an uncommon presentation of a mtDNA deletion.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Testing">
          <title>Testing</title>
          <p><bold>Kearns-Sayre syndrome</bold> and <bold>progressive external ophthalmoplegia</bold></p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Lactate and pyruvate concentrations</bold> in blood and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). Commonly elevated at rest and increase excessively in blood after moderate activity</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Electromyogram and nerve conduction studies.</bold> Consistent with a myopathy, but neuropathy may coexist</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Brain MRI.</bold> Sometimes shows leukoencephalopathy, often associated with cerebral or cerebellar atrophy or basal ganglia lesions</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Fasting serum glucose concentration to screen for diabetes mellitus</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Echocardiogram and electrocardiogram</bold> to evaluate cardiac conduction and contractility</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Muscle biopsy.</bold> Typically shows ragged-red fibers (RRF) with the modified Gomori trichrome stain and hyperactive fibers with the succinate dehydrogenase (SDH) stain. Both RRF and some non-RRF fail to stain with the histochemical reaction for cytochrome <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> oxidase (COX).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Biochemical studies of respiratory chain enzymes</bold> in muscle extracts. Usually show decreased activities of respiratory chain complexes containing mtDNA-encoded subunits, especially when enzyme values are referred to the activity of citrate synthase, a good marker of mitochondrial "mass" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.dimauro.2002.597">DiMauro et al 2002</xref>]. However, depending on the mutational load, biochemical studies may also be normal.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Pearson syndrome</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Sideroblastic anemia</bold> is defined by the presence of anemia and ringed sideroblasts in the bone marrow. Ringed sideroblasts are normoblasts with excessive deposits of iron in mitochondria and are detected by iron stains of bone marrow.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Exocrine pancreatic dysfunction</bold> is manifest clinically by excessive fat excretion in the stools (steatorrhea), which can be documented qualitatively by Sudan staining of the feces or quantitatively by measuring fecal fat. The gold standard is the secretin stimulation test, which requires placing a catheter in the duodenum and is difficult to perform in infants.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Leigh syndrome</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Brain MRI</bold> shows characteristic T<sub>2</sub>-weighted hyperintense lesions in the basal ganglia and midline brain stem.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <sec id="kss.Molecular_Genetic_Testing">
            <title>Molecular Genetic Testing</title>
            <p><bold>Gene.</bold> Deletions of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA), ranging in size from 1.1 to 10 kb, are associated with Kearns-Sayre syndrome, Pearson syndrome, progressive external ophthalmoplegia, and rarely Leigh syndrome.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>More than 150 different mtDNA deletions have been associated with KSS. A deletion of 4977 bp known as <xref ref-type="table" rid="kss.T.selected_mitochondrial_dna_deletio">m.8470_13446del4977</xref> is encountered most frequently ("common deletion") [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.schon.2003">Schon 2003</xref>].</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>The same <xref ref-type="table" rid="kss.T.selected_mitochondrial_dna_deletio">m.8470_13446del4977</xref> and numerous other types of deletions of varying length have been identified in Pearson syndrome and PEO.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Clinical testing.</bold> Duplication/deletion analysis identifies deletions/duplications not readily detectable by sequence analysis of genomic DNA. A variety of methods can be used (<xref ref-type="table" rid="kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi">Table 1</xref>, footnote 2).</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Southern blot</bold> (or other methodology)</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p><bold>Kearns-Sayre syndrome.</bold> Deletions can vary in size and abundance among affected individuals, but deleted mtDNA of a given length is present in each individual. Approximately 90% of individuals with KSS have a large-scale (i.e., 1.1- to 10-kb) mtDNA deletion.</p>
                    <p>Note: (1) Deletions are usually present in all tissues of individuals with KSS, and can be looked for in blood leukocytes. However, the occurrence of "heteroplasmy" in disorders of mtDNA can result in varying tissue distribution of "deleted" mtDNA. Since mutated mtDNA may be undetectable in blood cells, muscle biopsy may be necessary. (2) Large-scale duplications of mtDNA coexist with deletions in some individuals with KSS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.poulton.1989.236">Poulton et al 1989</xref>].</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p><bold>Pearson syndrome.</bold> Mitochondrial DNA deletions are usually more abundant in blood than in other tissues. The diagnosis of Pearson syndrome is reliably made in leukocyte DNA by Southern blot analysis or another type of analysis.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p><bold>Progressive external ophthalmoplegia (PEO).</bold> Mitochondrial DNA deletions are confined to skeletal muscle. The molecular diagnosis of PEO requires analysis of a muscle biopsy by Southern blot or another appropriate method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.moraes.1989.1293">Moraes et al 1989</xref>].</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p><bold>Leigh syndrome.</bold> Mitochondrial DNA deletions are detected in post-mitotic tissues such as muscle and brain, but not in blood or other replicating cells.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Long PCR analysis.</bold> Long PCR (also known as deletion-specific PCR) analysis detects deletions throughout the mtDNA; however, this method has high sensitivity and low specificity. Because mtDNA deletions accumulate normally with age, detection of the common deletion or of multiple deletions by PCR may lead to misdiagnosis. As a result, Southern blot analysis is the preferred method for diagnosis. It is advisable to consult with the testing laboratory about the method employed and its sensitivity and specificity.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <table-wrap id="kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 1. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Mitochondrial DNA Deletion Syndromes</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_1">Test Method</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_2">Pathogenic Variants Detected</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="3" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Variant Detection Frequency by Phenotype&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">KSS</th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEO</th>
                    <th headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3" id="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leigh syndrome</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duplication/deletion analysis&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrial DNA deletions&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3 hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90%&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3 hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_1_3 hd_h_kss.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testi_1_1_2_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;5%</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
              <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn id="kss.TF.1.1">
                  <label>1. </label>
                  <p>For KSS and Pearson syndrome, the detection rate is not 100% because rare individuals have syndromes that mimic KSS but are caused by other mtDNA pathogenic variants. For PEO, however, numerous pathogenic variants in either mtDNA or nuclear genes also cause PEO often associated with other manifestations. For Leigh syndrome, the detection rate is estimated at &#x0003c;5% of all Leigh syndrome [Author, personal observation].</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="kss.TF.1.2">
                  <label>2. </label>
                  <p>Testing that identifies partial or whole-gene deletions/duplications not readily detectable by sequence analysis of the coding and flanking intronic regions of genomic DNA; included in the variety of methods that may be used are: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and chromosomal microarray (CMA) that includes this gene/chromosome segment.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="kss.TF.1.3">
                  <label>3. </label>
                  <p>Usually deletions, but rarely duplications, and often the two rearrangements occurring together</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="kss.TF.1.4">
                  <label>4. </label>
                  <p>Detection frequency may depend on the methodology employed and vary among laboratories.</p>
                </fn>
              </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Testing_Strategy">
          <title>Testing Strategy</title>
          <p><bold>To confirm/establish the diagnosis in a proband.</bold> The clinical diagnosis must be confirmed by molecular studies documenting rearrangements (usually deletions, but rarely duplications, and often the two together) of mtDNA in leukocytes or muscle.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="kss.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <sec id="kss.KearnsSayre_Syndrome_KSS">
            <title>Kearns-Sayre Syndrome (KSS)</title>
            <p>KSS is a multisystem disorder affecting predominantly the central nervous system, skeletal muscle, and heart. Onset is usually in childhood, with ptosis, ophthalmoplegia, or both. Exercise intolerance and impaired night vision may be early symptoms. Dysphagia caused by oropharyngeal weakness, incomplete opening of the upper esophageal sphincter (cricopharyngeal achalasia), or both is common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.kornblum.2001.1409">Kornblum et al 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.aur_.2007.1516">Aur&#x000e9; et al 2007</xref>]. The disease usually progresses to death in young adulthood.</p>
            <p><bold>Central nervous system</bold> involvement is manifest by cerebellar ataxia, impaired intellect (intellectual disability, dementia, or both), and sensorineural hearing loss. Compared to other mitochondrial encephalomyopathies (e.g., <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="melas" document-type="chapter">MELAS</related-object>, <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="merrf" document-type="chapter">MERRF</related-object>, and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="narp" document-type="chapter">NARP</related-object>), KSS is notable for the extreme rarity of epilepsy. Strokes are also rare. In two individuals, strokes were attributed to cardiac emboli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.kosinski.1995.1950">Kosinski et al 1995</xref>, Provenzale &#x00026; Van Landingham 1996].</p>
            <p><bold>Muscle</bold> involvement is manifest by PEO, ptosis, oropharyngeal and esophageal dysfunction, exercise intolerance, and proximal more than distal limb muscle weakness. The defect of extraocular movement is usually symmetric but may cause blurred or double vision.</p>
            <p><bold>Heart</bold> involvement is characterized by conduction block, which can lead to complete heart block if a pacemaker is not placed in a timely fashion. Cardiomyopathy, less common than cardiac conduction block, has been reported in several individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.aur_.2007.1516">Aur&#x000e9; et al 2007</xref>].</p>
            <p><bold>Endocrinopathies</bold> are common in KSS and include diabetes mellitus, hypoparathyroidism, irregular menses, and growth hormone deficiency. The diabetes mellitus is caused by insufficient insulin secretion rather than a defect of insulin receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.piccolo.1989.163">Piccolo et al 1989</xref>]. Short stature may be the result of growth hormone deficiency.</p>
            <p><bold>Renal tubular acidosis</bold> can be part of KSS and in some cases is the presenting feature.</p>
            <p>The <bold>pigmentary retinopathy</bold> of KSS affects low-light vision more prominently than visual acuity; hence, affected individuals complain of difficulty with night vision. Peripheral vision may be compromised by ptosis. Vision generally deteriorates insidiously; therefore, the age at onset is often difficult to discern (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua">Table 2</xref>).</p>
            <table-wrap id="kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 2. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Signs and Symptoms in 86 Individuals with KSS</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sign or Symptom</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present/Evaluated</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Onset age &#x0003c;20 yrs</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86/86</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pigmentary retinopathy</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86/86</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEO</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86/86</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebellar syndrome</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53/63</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limb weakness</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61/65</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensorineural hearing loss</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33/34</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Impaired intellect</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/29</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes mellitus</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/86</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seizures</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/86</td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.signs_and_symptoms_in_86_individua_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2%</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
          <sec id="kss.Pearson_Syndrome">
            <title>Pearson Syndrome</title>
            <p>Pearson syndrome is often fatal in infancy. Individuals with Pearson syndrome who survive beyond infancy develop the symptoms and signs of KSS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.mcshane.1991.39">McShane et al 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.lee.2007.208">Lee et al 2007</xref>].</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="kss.Progressive_External_Ophthalmoplegia">
            <title>Progressive External Ophthalmoplegia (PEO)</title>
            <p>PEO is characterized by drooping of the eyelids (ptosis), paralysis of the extraocular muscles (ophthalmoplegia), and variably severe oropharyngeal and proximal limb weakness. The disorder is relatively benign and compatible with a normal life span.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="kss.Leigh_Syndrome">
            <title>Leigh Syndrome</title>
            <p>Leigh syndrome typically begins in infancy and is characterized by psychomotor regression or delay with manifestations of disease in the brain stem, basal ganglia, or both.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>No correlation exists between size or location of the mtDNA deletion and phenotype.</p>
          <p>For all mtDNA pathogenic variants, clinical expressivity depends on the three following factors:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The relative abundance of mutated mtDNA <bold>(heteroplasmy)</bold></p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The tissue distribution of the mutated mtDNAs</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The vulnerability of each tissue to impaired oxidative metabolism <bold>(threshold effect)</bold></p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>The tissue vulnerability threshold probably does not vary substantially among affected individuals, but variable mutational load and tissue distribution may account for the spectrum of clinical findings in individuals with KSS.</p>
          <p>The fact that mtDNA deletions are present in all tissues in individuals with KSS, are predominantly present in hematopoietic cells of individuals with Pearson syndrome, and are confined to skeletal muscle in PEO explains the different clinical phenotypes. The gradual decrease in mtDNA deletions in rapidly dividing blood cells and their gradual increase in post-mitotic tissues is an example of <bold>mitotic</bold>
<bold>segregation</bold> and explains how infants with Pearson syndrome may develop KSS later in life.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>In mtDNA-related disorders, penetrance is a function of the mutational load. As a general rule, heteroplasmic levels above 80%-90% cause mitochondrial dysfunction and clinical symptoms.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>The general terms for the neuromuscular disorders include progressive external ophthalmoplegia (PEO) and chronic progressive external ophthalmoplegia (CPEO).</p>
          <p>The multisystemic form is called Kearns-Sayre syndrome (KSS); in the past, KSS was also referred to as "ophthalmoplegia-plus," a term now used to describe individuals who have more than isolated myopathy but do not fulfill the canonical criteria for KSS.</p>
          <p>For Pearson syndrome, the term "Pearson marrow pancreas syndrome" is a synonym; the term "sideroblastic anemia and exocrine pancreatic dysfunction" is not currently used.</p>
          <p>Leigh syndrome has also been described as subacute necrotizing encephalomyelopathy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>An epidemiologic study of an adult population in the North East of England estimated the prevalence of large-scale mtDNA deletions at 1.2:100,000 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.schaefer.2008.35">Schaefer et al 2008</xref>].</p>
          <p>See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mt-overview" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial Disorders Overview</related-object> for general prevalence.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disorder">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No other phenotypes are known to be associated with single deletions of mtDNA. See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mt-overview" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial Disorders Overview</related-object>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p><bold>Ataxia.</bold> See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="ataxias" document-type="chapter">Hereditary Ataxia Overview</related-object>.</p>
        <p><bold>Sensorineural hearing loss.</bold> See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="deafness-overview" document-type="chapter">Hereditary Hearing Loss and Deafness Overview</related-object>.</p>
        <p><bold>Pigmentary retinopathy.</bold> See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="rp-overview" document-type="chapter">Retinitis Pigmentosa Overview</related-object>.</p>
        <p><bold>Sensorineural hearing loss and retinitis pigmentosa.</bold> See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="usher1" document-type="chapter">Usher Syndrome Type 1</related-object> and <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="usher2" document-type="chapter">Usher Syndrome Type 2</related-object>.</p>
        <p><bold>Progressive external ophthalmoplegia.</bold> KSS and PEO must be differentiated from other disorders associated with ophthalmoplegia. These include (with distinguishing features):</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Myasthenia gravis (fluctuating weakness and diplopia)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="opmd" document-type="chapter">Oculopharyngeal muscular dystrophy</related-object> (late onset, ptosis with mild ophthalmoparesis, severe dysphagia, autosomal dominant inheritance)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Oculopharyngodistal myopathy (onset in early adulthood, distal limb weakness, frequent respiratory muscle weakness, autosomal dominant or recessive inheritance)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="myotonic-d" document-type="chapter">Myotonic dystrophy type 1</related-object> (myotonia, autosomal dominant inheritance)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Myopathy caused by pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">MYH2</italic> encoding fast IIa myosin heavy chain (autosomal recessive childhood-onset myopathy with generalized and extraocular muscle weakness and minor progression)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Mendelian PEOs associated with multiple deletions of mtDNA caused by pathogenic variants in the following genes:</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC25A4</italic>, encoding ANT1</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">TWNK</italic> (previously known as <italic toggle="yes">C10orf2</italic>), encoding twinkle</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic> (previously known as <italic toggle="yes">POLG1</italic>), encoding the catalytic subunit of mtDNA polymerase (See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="alpers" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">POLG</italic>-Related Disorders</related-object>.)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">TYMP</italic> (previously known as <italic toggle="yes">ECGF1</italic>), encoding thymidine phosphorylase (autosomal recessive inheritance, CPEO, peripheral neuropathy and gastrointestinal dysmotility) (See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mngie" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial Neurogastrointestinal Encephalopathy Disease</related-object>.)</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><italic toggle="yes">OPA1</italic>, encoding a dynamin-related GTPase, causing autosomal dominant nonsyndromic optic atrophy and syndromic optic atrophy, CPEO, and deafness with variable other neurologic signs (See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="opa" document-type="chapter">Optic Atrophy Type 1</related-object>.)</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Maternally inherited PEOs caused by various mtDNA single-nucleotide variants (maternal inheritance) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.hirano.2001.2163">Hirano &#x00026; DiMauro 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.lamantea.2002.211">Lamantea et al 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.agostino.2003.1354">Agostino et al 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.filosto.2003.1279">Filosto et al 2003</xref>]</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold>Leigh syndrome</bold> has been associated with multiple pathogenic variants causing mitochondrial dysfunction including defects of the pyruvate dehydrogenase complex and deficiencies of respiratory chain enzymes. Autosomal recessive, X-linked, and maternally inherited forms have been reported (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="narp" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial DNA-Associated Leigh Syndrome and NARP</related-object>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="kss.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diagno">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease in an individual diagnosed with a mitochondrial DNA deletion syndrome, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Complete neurologic, cardiologic, ophthalmologic, and endocrinologic evaluations for KSS and PEO in children and adults</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Complete hematologic and gastroenterologic evaluations for Pearson syndrome in infants</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Complete neurologic, cardiac, gastrointestinal, endocrinologic, and renal evaluations for Leigh syndrome.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>The following are appropriate:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Placement of cardiac pacemaker in individuals with cardiac conduction block to reduce the risk of sudden death</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Placement of eyelid slings for severe ptosis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Cochlear implants and hearing aids for neurosensory hearing loss</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Hormone replacement for endocrinopathies</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Dilation of the upper esophageal sphincter to alleviate cricopharyngeal achalasia</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Folinic acid supplementation in individuals with KSS with low CSF folic acid</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Replacement of pancreatic enzymes in Pearson syndrome</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Administration of coenzyme Q<sub>10</sub> (50-200 mg 3x/day) and L-carnitine (330 mg 3x/day)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Physical and occupational therapy</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Treatment of depression</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ventilatory support for respiratory abnormalities in Leigh syndrome.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complication">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>Antioxidants may ameliorate damage from reactive oxygen species (ROS).</p>
          <p>Percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy (PEG) may improve nutritional intake and prevent aspiration pneumonia in individuals with severe dysphagia.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Surveillance includes the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>ECG and echocardiogram every six to 12 months to monitor cardiac conduction and contractility</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Yearly audiometry and endocrinologic evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Medications to avoid:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Drugs potentially toxic to mitochondria, including chloramphenicol, aminoglycosides, linezolide, valproic acid, nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Dichloroacetate (DCA) as a lactate-lowering agent, as DCA has been proven to cause peripheral neuropathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.kaufmann.2006.324">Kaufmann et al 2006</xref>]</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>Symptomatic maternal relatives should be screened for the specific mtDNA deletion.</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="kss.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions. Note: There may not be clinical trials for this disorder.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="kss.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>Mitochondrial DNA deletion syndromes are caused by deletion of mtDNA and, when inherited, are transmitted by maternal inheritance.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Risk_to_Family_Members">
          <title>Risk to Family Members</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The father of a proband is not at risk of having the mtDNA pathogenic variant.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The mother of a proband with a mtDNA deletion syndrome is usually unaffected and does not have mtDNA deletions in her tissues.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>The mtDNA deletion is usually <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> in the proband, occurring either in the mother's oocyte or during embryogenesis.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to the sibs of a proband is usually extremely low.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the mother and one child are affected, the risk to other children is very low: thus far, maternal transmission to more than one child has not been reported.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Offspring of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Affected women have a small but finite chance of having an affected child, calculated to be approximately one in 24 births [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.chinnery.2004.592">Chinnery et al 2004</xref>].</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Offspring of males with a mtDNA pathogenic variant are not at risk.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Other family members of a proband</bold>. The risk to other family members of being affected or of having a mtDNA deletion is extremely low.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Prenatal_Testing">
          <title>Prenatal Testing</title>
          <p>Prenatal testing is possible; however, accurate interpretation of prenatal diagnostic results of a mtDNA pathogenic variant is extremely problematic. Because of mitotic segregation, the mtDNA mutational load in amniocytes and chorionic villi is unlikely to correspond to that of other fetal or adult tissues.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="kss.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>Mitochondrial DNA deletion syndromes are almost never inherited, suggesting that these disorders are caused by <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> mtDNA deletions that occur in the mother's oocytes during germline development or in the embryo during embryogenesis. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.chen.1995.239">Chen et al [1995]</xref> showed that the "common deletion" (m.8470_13446del4977) accounted for 0.1% of the approximately 150,000 mtDNAs in a human oocyte. A "bottleneck" between oocyte and embryo allows only a minority of maternal mtDNAs to populate the fetus. On rare occasions, a "deleted" mtDNA may slip through. From the blastocyst, deleted mtDNAs can enter all three germ layers and cause KSS, segregate predominantly to the hematopoietic lineage and cause Pearson syndrome, or segregate to muscle and cause PEO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.dimauro.2003.2656">DiMauro &#x00026; Schon 2003</xref>].</p>
          <p>The origin of mtDNA deletions is uncertain. However, it has been noted that deletions fall into two classes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.mita.1990.561">Mita et al 1990</xref>]:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Class I pathogenic variants are flanked by perfect direct repeats.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Class II pathogenic variants are not flanked by any unique elements.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Homologous recombination or slipped mispairing (i.e., unequal crossing over) may explain the origin of class I deletions; the genesis of class II deletions remains unknown. The fact that a mtDNA deletion of a given length is found in a given individual implies that the population of deleted mtDNAs is a clonal expansion of a single mutation event that occurred early in oogenesis or in embryogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.schon.2003">Schon 2003</xref>]. The hypothesis of clonality implies that a single rearranged molecule present in the oocyte or the embryo multiplies wildly to form the trillions of deleted mtDNAs in the affected individual. How the selective amplification of deleted mtDNAs occurs is currently unknown, but the bottleneck concept described above may provide an answer.</p>
          <p><bold>Benign variants.</bold> See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mt-overview" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial Disorders Overview</related-object>.</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> Deletions can vary in size and abundance among affected individuals, but deleted mtDNA of a given length is present in each individual. Approximately 90% of individuals with KSS have a large-scale (i.e., 1.1- to 10-kb) mtDNA deletion. The "common deletion" (m.8470_13446del4977) is present in about one third of affected individuals.</p>
          <table-wrap id="kss.T.selected_mitochondrial_dna_deletio" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Selected Mitochondrial DNA Deletion Syndrome Pathogenic Variants</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_kss.T.selected_mitochondrial_dna_deletio_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change <break/>(Alias&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup>)</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_kss.T.selected_mitochondrial_dna_deletio_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_kss.T.selected_mitochondrial_dna_deletio_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequence</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.selected_mitochondrial_dna_deletio_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">m.8470_13446del4977<break/>(4977-bp deletion)</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.selected_mitochondrial_dna_deletio_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_kss.T.selected_mitochondrial_dna_deletio_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NC_012920?log$=seqview_status">NC_012920.1</ext-link>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="kss.TF.3.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>Variant designation that does not conform to current naming conventions</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mt-overview" document-type="chapter">Mitochondrial Disorders Overview</related-object>.</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> The similarly deleterious effects of different mtDNA deletions can be explained by the fact that even the smallest mtDNA deletion encompasses several tRNA genes; thus, "deleted" mtDNAs are transcribed into RNA in the usual way, but the processed transcript encoding polypeptides is not translated because the deletions remove essential tRNAs needed for protein synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="kss.REF.schon.2003">Schon 2003</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="kss.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="kss.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="kss.REF.agostino.2003.1354">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Agostino</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valletta</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chinnery</surname>
                    <given-names>PF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ferrari</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrara</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>RW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Turnbull</surname>
                    <given-names>DM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tiranti</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeviani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Mutations of ANT1, Twinkle, and POLG1 in sporadic progressive external ophthalmoplegia (PEO).</article-title>
                <source>Neurology</source>
                <volume>60</volume>
                <fpage>1354</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12707443</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.aur_.2007.1516">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aur&#x000e9;</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ogier de Baulny</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laforet</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jardel</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eymard</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lombes</surname>
                    <given-names>A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Chronic progressive ophthalmoplegia with large-scale mtDNA rearrangement: can we predict progression?</article-title>
                <source>Brain.</source>
                <volume>130</volume>
                <fpage>1516</fpage>
                <lpage>24</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17439982</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.chen.1995.239">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prosser</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Simonetti</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sadlock</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jagiello</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schon</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1995</year>
                <article-title>Rearranged mitochondrial genomes are present in human oocytes.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>57</volume>
                <fpage>239</fpage>
                <lpage>47</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7668249</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.chinnery.2004.592">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chinnery</surname>
                    <given-names>PF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shanske</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schon</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeviani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mariotti</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carrara</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lombes</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laforet</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ogier</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jaksch</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lochmuller</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Horvath</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Deschauer</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thorburn</surname>
                    <given-names>DR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bindoff</surname>
                    <given-names>LA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Poulton</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>RW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Matthews</surname>
                    <given-names>JN</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Turnbull</surname>
                    <given-names>DM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2004</year>
                <article-title>Risk of developing a mitochondrial DNA deletion disorder.</article-title>
                <source>Lancet</source>
                <volume>364</volume>
                <fpage>592</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15313359</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.dimauro.2003.2656">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schon</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Mitochondrial respiratory-chain diseases.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>348</volume>
                <fpage>2656</fpage>
                <lpage>68</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12826641</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.dimauro.2002.597">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tanji</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonilla</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pallotti</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schon</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>Mitochondrial abnormalities in muscle and other aging cells: classification, causes, and effects.</article-title>
                <source>Muscle Nerve</source>
                <volume>26</volume>
                <fpage>597</fpage>
                <lpage>607</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12402281</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.filosto.2003.1279">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Filosto</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mancuso</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishigaki</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pancrudo</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harati</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gooch</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mankodi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bayne</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonilla</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shanske</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hirano</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2003</year>
                <article-title>Clinical and genetic heterogeneity in progressive external ophthalmoplegia due to mutations in polymerase gamma.</article-title>
                <source>Arch Neurol</source>
                <volume>60</volume>
                <fpage>1279</fpage>
                <lpage>84</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12975295</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.hirano.2001.2163">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hirano</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>ANT1, Twinkle, POLG, and TP: new genes open our eyes to ophthalmoplegia.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology</source>
                <volume>57</volume>
                <fpage>2163</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11756592</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.kaufmann.2006.324">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaufmann</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Engelstad</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wei</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jhung</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sano</surname>
                    <given-names>MC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shungu</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Millar</surname>
                    <given-names>WS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hong</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gooch</surname>
                    <given-names>CL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mao</surname>
                    <given-names>X</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pascual</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hirano</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Stacpoole</surname>
                    <given-names>PW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>De Vivo</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Dichloroacetate causes toxic neuropathy in MELAS: a randomized, controlled clinical trial.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology</source>
                <volume>66</volume>
                <fpage>324</fpage>
                <lpage>30</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16476929</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.kearns.1958.280">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kearns</surname>
                    <given-names>TP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sayre</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1958</year>
                <article-title>Retinitis pigmentosa, external ophthalmophegia, and complete heart block: unusual syndrome with histologic study in one of two cases.</article-title>
                <source>AMA Arch Ophthalmol</source>
                <volume>60</volume>
                <fpage>280</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13558799</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.kornblum.2001.1409">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kornblum</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Broicher</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Walther</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Seibel</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reichmann</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Klockgether</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Herberhold</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schroder</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>Cricopharyngeal achalasia is a common cause of dysphagia in patients with mtDNA deletions.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology</source>
                <volume>56</volume>
                <fpage>1409</fpage>
                <lpage>12</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11376201</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.kosinski.1995.1950">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kosinski</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mull</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lethen</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Topper</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1995</year>
                <article-title>Evidence for cardioembolic stroke in a case of Kearns-Sayre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Stroke</source>
                <volume>26</volume>
                <fpage>1950</fpage>
                <lpage>2</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7570754</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.lamantea.2002.211">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lamantea</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tiranti</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bordoni</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Toscano</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bono</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Servidei</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Papadimitriou</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spelbrink</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Silvestri</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Casari</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Comi</surname>
                    <given-names>GP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeviani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>Mutations of mitochondrial DNA polymerase gammaA are a frequent cause of autosomal dominant or recessive progressive external ophthalmoplegia.</article-title>
                <source>Ann Neurol</source>
                <volume>52</volume>
                <fpage>211</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12210792</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.lee.2007.208">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>HF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chi</surname>
                    <given-names>CS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tsai</surname>
                    <given-names>CR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chang</surname>
                    <given-names>TK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>The neurological evolution of Pearson syndrome: case report and literature review.</article-title>
                <source>Eur J Paediatr Neurol.</source>
                <volume>11</volume>
                <fpage>208</fpage>
                <lpage>14</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17434771</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.mcshane.1991.39">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McShane</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hammans</surname>
                    <given-names>SR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sweeney</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Holt</surname>
                    <given-names>IJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Beattie</surname>
                    <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brett</surname>
                    <given-names>EM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Harding</surname>
                    <given-names>AE</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1991</year>
                <article-title>Pearson syndrome and mitochondrial encephalomyopathy in a patient with a deletion of mtDNA.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
                <volume>48</volume>
                <fpage>39</fpage>
                <lpage>42</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1985462</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.mita.1990.561">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mita</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rizzuto</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moraes</surname>
                    <given-names>CT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shanske</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arnaudo</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fabrizi</surname>
                    <given-names>GM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koga</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schon</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1990</year>
                <article-title>Recombination via flanking direct repeats is a major cause of large-scale deletions of human mitochondrial DNA.</article-title>
                <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
                <volume>18</volume>
                <fpage>561</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2308845</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.moraes.1989.1293">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Moraes</surname>
                    <given-names>CT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zeviani</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lombes</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shanske</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Miranda</surname>
                    <given-names>AF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakase</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonilla</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Werneck</surname>
                    <given-names>LC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Servidei</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nonaka</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Koga</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spiro</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Brownell</surname>
                    <given-names>AKW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schotland</surname>
                    <given-names>DL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zupanc</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DeVivo</surname>
                    <given-names>DC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schon</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rowland</surname>
                    <given-names>LP</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mitochondrial DNA deletions in progressive external ophthalmoplegia and Kearns-Sayre syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med.</source>
                <year>1989</year>
                <volume>320</volume>
                <fpage>1293</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2541333</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.piccolo.1989.163">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Piccolo</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aschei</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ricordi</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Banfi</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lo Curto</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fratino</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1989</year>
                <article-title>Normal insulin receptors in mitochondrial myopathies with ophthalmoplegia.</article-title>
                <source>J Neurol Sci</source>
                <volume>94</volume>
                <fpage>163</fpage>
                <lpage>72</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2614464</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.poulton.1989.236">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Poulton</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Deadman</surname>
                    <given-names>ME</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gardiner</surname>
                    <given-names>RM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1989</year>
                <article-title>Duplications of mitochondrial DNA in mitochondrial myopathy.</article-title>
                <source>Lancet</source>
                <volume>1</volume>
                <fpage>236</fpage>
                <lpage>40</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2563411</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.provenzale.1996.826">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Provenzale</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>VanLandingham</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1996</year>
                <article-title>Cerebral infarction associated with Kearns-Sayre syndrome-related cardiomyopathy.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology</source>
                <volume>46</volume>
                <fpage>826</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8618693</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.r_tig.1990.1601">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>R&#x000f6;tig</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cormier</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blanche</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bonnefont</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ledeist</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Romero</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schmitz</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rustin</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Fischer</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Saudubray</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>1990</year>
                <article-title>Pearson's marrow-pancreas syndrome. A multisystem mitochondrial disorder in infancy.</article-title>
                <source>J Clin Invest</source>
                <volume>86</volume>
                <fpage>1601</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2243133</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.rowland.1983">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Rowland LP, Hays AP, DiMauro S, De Vivo DC, Behrens M. Diverse clinical disorders associated with morphological abnormalities in mitochondria. In: Scarlato G, Cerri C, eds. <italic toggle="yes">Mitochondrial Pathology in Muscle Diseases.</italic> Padua, Italy: Piccin; 1983:141-58.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.schaefer.2008.35">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schaefer</surname>
                    <given-names>AM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McFarland</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Blakely</surname>
                    <given-names>EL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>He</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Whittaker</surname>
                    <given-names>RG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>RW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chinnery</surname>
                    <given-names>PF</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Turnbull</surname>
                    <given-names>DM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Prevalence of mitochondrial DNA disease in adults.</article-title>
                <source>Ann Neurol.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>63</volume>
                <fpage>35</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17886296</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.schon.2003">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Schon EA. Rearrangements of mitochondrial DNA. In: Holt I, ed. <italic toggle="yes">Genetics of Mitochondrial Diseases.</italic> Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press; 2003:111-24.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="kss.Suggested_Reading">
          <title>Suggested Reading</title>
          <ref-list id="kss.Suggested_Reading.reflist0">
            <ref id="kss.REF.dimauro.2008.91">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>DiMauro</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Schon</surname>
                    <given-names>EA</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Mitochondrial disorders in the nervous system.</article-title>
                <source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
                <volume>31</volume>
                <fpage>91</fpage>
                <lpage>123</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18333761</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.hirano.2010">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="web">Hirano M. Kearns-Sayre syndrome. In: Gilman S, editor-in-chief. <italic toggle="yes">Medlink Neurology</italic>. San Diego: Medlink Corporation. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medlink.com/">online</ext-link> (subscription required). 2010.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="kss.REF.yamashita.2008.598">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yamashita</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishino</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nonaka</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goto</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Genotype and phenotype analyses in 136 patients with single large-scale mitochondrial DNA deletions.</article-title>
                <source>J Hum Genet.</source>
                <volume>53</volume>
                <fpage>598</fpage>
                <lpage>606</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18414780</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="kss.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="kss.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>3 May 2011 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>19 April 2007 (sdm) Revision: prenatal testing available on a clinical basis</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>8 February 2006 (me) Comprehensive update posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>17 December 2003 (me) Review posted to live Web site</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>17 July 2003 (sdm) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
