<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="pf" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">pf</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>Pulmonary Fibrosis, Familial</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: Familial Interstitial
Pneumonia</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Talbert</surname>
            <given-names>Janet L</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS, CGC</degrees>
          <email>janet.talbert@ucdenver.edu</email>
          <aff>University of Colorado Denver<break/>Aurora, Colorado<break/>National Jewish
Health<break/>Denver, Colorado </aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Schwartz</surname>
            <given-names>David A</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <email>david.schwartz@ucdenver.edu</email>
          <aff>University of Colorado Denver<break/>Aurora, Colorado<break/>National Jewish
Health<break/>Denver, Colorado</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date iso-8601-date="2005-01-21" date-type="created">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2015-03-19" date-type="updated">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date iso-8601-date="2009-02-03" date-type="revised">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="pxe" document-type="chapter">Pseudoxanthoma Elasticum</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="pds" document-type="chapter">Pyridoxine-Dependent Epilepsy</related-object>
      <abstract id="pf.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>Familial pulmonary fibrosis (FPF in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>) is defined
as idiopathic interstitial pneumonia (IIP) in two or more first-degree relatives
(parent, sib, or offspring). Up to 20% of cases of IIP cluster in families. The
clinical findings of IIP are bibasilar reticular abnormalities, ground glass
opacities, or diffuse nodular lesions on high-resolution computed tomography and
abnormal pulmonary function studies that include evidence of restriction
(reduced VC with an increase in FEV1/FVC ratio) and/or impaired gas exchange
(increased P<sub>(A-a)</sub>O<sub>2</sub> with rest or exercise or decreased
diffusion capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide [DLCO]). FPF usually presents
between ages 50 and 70 years. FPF may be complicated by lung cancer;
bronchoalveolar cell carcinoma, small-cell carcinoma, and adenocarcinoma have
been described.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of FPF is based on established clinical diagnostic criteria. Some,
but not all of the loci/genes associated with FPF are known. Pathogenic variants
in <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>, and
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> have been identified in about 8%-15% of individuals
with FPF and 1%-3% of simplex cases (i.e., a single occurrence in a family) of
IIP. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Management of FPF and IIP is
similar and depends on the type of IIP diagnosed in an individual; oxygen
therapy may improve exercise tolerance in those with hypoxemia; lung
transplantation may be considered, particularly in those who are unresponsive to
immunosuppressive therapy, have significant functional impairment, and have no
other major illnesses that would preclude transplantation. Generally,
pharmacologic interventions have not been shown to alter the course of IPF
(idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, the most common form of IIP) or FPF; however,
antifibrotic treatments have been shown in clinical trials to slow the decline
in lung function in IPF.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> The frequency of follow-up evaluations depends on
the patient-specific diagnosis and status; those who are stable may be
reevaluated every three to six months, while others may need more frequent
follow up. </p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic> Cigarette smoking. </p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> Every five years, in
asymptomatic first-degree relatives (of an individual with FPF) age &#x0003e;50
years: pulmonary function tests, high-resolution computed tomography scan of the
chest to detect early abnormalities, and standardized questionnaire to assess
the presence of respiratory symptoms. Family members who have a positive screen
(i.e., at least class 2 dyspnea [breathlessness when hurrying on a level surface
or walking up a slight hill], a DL<sub>CO</sub> below 80% of predicted, or
presence of at least ILO category I findings on chest x-ray) require further
evaluation. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>The inheritance of familial pulmonary fibrosis is not clear. Complex inheritance
including autosomal dominant inheritance with reduced penetrance appears likely,
though autosomal recessive inheritance remains a possibility. Prenatal diagnosis
is possible for pregnancies at increased risk in families in which the
<italic toggle="yes">TERT,</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">TERC, SFTPC</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> pathogenic variant has
been identified; however, the predictive value of such test results is as yet
unclear. </p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="pf.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <p>Familial pulmonary fibrosis (FPF) is defined as idiopathic interstitial pneumonia
(IIP) in two or more first-degree relatives (parent, sib, or offspring).
Confirmation of the diagnosis of IIP is the first step in making the diagnosis of
FPF. </p>
        <sec id="pf.Findings_Suggestive_of_Idiopathic_Int">
          <title>Findings Suggestive of Idiopathic Interstitial Pneumonia (IIP) </title>
          <p>Diagnosis of idiopathic interstitial pneumonia (IIP) should be
<bold>suspected</bold> in individuals with the presence of at least three of
the following four criteria: </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Age older than 50 years </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Insidious onset of otherwise unexplained dyspnea on exertion </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Duration of illness &#x02265;3 months </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Bibasilar, inspiratory crackles (dry or "velcro"-type in quality) </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Establishing_the_Diagnosis_of_IIP">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis of IIP</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of IIP is established by the presence of all of the following
findings, based on criteria published as a consensus statement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.american_thoracic_society.2000.646">American
Thoracic Society 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.american_thoracic_society.2002.277">American Thoracic
Society &#x00026; European Respiratory Society
2002</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.raghu.2011.788">Raghu et al 2011</xref>]
and approved by the American Thoracic Society, the American College of Chest
Physicians, and the European Respiratory Society: </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>No significant exposure to environmental agents</bold> (e.g.,
asbestos, silica, metal dust, wood dust); no findings suggestive of
hypersensitivity pneumonitis; no history of chronic infection or left
ventricular failure; no evidence of collagen vascular disease (e.g.,
scleroderma or systemic lupus erythematosus); and no previous exposure
to drugs associated with pulmonary fibrosis (e.g., bleomycin,
methotrexate, cyclophosphamide, nitrofurantoin) in an individual who is
immunocompetent </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Abnormal pulmonary function studies</bold> that include evidence of
restriction (reduced VC with an increase in FEV1/FVC ratio) and/or
impaired gas exchange (increased P<sub>(A-a)</sub>O<sub>2</sub> with
rest or exercise or decreased carbon monoxide diffusing capacity
[DL<sub>CO</sub>]) </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>A high-resolution computed tomography (HRCT) scan</bold> in the
prone position (one 1.5-mm image every 2 cm from the apex to the base of
the lungs) that demonstrates bibasilar reticular abnormalities with or
without ground glass opacities </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Either</bold> of the following criteria: </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>A surgical lung biopsy</bold> that demonstrates a
histologic pattern consistent with one of the forms of IIP
(i.e., usual interstitial pneumonia [UIP], nonspecific
interstitial pneumonia [NSIP], acute interstitial pneumonia
[AIP], cryptogenic organizing pneumonia [COP], respiratory
bronchiolitis interstitial lung disease [RB-ILD], or
desquamative interstitial pneumonia [DIP]) and cultures of the
biopsies that are negative for bacteria, mycobacterium, and
fungi</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p><bold>A transbronchial biopsy or bronchoalveolar lavage</bold>
(BAL) that excludes alternative diagnoses </p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Multidisciplinary team discussion</bold> to include radiologists,
pathologists, and pulmonologists is strongly recommended.</p>
          <p>The different forms of IIP that can be associated with FPF are as follows (listed
in order of relative frequency): </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF)/cryptogenic fibrosing alveolitis
(CFA)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Nonspecific interstitial pneumonitis (NSIP) </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Cryptogenic organizing pneumonia (COP) </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Acute interstitial pneumonia (AIP; also called Hamman-Rich syndrome)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Respiratory bronchiolitis associated interstitial lung disease (RB-ILD)
</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Desquamative interstitial pneumonitis (DIP)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Lymphocytic interstitial pneumonitis (LIP) </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) is the most common form of IIP and is present
in approximately 55% of families with FPF. Approximately 45% of families with
FPF are heterogeneous for the other subtypes of IIP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.steele.2005.1146">Steele et al 2005</xref>]. Achieving a correct
diagnosis is a dynamic process based on the criteria listed above. The final
diagnosis should be rendered only after the pulmonologist, radiologist, and
pathologist have reviewed all of the clinical, radiologic, and pathologic data
obtained from the patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.american_thoracic_society.2002.277">American Thoracic
Society &#x00026; European Respiratory Society 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.raghu.2011.788">Raghu et al 2011</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Establishing_the_Diagnosis_of_Familia">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis of Familial Pulmonary Fibrosis (FPF)</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of familial pulmonary fibrosis (FPF) is established in a proband
<bold>with IIP</bold> who has </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At least one other first-degree relative (parent, sib, or offspring) with
IIP AND/OR </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A pathogenic variant identified on molecular genetic testing in one of
the four genes known to be associated with FPF (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin">Table1</xref>). </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Approaches to molecular genetic testing</bold> can include:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Serial single-gene testing</bold> of <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>,
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>, and
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> based on family history, age of onset,
phenotypes suggestive of a telomerase syndrome, or the presence of lung
cancer:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p><italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> account for the
majority of families with a pathogenic variant and may or may
not show clinical features of a &#x0201c;telomerase syndrome&#x0201d; as
described below. </p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>If age of onset is younger than 50 in affected family members
and/or pediatric interstitial lung disease is present, mutation
of <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> may be suspected.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic>, described in two
families with bronchoalveolar cell (BAC) cancer, represent a
smaller contribution to families with pathogenic variants. </p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Sequence analysis is performed first<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> If no
pathogenic variant is found, deletion/duplication analysis can
be considered, although large deletions/duplications have not
been reported to date in the genes associated with FPF. </p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Use of a multi-gene panel</bold> that includes
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>,
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2,</italic> and other genes of
interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pf.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>). Note: The genes included in
multi-gene panels vary by laboratory and over time. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <table-wrap id="pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Table 1. </label>
            <caption>
              <p>Summary of Molecular Genetic Testing Used in Familial Pulmonary
Fibrosis</p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup>
</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Familial Pulmonary Fibrosis Attributed to
Mutation of This Gene</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>
</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">~18%&#x000a0;<sup>2,&#x000a0;3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence
analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>
</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">~1%&#x000a0;<sup>2,&#x000a0;3</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence
analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>
</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">~1-25%&#x000a0;<sup>2,&#x000a0;6</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence
analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic>
</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1%&#x000a0;<sup>7</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence
analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="top" colspan="1" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1">Deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>5</sup></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown&#x000a0;<sup>8</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_pf.T.summary_of_molecular_genetic_testin_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn id="pf.TF.1.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="pf" object-id="pf.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and
Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein
name. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pf.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular
Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants. </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pf.TF.1.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>Estimated frequencies as summarized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.diaz_de_leon.2010.e10680">Diaz de Leon et al
[2010]</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.garcia.2011.158">Garcia [2011]</xref> reported that
18% of FPF kindreds had heterozygous pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pf.TF.1.3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <p>Germline pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> and
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> are present in 1%-3% of simplex cases of
IPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.armanios.2009.45">Armanios
2009</xref>]. </p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pf.TF.1.4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of
unknown significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic
variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and
missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exonic or
whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to
consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pf.TF.1.5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <p>Testing that identifies exonic or whole-gene deletions/duplications
not detectable by sequence analysis of the coding and flanking
intronic regions of genomic DNA. Included in the variety of methods
that may be used are: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex
ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and chromosomal
microarray (CMA) that includes this gene/chromosome segment.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pf.TF.1.6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <p>In a Dutch cohort, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.van_moorsel.2010.1419">van Moorsel et al
[2010]</xref> reported that 5 of 20 unrelated individuals with
FPF had <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> pathogenic variants, the highest
frequency of <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> pathogenic variants yet
reported.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pf.TF.1.7">
                <label>7. </label>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.wang.2009.52">Wang et al
[2009]</xref> reported pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> in two families with FPF and lung
cancer.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="pf.TF.1.8">
                <label>8. </label>
                <p>No other genes with rare pathogenic variants are definitely known to
be associated with FPF; however, several observations suggest
possible roles for other genes in FPF causation (click
<inline-supplementary-material xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="media" xlink:href="pf-locus-heterogeneity.pdf" content-type="local-data">here</inline-supplementary-material> for information on
evidence for further locus heterogeneity). </p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pf.Clinical_Description">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="pf.Natural_History">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p><bold>Age of diagnosis.</bold> Individuals with familial pulmonary fibrosis (FPF)
usually present between ages 50 and 70 years. For individuals with mutation of
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>, age at diagnosis can range from infancy to adulthood
even within families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.hamvas.2007.311">Hamvas
et al 2007</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Presentation.</bold> The most common symptoms are shortness of breath on
exertion and a dry cough regardless of the type of underlying IIP. Digital
clubbing may be present. Some affected individuals may experience fever, weight
loss, fatigue, and muscle and joint pain. </p>
          <p><bold>Pulmonary findings</bold>. Bibasilar, inspiratory crackles (dry or
"velcro"-type in quality) on auscultation. </p>
          <p>Pulmonary function studies inclusive of forced vital capacity (FVC), diffusion
capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide (DLCO), and the six-minute walk test
(6-MWT) distance and oxyhemoglobin saturation change at baseline are vital
measurements to serially monitor disease course. </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Reduced VC with an increase in FEV1/FVC ratio and/or impaired gas
exchange (increased P<sub>(A-a)</sub>O<sub>2</sub> with rest or exercise
or decreased diffusion capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide [DLCO])
are findings of an abnormal pulmonary function study . </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Longitudinal declines in these measurements have been associated with
predictors of mortality. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Rate of progression varies among patients and is unpredictable at the time of
diagnosis. The majority of patients have a slow, progressive decline but some
can be stable or progress rapidly. Some may have acute worsening. Other
comorbidities may affect the disease course. Need for oxygen is based on
clinically significant resting hypoxemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.raghu.2011.788">Raghu et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.steele.2005.1146">Steele et al [2005]</xref>
found that 45% of pedigrees showed phenotypic heterogeneity with several
subtypes of idiopathic interstitial pneumonias (IPF, NSIP, COP) occurring within
a family. </p>
          <p>Pulmonary findings in individuals with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> may
vary from asymptomatic to having respiratory failure requiring lung
transplantation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.hamvas.2007.311">Hamvas et al
2007</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Other.</bold> Patients with FPF may have other comorbidities that include
pulmonary hypertension, obstructive sleep apnea, emphysema, gastroesophageal
reflux disease (GERD), and obesity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.raghu.2011.788">Raghu et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Cancer risk.</bold> FPF may be complicated by lung cancer. Bronchoalveolar
cell carcinoma, small-cell carcinoma, and adenocarcinoma have been described
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.ozawa.2009.723">Ozawa et al 2009</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.wang.2009.52">Wang et al 2009</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Life span.</bold> Average survival of individuals with IPF is two to three
years from diagnosis. FPF survival is thought not to differ from IPF survival.
Cause of death is usually respiratory failure.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.GenotypePhenotype_Correlations">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>No genotype-phenotype correlations are known. </p>
          <p>In families with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>,
pathogenic variants have been observed in relatives with bone marrow dysfunction
and/or fibrosis in the lung and liver. Of note, diseases related to telomerase
dysfunction (see Molecular Genetics, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pf.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">Molecular Genetic
Pathogenesis</xref>) can be seen in different family members rather than in
the same individual especially in kindreds segregating a <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>
mutation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.diaz_de_leon.2010.e10680">Diaz de
Leon et al 2010</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> pathogenic variants appear
more likely to be associated with the phenotypes of dyskeratosis congenita (DC)
and bone marrow failure than FPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.garcia.2007.7406">Garcia et al 2007</xref>]. </p>
          <p>The range of phenotypes associated with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> is
unknown. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> appear to be more
prevalent in children with interstitial lung disease than in adults. Of note,
pediatric interstitial lung disease does not usually fit the definition of
adult-onset IIP. Multiple studies have reported <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>
pathogenic variants in familial IPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.nogee.2001.573">Nogee et al 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.thomas.2002.1322">Thomas et al 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.guillot.2009.490">Guillot et al 2009</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.van_moorsel.2010.1419">van Moorsel et al
2010</xref>]. In a study of more than 100 adults with sporadic IPF, only one
person had an <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> pathogenic variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.lawson.2004.977">Lawson et al 2004</xref>]. </p>
          <p>Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> were reported to show a causal
relationship between familial IPF and adenocarcinoma of the lung and
bronchioalveolar cell carcinoma (BAC) of the lung. These same pathogenic
variants were not found in 3557 population-based controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.wang.2009.52">Wang et al 2009</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Penetrance">
          <title>Penetrance</title>
          <p>Penetrance for the phenotype associated with pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>, and
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> is unknown but thought to be incomplete. In the
first report of penetrance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.diaz_de_leon.2010.e10680">Diaz de Leon et al [2010]</xref>
observed incomplete penetrance (~40%) in families with pulmonary fibrosis and
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> pathogenic variants and variable phenotype ranging
from lung disease to liver disease to bone marrow dysfunction. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Nomenclature">
          <title>Nomenclature</title>
          <p>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis has also been referred to as adult familial
cryptogenic fibrosing alveolitis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.marshall.2000.143">Marshall et al [2000]</xref>
estimated that familial cases account for 0.5%-2.2% of all cases of IPF and
reported the prevalence of FPF as 1.34 per 10<sup>6</sup> in the UK
population.</p>
          <p>Recent studies suggest that 0.5%-3.7% of IPF is familial with up to 19%-20% of
persons with IPF reporting a family history significant for interstitial lung
disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.hodgson.2002.338">Hodgson et al
2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.lawson.2006.345">Lawson &#x00026;
Loyd 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.garciasancho.2011.1902">Garc&#x000ed;a-Sancho et al
2011</xref>].
Therefore, the prevalence may be higher. More studies on prevalence are
needed.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pf.Genetically_Related_Allelic_Disorders">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">TERT/TERC</italic>.</bold> Phenotypes known to be associated with
heterozygous pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> or
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Autosomal dominant <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dkc" document-type="chapter">dyskeratosis
congenita</related-object> (DC)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Aplastic anemia or acute leukemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.calado.2009.2353">Calado &#x00026; Young 2009</xref>]</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Cryptogenic cirrhosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.armanios.2009.45">Armanios 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.calado.2011.1600">Calado et al
2011</xref>]</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Myelodysplastic Syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.yamaguchi.2003.916">Yamaguchi et al 2003</xref>]</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Coronary artery disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.matsubara.2006.669">Matsubara et al 2006</xref>] </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p><bold><italic toggle="yes">SFTPC.</italic></bold> Phenotypes known to be associated with
heterozygous pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p>Respiratory distress syndrome (RDS) in pre-term infants</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Infantile-onset respiratory insufficiency</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Chronic pediatric idiopathic interstitial lung disease (diffuse lung
disease)</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Pulmonary surfactant metabolism dysfunction type 2, also known as
pulmonary alveolar proteinosis</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are
known to be associated with mutation of <italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic>.]</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pf.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <p><bold>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF)</bold> is an incurable disease with a
five-year survival of 30%-50% from the time of diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.american_thoracic_society.2000.646">American Thoracic Society
2000</xref>]. Although progress has been made in understanding the molecular and
cellular events involved in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, the exact pathogenesis
has yet to be determined. The initiating stimulus is unknown in the majority of
individuals, and only a subset of individuals (5%-20%) exposed to known fibrogenic
agents actually develop PF. IPF is distinguished from FPF by lack of other affected
family members.</p>
        <p>Other inherited disorders that exhibit diffuse parenchymal lung disease as a clinical
feature:</p>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hps" document-type="chapter"><bold>Hermansky-Pudlak
syndrome</bold></related-object>
<bold>(HPS)</bold> is a multisystem disorder characterized by
tyrosinase-positive oculocutaneous albinism, a bleeding diathesis resulting
from a platelet storage pool deficiency, and, in some cases, pulmonary
fibrosis or granulomatous colitis. Pulmonary fibrosis typically causes
symptoms in the early thirties and progresses to death within a decade.
Hermansky-Pudlak syndrome is known to be associated with a defect in
five-hydroxytryptamine and lysosomal metabolism. In Hermansky-Pudlak
syndrome, the release of PDGF-B by alveolar macrophages is enhanced. This
growth factor is thought to play a pathogenic role in idiopathic pulmonary
fibrosis. Pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">HPS1</italic>,
<italic toggle="yes">AP3B1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HPS2</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">HPS3</italic>,
<italic toggle="yes">HPS4</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HPS5</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">HPS6</italic>,
<italic toggle="yes">DTNBP1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HPS7</italic>),
<italic toggle="yes">BLOC1S3</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">HPS8</italic>), and
<italic toggle="yes">BLOC1S6</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">PLDN</italic>) are known to cause HPS.
Inheritance is autosomal recessive.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nf1" document-type="chapter"><bold>Neurofibromatosis type
1</bold></related-object>
<bold>(NF1)</bold> is characterized by multiple caf&#x000e9;-au-lait spots, axillary
and inguinal freckling, multiple discrete dermal neurofibromas, and iris
Lisch nodules. Learning disabilities are common. Less common but potentially
more serious manifestations include plexiform neurofibromas, optic and other
central nervous system gliomas, malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumors,
osseous lesions, and vasculopathy. NF1 is caused by pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">NF1</italic>. Inheritance is autosomal
dominant.Pulmonary fibrosis is an occasional finding,
though the association of pulmonary fibrosis with NF1 is somewhat
controversial today [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.ryu.2005.2381">Ryu et
al 2005</xref>]. The symptomatic onset of lung disease, when it occurs,
is usually between ages 35 and 60 years, although symptomatic pulmonary
fibrosis has developed as early as the second decade. Dyspnea is the usual
presenting symptom. Pulmonary function tests show restrictive or obstructive
lung defect with a reduced carbon monoxide diffusing capacity
(DL<sub>CO</sub>). The natural history of interstitial lung disease in
NF1 is unclear. Progression to respiratory failure, pulmonary hypertension,
and cor pulmonale may occur. No effective treatment is known. Like IPF, the
interstitial lung disease in NF1 is sometimes complicated by scar
carcinoma.Radiographic findings include diffuse
interstitial pulmonary fibrosis and bullae. The bullae are usually apical,
may appear with or without fibrosis, and are often large. A chest
roentgenogram early in the course of the disease may show patchy airspace
disease and may even be normal despite interstitial pulmonary fibrosis
documented by lung biopsy. Pleural disease and mediastinal adenopathy are
not known features of this disease, although neurofibromas can sometimes
simulate pleural thickening or a mediastinal mass.The
pathologic features of interstitial lung disease in NF1 are nonspecific.
Since these were described prior to the currently evolved understanding of
specific histologic subgroups, it is unclear if the fibrotic pattern is
unclassifiable or represents one of the precisely defined histologic
subgroups.Other thoracic radiographic manifestations are
caused by the direct effect of neurofibromas. Intrathoracic
meningomyeloceles may present as a posterior mediastinal mass. 'Twisted
ribbon' rib deformities caused by the pressure of intercostal fibromas,
vertebral defects, and scoliosis have been described. </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="tuberous-sclerosis" document-type="chapter"><bold>Tuberous sclerosis
complex</bold></related-object>
<bold>(TSC)</bold> involves abnormalities of the skin (hypomelanotic
macules, facial angiofibromas, shagreen patches, fibrous facial plaques,
ungual fibromas), brain (cortical tubers, subependymal nodules, seizures,
intellectual disability/developmental delay), kidney (angiomyolipomas,
cysts, renal cell carcinomas), and heart (rhabdomyomas, arrhythmias).
Pulmonary lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM) occurs in a small proportion of
premenopausal women with TSC. Individuals with LAM typically present with
symptoms of dyspnea on exertion and progressive loss of lung function that
may resemble some of the presenting symptoms of FPF. The
diagnosis of TSC is based on clinical findings. Pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">TSC1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TSC2</italic> are causative. Two
thirds of affected individuals have TSC as the result of <italic toggle="yes">de
novo</italic> mutation. Inheritance is autosomal dominant. </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Niemann-Pick disease type B</bold>
<bold>(</bold><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="npab" document-type="chapter"><bold>acid
sphinomyelinase deficiency</bold></related-object><bold>)</bold> is
characterized by hepatosplenomegaly with progressive hypersplenism and
stable liver dysfunction, gradual deterioration in pulmonary function, and
atherogenic lipid profile. Progressive and/or clinically significant
neurologic manifestations occur infrequently. Survival to adulthood can
occur. Niemann-Pick disease type B is caused by pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">SMPD1</italic>. Inheritance is autosomal
recessive.The incidence of lung involvement is unknown.
Chest radiography may show a reticulonodular or miliary pattern; progression
to honeycombing has been described. Reticuloendothelial cells filled with
sphingomyelin may fill the alveolar spaces and interstitium and can be
recovered with bronchoalveolar lavage. No effective treatment is known.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="gaucher" document-type="chapter"><bold>Gaucher disease</bold></related-object>
encompasses a continuum of five clinical subtypes that range from a
perinatal-lethal form to an asymptomatic form. The pulmonary manifestations
of Gaucher disease type 1 are caused by Gaucher cells infiltrating the
interstitium, filling the alveoli or obstructing pulmonary capillaries.
Obliteration of pulmonary capillaries may result in pulmonary hypertension
and cor pulmonale. Acute fatal bone marrow embolization of Gaucher cells to
the lungs has been described. Pulmonary infections occur with increased
frequency. Histopathologic examination shows Gaucher cell
infiltration, but inflammation and fibrosis are not usual features. The
Gaucher cells stain positively with PAS and autofluoresce. Gaucher cells may
be found in the sputum or in the bronchial washes. Chest radiographic
findings are not specific. Diffuse interstitial infiltrates that
occasionally have a miliary appearance have been described, as has
mediastinal adenopathy. Pulmonary function tests reveal typical restrictive
lung defect with a reduced DL<sub>CO</sub>.The diagnosis
of Gaucher disease relies on demonstration of deficient glucosylceramidase
enzyme activity in peripheral blood leukocytes or other nucleated cells.
Gaucher disease is caused by mutation of <italic toggle="yes">GBA</italic>. Inheritance
is autosomal recessive. </p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><bold>Familial hypocalciuric hypercalcemia type 1</bold> (OMIM <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omim.org/entry/145980">145980</ext-link>) is a very rare disorder
characterized by hypocalciuric hypercalcemia, interstitial lung disease
(ILD) / pulmonary fibrosis, and recurrent respiratory tract infections
caused by granulocyte dysfunction associated with a relative deficiency in
myeloperoxidase. The disease usually presents in the fourth decade.
Reticulonodular infiltrates that may progress to honeycombing on chest
radiograph and restrictive pulmonary physiology are typical findings.
Disease progression appears to be slow: survival after diagnosis is
approximately ten years. The mode of inheritance is probably autosomal
dominant manner, based on the report of one family with three sibs
clinically affected by ILD. In this relatively large family, 45% of 38
family members studied had a reduced DL<sub>CO</sub>, suggesting subclinical
disease. Several asymptomatic individuals also had abnormalities of BAL
fluid cell count, suggesting active alveolitis. In addition, 60% had
recurrent respiratory tract infections. The disorder is caused by mutation
of <italic toggle="yes">CASR</italic> (which encodes the calcium-sensing receptor). </p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pf.Management_1">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="pf.Evaluations_Following_Initial_Diagnos">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with
familial pulmonary fibrosis (FPF), the following evaluations are recommended: </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Clinical history </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Chest radiograph</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>High-resolution computed tomography (HRCT) scan of the chest</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Pulmonary function studies </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation by a pulmonologist, preferably one with experience in IPF</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Medical genetics consultation</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p>The management of the individual with familial pulmonary fibrosis (FPF) is
similar to that for interstitial idiopathic pneumonia (IIP) and depends on the
type of IIP diagnosed for each individual within the family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.american_thoracic_society.2000.646">American
Thoracic Society 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.american_thoracic_society.2002.277">American Thoracic
Society &#x00026; European Respiratory Society 2002</xref>].</p>
          <p>Lung transplantation may be a consideration in selected individuals with FPF. In
general, those who are unresponsive to therapy, have significant functional
impairment, and have no other major illnesses that would preclude
transplantation are good candidates. Five-year survival rates post transplant in
IPF have been estimated at 50%-56% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.raghu.2011.788">Raghu et al 2011</xref>].</p>
          <p>Non-pharmologic treatments:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Oxygen therapy may improve exercise tolerance in patients with
hypoxemia.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Pulmonary rehabilitation is a recommended option for patients who would
benefit. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Pharmacologic interventions have not generally been shown to alter the course of
IPF. Treatments have been categorized into classes such as corticosteroids,
immunosuppressive/cytotoxic agents, and antifibrotic agents. However, at least
two antifibrotic pharmacologic interventions recently approved may be an option
for patients with FPF to slow the decline of lung function. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pf.Therapies_Under_Investigation">Therapies Under
Investigation</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Prevention_of_Secondary_Complications">
          <title>Prevention of Secondary Complications</title>
          <p>The following are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Prevention and prompt treatment of acute exacerbations</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Treatment of coexisting comorbidities if appropriate including:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Pulmonary hypertension</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Pulmonary embolism</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Lung cancer</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Coronary artery disease</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Respiratory infections</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Pneumothorax</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Aspiration</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>The frequency of follow-up evaluations for persons with FPF depends largely on
the patient's individual diagnosis and status. Surveillance would follow the
guidelines for IPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.raghu.2011.788">Raghu et
al 2011</xref>] or the specific type of IIP. Those who are stable may be
evaluated every three to six months, while others may need more frequent follow
up. </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Pulmonary function studies including the following to serially monitor
disease course [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.raghu.2011.788">Raghu
et al 2011</xref>]:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Forced vital capacity (FVC)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Diffusion capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide (DLCO)</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>The six-minute walk test (6-MWT) distance and oxyhemoglobin
saturation change at baseline</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Monitoring for progression of disease by HRCT of the chest</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Oxygen saturation by resting pulse oximetry</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Serologic monitoring for connective tissue disease (CTD) in patients
suspected of an underlying possibility for CTD-related ILD</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Monitoring for any side effects known from pharmacologic treatments</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Symptom control</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoid">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>Cigarette smoking is a risk factor for developing idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis
(IPF) and was shown to be an independent risk factor in families with FPF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.steele.2005.1146">Steele et al 2005</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>It is appropriate to evaluate relatives at risk in order to identify as early as
possible those who would benefit from initiation of treatment. </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>If the pathogenic variant in the family is known, molecular genetic
testing can be used to clarify the genetic status of at-risk relatives.
</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If the pathogenic variant in the family is not known, simple screening
tests have been found to be sensitive for establishing the diagnosis in
relatives at risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.watters.1986.97">Watters et al 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.hartley.1994.271">Hartley et al 1994</xref>] and
prognosis of pulmonary fibrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.watters.1986.97">Watters et al 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.schwartz.1994a.450">Schwartz et al
1994a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.schwartz.1994b.444">Schwartz et al 1994b</xref>]. </p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>It is recommended that every five years, asymptomatic
first-degree relatives (of individuals with FPF) older than age
50 years undergo pulmonary function tests, obtain an HRCT scan
of the chest to detect early abnormalities, and complete a
standardized questionnaire to assess the presence of respiratory
symptoms. </p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Family members are considered to have a positive screening
evaluation (i.e., to possibly have pulmonary fibrosis) if they
have at least class 2 dyspnea (breathlessness when hurrying on a
level surface or walking up a slight hill), a DL<sub>CO</sub>
below 80% of predicted, or presence of at least ILO category 1
findings on chest x-ray [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF18">International Labour Office 2011</xref>]. Family members
who have a positive screen require further evaluation (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pf.Diagnosis">Diagnosis</xref>).</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A study of asymptomatic at-risk family members in a FPF cohort by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.kropski.2015.417">Kropski et al
[2015]</xref> identified more than 25% of subjects with subtle
radiologic and histopathologic abnormalities suggestive of possible
early interstitial lung disease. It is unknown if these findings would
become symptomatic FPF in the subjects. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pf.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">Genetic
Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for
genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Therapies_Under_Investigation">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Several therapies remain under investigation for the treatment of IPF. Agents
targeted to fibroblast proliferation, pulmonary hypertension, anti-inflammatory,
anticoagulation, and various chemokine and monoclonal antibodies among other
targets remain under investigation as potential treatments. Two antifibrotic
agents recently approved by the FDA for use in IPF as of October 2014 include
pirfenidone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.king.2014.2083">King et al
2014</xref>] and nintedanib [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.richeldi.2014.2071">Richeldi et al 2014</xref>]; the former has
been available in Japan and Europe for several years as a therapy for IPF. </p>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information
on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pf.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="pf.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>The inheritance of familial pulmonary fibrosis (FPF) is not clear. Complex
inheritance (including multifactorial inheritance and autosomal dominant
inheritance with reduced penetrance) appears likely though autosomal recessive
inheritance remains a possibility. The largest study of families with FPF to
date [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.steele.2005.1146">Steele et al
2005</xref>] supports an autosomal dominant mode of inheritance with reduced
penetrance. Subsequent family studies support this model as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.lawson.2006.345">Lawson &#x00026; Loyd 2006</xref>].
The study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.marshall.2000.143">Marshall et al
[2000]</xref> investigating 25 families with FPF also supports this model
but cannot exclude autosomal recessive inheritance. Further studies are
warranted to delineate all inheritance patterns.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Risk_to_Family_Members__Autosomal_Dom">
          <title>Risk to Family Members &#x02014; Autosomal Dominant Inheritance</title>
          <p>
<bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Most individuals diagnosed with FPF have an affected parent. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Although most individuals diagnosed with FPF have an affected parent, the
disorder may appear to have skipped a generation (i.e., the individual
diagnosed has an affected grandparent related through an unaffected
parent) because of reduced penetrance. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A proband with FPF may have the disorder as the result of <italic toggle="yes">de
novo</italic> mutation. However, the overall proportion of cases
caused by <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> mutation is unknown.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Note: The family history of some individuals diagnosed with FPF may appear to be
negative because of reduced penetrance, failure to recognize the disorder in
family members, early death of the parent before the onset of symptoms, or late
onset of the disease in the affected parent. Therefore, an apparently negative
family history cannot be confirmed unless appropriate evaluations have been
performed on the parents of the proband (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pf.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at
Risk</xref>).</p>
          <p>
<bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to the sibs of the proband depends on the genetic status of the
proband's parents. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent of the proband is affected or known to have a
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>,
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> pathogenic variant,
the risk to the sibs of inheriting the pathogenic variant is 50%.
Because penetrance is likely reduced, the risk to sibs of being affected
is less than 50%. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband</bold> In families with an autosomal dominant
pattern of FPF inheritance and/or a <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>,
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic>
pathogenic variant, offspring have a 50% chance of inheriting a pathogenic
variant. However, the risk of developing FPF is less than 50% due to reduced
penetrance. </p>
          <p>
<bold>Other family members of a proband</bold>
</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The risk to other family members depends on the status of the proband's
parents. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>If a parent is affected, his or her family members are at risk. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Related_Genetic_Counseling_Issues">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="pf.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at_Risk">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating
at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment</p>
          <p><bold>Other modes of inheritance.</bold> Autosomal recessive inheritance may need
to be considered in simplex cases (i.e., cases with only one affected individual
in a family) and in families with only affected sibs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.marshall.2000.143">Marshall et al 2000</xref>]. X-linked
inheritance may also be possible [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.kropski.2014.e1">Kropski et al 2014</xref>].</p>
          <p>
<bold>Family planning</bold>
</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk and discussion of the
availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of
potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults
who are affected or at risk. </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white
blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing
methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will
improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected
individuals. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Prenatal_Testing">
          <title>Prenatal Testing</title>
          <p>If the <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>, or
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> pathogenic variant has been identified in an
affected family member, prenatal testing for pregnancies at increased risk may
be available from a clinical laboratory that offers either testing of this gene
or custom prenatal testing. </p>
          <p>Requests for prenatal testing for adult-onset conditions which (like familial
pulmonary fibrosis) do not affect intellect and have some treatment available
are not common. Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals
and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the
testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than
early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions about prenatal
testing are the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is
appropriate.</p>
          <p><bold>Preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)</bold> may be an option for some
families in which the <italic toggle="yes">TERT, TERC, SFTPC, or SFTPA2</italic> pathogenic
variant has been identified. </p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pf.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pf.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <p>Not all of the loci/genes associated with familial pulmonary fibrosis are known.</p>
        <sec id="pf.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogenesis">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p>Telomeres are DNA-protein structures that protect chromosome ends and provide
chromosomal integrity. They consist of TTAGGG repeats that are bound by a
specialized protein complex known as shelterin. The asymmetric replication of
DNA during mitosis and the ensuing &#x0201c;end-replication problem&#x0201d; leaves newly
synthesized DNA strands shorter than the original template, and ultimately
causes telomeres to shorten successively with each cell division, activating a
p53-dependent cell-cycle checkpoint that signals the arrest of cell
proliferation, senescence, and apoptosis. </p>
          <p>The enzyme telomerase solves this end-replication problem by providing a
repetitive template for enzymatic repair of the ends of chromosomes by
synthesizing new telomeres and providing telomere elongation. The enzyme
telomerase is made up of telomerase reverse transcriptase (encoded by
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>) and the telomerase RNA component (product of
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>), which functions as a template to synthesize telomere
DNA. Telomerase is normally repressed in postnatal somatic cells, resulting in
progressive shortening of telomeres; telomerase reverse transcriptase is only
highly expressed in specific germline cells, proliferative stem cells of renewal
tissues, and immortal cancer cells. Telomerase RNA component is expressed in all
tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.garcia.2007.7406">Garcia et al
2007</xref>].</p>
          <p>Pathogenic variants in telomerase components were first described in <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dkc" document-type="chapter">dyskeratosis congenita</related-object> (DC),
characterized by abnormal skin findings, bone marrow failure, and interstitial
lung disease (e.g., pulmonary fibrosis). Telomere shortening is a common feature
of DC and bone marrow failure syndromes, two diseases previously associated with
pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">DKC1</italic> (encoding dyskerin),
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">TINF2</italic> (a
shelterin component). All persons with DC have short telomeres in their
circulating leukocytes regardless of which gene is mutated. Pathogenic variants
in <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> are present in up to 4% of individuals with acquired
aplastic anemia and yet short telomere lengths are found in 34% of persons with
that disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.cronkhite.2008.729">Cronkhite et
al 2008</xref>]. </p>
          <p>Since telomere shortening can result from pathogenic variants in the genes
encoding the telomerase complex, it is hypothesized that telomere shortening may
play a role in the development of both familial and idiopathic pulmonary
fibrosis. The presence of short telomeres may explain the increased occurrence
of pulmonary fibrosis in older individuals. However, it has been shown that a
significant fraction of individuals with pulmonary fibrosis (20%-25%) have short
telomere lengths that cannot always be explained by pathogenic variants in the
genes that encode telomerase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.cronkhite.2008.729">Cronkhite et al 2008</xref>]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.diaz_de_leon.2010.e10680">Diaz de Leon et al
[2010]</xref> showed that family members within kindreds who do not inherit
a <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> pathogenic variant may have shorter telomere lengths
than controls, demonstrating that factors other than pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> (e.g., pathogenic variants in other genes, epigenetic
inheritance) can affect telomere length. </p>
          <sec id="pf.TERT">
            <title>
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>
</title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> consists of 16 exons and 15 introns spanning 35 kb.
Alternatively spliced transcript variants encode different isoforms of
telomerase. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information, see
<related-object source-id="gene" document-id="pf" object-id="pf.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene
</bold>.</p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> Pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> have been shown to associate with the FPF/IPF
phenotype, but have yet to be demonstrated to cause disease. </p>
            <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.tsakiri.2007.7552">Tsakiri et al
[2007]</xref> found two frameshift deletions and five missense mutations
in persons with pulmonary fibrosis. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.armanios.2007.1317">Armanios et al [2007]</xref> found two
missense, two splice-junction, and one frameshift mutation in their cohort
of individuals with pulmonary fibrosis. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.cronkhite.2008.729">Cronkhite et al [2008]</xref> found six
novel mutations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.diaz_de_leon.2010.e10680">Diaz de Leon et al [2010]</xref> expanded upon the familial cohorts of
Tsakiri and Cronkhite and found six additional pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.dai.2015.122">Dai et al [2015]</xref> found four novel mutations in Chinese
individuals with sporadic IPF, the first study to evaluate telomerase
mutations in that population.</p>
            <p>At least 28 <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> pathogenic variants for pulmonary fibrosis
have been reported through these and other studies listed in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://telomerase.asu.edu/diseases.html">Telomerase Database</ext-link>. The pathogenic
variants found thus far are spread across the three domains of
<italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> but cluster in conserved regions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.diaz_de_leon.2010.e10680">Diaz de Leon et al
[2010]</xref> reported two pathogenic variants that were found in
different unrelated families. No other common pathogenic variants have been
reported. </p>
            <p>More information can be found in the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://telomerase.asu.edu/diseases.html">Telomerase Database</ext-link>. </p>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> Telomerase is a ribonucleoprotein
polymerase that maintains telomere ends by addition of the telomere repeat
TTAGGG. The protein is made up of 1132 amino acids and three domains: the
N-terminal extension, the reverse transcriptase, and the C-terminal
extension. </p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> It is thought that loss-of-function
mutations in <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> impair the ability of telomerase to
repair telomeres after cell division. Short dysfunctional telomeres then
signal the arrest of cell proliferation, ultimately leading to cell death
and organ failure. In addition, <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> is only highly
expressed in specific germline cells, proliferative stem cells of renewal
tissues, and immortal cancer cells. The bronchoalveolar epithelium is
thought to be constantly replaced and may rely on a supply of local
progenitor reserves that may be limited by short telomeres [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.armanios.2007.1317">Armanios et al
2007</xref>]. </p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="pf.TERC">
            <title>
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>
</title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> comprises one exon (consisting of 451 bp of DNA) that
encodes the telomerase RNA component. <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> contains the
template that encodes for telomeric repeats and binds to telomerase reverse
transcriptase (TERT) for DNA synthesis. For a detailed summary of gene and
protein information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="pf" object-id="pf.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene
</bold>.</p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> Pathogenic variants in
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> have been shown to associate with the FPF/IPF
phenotype, but have yet to be determined to be the cause of disease. The
following <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> pathogenic variants have been reported to
date in persons with pulmonary fibrosis (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://telomerase.asu.edu/diseases.html">Telomerase Database</ext-link>).</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.tsakiri.2007.7552">Tsakiri et al
[2007]</xref> found a pathogenic variant in the terminal residue
of the P1b helix of the pseudoknot region in one proband. This
change was not found in 94 ethnically matched controls but had been
reported previously in one person with severe aplastic anemia who
was a compound heterozygote for variants in <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic>.
</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.armanios.2007.1317">Armanios et al
[2007]</xref> found one pathogenic variant in the pseudoknot
region in a proband.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.marrone.2007.1013">Marrone et al
[2007]</xref> found a deletion in one person with a history of
aplastic anemia and pulmonary fibrosis and a family history of
pulmonary fibrosis. </p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.alder.2008.13051">Alder et al
[2008]</xref> described a previously unreported germline
mutation in conserved regions 4 and 5 in a simplex IIP case as well
as the individual&#x02019;s younger asymptomatic siblings. </p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.dai.2015.122">Dai et al
[2015]</xref> found three novel mutations in Chinese persons
with sporadic IPF, the first study to evaluate telomerase mutations
in that population.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> Telomerase consists of a protein component
with reverse transcriptase activity (TERT), and an RNA component (TERC),
encoded by this gene, that serves as a template for the telomere repeat.
Three domains characterize TERC: a pseudoknot that includes the template,
conserved regions 4 and 5 (CR4-CR5), and ScaRNA domain for nuclear
recruitment. Pathogenic variants associated with pulmonary fibrosis have
been found in the pseudoknot and CR4-CR5 regions. </p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> It is thought that loss-of-function
mutations in <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> impair repair of telomeres after cell
division. Short dysfunctional telomeres then signal the arrest of cell
proliferation, ultimately leading to cell death and organ failure. This is
especially true in cells with high turnover. </p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="pf.SFTPC">
            <title>
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic>
</title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> consists of six exons and spans approximately 3.5 kb.
Alternatively spliced transcript variants encoding different protein
isoforms have been identified. For a detailed summary of gene and protein
information, see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="pf" object-id="pf.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene
</bold>. </p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold> Multiple pathogenic variants in
this gene cause pulmonary surfactant metabolism dysfunction type 2 (also
called pulmonary alveolar proteinosis) resulting from surfactant protein C
deficiency, and are associated with interstitial lung disease in older
infants, children, and less often in adults. Only a few pathogenic variants
associated with FPF have been described. </p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p>The p.Ile73Thr pathogenic variant, the most prevalent
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> pathogenic variant reported to date in
children, can be <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> or inherited. </p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>In an infant and mother with respiratory insufficiency resulting from
surfactant metabolism dysfunction and surfactant protein C
deficiency, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.nogee.2001.573">Nogee
et al [2001]</xref> identified a heterozygous pathogenic variant
in the splice donor site of intron 4, resulting in a
dominant-negative effect. </p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.thomas.2002.1322">Thomas et al
[2002]</xref> reported a pathogenic variant in one large kindred
in both adult and childhood onset of interstitial lung disease. </p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.guillot.2009.490">Guillot et al
[2009]</xref> identified a novel pathogenic variant in affected
members of a family with surfactant protein C deficiency. The
proband had onset of interstitial lung disease at age two months;
adults developed pulmonary fibrosis. </p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p>In a Dutch cohort, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.van_moorsel.2010.1419">van Moorsel et al
[2010]</xref> reported that five of 20 unrelated individuals
with FPF had <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> pathogenic variants, the highest
frequency of <italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> pathogenic variants yet
reported.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold> Pulmonary-associated surfactant protein C
(SPC) is an extremely hydrophobic surfactant protein essential for lung
function and homeostasis after birth. Pulmonary surfactant is a
surface-active lipoprotein complex composed of 90% lipids and 10% proteins
which include plasma proteins and apolipoproteins SPA, SPB, SPC, and SPD.
The surfactant is secreted by the alveolar cells of the lung and maintains
the stability of pulmonary tissue by reducing the surface tension of fluids
that coat the lung. SPC is synthesized as a 197 amino-acid proprotein
(proSP-C) that undergoes multiple processing steps to the mature SP-C
peptide of 35 amino acids, to be finally released in the alveoli associated
with the other surfactant proteins and phospholipids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.guillot.2009.490">Guillot et al 2009</xref>]. </p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold> Mechanisms proposed for
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPC</italic> pathogenic variants causing diffuse lung disease
include alteration of SP-C metabolism or complete SP-C deficiency. </p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="pf.SFTPA2">
            <title>
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic>
</title>
            <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> consists of five exons and encodes an isoform of
surfactant-associate protein, SPA. <italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> shares greater
than 90% of identity across coding and noncoding regions with nearby
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA1</italic> which codes for the other isoform of protein
SPA, known as SPA1. For a detailed summary of gene and protein information,
see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="pf" object-id="pf.molgen.TA">Table A</related-object>, <bold>Gene
</bold>.</p>
            <p><bold>Pathogenic allelic variants.</bold>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.wang.2009.52">Wang et al [2009]</xref>
used linkage in a family with FPF and lung cancer resulting in the finding
of a rare heterozygous missense mutation c.692G&#x0003e;T (Gly231Val) in
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic>, which segregated in family members with FPF
and/or lung cancer. Further interrogation of 58 probands within their
familial cohort revealed another heterozygous mutation in
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> in a proband with IPF and lung cancer
(c.593T&#x0003e;C, Phe198Ser). No other affected family members of this proband
were available for testing. In an analysis of more than 1,000 ethnically
matched subjects, neither of these mutations was found. </p>
            <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SFTPA2</italic> encodes a protein of 248 amino acids; it includes a
collagen-like region, a neck domain, and a C-terminal
carbohydrate-recognition domain.</p>
            <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.wang.2009.52">Wang et al [2009]</xref>
showed that the two missense mutations were in a highly conserved region of
the C-terminal carbohydrate recognition lectin domain (CRD) and most likely
interrupted proper protein folding and cellular trafficking. </p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pf.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="pf.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="pf.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="pf.REF.alder.2008.13051">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alder</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Danoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cogan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vulto</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tuder</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lansdorp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armanios</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Short telomeres are a risk factor for idiopathic
pulmonary fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source>
                <volume>105</volume>
                <fpage>13051</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18753630</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.american_thoracic_society.2000.646">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<collab>American Thoracic Society</collab>
</person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>American Thoracic Society. Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis:
diagnosis and treatment. International consensus statement. American
Thoracic Society (ATS), and the European Respiratory Society
(ERS).</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med.</source>
                <volume>161</volume>
                <fpage>646</fpage>
                <lpage>64</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10673212</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.american_thoracic_society.2002.277">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<collab>American Thoracic Society</collab>
<collab>European Respiratory Society</collab>
</person-group>
                <article-title>American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society
International Multidisciplinary Consensus Classification of the
Idiopathic Interstitial Pneumonias. This joint statement of the
American Thoracic Society (ATS), and the European Respiratory
Society (ERS) was adopted by the ATS board of directors, June 2001
and by the ERS Executive Committee, June 2001.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med.</source>
                <year>2002</year>
                <volume>165</volume>
                <fpage>277</fpage>
                <lpage>304</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11790668</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.armanios.2009.45">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armanios</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2009</year>
                <article-title>Syndromes of telomere shortening.</article-title>
                <source>Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet.</source>
                <volume>10</volume>
                <fpage>45</fpage>
                <lpage>61</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19405848</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.armanios.2007.1317">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armanios</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cogan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alder</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ingersoll</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Markin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vulto</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lansdorp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Greider</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Telomerase mutations in families with idiopathic
pulmonary fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>356</volume>
                <fpage>1317</fpage>
                <lpage>26</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17392301</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.calado.2009.2353">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Calado</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2009</year>
                <article-title>Telomere diseases.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>361</volume>
                <fpage>2353</fpage>
                <lpage>65</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20007561</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.calado.2011.1600">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Calado</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brudno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zago</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chanock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Constitutional telomerase mutations are genetic risk
factors for cirrhosis.</article-title>
                <source>Hepatology</source>
                <volume>53</volume>
                <fpage>1600</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21520173</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.cronkhite.2008.729">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cronkhite</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2008</year>
                <article-title>Telomere shortening in familial and sporadic pulmonary
fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med.</source>
                <volume>178</volume>
                <fpage>729</fpage>
                <lpage>37</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635888</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.dai.2015.122">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2015</year>
                <article-title>Telomerase gene mutations and telomere length shortening
in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis in a Chinese
population.</article-title>
                <source>Respirology</source>
                <volume>20</volume>
                <fpage>122</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25346280</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.diaz_de_leon.2010.e10680">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz de Leon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cronkhite</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Katzenstein</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Godwin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Glazer</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Girod</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garrity</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2010</year>
                <article-title>Telomere lengths, pulmonary fibrosis and telomerase
(TERT) mutations.</article-title>
                <source>PLoS One.</source>
                <volume>5</volume>
                <fpage>e10680</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20502709</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.garcia.2007.7406">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Human diseases of telomerase dysfunction: insights into
tissue aging.</article-title>
                <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
                <volume>35</volume>
                <fpage>7406</fpage>
                <lpage>16</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17913752</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.garcia.2011.158">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Am Thorac Soc</source>
                <volume>8</volume>
                <fpage>158</fpage>
                <lpage>62</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21543794</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.garciasancho.2011.1902">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Sancho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Buendia-Roldan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Plata</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Padilla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Selman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>Familial pulmonary fibrosis is the strongest risk factor
for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Respir Med</source>
                <volume>105</volume>
                <fpage>1902</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21917441</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.guillot.2009.490">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Guillot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Epaud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thouvenin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jonard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mohsni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Couderc</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Counil</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Blic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taam</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Le Bourgeois</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reix</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Flamein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2009</year>
                <article-title>New surfactant protein C gene mutations associated with
diffuse lung disease.</article-title>
                <source>J Med Genet</source>
                <volume>46</volume>
                <fpage>490</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19443464</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.hamvas.2007.311">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamvas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nogee</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Genetic disorders of surfactant proteins.</article-title>
                <source>Neonatology.</source>
                <volume>91</volume>
                <fpage>311</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17575475</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.hartley.1994.271">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Galvin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hunninghake</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yagla</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Speakman</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>1994</year>
                <article-title>High-resolution CT-derived measures of lung density are
valid indexes of interstitial lung disease.</article-title>
                <source>J Appl Physiol.</source>
                <volume>76</volume>
                <fpage>271</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8175517</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.hodgson.2002.338">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tukiainen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <article-title>Nationwide prevalence of sporadic and familial idiopathic
pulmonary fibrosis: evidence of founder effect among multiplex
families in Finland.</article-title>
                <source>Thorax.</source>
                <year>2002</year>
                <month>Apr</month>
                <volume>57</volume>
                <issue>4</issue>
                <fpage>338</fpage>
                <lpage>42</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11923553</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF18">
              <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">International Labour
Office. Guidelines for the use of the ILO International Classification
of Radiographs of Pneumoconioses, revised edition. Geneva, Switzerland:
International Labour Organization. Available <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ilo.org/safework/info/publications/WCMS_168260/lang--en/index.htm">online</ext-link>. 2011. Accessed
3-11-15.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.king.2014.2083">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>TE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Castro-Bernardini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fagan</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Glaspole</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Glassberg</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gorina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kardatzke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lederer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sahn</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sussman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Swigris</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
<collab>ASCEND Study Group</collab>
</person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>A phase 3 trial of pirfenidone in patients with
idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>370</volume>
                <fpage>2083</fpage>
                <lpage>92</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24836312</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.kropski.2015.417">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kropski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchett</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zoz</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Crossno</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Markin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garnett</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Degryse</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Polosukhin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rickman</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McConaha</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gleaves</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Worrell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Solus</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Massion</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zaynagetdinov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtis</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Groshong</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JA</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cogan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2015</year>
                <article-title>Extensive phenotyping of individuals at-risk for familial
interstitial pneumonia reveals clues to the pathogenesis of
interstitial lung disease.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
                <volume>191</volume>
                <fpage>417</fpage>
                <lpage>26</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25389906</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.kropski.2014.e1">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kropski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Markin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Polsukhin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JA</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cogan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>A novel dyskerin (DKC1) mutation is associated with
familial interstitial pneumonia.</article-title>
                <source>Chest</source>
                <volume>146</volume>
                <fpage>e1</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24504062</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.lawson.2004.977">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ambrosini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Womble</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Markin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Renzoni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lympany</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roldan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>du Bois</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2004</year>
                <article-title>Genetic mutations in surfactant protein C are a rare
cause of sporadic cases of IPF.</article-title>
                <source>Thorax</source>
                <volume>59</volume>
                <fpage>977</fpage>
                <lpage>80</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15516475</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.lawson.2006.345">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>The genetic approach in pulmonary
fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Am Thorac Soc</source>
                <volume>3</volume>
                <fpage>345</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16738199</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.marrone.2007.1013">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marrone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sokhal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Walne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Beswick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kirwan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Killick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Vulliamy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dokal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Functional characterization of novel telomerase RNA
(TERC) mutations in patients with diverse clinical and pathological
presentations.</article-title>
                <source>Haematologica</source>
                <volume>92</volume>
                <fpage>1013</fpage>
                <lpage>20</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17640862</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.marshall.2000.143">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Puddicombe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cookson</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2000</year>
                <article-title>Adult familial cryptogenic fibrosing alveolitis in the
United Kingdom.</article-title>
                <source>Thorax</source>
                <volume>55</volume>
                <fpage>143</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10639533</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.matsubara.2006.669">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Miyaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Omae</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Matsushita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Coronary artery disease and a functional polymorphism of
hTERT.</article-title>
                <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source>
                <volume>348</volume>
                <fpage>669</fpage>
                <lpage>72</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16890917</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.nogee.2001.573">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nogee</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>AE</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wert</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Askin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamvas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Whitsett</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2001</year>
                <article-title>A mutation in the surfactant protein C gene associated
with familial interstitial lung disease.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>344</volume>
                <fpage>573</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11207353</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.ozawa.2009.723">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Enomoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Inui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2009</year>
                <article-title>Cumulative incidence of and predictive factors for lung
cancer in IPF.</article-title>
                <source>Respirology</source>
                <volume>14</volume>
                <fpage>723</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19659650</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.raghu.2011.788">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Collard</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Behr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Colby</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cordier</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lasky</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Swigris</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ancochea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bouros</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Costabel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ebina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hansell</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johkoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>TE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kondoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Richeldi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Selman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dudden</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Griss</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Protzko</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sch&#x000fc;nemann</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<collab>ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT Committee on Idiopathic
Pulmonary Fibrosis</collab>
</person-group>
                <year>2011</year>
                <article-title>An Official ATS/ERS/JRS/ALAT Statement: Idiopathic
Pulmonary Fibrosis: Evidence-based Guidelines for Diagnosis and
Management.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
                <volume>183</volume>
                <fpage>788</fpage>
                <lpage>824</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21471066</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.richeldi.2014.2071">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Richeldi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>du Bois</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Costabel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hansell</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Selman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Le Maulf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stowasser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schlenker-Herceg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Disse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Collard</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
<collab>INPULSIS Trial Investigators</collab>
</person-group>
                <year>2014</year>
                <article-title>Efficacy and safety of nintedanib in idiopathic pulmonary
fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                <volume>370</volume>
                <fpage>2071</fpage>
                <lpage>82</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24836310</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.ryu.2005.2381">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Parambil</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McGrann</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aughenbaugh</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Lack of evidence for an association between
neurofibromatosis and pulmonary fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Chest</source>
                <volume>128</volume>
                <fpage>2381</fpage>
                <lpage>6</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236898</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.schwartz.1994a.450">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Helmers</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Galvin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Van Fossen</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Frees</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dayton</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burmeister</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hunninghake</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>1994a</year>
                <article-title>Determinants of survial in idiopathic pulmonary
fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
                <volume>149</volume>
                <fpage>450</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8306044</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.schwartz.1994b.444">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Van Fossen</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Helmers</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dayton</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burmeister</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hunninghake</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>1994b</year>
                <article-title>Determinants of progression in idiopathic pulmonary
fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
                <volume>149</volume>
                <fpage>444</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8306043</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.steele.2005.1146">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Speer</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Herron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slifer</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Burch</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wahidi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sporn</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Clinical and pathologic features of familial interstitial
pneumonia.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
                <volume>172</volume>
                <fpage>1146</fpage>
                <lpage>52</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16109978</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.thomas.2002.1322">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Markin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Speer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gaddipati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marney</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stahlman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loyd</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2002</year>
                <article-title>Heterozygosity for a surfactant protein C gene mutation
associated with usual interstitial pneumonitis and cellular
nonspecific interstitial pneumonitis in one kindred.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
                <volume>165</volume>
                <fpage>1322</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11991887</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.tsakiri.2007.7552">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tsakiri</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cronkhite</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kuan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Weissler</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2007</year>
                <article-title>Adult-onset pulmonary fibrosis caused by mutations in
telomerase.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                <volume>104</volume>
                <fpage>7552</fpage>
                <lpage>7</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17460043</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.van_moorsel.2010.1419">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>van Moorsel</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>van Oosterhout</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barlo</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>van der Vis</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ruven</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>van Es</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>van den Bosch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grutters</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <article-title>Surfactant protein C mutations are the basis of a
significant portion of adult familial pulmonary fibrosis in a dutch
cohort.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med.</source>
                <year>2010</year>
                <month>Dec</month>
                <day>1</day>
                <volume>182</volume>
                <issue>11</issue>
                <fpage>1419</fpage>
                <lpage>25</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20656946</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.wang.2009.52">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kuan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cronkhite</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>DiMaio</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kinch</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grishin</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2009</year>
                <article-title>Genetic defects in surfactant protein A2 are associated
with pulmonary fibrosis and lung cancer.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <volume>84</volume>
                <fpage>52</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19100526</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.watters.1986.97">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Watters</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stanford</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cherniack</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>1986</year>
                <article-title>A clinical, radiographic, and physiologic scoring system
for the longitudinal assessment of patients with idiopathic
pulmonary fibrosis.</article-title>
                <source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source>
                <volume>133</volume>
                <fpage>97</fpage>
                <lpage>103</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3942381</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.yamaguchi.2003.916">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baerlocher</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lansdorp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chanock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sloand</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations of the human telomerase RNA gene (TERC) in
aplastic anemia and myelodysplastic syndrome.</article-title>
                <source>Blood.</source>
                <year>2003</year>
                <volume>102</volume>
                <fpage>916</fpage>
                <lpage>8</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676774</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Suggested_Reading">
          <title>Suggested Reading</title>
          <ref-list id="pf.Suggested_Reading.reflist0">
            <ref id="pf.REF.armanios.2005.15960">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Armanios</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brodsky</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eshleman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chakravarti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Greider</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2005</year>
                <article-title>Haploinsufficiency of telomerase reverse transcriptase
leads to anticipation in autosomal dominant dyskeratosis
congenita.</article-title>
                <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source>
                <volume>102</volume>
                <fpage>15960</fpage>
                <lpage>4</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16247010</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pf.REF.hamvas.2006.316">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamvas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>
                <year>2006</year>
                <article-title>Inherited surfactant protein-B deficiency and surfactant
protein-C associated disease: clinical features and
evaluation.</article-title>
                <source>Semin Perinatol.</source>
                <volume>30</volume>
                <fpage>316</fpage>
                <lpage>26</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17142157</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="pf.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="pf.Author_Notes">
          <title>Author Notes</title>
          <p>David Schwartz is a professor of medicine and immunology at the University of
Colorado and National Jewish Health, and is serving as the Robert Schrier Chair
of the Department of Medicine at the University of Colorado. Throughout his
career, Dr. Schwartz has made numerous contributions toward understanding the
role that biological and genetic determinants play in the onset of diseases that
are influenced by the environment. These efforts have provided new insights into
the genetics, epigenetics, and genomics of interstitial lung disease, asthma,
and innate immunity. His work has led to the recognition that genetic
susceptibility, and specifically <italic toggle="yes">MUC5B</italic>, plays a role in the
etiology of pulmonary fibrosis. Dr. Schwartz&#x02019;s lab was the first to clone the
human<italic toggle="yes">TLR4</italic> gene and demonstrate that variation in this gene
decreased immune responsiveness to endotoxin, enhanced the risk of Gram negative
sepsis, and protected individuals from the development of coronary artery
disease. In addition, the Schwartz lab demonstrated the potential importance of
locus-specific DNA methylation in the development of allergic airway disease in
mice and young children by directing the maturation of T lymphocytes toward a
Th2 phenotype. Prior to moving to Denver, Dr. Schwartz served as Director of the
National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences at the NIH. While at the
NIH, he developed the Genes, Environment and Health Initiative, the Epigenomics
Roadmap Initiative, and a program in translational research in environmental
sciences. Between 2000 and 2005, Dr. Schwartz served at Duke University, where
he held concurrent positions as Vice Chair for Research and Director of
Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine. While at Duke, Dr. Schwartz established
three interdisciplinary Centers in Environmental Health Sciences, Environmental
Genomics, and Environmental Asthma, illustrating his commitment to critical
biomedical concerns and public health issues. He is a member of the American
Society for Clinical Investigation, the Association of American Physicians, and
the American Clinical and Climatological Association, and a recipient of the
2003 ATS Scientific Accomplishment Award, the 2013 ATS Amberson Lectureship
Award, and the 2014 Bonfils-Stanton Science and Medicine Award.</p>
          <p>Janet Talbert earned her Bachelor of Science (BS) at Tennessee Technological
University and her Master of Science (MS) in Biophysics and Genetics at the
University of Colorado Denver Health Sciences Center. She became a certified
genetic counselor through board certification by the Diplomate of the American
Board of Genetic Counselors (ABGC) in 2009. She is a member of the National
Society of Genetic Counselors (NSGC). After laboratory experience for genetic
identity testing and genetic research, she turned her focus to clinical
research. She has been part of the Interstitial Lung Disease Program at National
Jewish Health since 2003 in roles that include coordinating a Familial Pulmonary
Fibrosis study and providing genetic counseling services for the institution at
large and to patients and families with IPF. She is the director of the Familial
Pulmonary Fibrosis Genetic Counseling telephone line at National Jewish Health
which is supported by the Coalition for Pulmonary Fibrosis (CPF) and the
Pulmonary Fibrosis Foundation (PFF). She serves on the medical advisory board of
the PFF and is part of an education outreach Ambassador Program for the PFF.
</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Author_History">
          <title>Author History </title>
          <p>Janet Talbert, MS, CGC (2010-present)David Schwartz, MD
(2005-present)Anastasia Wise, PhD; National Jewish Health
(2005-2010)</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="pf.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>19 March 2015 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>19 October 2010 (me) Comprehensive update posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>3 February 2009 (cd) Revision: prenatal testing for <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic>
and <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> mutations available clinically</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>2 October 2007 (cd) Revision: mutations in <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> and
<italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> reported to "increase susceptibility to
adult-onset IPF" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.armanios.2007.1317">Armanios et al 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pf.REF.tsakiri.2007.7552">Tsakiri et al 2007</xref>]; molecular
testing for <italic toggle="yes">TERT</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">TERC</italic> mutations
available on a clinical basis but the predictive value of the tests is
as yet unclear. </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>11 June 2007 (me) Comprehensive update posted to live Web site </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>21 January 2005 (me) Review posted to live Web site </p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>8 April 2004 (ds) Original submission </p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
