<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book-part-wrapper PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD BITS Book Interchange DTD v2.0 20151225//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/extensions/bits/2.0/BITS-book2.dtd">
<book-part-wrapper id="slc39a14-def" content-type="chapter" from-where="body" dtd-version="2.0">
  <book-meta>
    <book-id book-id-type="pmcid">gene</book-id>
    <book-title-group>
      <book-title>GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></book-title>
    </book-title-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Adam</surname>
          <given-names>Margaret P</given-names>
        </name>
        <role>Editor-in-Chief</role>
      </contrib>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ardinger</surname>
          <given-names>Holly H</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Pagon</surname>
          <given-names>Roberta A</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Wallace</surname>
          <given-names>Stephanie E</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Senior Editors</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Bean</surname>
          <given-names>Lora JH</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Mefford</surname>
          <given-names>Heather C</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Stephens</surname>
          <given-names>Karen</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Molecular Genetics</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <contrib-group>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Amemiya</surname>
          <given-names>Anne</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <contrib contrib-type="editor">
        <name name-style="western">
          <surname>Ledbetter</surname>
          <given-names>Nikki</given-names>
        </name>
      </contrib>
      <role>Genetic Counseling</role>
    </contrib-group>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>1993</year>
    </pub-date>
    <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pubr">
      <year>2017</year>
    </pub-date>
    <issn>2372-0697</issn>
    <publisher>
      <publisher-name>University of Washington, Seattle</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc>
    </publisher>
    <permissions>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 1993-2017, University of Washington, Seattle. GeneReviews is a registered trademark of the University of Washington, Seattle. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
      <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK138602/">
        <license-p>GeneReviews&#x000ae; chapters are owned by the University of Washington. Permission is hereby granted to reproduce, distribute, and translate copies of content materials for noncommercial research purposes only, provided that (i) credit for source (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genereviews.org/">http://www.genereviews.org/</ext-link>) and copyright (&#x000a9; 1993-2017 University of Washington) are included with each copy; (ii) a link to the original material is provided whenever the material is published elsewhere on the Web; and (iii) reproducers, distributors, and/or translators comply with the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>. No further modifications are allowed. For clarity, excerpts of GeneReviews chapters for use in lab reports and clinic notes are a permitted use.</license-p>
        <license-p>For more information, see the <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="GRcopyright_permiss">GeneReviews&#x000ae; Copyright Notice and Usage Disclaimer</related-object>.</license-p>
        <license-p>For questions regarding permissions or whether a specified use is allowed, contact: <email>admasst@uw.edu</email>.</license-p>
      </license>
    </permissions>
    <custom-meta-group>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Genetics</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Medicine</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-subject</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Diseases</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
      <custom-meta>
        <meta-name>books-source-type</meta-name>
        <meta-value>Database</meta-value>
      </custom-meta>
    </custom-meta-group>
    <notes notes-type="ednotes">
      <p content-type="genetic_counseling">
<italic toggle="yes">Genetic counseling is the process of
providing individuals and families with information on the nature, inheritance,
and implications of genetic disorders to help them make informed medical and
personal decisions. The following section deals with genetic risk assessment and
the use of family history and genetic testing to clarify genetic status for
family members. This section is not meant to address all personal, cultural, or
ethical issues that individuals may face or to substitute for consultation with
a genetics professional</italic>. &#x02014;ED.</p>
      <p content-type="resources">
<italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews staff has selected the following disease-specific and/or
umbrella support organizations and/or registries for the benefit of individuals
with this disorder and their families. GeneReviews is not responsible for the
information provided by other organizations. For information on selection
criteria, click <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="app4">here</related-object>.</italic></p>
    </notes>
  </book-meta>
  <book-part book-part-type="chapter">
    <book-part-meta>
      <book-part-id book-part-id-type="pmcid">slc39a14-def</book-part-id>
      <title-group>
        <title>SLC39A14 Deficiency</title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="alt-title">Synonym: <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic>-Related Early-Onset Dystonia-Parkinsonism</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Tuschl</surname>
            <given-names>Karin</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>UCL Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health<break/>King&#x02019;s College London<break/>London, United Kingdom</aff>
          <email>k.tuschl@ucl.ac.uk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gregory</surname>
            <given-names>Allison</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS, CGC</degrees>
          <aff>Oregon Health and Science University<break/>Portland, Oregon</aff>
          <email>gregorya@ohsu.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Meyer</surname>
            <given-names>Esther</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>UCL Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health<break/>London, United Kingdom</aff>
          <email>esther.meyer@nbt.nhs.uk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Clayton</surname>
            <given-names>Peter T</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>UCL Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health<break/>London, United Kingdom</aff>
          <email>peter.clayton@ucl.ac.uk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hayflick</surname>
            <given-names>Susan J</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Oregon Health and Science University<break/>Portland, Oregon</aff>
          <email>hayflick@ohsu.edu</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mills</surname>
            <given-names>Philippa B</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>UCL Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health<break/>London, United Kingdom</aff>
          <email>p.mills@ucl.ac.uk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kurian</surname>
            <given-names>Manju A</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>UCL Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health<break/>London, United Kingdom</aff>
          <email>manju.kurian@ucl.ac.uk</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-history>
        <date date-type="created">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </pub-history>
      <related-object link-type="parent-book-link" source-id="gene">GeneReviews<sup>&#x000ae;</sup></related-object>
      <related-object link-type="previous-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="lwd" document-type="chapter">SHOX Deficiency Disorders</related-object>
      <related-object link-type="next-part-link" source-id="gene" document-id="slc6a3-dtds" document-type="chapter"><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>-Related Dopamine Transporter Deficiency Syndrome</related-object>
      <abstract id="slc39a14-def.Summary">
        <title>Summary</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical characteristics</title>
          <p>SLC39A14 deficiency is characterized by evidence between ages six months and three years of delay or loss of motor developmental milestones (e.g., delayed walking, gait disturbance). Early in the disease course, children show axial hypotonia followed by dystonia, spasticity, dysarthria, bulbar dysfunction, and signs of parkinsonism including bradykinesia, hypomimia, and tremor. By the end of the first decade they develop severe, generalized, pharmaco-resistant dystonia, limb contractures, and scoliosis, and lose independent ambulation. Cognitive impairment appears to be less prominent than motor disability. Some affected children have succumbed in their first decade due to secondary complications such as respiratory infections.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnosis/testing</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of SLC39A14 deficiency is established in a proband with progressive dystonia-parkinsonism (often combined with other signs such as spasticity and parkinsonian features), characteristic neuroimaging findings, hypermanganesemia, and biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> on molecular genetic testing.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Management</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Treatment of manifestations:</italic> Symptomatic treatment includes physiotherapy and orthopedic management to prevent contractures and maintain ambulation; use of adaptive aids (walker or wheelchair) for gait abnormalities; and use of assistive communication devices. Support by a speech and language/feeding specialist and nutritionist to assure adequate nutrition and to reduce the risk of aspiration. When an adequate oral diet can no longer be maintained, gastrostomy tube placement should be considered. Antispasticity medications (baclofen and botulinum toxin) and L-dopa have had limited success. While chelation therapy with intravenous administration of disodium calcium edetate early in the disease course shows promise, additional studies are warranted.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Prevention of primary manifestations:</italic> Unknown, but disodium calcium edetate chelation therapy shows promise; additional studies are warranted.</p>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Surveillance:</italic> Routine monitoring of:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Height and weight using age- and gender-appropriate growth charts;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Swallowing and diet to assure adequate nutrition;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ambulation and speech;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Whole-blood manganese levels and brain MRI to assess treatment response and disease progression.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <italic toggle="yes">Agents/circumstances to avoid:</italic>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Environmental manganese exposure (i.e., contaminated drinking water, occupational manganese exposure in welding/mining industries, contaminated ephedrone preparations)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>High manganese content of total parenteral nutrition</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Foods very high in manganese, including: cloves; saffron; nuts; mussels; dark chocolate; pumpkin, sesame, and sunflower seeds</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">Evaluation of relatives at risk:</italic> Molecular genetic testing for the familial <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variants of apparently asymptomatic younger sibs of an affected individual allows early identification of sibs who would benefit from prompt initiation of treatment and preventive measures.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Genetic counseling</title>
          <p>SLC39A14 deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder. At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier. Once the <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, carrier testing of at-risk relatives, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk, and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </book-part-meta>
    <body>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.Diagnosis">
        <title>Diagnosis</title>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Suggestive_Findings">
          <title>Suggestive Findings</title>
          <p>SLC39A14 deficiency <bold>should be suspected</bold> in individuals with typical clinical, neuroimaging, and laboratory findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>]:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Clinical findings.</bold> Infantile or early-childhood onset of:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Delay in acquisition of developmental motor milestones or loss of developmental motor milestones;</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Progressive pharmaco-resistant dystonia;</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Parkinsonism signs (tremor, bradykinesia, hypomimia);</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Bulbar dysfunction;</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Dysarthria.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Neuroimaging.</bold> Brain MRI findings characteristic of manganese deposition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="slc39a14-def.F1">Figure 1</xref>) including T<sub>1</sub>-weighted hyperintensity of the following:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>Globus pallidus and striatum, with thalamic sparing;</p>
                  <p>Note: Basal ganglia changes on T<sub>1</sub>-weighted imaging are accompanied by T<sub>2</sub>-weighted hypointensity.</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>White matter including the cerebellum, spinal cord, and dorsal pons, with sparing of the ventral pons;</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>Anterior pituitary gland.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p><bold>Laboratory findings.</bold> Hypermanganesemia. Whole-blood manganese levels are markedly elevated, usually above 1,000 nmol/L (normal reference range &#x0003c;320 nmol/L).</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Establishing_the_Diagnosis">
          <title>Establishing the Diagnosis</title>
          <p>The diagnosis of SLC39A14 deficiency <bold>is established</bold> in a proband with progressive dystonia (often combined with other signs such as spasticity and parkinsonian features), characteristic neuroimaging findings, hypermanganesemia, and identification of biallelic pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> on molecular genetic testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing">Table 1</xref>).</p>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing approaches can include a combination of <bold>gene-targeted testing</bold> (single-gene testing or a multi-gene panel) and <bold>genomic testing</bold> (comprehensive genome sequencing) depending on the phenotype.</p>
          <p>Gene-targeted testing requires the clinician to determine which gene(s) are likely involved, whereas genomic testing does not. Because the phenotype of SLC39A14 deficiency is likely to be broad, children with the suggestive clinical, laboratory, and neuroimaging findings could be diagnosed using gene-targeted testing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc39a14-def.Option_1">Option 1</xref>), whereas those with early-onset dystonia-parkinsonism indistinguishable from other inherited disorders with parkinsonism-dystonia are more likely to be diagnosed using genomic testing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc39a14-def.Option_2">Option 2</xref>).</p>
          <sec id="slc39a14-def.Option_1">
            <title>Option 1</title>
            <p>When the clinical, laboratory, and brain MRI findings suggest the diagnosis of SLC39A14 deficiency, molecular genetic testing approaches can include <bold>single-gene testing</bold> and use of a <bold>multi-gene panel</bold>.</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Single-gene testing.</bold> Sequence analysis of <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> is performed first. If only one pathogenic variant is found, gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis could be considered; however, to date no exon or whole-gene deletions have been reported.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>A multi-gene panel</bold> that includes <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc39a14-def.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may also be considered.</p>
                <p>Note: (1) The genes included in the panel and the diagnostic sensitivity of the testing used for each gene vary by laboratory and over time. (2) Some multi-gene panels may include genes not associated with the condition discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic>; thus, clinicians need to determine which multi-gene panel provides the best opportunity to identify the genetic cause of condition at the most reasonable cost while limiting identification of pathogenic variants in genes that do not explain the underlying phenotype. (3) Methods used in a panel may include sequence analysis, deletion/duplication analysis, and/or other non-sequencing based tests.</p>
                <p>For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
          </sec>
          <sec id="slc39a14-def.Option_2">
            <title>Option 2</title>
            <p>When the phenotype is indistinguishable from other movement disorders, molecular genetic testing approaches can include a combination of <bold>genomic testing</bold> (comprehensive genome sequencing; recommended) or <bold>gene-targeted testing</bold> (multi-gene panel; to consider).</p>
            <list list-type="bullet">
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Recommended testing.</bold> Comprehensive genome sequencing (when available) includes exome sequencing and genome sequencing. For more information on comprehensive genome sequencing, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.Comprehensive_Genome_Sequencing" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
              </list-item>
              <list-item>
                <p><bold>Testing to consider.</bold> A multi-gene panel that includes <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> and other genes of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc39a14-def.Differential_Diagnosis">Differential Diagnosis</xref>) may be considered; however, given the rarity of SLC39A14 deficiency, many panels for inherited dystonia-parkinsonism and/or this complex neurologic phenotype may not include this gene. For more information on multi-gene panels click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app5" document-type="appendix" object-id="app5.MultiGene_Panels" object-type="sec">here</related-object>.</p>
              </list-item>
            </list>
            <table-wrap id="slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
              <label>Table 1. </label>
              <caption>
                <p>Molecular Genetic Testing Used in SLC39A14 Deficiency</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></th>
                    <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test Method</th>
                    <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of Probands with Pathogenic Variants&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup> Detectable by This Method</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">SLC</italic>3<italic toggle="yes">9A14</italic></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence analysis&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/7&#x000a0;<sup>6</sup></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                    <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.molecular_genetic_testing_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None reported</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
              <table-wrap-foot>
                <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.1.1">
                  <label>1. </label>
                  <p>See <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="slc39a14-def" object-id="slc39a14-def.molgen.TA">Table A. Genes and Databases</related-object> for chromosome locus and protein.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.1.2">
                  <label>2. </label>
                  <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc39a14-def.Molecular_Genetics">Molecular Genetics</xref> for information on allelic variants detected in this gene.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.1.3">
                  <label>3. </label>
                  <p>Sequence analysis detects variants that are benign, likely benign, of uncertain significance, likely pathogenic, or pathogenic. Pathogenic variants may include small intragenic deletions/insertions and missense, nonsense, and splice site variants; typically, exon or whole-gene deletions/duplications are not detected. For issues to consider in interpretation of sequence analysis results, click <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app2" document-type="appendix">here</related-object>.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.1.4">
                  <label>4. </label>
                  <p>Gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis detects intragenic deletions or duplications. Methods that may be used include: quantitative PCR, long-range PCR, multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification (MLPA), and a gene-targeted microarray designed to detect single-exon deletions or duplications.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.1.5">
                  <label>5. </label>
                  <p>No data on detection rate of gene-targeted deletion/duplication analysis are available.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.1.6">
                  <label>6. </label>
                  <p>Five reported consanguineous families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>] and two other families, one consanguineous and one non-consanguineous [Author, personal observation]</p>
                </fn>
              </table-wrap-foot>
            </table-wrap>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.Clinical_Characteristics">
        <title>Clinical Characteristics</title>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Clinical_Description">
          <title>Clinical Description</title>
          <p>SLC39A14 deficiency has only recently been identified in 11 individuals from seven families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>; Author, personal observation]; therefore, information on the phenotypic spectrum and disease progression is limited.</p>
          <p>Onset occurs between ages six months and three years. Affected children present with delay or loss of motor developmental milestones (e.g., delayed walking, gait disturbance).</p>
          <p>Early in the disease course, children show axial hypotonia followed by dystonia, spasticity, dysarthria, bulbar dysfunction, and signs of parkinsonism including bradykinesia, hypomimia, and tremor.</p>
          <p>By the end of the first decade, they develop severe, generalized, pharmaco-resistant dystonia, limb contractures, scoliosis, and loss of independent ambulation.</p>
          <p>Although there appears to be relative cognitive sparing (psychometric testing has not been possible), a degree of learning disability is present in all children.</p>
          <p>Some affected children succumb in their first decade due to secondary complications such as respiratory infections.</p>
          <p><bold>Neuropathology.</bold> The neuropathologic findings in one individual with SLC39A14 deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>] included:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Extensive gliosis and neuronal loss in the globus pallidus and dentate nucleus;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Preservation of neurons in the cerebral and cerebellar cortex as well as the caudate, putamen, and thalamus;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>A vacuolated myelinopathy with patchy axonal loss in the cerebral and cerebellar white matter.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.GenotypePhenotype_Correlati">
          <title>Genotype-Phenotype Correlations</title>
          <p>No genotype-phenotype correlations are known.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Prevalence">
          <title>Prevalence</title>
          <p>The disease prevalence is not established. To date only 11 individuals with SLC39A14 deficiency from seven families have been identified. These seven families are from different ethnic backgrounds and six are consanguineous [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>; Author, personal observation].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.Genetically_Related_Allelic">
        <title>Genetically Related (Allelic) Disorders</title>
        <p>No phenotypes other than those discussed in this <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic> are known to be associated with pathogenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.Differential_Diagnosis">
        <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
        <table-wrap id="slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
          <label>Table 2. </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Disorders to Consider in the Differential Diagnosis of SLC39A14 Deficiency</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" rowspan="2" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1">Disorder</th>
                <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2">Gene(s)</th>
                <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1" headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3">MOI</th>
                <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" valign="middle" colspan="2" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Clinical Features of This Disorder</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Overlapping with SLC39A14 Deficiency</th>
                <th headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4" id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distinguishing from SLC39A14 Deficiency</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Disorders of manganese homeostasis</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="hmdpc" document-type="chapter">Dystonia/parkinsonism, hypermanganesemia, polycythemia, and chronic liver disease</related-object> (SLC30A10 deficiency)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">SLC30A10</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Dystonia-parkinsonism</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hypermanganesemia</p></list-item><list-item><p>Brain MRI features consistent w/manganese deposition</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Presents with polycythemia, abnormal iron indices, &#x00026; liver disease in addition to the neurologic phenotype</p></list-item><list-item><p>Absence of Mn deposition in the liver w/T<sub>1</sub> hyperintensity on liver MRI</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Acquired hypermanganesemia&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Often presents w/psychiatric symptoms</p></list-item><list-item><p>History of Mn exposure from environmental sources, parenteral nutrition, or contaminated ephedrone preparations</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Acquired hepatocerebral degeneration&#x000a0;<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Liver disease is the predominant feature; it precedes development of neurologic symptoms.</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" rowspan="7" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><bold>Early-onset NBIA disorders</bold> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="nbia-ov" document-type="chapter">NBIA Overview</related-object>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="pkan" document-type="chapter">PKAN</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">PANK2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_1" rowspan="7" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Parkinsonism-dystonia</p></list-item><list-item><p>T<sub>2</sub>-weighted hypointensity of the globus pallidus on brain MRI</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" rowspan="7" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Usually presents w/additional clinical features (e.g., pigmentary retinopathy, optic atrophy, oculomotor abnormalities, axonal neuropathy, cognitive decline, seizures)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Lacks the T<sub>1</sub>-weighted hyperintensity of the globus pallidus on brain MRI due to Mn deposition</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="inad" document-type="chapter">PLAN</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">PLA2G6</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="mt-mpan" document-type="chapter">MPAN</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">C19orf12</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="bpan" document-type="chapter">BPAN</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">WDR45</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XL</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="fahn" document-type="chapter">FAHN</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">FA2H</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">Kufor-Rakeb syndrome</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ATP13A2</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">CoPAN</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">COASY</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Disorders of copper metabolism</bold>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="wilson" document-type="chapter">Wilson disease</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">ATP7B</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Parkinsonism-dystonia</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Liver disease, psychiatric symptoms, low serum ceruloplasmin &#x00026; high non-ceruloplasmin-bound serum copper</p></list-item><list-item><p>Absence of Mn deposition on brain MRI</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" rowspan="7" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1"><bold>Inherited forms of dystonia</bold> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" document-type="chapter">Dystonia Overview</related-object>)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia" document-type="chapter">DYT1 early-onset isolated dystonia</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">TOR1A</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_1" rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Early-onset generalized dystonia</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>No features consistent w/Mn deposition on brain MRI</p></list-item><list-item><p>Absent hypermanganesemia</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">KMT2B</italic>-related early-onset dystonia&#x000a0;<sup>3</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">KMT2B</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">MECR</italic>-related childhood-onset dystonia and optic atrophy&#x000a0;<sup>4</sup></td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">MECR</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" rowspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Additional optic atrophy</p></list-item><list-item><p>No features consistent w/Mn deposition on brain MRI</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>-related dopamine transporter deficiency syndrome</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">SLC6A3</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_1" rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Parkinsonism-dystonia</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>No features consistent w/Mn deposition on brain MRI</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="thdrd" document-type="chapter">Tyrosine hydroxylase-deficient dopa-responsive dystonia</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">TH</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="drd" document-type="chapter">GTP cyclohydrolase 1-deficient dopa-responsive dystonia</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">GCH1</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">AD</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" colspan="1" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1">
                  <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="spr-def" document-type="chapter">Sepiapterin reductase deficiency dopa-responsive dystonia</related-object>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic toggle="yes">SPR</italic>
                </td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="4" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1"><bold>Inherited Forms of Parkinson Disease</bold> (see <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="parkinson-overview" document-type="chapter">Parkinson Disease Overview</related-object>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_1 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_2 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" colspan="4" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1"><bold>Inherited neurodegenerative/metabolic disorders</bold><break/>(see <related-object source-id="gene" document-id="dystonia-ov" object-id="dystonia-ov.table4">Dystonia Overview, Table 4</related-object> for hereditary neurodegenerative or metabolic<break/>disorders characterized by complex dystonia)</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_1" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Complex dystonia</p></list-item></list>
</td>
                <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_1_4 hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.disorders_to_consider_in_1_1_2_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>No features consistent w/Mn deposition on brain MRI</p></list-item></list>
</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>Mn = manganese</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>MOI = mode of inheritance</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AD = autosomal dominant</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>AR = autosomal recessive</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>XL = X-linked</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>NBIA = neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>PKAN = pantothenate kinase-associated neurodegeneration</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>PLAN = <italic toggle="yes">PLA2G6</italic>-associated neurodegeneration</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>MPAN = mitochondrial membrane protein-associated neurodegeneration</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>BPAN = beta-propeller protein-associated neurodegeneration</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>FAHN = fatty acid hydroxylase-associated neurodegeneration</p>
            </fn>
            <fn>
              <p>CoPAN = COASY protein-associated neurodegeneration</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.2.1">
              <label>1. </label>
              <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.mortimer.2012.1174">Mortimer et al [2012]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.santos.2014.36">Santos et al [2014]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.janochalitwin.2015.832">Janocha-Litwin et al [2015]</xref></p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.2.2">
              <label>2. </label>
              <p>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.mileti_.2014.207">Mileti&#x00107; et al [2014]</xref>
              </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.2.3">
              <label>3. </label>
              <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.zech.2016.1377">Zech et al [2016]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.meyer.2017.223">Meyer et al [2017]</xref></p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.2.4">
              <label>4. </label>
              <p>
                <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.heimer.2016.1229">Heimer et al [2016]</xref>
              </p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.Management">
        <title>Management</title>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Evaluations_Following_Initi">
          <title>Evaluations Following Initial Diagnosis</title>
          <p>To establish the extent of disease and needs in an individual diagnosed with SLC39A14 deficiency, the following evaluations are recommended:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Neurologic examination for dystonia, parkinsonism, and spasticity, including evaluation of ambulation and speech</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment for physiotherapy, occupational therapy, and/or speech therapy</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Evaluation of swallowing and nutritional status</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Brain MRI, if not performed as part of the diagnostic evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of whole-blood manganese levels, if not performed as part of the diagnostic evaluation</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Consultation with a clinical geneticist and/or genetic counselor</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Treatment_of_Manifestations">
          <title>Treatment of Manifestations</title>
          <p><bold>Symptomatic treatment.</bold> Early initiation of physiotherapy and orthopedic management aims to prevent contractures and maintain ambulation. As needed, individuals should be referred for adaptive aids (e.g., a walker or wheelchair for gait abnormalities) and assistive communication devices.</p>
          <p>Support by a speech and language/feeding specialist and nutritionist is indicated to assure adequate nutrition and to reduce the risk of aspiration. When an adequate oral diet can no longer be maintained, gastrostomy tube placement should be considered. Gastric feeding tube and/or tracheostomy may be required to prevent aspiration pneumonia.</p>
          <p>Note that symptomatic treatment with L-dopa and antispasticity medications including benzodiazepines, baclofen, and botulinum toxin has been attempted with limited success. There has been partial but poorly sustained response to trihexyphenidyl at high doses of 20 mg/day and intrathecal baclofen of 1,500-2,000 &#x000b5;g/day in two older sibs reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al [2016]</xref>.</p>
          <p><bold>Chelation therapy.</bold> Disodium calcium edetate, which primarily promotes the urinary excretion of manganese, was given intravenously (20 mg/kg/dose) twice daily for five days each month to a female age five years with SLC39A14 deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>]. After six months of treatment, neurologic manifestations improved and the child regained the ability to walk.</p>
          <p>In contrast, treatment of a female age 17 years with advanced disease (severe generalized dystonia with prominent oromandibular involvement, contractures, and scoliosis) did not affect disease progression as she continued to deteriorate with worsening tremor and stiffness. Hence, it is likely necessary to initiate chelation treatment early in the disease course.</p>
          <p>It is anticipated that chelation therapy will need to be lifelong.</p>
          <p>Potential adverse effects of disodium calcium edetate chelation therapy include thrombocytopenia and leukopenia, nephrotoxicity, hepatoxicity, hypocalcemia, and trace metal and vitamin deficiencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.lamas.2012.7">Lamas et al 2012</xref>]. Monitoring includes the following:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Complete blood count</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of renal function including urinalysis assessed at baseline and monthly thereafter. Monitoring may be extended to every other month once on a stable dose.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of liver function</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Measurement of the concentrations of electrolytes, calcium, magnesium, and phosphate</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Measurement of the concentrations of trace metals (manganese, zinc, copper, and selenium)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Assessment of iron status</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>Treatment may need to be discontinued if:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>White blood count is &#x0003c;3.5x10<sup>9</sup>/L</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Neutrophil count is &#x0003c;2.0x10<sup>9</sup>/L</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Platelet count is &#x0003c;150x10<sup>9</sup>/L</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>&#x0003e;2+ proteinuria is detected on more than one occasion (with no evidence of infection)</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>The above cut-off values are based on guidelines for D-penicillamine treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.chakravarty.2008.924">Chakravarty et al 2008</xref>]. Because chelation treatment with disodium calcium edetate may prevent early death and reduce morbidity in SLC39A14 deficiency, lower cut-off values may be acceptable. For each affected individual, the benefits of clinical treatment need to be carefully weighed against the risk of adverse effects.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Prevention_of_Primary_Manif">
          <title>Prevention of Primary Manifestations</title>
          <p>Chelation therapy with disodium calcium edetate may prevent primary disease manifestations in affected sibs who are asymptomatic (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc39a14-def.Treatment_of_Manifestations">Treatment of Manifestations</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Surveillance">
          <title>Surveillance</title>
          <p>Routine monitoring of:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Height and weight using age and gender appropriate growth charts;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Swallowing and diet to assure adequate nutrition;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Ambulation and speech;</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Whole-blood manganese levels and brain MRI to assess treatment response and disease progression.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoi">
          <title>Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</title>
          <p>The following should be avoided:</p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Environmental manganese exposure (i.e., contaminated drinking water, occupational manganese exposure in welding/mining industries, contaminated ephedrone preparations)</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>High manganese content of total parenteral nutrition</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Foods very high in manganese, including: cloves; saffron; nuts; mussels; dark chocolate; and pumpkin, sesame, and sunflower seeds</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at">
          <title>Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</title>
          <p>Molecular genetic testing of apparently asymptomatic younger sibs of an affected individual for the familial <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variants allows early identification of sibs who would benefit from prompt initiation of treatment and preventive measures (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc39a14-def.AgentsCircumstances_to_Avoi">Agents/Circumstances to Avoid</xref>).</p>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc39a14-def.Related_Genetic_Counseling">Genetic Counseling</xref> for issues related to testing of at-risk relatives for genetic counseling purposes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Therapies_Under_Investigati">
          <title>Therapies Under Investigation</title>
          <p>Search <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> for access to information on clinical studies for a wide range of diseases and conditions.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.Genetic_Counseling">
        <title>Genetic Counseling</title>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Mode_of_Inheritance">
          <title>Mode of Inheritance</title>
          <p>SLC39A14 deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Six of the seven families reported to date were consanguineous.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Parents of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The parents of an affected child are obligate heterozygotes (i.e., carriers of one <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variant).</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <bold>Sibs of a proband</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>At conception, each sib of an affected individual has a 25% chance of being affected, a 50% chance of being an asymptomatic carrier, and a 25% chance of being unaffected and not a carrier.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>Heterozygotes (carriers) are asymptomatic and are not at risk of developing the disorder.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>Offspring of a proband.</bold> The offspring of an individual with SLC39A14 deficiency are obligate heterozygotes (carriers) for a pathogenic variant in <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic>.</p>
          <p><bold>Other family members.</bold> Each sib of the proband&#x02019;s parents is at a 50% risk of being a carrier of a <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Carrier_Heterozygote_Detect">
          <title>Carrier (Heterozygote) Detection</title>
          <p>Carrier testing for at-risk relatives requires prior identification of the <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variants in the family. Carrier testing for reproductive partners of known carriers is appropriate, particularly if consanguinity is likely.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Related_Genetic_Counseling">
          <title>Related Genetic Counseling Issues</title>
          <p>See Management, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="slc39a14-def.Evaluation_of_Relatives_at">Evaluation of Relatives at Risk</xref> for information on evaluating at-risk relatives for the purpose of early diagnosis and treatment.</p>
          <p>
            <bold>Family planning</bold>
          </p>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>The optimal time for determination of genetic risk, clarification of carrier status, and discussion of the availability of prenatal testing is before pregnancy.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>It is appropriate to offer genetic counseling (including discussion of potential risks to offspring and reproductive options) to young adults who are affected, are carriers, or are at risk of being carriers.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
          <p><bold>DNA banking</bold> is the storage of DNA (typically extracted from white blood cells) for possible future use. Because it is likely that testing methodology and our understanding of genes, allelic variants, and diseases will improve in the future, consideration should be given to banking DNA of affected individuals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Prenatal_Testing_and_Preimp">
          <title>Prenatal Testing and Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis</title>
          <p>Once the <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variants have been identified in an affected family member, prenatal testing for a pregnancy at increased risk and preimplantation genetic diagnosis are possible.</p>
          <p>Differences in perspective may exist among medical professionals and within families regarding the use of prenatal testing, particularly if the testing is being considered for the purpose of pregnancy termination rather than early diagnosis. Although most centers would consider decisions about prenatal testing to be the choice of the parents, discussion of these issues is appropriate.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.Resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.Molecular_Genetics">
        <title>Molecular Genetics</title>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Molecular_Genetic_Pathogene">
          <title>Molecular Genetic Pathogenesis</title>
          <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> encodes a divalent metal transporter that is required for cellular uptake of manganese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>]. It plays a crucial role as a regulator of manganese homeostasis by facilitating manganese uptake into the liver for subsequent excretion in bile.</p>
          <p>Biallelic <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variants are thought to impair hepatic manganese uptake and lead to accumulation of manganese in the blood. Subsequent deposition of manganese in the brain, particularly the globus pallidus, results in manganese toxicity and causes progressive dystonia (often combined with other signs such as spasticity and parkinsonian features) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Gene structure.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> comprises nine exons and encodes four transcripts. Two transcripts differ by an alternative 5&#x02019;UTR (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001128431.2">NM_001128431.2</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001135153">NM_001135153</ext-link>). Alternative splicing of exon 4 and 9 generates two alternative transcripts (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_015359.4">NM_015359.4</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_001135154.1">NM_001135154.1</ext-link>).</p>
          <p><bold>Pathogenic variants.</bold> Homozygous or compound heterozygous <italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variants documented in seven families include missense, nonsense and deletion variants (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss">Table 3</xref>).</p>
          <p>Pathogenic variants are predicted to (1) cause a significantly truncated protein because of a frameshift and premature stop codon, (2) affect an evolutionary highly conserved area of the protein, or (3) lead to abnormal splicing. Therefore, these sequence changes have detrimental effects on protein function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <table-wrap id="slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <label>Table 3. </label>
            <caption>
              <p><italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> Variants Discussed in This <italic toggle="yes">GeneReview</italic></p>
            </caption>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA Nucleotide Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predicted Protein Change</th>
                  <th id="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_3" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference Sequences</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.292T&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Phe98Val</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_3" rowspan="8" valign="middle" align="left" colspan="1">
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NM_015359.4">NM_015359.4</ext-link>
                    <break/>
                    <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_056174.2">NP_056174.2</ext-link>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.313G&#x0003e;T</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Glu105Ter</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.367C&#x0003e;T</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gln123Ter</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.477_478delCA</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ser160CysfsTer5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.512G&#x0003e;A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly171Glu</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1147G&#x0003e;A</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly383Arg</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.1407C&#x0003e;G</td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Asn469Lys</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_1" valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.751-9C&#x0003e;G&#x000a0;<sup>1,&#x000a0;2</sup></td>
                  <td headers="hd_h_slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss_1_1_1_2" valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.His251ProfsTer26&#x000a0;<sup>1</sup></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            <table-wrap-foot>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on variant classification: Variants listed in the table have been provided by the authors. <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> staff have not independently verified the classification of variants.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>Note on nomenclature: <italic toggle="yes">GeneReviews</italic> follows the standard naming conventions of the Human Genome Variation Society (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://varnomen.hgvs.org/">varnomen.hgvs.org</ext-link>). See <related-object link-type="booklink" source-id="gene" document-id="app3" document-type="appendix">Quick Reference</related-object> for an explanation of nomenclature.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.3.1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <p>cDNA analysis confirmed an eight-nucleotide insertion (c.751_752insCTTCCAGC) from intron 5 indicating that this variant creates a new splice-acceptor site [Author, personal observation].</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="slc39a14-def.TF.3.2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <p>g.22,273,273C&#x0003e;G (GRCh37/hg19)</p>
              </fn>
            </table-wrap-foot>
          </table-wrap>
          <p><bold>Normal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> encodes three protein isoforms. Isoforms 1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_001121903">NP_001121903</ext-link>) and 2 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_056174.2">NP_056174</ext-link>) have 492 amino acids; isoform 3 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_001128626">NP_001128626</ext-link>) has 481 amino acids. They contain eight transmembrane domains, a histidine-rich motif (HXHXHX), and a metalloprotease motif (H/EEXPHEXGD) required for metal transport [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.taylor.2005.427">Taylor et al 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tominaga.2005.1590">Tominaga et al 2005</xref>].</p>
          <p>Only isoforms 1 and 2 have been studied in detail; both localize to the plasma membrane and transport manganese, iron, zinc, and cadmium. While isoform 1 is ubiquitously expressed, expression of isoform 2 is restricted to liver, gastrointestinal tract, kidney, and pancreas with no expression in the brain. Isoform 2 is thought to act as the main regulator of manganese homeostasis, facilitating hepatic manganese uptake for biliary excretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>].</p>
          <p><bold>Abnormal gene product.</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">SLC39A14</italic> pathogenic variants described in affected individuals (<xref ref-type="table" rid="slc39a14-def.T.slc39a14_variants_discuss">Table 3</xref>) have deleterious effects on protein function. While wild-type SLC39A14 expressed in HEK-293 cells facilitates manganese uptake, mutated SLC39A14 results in greatly reduced manganese uptake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">Tuschl et al 2016</xref>].</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.References">
        <title>References</title>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Literature_Cited">
          <title>Literature Cited</title>
          <ref-list id="slc39a14-def.Literature_Cited.reflist0">
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.chakravarty.2008.924">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chakravarty</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McDonald</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pullar</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taggart</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chalmers</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Oliver</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mooney</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Somerville</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bosworth</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kennedy</surname>
                    <given-names>T.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>BSR/BHPR guideline for disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drug (DMARD) therapy in consultation with the British Association of Dermatologists.</article-title>
                <source>Rheumatology.</source>
                <year>2008</year>
                <volume>47</volume>
                <fpage>924</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16940305</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.heimer.2016.1229">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heimer</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ker&#x000e4;t&#x000e4;r</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Riley</surname>
                    <given-names>LG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Balasubramaniam</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eyal</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pietik&#x000e4;inen</surname>
                    <given-names>LP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hiltunen</surname>
                    <given-names>JK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marek-Yagel</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hamada</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gregory</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rogers</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hogarth</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nance</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Shalva</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Veber</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tzadok</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nissenkorn</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tonduti</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Renaldo</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kraoua</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Panteghini</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valletta</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Garavaglia</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cowley</surname>
                    <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gayevskiy</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Roscioli</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Silberstein</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hoffmann</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raas-Rothschild</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tiranti</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Anikster</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Christodoulou</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kastaniotis</surname>
                    <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ben-Zeev</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>MECR mutations cause childhood-onset dystonia and optic atrophy, a mitochondrial fatty acid synthesis disorder.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>99</volume>
                <fpage>1229</fpage>
                <lpage>44</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27817865</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.janochalitwin.2015.832">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Janocha-Litwin</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marianska</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Serafinska</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Simon</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Manganese encephalopathy among ephedron abusers.</article-title>
                <source>J Neuroimaging.</source>
                <year>2015</year>
                <volume>25</volume>
                <fpage>832</fpage>
                <lpage>5</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25255816</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.lamas.2012.7">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lamas</surname>
                    <given-names>GA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Goertz</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boineau</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mark</surname>
                    <given-names>DB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rozema</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nahin</surname>
                    <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Drisko</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>KL</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Design of the Trial to Assess Chelation Therapy (TACT).</article-title>
                <source>Am Heart J.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>163</volume>
                <fpage>7</fpage>
                <lpage>12</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22172430</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.meyer.2017.223">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meyer</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carss</surname>
                    <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rankin</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nichols</surname>
                    <given-names>JM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Grozeva</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Joseph</surname>
                    <given-names>AP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mencacci</surname>
                    <given-names>NE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Papandreou</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ng</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barral</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ngoh</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ben-Pazi</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Willemsen</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Arkadir</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Barnicoat</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bergman</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhate</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boys</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Darin</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Foulds</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gutowski</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hills</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houlden</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hurst</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Israel</surname>
                    <given-names>Z</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kaminska</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Limousin</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lumsden</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>McKee</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Misra</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mohammed</surname>
                    <given-names>SS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nakou</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nicolai</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nilsson</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pall</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peall</surname>
                    <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Peters</surname>
                    <given-names>GB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prabhakar</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reuter</surname>
                    <given-names>MS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rump</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Segel</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sinnema</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Turnpenny</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>White</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wieczorek</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wiethoff</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wilson</surname>
                    <given-names>BT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Winter</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wragg</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pope</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Heales</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morrogh</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pittman</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Carr</surname>
                    <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Perez-Due&#x000f1;as</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Lin</surname>
                    <given-names>JP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Reis</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gahl</surname>
                    <given-names>WA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Toro</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                    <given-names>KP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wood</surname>
                    <given-names>NW</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kamsteeg</surname>
                    <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chong</surname>
                    <given-names>WK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gissen</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Topf</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dale</surname>
                    <given-names>RC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chubb</surname>
                    <given-names>JR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Raymond</surname>
                    <given-names>FL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kurian</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <etal/>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in the histone methyltransferase gene KMT2B cause complex early-onset dystonia.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Genet.</source>
                <year>2017</year>
                <volume>49</volume>
                <fpage>223</fpage>
                <lpage>37</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27992417</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.mileti_.2014.207">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mileti&#x00107;</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ozreti&#x00107;</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Relja</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Parkinsonian syndrome and ataxia as a presenting finding of acquired hepatocerebral degeneration.</article-title>
                <source>Metab Brain Dis.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>29</volume>
                <fpage>207</fpage>
                <lpage>9</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24390157</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.mortimer.2012.1174">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mortimer</surname>
                    <given-names>JA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Borenstein</surname>
                    <given-names>AR</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nelson</surname>
                    <given-names>LM</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Associations of welding and manganese exposure with Parkinson disease: review and meta-analysis.</article-title>
                <source>Neurology.</source>
                <year>2012</year>
                <volume>79</volume>
                <fpage>1174</fpage>
                <lpage>80</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22965675</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.santos.2014.36">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Santos</surname>
                    <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Batoreu</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mateus</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Marreilha Dos Santos</surname>
                    <given-names>AP</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Aschner</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Manganese in human parenteral nutrition: considerations for toxicity and biomonitoring.</article-title>
                <source>Neurotoxicology.</source>
                <year>2014</year>
                <volume>43</volume>
                <fpage>36</fpage>
                <lpage>45</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24184781</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.taylor.2005.427">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Taylor</surname>
                    <given-names>KM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Morgan</surname>
                    <given-names>HE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nicholson</surname>
                    <given-names>RI</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Structure-function analysis of a novel member of the LIV-1 subfamily of zinc transporters, ZIP14.</article-title>
                <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>579</volume>
                <fpage>427</fpage>
                <lpage>32</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642354</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.tominaga.2005.1590">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tominaga</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kagata</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Johmura</surname>
                    <given-names>Y</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hishida</surname>
                    <given-names>T</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Nishizuka</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Imagawa</surname>
                    <given-names>M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>SLC39A14, a LZT protein, is induced in adipogenesis and transports zinc.</article-title>
                <source>FEBS J.</source>
                <year>2005</year>
                <volume>272</volume>
                <fpage>1590</fpage>
                <lpage>99</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15794747</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.tuschl.2016.11601">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tuschl</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Meyer</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valdivia</surname>
                    <given-names>LE</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zhao</surname>
                    <given-names>N</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dadswell</surname>
                    <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Abdul-Sada</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hung</surname>
                    <given-names>CY</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Simpson</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Chong</surname>
                    <given-names>WK</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Jacques</surname>
                    <given-names>TS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Woltjer</surname>
                    <given-names>RL</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Eaton</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gregory</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Sanford</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kara</surname>
                    <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Houlden</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Cuno</surname>
                    <given-names>SM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Prokisch</surname>
                    <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Valletta</surname>
                    <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Tiranti</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Younis</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maher</surname>
                    <given-names>ER</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Spencer</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Straatman-Iwanowska</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Gissen</surname>
                    <given-names>P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Selim</surname>
                    <given-names>LA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pintos-Morell</surname>
                    <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Coroleu-Lletget</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mohammad</surname>
                    <given-names>SS</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Yoganathan</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Dale</surname>
                    <given-names>RC</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Thomas</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Rihel</surname>
                    <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Bodamer</surname>
                    <given-names>OA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Enns</surname>
                    <given-names>CA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Hayflick</surname>
                    <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Clayton</surname>
                    <given-names>PT</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Mills</surname>
                    <given-names>PB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Kurian</surname>
                    <given-names>MA</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Wilson</surname>
                    <given-names>SW</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Mutations in SLC39A14 disrupt manganese homeostasis and cause childhood-onset parkinsonism-dystonia.</article-title>
                <source>Nat Commun.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>7</volume>
                <fpage>11601</fpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27231142</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="slc39a14-def.REF.zech.2016.1377">
              <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                <person-group>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Zech</surname>
                    <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Boesch</surname>
                    <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Maier</surname>
                    <given-names>E M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Borggraefe</surname>
                    <given-names>I</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Vill</surname>
                    <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Laccone</surname>
                    <given-names>F</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Pilshofer</surname>
                    <given-names>V</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Ceballos-Baumann</surname>
                    <given-names>A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Alhaddad</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Berutt</surname>
                    <given-names>R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Poewe</surname>
                    <given-names>W</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haack</surname>
                    <given-names>TB</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Haslinger</surname>
                    <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Strom</surname>
                    <given-names>TM</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                    <surname>Winkelmann</surname>
                    <given-names>J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                </person-group>
                <article-title>Haploinsufficiency of KMT2B, encoding the lysine-specific histone methyltransferase 2B, results in early-onset generalized dystonia.</article-title>
                <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
                <year>2016</year>
                <volume>99</volume>
                <fpage>1377</fpage>
                <lpage>87</lpage>
                <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27839873</pub-id>
              </element-citation>
            </ref>
          </ref-list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="slc39a14-def.Chapter_Notes">
        <title>Chapter Notes</title>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Acknowledgments">
          <title>Acknowledgments</title>
          <p>This work was supported by grants from Action Medical Research, the Wellcome Trust, Great Ormond Street Hospital Children&#x02019;s Charity, NBIA Disorders Association, Gracious Heart Charity Foundation and Rosetrees Trust, and the GOSH National Institute for Health Research/Biomedical Research Centre.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="slc39a14-def.Revision_History">
          <title>Revision History</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>25 May 2017 (bp) Review posted live</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>29 November 2016 (kt) Original submission</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="figs-and-tables">
        <title/>
        <fig position="float" id="slc39a14-def.F1" orientation="portrait">
          <label>Figure 1<break/><break/></label>
          <caption>
            <p>A. Axial T<sub>1</sub>-weighted image showing the hyperintensity of the globus pallidus (white arrows), and the cerebral white matter (dashed arrows)B. Axial T<sub>2</sub>-weighted image showing the hypointensity of the globus pallidus (white arrows)C. Sagittal T<sub>1</sub>-weighted image showing the hyperintensity of the white matter in the cerebellum, spinal cord and dorsal pons with sparing of the ventral pons (white arrow), and the anterior pituitary (dashed arrow)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="slc39a14-def-Image001" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </body>
  </book-part>
</book-part-wrapper>
